1 Samuel  7 : 1 - 17

7 So the men of Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim came and took the Ark of Jehovah up into the house of A·binʹa·dab on the hill, and they sanctified his son El·e·aʹzar to guard the Ark of Jehovah.

^2 A long time elapsed, 20 years in all, from the day of the Ark’s coming to Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim, and all the house of Israel began to seek[*] after Jehovah. ^3 Samuel then said to all the house of Israel: “If you are returning to Jehovah with all your heart, put away the foreign gods and the Ashʹto·reth images from among you, and direct your heart unswervingly to Jehovah and serve only him, and he will rescue you from the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines.” ^4 At that the Israelites got rid of the Baʹals and the Ashʹto·reth images and served only Jehovah.

^5 Then Samuel said: “Gather all Israel together at Mizʹpah, and I will pray to Jehovah in your behalf.” ^6 So they gathered together at Mizʹpah, and they drew water and poured it out before Jehovah and kept a fast on that day. There they said: “We have sinned against Jehovah.” And Samuel began serving as judge over the Israelites in Mizʹpah.

^7 When the Phi·lisʹtines heard that the Israelites had gathered together at Mizʹpah, the lords of the Phi·lisʹtines went up against Israel. When the Israelites heard of it, they were afraid because of the Phi·lisʹtines. ^8 So the Israelites said to Samuel: “Do not stop calling to Jehovah our God to help us and to save us from the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines.” ^9 Then Samuel took a suckling lamb and offered it up as a whole burnt offering to Jehovah; and Samuel called to Jehovah for help in behalf of Israel, and Jehovah answered him. ^10 As Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Phi·lisʹtines advanced for battle against Israel. Jehovah now caused it to thunder loudly on that day against the Phi·lisʹtines, and He threw them into confusion, and they were defeated before Israel. ^11 At that the men of Israel went out from Mizʹpah and pursued the Phi·lisʹtines, striking them down as far as south of Beth-car. ^12 Then Samuel took a stone and set it between Mizʹpah and Jeshʹa·nah and named it Eb·en·eʹzer,[*] for he said: “Until now Jehovah has helped us.” ^13 Thus the Phi·lisʹtines were subdued, and they did not come again into the territory of Israel; and the hand of Jehovah continued against the Phi·lisʹtines all the days of Samuel. ^14 Also, the cities that the Phi·lisʹtines had taken from Israel were returned to Israel, from Ekʹron to Gath, and Israel recovered their territory from the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines.

There was also peace between Israel and the Amʹor·ites.

^15 Samuel kept on judging Israel throughout his life. ^16 Each year he traveled in a circuit to Bethʹel, Gilʹgal, and Mizʹpah, and he judged Israel in all these places. ^17 But he would return to Raʹmah, because his house was there, and there he also judged Israel. He built an altar there to Jehovah.

^ 1 Sam. 7:2 Or “mourn.”

^ 1 Sam. 7:12 Meaning “Stone of Help.”

1 Samuel  8 : 1 - 22

8 When Samuel had grown old, he appointed his sons as judges for Israel. ^2 The name of his firstborn son was Joel, and the name of his second, A·biʹjah; they were judges in Beʹer-sheʹba. ^3 But his sons did not walk in his ways; they were inclined to pursue dishonest profit, they accepted bribes, and they perverted justice.

^4 In time all the elders of Israel gathered together and came to Samuel at Raʹmah. ^5 They said to him: “Look! You have grown old, but your sons are not walking in your ways. Now appoint for us a king to judge us like all the other nations.” ^6 But it displeased[*] Samuel when they said: “Give us a king to judge us.” Then Samuel prayed to Jehovah, ^7 and Jehovah said to Samuel: “Listen to everything the people say to you; for it is not you whom they have rejected, but it is I whom they have rejected as their king. ^8 They are doing just as they have done from the day I brought them up out of Egypt until this day; they keep forsaking me and serving other gods, and that is what they are doing to you. ^9 Now listen to them. However, you should solemnly warn them; tell them what the king who rules over them will have the right to demand.”

^10 So Samuel told the people who were asking him for a king all the words of Jehovah. ^11 He said: “This is what the king who rules over you will have the right to demand: He will take your sons and put them in his chariots and make them his horsemen, and some will have to run before his chariots. ^12 And he will appoint for himself chiefs over thousands and chiefs over fifties, and some will do his plowing, reap his harvest, and make his weapons of war and equipment for his chariots. ^13 He will take your daughters to be ointment mixers,[*] cooks, and bakers. ^14 He will take the best of your fields, your vineyards, and your olive groves, and he will give them to his servants. ^15 He will take the tenth of your grainfields and your vineyards, and he will give it to his court officials and his servants. ^16 And he will take your male and female servants, your best herds, and your donkeys, and he will use them for his work. ^17 He will take the tenth of your flocks, and you will become his servants. ^18 The day will come when you will cry out because of the king you have chosen for yourselves, but Jehovah will not answer you in that day.”

^19 However, the people refused to listen to what Samuel told them, and they said: “No, we are determined to have a king over us. ^20 Then we will be like all the other nations, and our king will judge us and lead us and fight our battles.” ^21 After Samuel heard all the words of the people, he repeated them in the hearing of Jehovah. ^22 Jehovah said to Samuel: “Listen to them, and appoint a king to reign over them.” Samuel then said to the men of Israel: “Each of you should return to his city.”

^ 1 Sam. 8:6 Lit., “was bad in the eyes of.”

^ 1 Sam. 8:13 Or “perfume makers.”

1 Samuel  9 : 1 - 27

9 There was a man of Benjamin named Kish, the son of A·biʹel, the son of Zeʹror son of Be·coʹrath son of A·phiʹah, a Benʹja·min·ite and a very wealthy man. ^2 He had a son named Saul, who was young and handsome—there was no man among the Israelites more handsome than he—and he stood head and shoulders taller than all the people.

^3 When the donkeys[*] belonging to Saul’s father Kish got lost, Kish said to his son Saul: “Please take with you one of the attendants and go look for the donkeys.” ^4 They passed through the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im and through the land of Shalʹi·shah, and they did not find them. They traveled through the land of Shaʹa·lim, but the donkeys were not there. They passed through the entire land of the Benʹja·min·ites, and they did not find them.

^5 They came into the land of Zuph, and Saul said to his attendant who was with him: “Come, let us return, so that my father does not start worrying about us rather than the donkeys.” ^6 But the attendant replied: “Look, there is a man of God in this city, a man who is held in honor. All that he says is sure to come true. Let us go there now. Perhaps he can tell us which way to go.” ^7 At this Saul said to his attendant: “If we go, what can we take to the man? There is no bread in our bags; there is nothing to take as a gift to the man of the true God. What do we have?” ^8 So the attendant answered Saul again: “Look! There is a quarter of a shekel[*] of silver in my hand. I will give it to the man of the true God, and he will tell us which way to go.” ^9 (In former times in Israel, this was what a man would say when going to seek God: “Come, and let us go to the seer.” For the prophet of today used to be called a seer in former times.) ^10 Then Saul said to his attendant: “What you said is good. Let us go.” So they went to the city where the man of the true God was.

^11 While they were going up the ascent to the city, they met girls going out to draw water. So they said to them: “Is the seer in this place?” ^12 They answered: “He is. Look, he is just ahead of you. Hurry now, for today he has come to the city, because the people are making a sacrifice today on the high place. ^13 As soon as you come into the city, you will find him before he goes up to the high place to eat. The people will not eat until he comes, for he is the one who blesses the sacrifice. Once that is done, those who are invited may eat. So now go up right away, and you will find him.” ^14 So they went up to the city. As they were coming into the middle of the city, there was Samuel coming out to meet them to go up to the high place.

^15 The day before Saul came, Jehovah had told[*] Samuel: ^16 “Tomorrow about this time, I will send to you a man from the land of Benjamin. You must anoint him as leader over my people Israel, and he will save my people from the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines. For I have seen the affliction of my people, and their outcry has reached me.” ^17 When Samuel saw Saul, Jehovah told him: “Here is the man of whom I said to you, ‘This is the one who will govern my people.’”[*]

^18 Then Saul approached Samuel in the middle of the gate and said: “Tell me, please, where is the house of the seer?” ^19 Samuel answered Saul: “I am the seer. Go up ahead of me to the high place, and you will eat with me today. I will send you away in the morning, and I will tell you all that you want to know.[*] ^20 As for the donkeys that were lost three days ago, do not worry about them, for they have been found. And to whom does all that is desirable of Israel belong? Is it not to you and to the whole house of your father?” ^21 At this Saul answered: “Am I not a Benʹja·min·ite of the smallest of the tribes of Israel, and my family the most insignificant of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? So why have you spoken to me in this way?”

^22 Then Samuel took Saul and his attendant and brought them to the dining hall and gave them a place at the head of those invited; there were about 30 men. ^23 Samuel said to the cook: “Bring the portion that I gave you and told you, ‘Set it aside.’” ^24 At that the cook lifted up the leg and what was on it, and set it before Saul. And Samuel said: “What has been reserved has been set before you. Eat, because they have reserved it for you for this occasion. For I told them, ‘I invited guests.’” So Saul ate with Samuel on that day. ^25 Then they went down from the high place to the city, and he continued to speak with Saul on the housetop. ^26 They rose early, and at daybreak Samuel called to Saul on the housetop, saying: “Get ready, so that I may send you away.” So Saul got ready and both he and Samuel went outside. ^27 While they were descending toward the outskirts of the city, Samuel said to Saul: “Tell the attendant to go on ahead of us,” so he went on ahead. “But you, stand still now, so that I may let you hear the word of God.”

^ 1 Sam. 9:3 Lit., “female donkeys.”

^ 1 Sam. 9:8 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 9:15 Lit., “uncovered the ear of.”

^ 1 Sam. 9:17 Or “keep my people within bounds.”

^ 1 Sam. 9:19 Lit., “all that is in your heart.”

1 Samuel  10 : 1 - 27

10 Samuel then took the flask of oil and poured it out on Saul’s head. He kissed him and said: “Has not Jehovah anointed you as a leader over his inheritance? ^2 When you leave me today, you will find two men near the tomb of Rachel in the territory of Benjamin at Zelʹzah, and they will say to you, ‘The donkeys that you went to look for have been found, but now your father has forgotten about the donkeys and is worried about you. He is saying: “What should I do about my son?”’ ^3 Go on from there until you come to the big tree of Taʹbor, where you will meet three men going up to the true God at Bethʹel, one carrying three young goats, one carrying three loaves of bread, and one carrying a large jar of wine. ^4 They will ask about your welfare and give you two loaves, and you must accept the loaves from them. ^5 After that you will come to the hill of the true God, where there is a garrison of the Phi·lisʹtines. When you come to the city, you will meet a group of prophets coming down from the high place, and a stringed instrument and tambourine and flute and harp will be played ahead of them while they are prophesying. ^6 The spirit of Jehovah will empower you, and you will prophesy along with them and be changed into a different person. ^7 When these signs have taken place, do whatever your hand finds possible, because the true God is with you. ^8 Then go down ahead of me to Gilʹgal, and I will go down to you there to offer up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices. You should wait for seven days until I come to you. Then I will let you know what you should do.”

^9 As soon as Saul turned around to leave Samuel, God began changing his heart to be like that of someone else, and all these signs came true on that day. ^10 So they went from there to the hill, and a group of prophets met him. At once the spirit of God empowered him, and he began to prophesy among them. ^11 When all those who previously knew him saw him prophesying with the prophets, they said to one another: “What has happened to the son of Kish? Is Saul also among the prophets?” ^12 Then a man from there said: “But who is their father?” So it became a saying:[*] “Is Saul also among the prophets?”

^13 When he finished prophesying, he came to the high place. ^14 The brother of Saul’s father later said to him and to his attendant: “Where did you go?” At that he said: “To look for the donkeys, but we saw that they were not there, so we went to Samuel.” ^15 Saul’s uncle asked: “Please tell me, what did Samuel say to you?” ^16 Saul replied to his uncle: “He told us that the donkeys had already been found.” But Saul did not tell him what Samuel said about the matter of the kingship.

^17 Samuel then called the people together to Jehovah at Mizʹpah ^18 and said to the Israelites: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘It was I who brought Israel up out of Egypt and who rescued you from the hand of Egypt and from the hand of all the kingdoms that were oppressing you. ^19 But today you have rejected your God who was your Savior out of all your evils and distresses, and you said: “No, you should appoint a king over us.” Now take your stand before Jehovah by your tribes and by your thousands.’”[*]

^20 So Samuel had all the tribes of Israel draw near, and the tribe of Benjamin was selected. ^21 Then he had the tribe of Benjamin draw near by its families, and the family of the Matʹrites was selected. Finally Saul the son of Kish was selected. But when they went to look for him, he was nowhere to be found. ^22 So they inquired of Jehovah: “Has the man come here yet?” Jehovah answered: “There he is hiding himself among the luggage.” ^23 So they ran and brought him from there. When he stood in the middle of the people, he was head and shoulders taller than all the other people. ^24 Samuel said to all the people: “Do you see the one whom Jehovah has chosen, that there is none like him among all the people?” And all the people began to shout: “Long live the king!”

^25 Samuel spoke to the people about the rightful due of kings and wrote it in a book and deposited it before Jehovah. Then Samuel sent all the people away, everyone to his house. ^26 Saul also went to his home in Gibʹe·ah, accompanied by the warriors whose hearts Jehovah had touched. ^27 But some worthless men said: “How will this one save us?” So they despised him, and they did not bring any gift to him. But he said nothing about it.[*]

^ 1 Sam. 10:12 Or “a proverb.”

^ 1 Sam. 10:19 Or “clans.”

^ 1 Sam. 10:27 Lit., “And he was like someone speechless.”

1 Samuel  11 : 1 - 15

11 Then Naʹhash the Amʹmon·ite came up and camped against Jaʹbesh in Gilʹe·ad. All the men of Jaʹbesh said to Naʹhash: “Make a covenant[*] with us, and we will serve you.” ^2 Naʹhash the Amʹmon·ite said to them: “I will make it with you on this condition: that all your right eyes be bored out. I will do this to humiliate all Israel.” ^3 The elders of Jaʹbesh replied to him: “Give us seven days’ time so that we can send messengers into all the territory of Israel. Then, if there is no one to rescue us, we will surrender to you.” ^4 In time the messengers came to Gibʹe·ah of Saul and spoke these words in the hearing of the people, and all the people wept at the top of their voice.

^5 But Saul was coming from the field behind the herd, and Saul said: “What is the matter with the people? Why are they weeping?” So they related to him the words of the men of Jaʹbesh. ^6 The spirit of God empowered Saul when he heard these words, and he burned with anger. ^7 So he took a pair of bulls and cut them into pieces, and he sent these into all the territory of Israel by the hand of the messengers, who said: “Whoever does not follow Saul and Samuel should expect this to be done to his cattle!” And the fear of Jehovah fell upon the people, so that they came out with one accord.[*] ^8 Then he counted them in Beʹzek, and there were 300,000 Israelites and 30,000 men of Judah. ^9 They now said to the messengers who had come: “This is what you should say to the men of Jaʹbesh in Gilʹe·ad, ‘Tomorrow when the sun gets hot, you will be saved.’” With that the messengers came and told the men of Jaʹbesh, and they were overjoyed. ^10 So the men of Jaʹbesh said: “Tomorrow we will surrender to you, and you may do to us whatever seems good to you.”

^11 On the next day, Saul divided the people into three bands, and they made their way into the middle of the camp during the morning watch[*] and struck down the Amʹmon·ites until the day grew hot. Those who survived were scattered, so that no two of them were left together. ^12 Then the people said to Samuel: “Who was saying, ‘Is Saul to be king over us?’ Hand the men over, and we will put them to death.” ^13 However, Saul said: “Not a man should be put to death on this day, for today Jehovah has rescued Israel.”

^14 Samuel later said to the people: “Come and let us go to Gilʹgal to reconfirm the kingship.” ^15 So all the people went to Gilʹgal, and in Gilʹgal they made Saul king before Jehovah. Then they offered communion sacrifices there before Jehovah, and Saul and all the men of Israel celebrated with great joy.

^ 1 Sam. 11:1 Or “an agreement.”

^ 1 Sam. 11:7 Lit., “as one man.”

^ 1 Sam. 11:11 That is, about 2:00 a.m. until 6:00 a.m.

1 Samuel  12 : 1 - 25

12 Finally Samuel said to all Israel: “Here I have done[*] all that you asked of me, and I appointed a king to reign over you. ^2 Now here is the king who is leading[*] you! As for me, I have grown old and gray, and my sons are here with you, and I have led you from my youth until this day. ^3 Here I am. Testify against me before Jehovah and before his anointed one: Whose bull or whose donkey have I taken? Or whom have I defrauded or crushed? From whose hand have I accepted a bribe[*] to make me look the other way? If I have, I will restore it to you.” ^4 To this they said: “You have not defrauded us or crushed us or accepted anything at all from anyone’s hand.” ^5 So he said to them: “Jehovah is a witness against you, and his anointed one is a witness this day that you have found nothing to accuse me of.”[*] To this they said: “He is a witness.”

^6 So Samuel said to the people: “Jehovah, who used Moses and Aaron and who brought your forefathers up out of the land of Egypt, is a witness. ^7 And now take your positions, and I will judge you before Jehovah in view of all the righteous acts that Jehovah has done for you and for your forefathers.

^8 “As soon as Jacob had come into Egypt and your forefathers began calling to Jehovah for help, Jehovah sent Moses and Aaron to lead your forefathers out of Egypt and to cause them to dwell in this place. ^9 But they forgot Jehovah their God, and he sold them into the hand of Sisʹe·ra the chief of the army of Haʹzor and into the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines and into the hand of the king of Moʹab, and they fought against them. ^10 And they called to Jehovah for help and said, ‘We have sinned, for we have left Jehovah to serve the Baʹals and the Ashʹto·reth images; now rescue us out of the hand of our enemies so that we may serve you.’ ^11 Then Jehovah sent Jer·ub·baʹal and Beʹdan and Jephʹthah and Samuel and rescued you from the hand of the enemies all around you, so that you could live in security. ^12 When you saw that Naʹhash, the king of the Amʹmon·ites, had come against you, you kept saying to me, ‘No, we are determined to have a king over us!’ even though Jehovah your God is your King. ^13 Now here is the king whom you have chosen, the one you asked for. Look! Jehovah has appointed a king over you. ^14 If you fear Jehovah and serve him and obey his voice and you do not rebel against the order of Jehovah, and both you and the king who reigns over you follow Jehovah your God, fine. ^15 But if you do not obey the voice of Jehovah and you rebel against the order of Jehovah, the hand of Jehovah will be against you and your fathers. ^16 Now take your positions and see this great thing that Jehovah is doing before your eyes. ^17 Is it not the wheat harvest today? I will call on Jehovah to make it thunder and rain; then know and understand what an evil thing you have done in the eyes of Jehovah in asking for a king for yourselves.”

^18 At that Samuel called to Jehovah, and Jehovah made it thunder and rain on that day, so that all the people were greatly in fear of Jehovah and of Samuel. ^19 And all the people said to Samuel: “Pray to Jehovah your God for your servants, as we do not want to die, for we have added to all our sins another evil by asking for a king.”

^20 So Samuel said to the people: “Do not be afraid. You have indeed done all this evil. Only do not turn away from following Jehovah, and serve Jehovah with all your heart. ^21 Do not turn away to follow the empty things,[*] which are of no benefit and cannot rescue, because they are empty.[*] ^22 For the sake of his great name, Jehovah will not abandon his people, for Jehovah has taken it upon himself to make you his people. ^23 As for me, it is unthinkable for me to sin against Jehovah by ceasing to pray in your behalf, and I will continue to instruct you in the good and right way. ^24 Only fear Jehovah, and serve him faithfully[*] with all your heart, for see what great things he has done for you. ^25 But if you flagrantly do what is bad, you will be swept away, both you and your king.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:1 Lit., “listened to your voice as respects.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:2 Lit., “walking before.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:3 Or “hush money.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:5 Lit., “have not found anything in my hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:21 Or “unrealities.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:21 Or “unrealities.”

^ 1 Sam. 12:24 Or “in truth.”

1 Samuel  13 : 1 - 23

13 Saul was . . .[*] years old when he became king, and for two years he reigned over Israel. ^2 Saul chose 3,000 men out of Israel; 2,000 of these were with Saul at Michʹmash and in the mountainous region of Bethʹel and 1,000 were with Jonʹa·than at Gibʹe·ah of Benjamin. He sent the rest of the people away, each one to his tent. ^3 Then Jonʹa·than struck down the garrison of the Phi·lisʹtines that was in Geʹba, and the Phi·lisʹtines heard about it. And Saul had the horn blown throughout all the land, saying: “Let the Hebrews hear!” ^4 All Israel heard the news: “Saul has struck down a garrison of the Phi·lisʹtines, and now Israel has become a stench among the Phi·lisʹtines.” So the people were summoned to follow Saul at Gilʹgal.

^5 The Phi·lisʹtines also gathered together to fight against Israel, with 30,000 war chariots and 6,000 horsemen and troops as numerous as the grains of sand on the seashore; and they went up and camped in Michʹmash to the east of Beth-aʹven. ^6 And the men of Israel saw that they were in trouble, because they were hard-pressed; so the people hid in the caves, the hollows, the crags, the cellars,[*] and the cisterns. ^7 Some of the Hebrews even crossed the Jordan to the land of Gad and Gilʹe·ad. But Saul was still in Gilʹgal, and all the people following him were trembling. ^8 He continued waiting for seven days until the designated[*] time that Samuel had set, but Samuel did not come to Gilʹgal, and the people were scattering from him. ^9 Finally Saul said: “Bring to me the burnt sacrifice and the communion sacrifices.” And he offered up the burnt sacrifice.

^10 But as soon as he had finished offering up the burnt sacrifice, Samuel arrived. So Saul went out to meet him and bless him. ^11 Then Samuel said: “What have you done?” Saul replied: “I saw that the people were deserting me, and you did not come within the designated time, and the Phi·lisʹtines were gathering together at Michʹmash. ^12 So I said to myself, ‘Now the Phi·lisʹtines will come down against me at Gilʹgal, and I have not sought the favor[*] of Jehovah.’ So I felt obligated to offer up the burnt sacrifice.”

^13 At this Samuel said to Saul: “You have acted foolishly. You have not obeyed the commandment that Jehovah your God gave you. If you had, Jehovah would have made your kingdom firm over Israel forever. ^14 But now your kingdom will not last. Jehovah will find a man agreeable to his heart, and Jehovah will commission him as a leader over his people, because you did not obey what Jehovah commanded you.”

^15 Then Samuel rose and went his way up from Gilʹgal to Gibʹe·ah of Benjamin, and Saul took the count of the people; those still with him were about 600 men. ^16 Saul, his son Jonʹa·than, and the people still with them were dwelling in Geʹba of Benjamin, and the Phi·lisʹtines had encamped at Michʹmash. ^17 And the raiding parties would go out from the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines in three bands. One band would turn toward the road to Ophʹrah, to the land of Shuʹal; ^18 another band would turn toward the road of Beth-hoʹron; and the third band would turn toward the road leading to the boundary that overlooks the valley of Ze·boʹim, toward the wilderness.

^19 Now there was not a metalworker to be found in all the land of Israel, because the Phi·lisʹtines had said: “So that the Hebrews may not make a sword or a spear.” ^20 And all the Israelites had to go down to the Phi·lisʹtines to get their plowshares, mattocks, axes, or sickles sharpened. ^21 The price for sharpening was a pim[*] for the plowshares, for the mattocks, for the three-toothed instruments, for the axes, and for fixing fast the oxgoad. ^22 And on the day of battle, not a sword or a spear was found in the hand of any of the people who were with Saul and Jonʹa·than; only Saul and his son Jonʹa·than had weapons.

^23 Now a garrison[*] of the Phi·lisʹtines had gone out to the ravine pass of Michʹmash.

^ 1 Sam. 13:1 The number is missing in the Hebrew text.

^ 1 Sam. 13:6 Or “vaults.”

^ 1 Sam. 13:8 Or “appointed.”

^ 1 Sam. 13:12 Or “softened the face.”

^ 1 Sam. 13:21 An ancient weight, approximately two thirds of a shekel.

^ 1 Sam. 13:23 Or “an outpost.”

1 Samuel  14 : 1 - 52

14 One day Jonʹa·than the son of Saul said to the attendant carrying his weapons: “Come and let us cross over to the Phi·lisʹtine outpost on the other side.” But he did not tell his father. ^2 Saul was staying on the outskirts of Gibʹe·ah under the pomegranate tree in Migʹron, and there were about 600 men with him. ^3 (And A·hiʹjah the son of A·hiʹtub, the brother of Ichʹa·bod, the son of Phinʹe·has, the son of Eʹli, the priest of Jehovah in Shiʹloh, was carrying the ephʹod.) And the people did not know that Jonʹa·than had gone. ^4 Now between the passages that Jonʹa·than was trying to cross over to reach the outpost of the Phi·lisʹtines, there was a toothlike crag on one side and a toothlike crag on the other side; the name of the one was Boʹzez, and the name of the other was Seʹneh. ^5 The one crag was a pillar on the north facing Michʹmash, and the other was on the south facing Geʹba.

^6 So Jonʹa·than said to his armor-bearer: “Come and let us cross over to the outpost of these uncircumcised men. Perhaps Jehovah will act in our behalf, for nothing can hinder Jehovah from saving by many or by few.” ^7 At this his armor-bearer said to him: “Do whatever your heart impels you to do. Turn wherever you wish, and I will follow you wherever your heart impels you.” ^8 Then Jonʹa·than said: “We will cross over to those men and reveal our presence to them. ^9 If they say to us, ‘Stand still until we come to you!’ we will stand where we are and not go up to them. ^10 But if they say, ‘Come up against us!’ we will go up, because Jehovah will give them into our hand. This will be our sign.”

^11 Then both of them revealed their presence to the outpost of the Phi·lisʹtines. The Phi·lisʹtines said: “Look! The Hebrews are coming out from the holes where they have been hiding.” ^12 So the men of the outpost said to Jonʹa·than and his armor-bearer: “Come up to us, and we will teach you a lesson!” At once Jonʹa·than said to his armor-bearer: “Follow me, for Jehovah will give them into the hand of Israel.” ^13 And Jonʹa·than climbed up on his hands and feet, and his armor-bearer was behind him; and the Phi·lisʹtines began to fall before Jonʹa·than, and his armor-bearer was putting them to death behind him. ^14 In the first attack that Jonʹa·than and his armor-bearer made, they struck down about 20 men within about half the plowing line in an acre of field.[*]

^15 Then terror spread in the field camp and among all the people of the outpost, and even the raiding parties were terrified. The earth began quaking, and a terror from God ensued. ^16 Saul’s watchmen in Gibʹe·ah of Benjamin saw that the turmoil was spreading in every direction.

^17 Saul said to the people with him: “Take a count, please, and see who has left us.” When they took the count, they saw that Jonʹa·than and his armor-bearer were not there. ^18 Saul now said to A·hiʹjah: “Bring the Ark of the true God near!” (For the Ark of the true God was with the Israelites at that time.[*]) ^19 And while Saul was speaking to the priest, the turmoil in the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines was growing greater and greater. Then Saul said to the priest: “Stop what you are doing.”[*] ^20 So Saul and all the people with him assembled and went into the battle, where they found that the Phi·lisʹtines had turned their swords against one another, and the confusion was very great. ^21 Also, the Hebrews who had previously sided with the Phi·lisʹtines and who had come up with them into the camp were going over to Israel under Saul and Jonʹa·than. ^22 All the men of Israel who had hidden in the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im heard that the Phi·lisʹtines had fled, and they too joined in pursuing them in the battle. ^23 So Jehovah saved Israel on that day, and the battle extended as far as Beth-aʹven.

^24 But the men of Israel were hard-pressed on that day, for Saul had put the people under this oath: “Cursed is the man who eats any food[*] before the evening and until I have taken vengeance on my enemies!” So none of the people ate any food.

^25 And all the people[*] came into the forest, and there was honey on the ground. ^26 When the people came into the forest, they saw the honey dripping, but no one would put his hand to his mouth, because they feared the oath. ^27 But Jonʹa·than had not heard his father put the people under an oath, so he stretched out the tip of the staff that was in his hand and dipped it into the honeycomb. When he drew his hand back to his mouth, his eyes brightened. ^28 At this one of the people said: “Your father put the people under a strict oath, saying, ‘Cursed is the man who eats food today!’ That is why the people are so tired.” ^29 However, Jonʹa·than said: “My father has brought great trouble[*] on the land. Look at how my eyes brightened because I tasted this little bit of honey. ^30 How much better if the people had eaten freely today from the spoil of their enemies that they found! For then the slaughter of the Phi·lisʹtines would have been even greater.”

^31 On that day they kept striking down the Phi·lisʹtines from Michʹmash to Aiʹja·lon, and the people became very tired. ^32 So the people began rushing greedily at the spoil, and they took sheep and cattle and calves and slaughtered them on the ground, and they ate the meat along with the blood. ^33 So it was reported to Saul: “Look! The people are sinning against Jehovah by eating meat with the blood.” At this he said: “You have acted faithlessly. Roll a large stone to me immediately.” ^34 Saul then said: “Spread out among the people and say to them, ‘Each of you must bring his bull and his sheep and slaughter them here and then eat them. Do not sin against Jehovah by eating meat with the blood.’” So each of them brought his bull with him that night and slaughtered it there. ^35 And Saul built an altar to Jehovah. This was the first altar he built to Jehovah.

^36 Saul later said: “Let us go down after the Phi·lisʹtines by night and plunder them until the morning light. We will not leave a single survivor.” To this they said: “Do whatever seems good in your eyes.” Then the priest said: “Let us approach the true God here.” ^37 And Saul inquired of God: “Should I go down after the Phi·lisʹtines? Will you give them into the hand of Israel?” But God did not answer him on that day. ^38 So Saul said: “Come here, all you chiefs of the people, and find out what sin has been committed today. ^39 For as surely as Jehovah is alive, who rescued Israel, even if it turns out to be Jonʹa·than my son, he must die.” But none of the people would answer him. ^40 Then he said to all Israel: “You will be on one side, and my son Jonʹa·than and I will be on the other side.” At this the people said to Saul: “Do whatever seems good in your eyes.”

^41 Saul then said to Jehovah: “O God of Israel, answer with the Thumʹmim!” Then Jonʹa·than and Saul were selected, and the people went free. ^42 Saul now said: “Cast lots to decide between me and my son Jonʹa·than.” And Jonʹa·than was selected. ^43 Then Saul said to Jonʹa·than: “Tell me, what have you done?” So Jonʹa·than told him: “I merely tasted a little honey on the tip of the staff in my hand. Here I am! I am ready to die!”

^44 At this Saul said: “Thus may God do and may he add to it if you do not die, Jonʹa·than.” ^45 But the people said to Saul: “Should Jonʹa·than die—the one who brought this great victory[*] to Israel? It is unthinkable! As surely as Jehovah is alive, not even a single hair of his head should fall to the ground, for it was with God that he acted this day.” With that the people rescued[*] Jonʹa·than, and he did not die.

^46 So Saul stopped pursuing the Phi·lisʹtines, and the Phi·lisʹtines went to their own territory.

^47 Saul secured the kingship over Israel and fought against all his enemies on every side, against the Moʹab·ites, the Amʹmon·ites, the Eʹdom·ites, the kings of Zoʹbah, and the Phi·lisʹtines; and wherever he went he defeated them. ^48 And he fought bravely and conquered the A·malʹek·ites and rescued Israel from the hand of their plunderers.

^49 The sons of Saul were Jonʹa·than, Ishʹvi, and Malʹchi-shuʹa. And he had two daughters; the name of the older one was Meʹrab, and the name of the younger one, Miʹchal. ^50 The name of Saul’s wife was A·hinʹo·am the daughter of A·himʹa·az. The name of the chief of his army was Abʹner the son of Ner, the uncle of Saul. ^51 Kish was the father of Saul, and Ner the father of Abʹner was the son of A·biʹel.

^52 There was fierce warfare with the Phi·lisʹtines all the days of Saul. When Saul saw any strong or courageous man, he would recruit him into his service.

^ 1 Sam. 14:14 Lit., “a span of a field,” that is, the measure of land that a span of bulls can plow in a day.

^ 1 Sam. 14:18 Lit., “on that day.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:19 Lit., “Withdraw your hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:24 Lit., “bread.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:25 Lit., “land.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:29 Or “brought ostracism.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:45 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 14:45 Lit., “redeemed.”

1 Samuel  15 : 1 - 35

15 Then Samuel said to Saul: “Jehovah sent me to anoint you as king over his people Israel; now listen to what Jehovah has to say. ^2 This is what Jehovah of armies says: ‘I will call to account the A·malʹek·ites for what they did to Israel when they opposed them along their way coming up from Egypt. ^3 Now go, and strike down the A·malʹek·ites, and devote them to destruction along with all that they have. You must not spare[*] them; you are to put them to death, man as well as woman, child as well as infant, bull as well as sheep, camel as well as donkey.’” ^4 Saul summoned the people and counted them in Te·laʹim: There were 200,000 foot soldiers and 10,000 men of Judah.

^5 Saul advanced as far as the city of Amʹa·lek and set an ambush by the valley.[*] ^6 Saul then said to the Kenʹites: “Go, depart from among the A·malʹek·ites, so that I do not sweep you away with them. For you showed loyal love to all the people of Israel at the time they came up out of Egypt.” So the Kenʹites departed from the midst of Amʹa·lek. ^7 After that Saul struck down the A·malʹek·ites from Havʹi·lah as far as Shur, which is next to Egypt. ^8 He caught Aʹgag the king of Amʹa·lek alive, but all the other people he devoted to destruction with the sword. ^9 However, Saul and the people spared[*] Aʹgag and the best of the flock, the herd, the fattened animals, the rams, and all that was good. They did not want to devote them to destruction. But all the goods that were worthless and unwanted, these they devoted to destruction.

^10 Then the word of Jehovah came to Samuel: ^11 “I regret[*] that I have made Saul king, for he has turned away from following me and he has not carried out my words.” Samuel became very upset, and he kept crying out to Jehovah all night long. ^12 When Samuel got up early in the morning to meet Saul, Samuel was told: “Saul went to Carʹmel, and there he erected a monument for himself. Then he turned around and went down to Gilʹgal.” ^13 When Samuel finally came to him, Saul said to him: “May Jehovah bless you. I have carried out the word of Jehovah.” ^14 But Samuel said: “Then what is this sound of the flock in my ears and the sound of the cattle that I hear?” ^15 To this Saul said: “They were brought from the A·malʹek·ites, because the people spared[*] the best of the flock and the herd for sacrificing them to Jehovah your God; but what was left we devoted to destruction.” ^16 At this Samuel said to Saul: “Stop! Let me tell you what Jehovah said to me last night.” So he said to him: “Speak!”

^17 Samuel continued: “Were you not insignificant in your own eyes when you were made head of the tribes of Israel and when Jehovah anointed you as king over Israel? ^18 Jehovah later sent you on a mission and said, ‘Go, and devote the sinful A·malʹek·ites to destruction. Fight against them until you have exterminated them.’ ^19 So why did you not obey the voice of Jehovah? Instead, you rushed greedily toward the spoil and did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah!”

^20 However, Saul said to Samuel: “But I have obeyed the voice of Jehovah! I went on the mission to which Jehovah sent me, and I brought back Aʹgag the king of Amʹa·lek, and I devoted the A·malʹek·ites to destruction. ^21 But the people took sheep and cattle from the spoil, the best of what was devoted to destruction, to sacrifice to Jehovah your God at Gilʹgal.”

^22 Samuel then said: “Does Jehovah take as much pleasure in burnt offerings and sacrifices as in obeying the voice of Jehovah? Look! To obey is better than a sacrifice, and to pay attention than the fat of rams; ^23 for rebelliousness is the same as the sin of divination, and pushing ahead presumptuously the same as using magical power and idolatry.[*] Because you have rejected the word of Jehovah, he has rejected you from being king.”

^24 Then Saul said to Samuel: “I have sinned, for I have overstepped the order of Jehovah and your words, because I feared the people and listened to what they said. ^25 And now, please, pardon my sin, and return with me so that I may bow down to Jehovah.” ^26 But Samuel said to Saul: “I will not return with you, for you have rejected the word of Jehovah, and Jehovah has rejected you from continuing as king over Israel.” ^27 As Samuel was turning to go, Saul grabbed hold of the hem of his sleeveless coat, but it ripped away. ^28 At this Samuel said to him: “Jehovah has ripped away the royal rule of Israel from you today, and he will give it to one of your fellow men who is better than you. ^29 Moreover, the Excellency of Israel will not prove false or change his mind,[*] for He is not a mere man that he should change his mind.”[*]

^30 At this he said: “I have sinned. But honor me, please, in front of the elders of my people and in front of Israel. Return with me, and I will bow down to Jehovah your God.” ^31 So Samuel returned behind Saul, and Saul bowed down to Jehovah. ^32 And Samuel said: “Bring Aʹgag the king of Amʹa·lek near to me.” Then Aʹgag went to him reluctantly,[*] for Aʹgag had been saying to himself: ‘Surely the threat[*] of death is past.’ ^33 However, Samuel said: “Just as your sword has bereaved women of children, so your mother will be most bereaved among women.” With that Samuel hacked Aʹgag to pieces before Jehovah at Gilʹgal.

^34 Samuel now went to Raʹmah, and Saul went up to his own house at Gibʹe·ah of Saul. ^35 Samuel did not see Saul again until the day of his death, for Samuel went into mourning for Saul. And Jehovah regretted that he had made Saul king over Israel.

^ 1 Sam. 15:3 Or “show compassion to.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:5 Or “wadi.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:9 Or “showed compassion to.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:11 Or “am grieved.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:15 Or “showed compassion to.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:23 Lit., “teraphim statues,” that is, household gods; idols.

^ 1 Sam. 15:29 Or “feel regret.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:29 Or “feel regret.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:32 Or possibly, “confidently.”

^ 1 Sam. 15:32 Lit., “bitterness.”

1 Samuel  16 : 1 - 23

16 Jehovah eventually said to Samuel: “How long will you mourn for Saul now that I have rejected him from ruling as king over Israel? Fill your horn with oil and go. I will send you to Jesʹse the Bethʹle·hem·ite, because I have selected from among his sons a king for myself.” ^2 But Samuel said: “How can I go? When Saul hears about it, he will kill me.” Jehovah replied: “Take a young cow with you and say, ‘I have come to sacrifice to Jehovah.’ ^3 Invite Jesʹse to the sacrifice; then I will make known to you what to do. You must anoint for me the one whom I designate to you.”

^4 Samuel did what Jehovah said. When he came to Bethʹle·hem, the elders of the city were trembling at meeting him, and they said: “Does your coming mean peace?” ^5 To this he said: “It means peace. I have come to sacrifice to Jehovah. Sanctify yourselves, and come with me to the sacrifice.” Then he sanctified Jesʹse and his sons, after which he summoned them to the sacrifice. ^6 As they came in and he saw E·liʹab, he said: “Surely here before Jehovah stands his anointed one.” ^7 But Jehovah said to Samuel: “Do not pay attention to his appearance and how tall he is, for I have rejected him. For the way man sees is not the way God sees, because mere man sees what appears to the eyes, but Jehovah sees into the heart.” ^8 Then Jesʹse called A·binʹa·dab and had him pass before Samuel, but he said: “Jehovah has not chosen this one either.” ^9 Next Jesʹse presented Shamʹmah, but he said: “Jehovah has not chosen this one either.” ^10 So Jesʹse had seven of his sons pass before Samuel, but Samuel said to Jesʹse: “Jehovah has not chosen any of these.”

^11 Finally Samuel said to Jesʹse: “Are these all of your boys?” To this he said: “The youngest has been left out until now; he is pasturing the sheep.” Then Samuel said to Jesʹse: “Send for him, because we will not sit down for the meal until he comes here.” ^12 So he sent for him and brought him in. Now he was ruddy, with beautiful eyes, and handsome in appearance. Then Jehovah said: “Get up, anoint him, for this is the one!” ^13 So Samuel took the horn of oil and anointed him in the presence of his brothers. And the spirit of Jehovah began to empower David from that day forward. Samuel later rose and went his way to Raʹmah.

^14 Now the spirit of Jehovah had departed from Saul, and a bad spirit from Jehovah terrorized him. ^15 The servants of Saul said to him: “You see that a bad spirit from God is terrorizing you. ^16 Let our lord, please, command your servants before you to look for a man who is skilled at playing the harp. Whenever a bad spirit from God comes upon you, he will play it, and you will feel better.” ^17 So Saul said to his servants: “Find me, please, a man who plays well, and bring him to me.”

^18 One of the attendants said: “Look! I have seen how a son of Jesʹse the Bethʹle·hem·ite plays skillfully, and he is a courageous, mighty warrior. He can speak well, and he is handsome, and Jehovah is with him.” ^19 Saul then sent messengers to Jesʹse and said: “Send to me your son David, who is with the flock.” ^20 So Jesʹse loaded a donkey with bread, a skin bottle of wine, and a young goat and sent them to Saul with his son David. ^21 Thus David came to Saul and began serving him. Saul grew to love him very much, and he became his armor-bearer. ^22 Saul sent a message to Jesʹse: “Please let David remain in my service, for he has found favor in my eyes.” ^23 Whenever a bad spirit from God came upon Saul, David took the harp and played it, and Saul found relief and felt better, and the bad spirit would depart from him.

1 Samuel  17 : 1 - 58

17 And the Phi·lisʹtines assembled their armies[*] for war. They assembled at Soʹcoh, which belongs to Judah, and they camped between Soʹcoh and A·zeʹkah, in Eʹphes-damʹmim. ^2 Saul and the men of Israel assembled and camped in the Valley[*] of Eʹlah, and they drew up in battle formation to meet the Phi·lisʹtines. ^3 The Phi·lisʹtines occupied the mountain on one side, and the Israelites occupied the mountain on the other side, with the valley between them.

^4 Then a champion came out from the camps of the Phi·lisʹtines; his name was Go·liʹath, from Gath, and his height was six cubits and a span.[*] ^5 He had a helmet of copper on his head, and he was wearing a coat of mail of overlapping scales. The weight of the copper coat of mail was 5,000 shekels.[*] ^6 He had shin guards of copper on his legs and a javelin of copper slung between his shoulders. ^7 The wooden shaft of his spear was like the beam of loom workers, and the iron blade of his spear weighed 600 shekels;[*] and his shield-bearer was marching ahead of him. ^8 Then he stood and called out to the battle line of Israel and said to them: “Why have you come out to draw up in battle formation? Am I not the Phi·lisʹtine, and are you not the servants of Saul? Choose a man for yourselves, and let him come down to me. ^9 If he is able to fight with me and strike me down, we will then become your servants. But if I prevail against him and strike him down, you will become our servants and serve us.” ^10 The Phi·lisʹtine then said: “I do taunt[*] the battle line of Israel this day. Give me a man, and let us fight it out!”

^11 When Saul and all Israel heard these words of the Phi·lisʹtine, they became terrified and greatly afraid.

^12 Now David was the son of the Ephʹrath·ite from Bethʹle·hem of Judah named Jesʹse, who had eight sons and who in the days of Saul was already an old man. ^13 The three oldest sons of Jesʹse had followed Saul to the war. The names of his three sons who went to war were E·liʹab the firstborn, his second son A·binʹa·dab, and the third Shamʹmah. ^14 David was the youngest, and the three oldest followed Saul.

^15 David was going back and forth from Saul to tend the sheep of his father at Bethʹle·hem. ^16 Meanwhile, the Phi·lisʹtine would come forward and take his position each morning and each evening for 40 days.

^17 Then Jesʹse said to his son David: “Take, please, this eʹphah[*] of roasted grain and these ten loaves of bread, and carry them quickly to your brothers in the camp. ^18 And take these ten portions of cheese[*] to the chief of the thousand; also, you should check on the welfare of your brothers and bring back some token from them.” ^19 They were with Saul and all the other men of Israel in the Valley[*] of Eʹlah, fighting against the Phi·lisʹtines.

^20 So David got up early in the morning and left someone in charge of the sheep; then he packed up and went just as Jesʹse had commanded him. When he came to the camp enclosure, the army was going out to the battle line, shouting a battle cry. ^21 Israel and the Phi·lisʹtines drew up so that one battle line faced the other battle line. ^22 David immediately left his baggage in the care of the baggage keeper and ran to the battle line. When he arrived, he began asking about the welfare of his brothers.

^23 While he was speaking with them, there came the champion named Go·liʹath, the Phi·lisʹtine from Gath. He came out from the battle line of the Phi·lisʹtines, and he spoke the same words as before, and David heard him. ^24 When all the men of Israel saw the man, they fled from him, terrified. ^25 The men of Israel were saying: “Have you seen this man who is coming out? He comes to taunt[*] Israel. The king will give great riches to the man who strikes him down, he will give him his own daughter, and he will give the house of his father exemption in Israel.”

^26 David began to say to the men who were standing near him: “What will be done for the man who strikes down that Phi·lisʹtine over there and takes away reproach from Israel? For who is this uncircumcised Phi·lisʹtine that he should taunt[*] the battle line of the living God?” ^27 Then the people told him the same thing as before: “This is what will be done for the man who strikes him down.” ^28 When his oldest brother E·liʹab heard him speak to the men, he became angry with David and said: “Why have you come down? And with whom did you leave those few sheep in the wilderness? I well know your presumptuousness and the bad intentions of your heart; you came down just to see the battle.” ^29 To this David said: “What have I done now? I was only asking a question!” ^30 So he turned from him toward someone else and asked the same thing as before, and the people gave him the same reply as before.

^31 The words that David had spoken were overheard and reported to Saul. So he sent for him. ^32 David said to Saul: “Let no one lose heart[*] because of him. Your servant will go and fight with this Phi·lisʹtine.” ^33 But Saul said to David: “You are not able to go fight against this Phi·lisʹtine, for you are but a boy, and he has been a soldier[*] from his youth.” ^34 David then said to Saul: “Your servant became a shepherd of his father’s flock, and a lion came, also a bear, and each carried off a sheep from the flock. ^35 I went out after it and struck it down and rescued it from its mouth. When it rose up against me, I grabbed it by its fur[*] and struck it down and put it to death. ^36 Your servant struck down both the lion and the bear, and this uncircumcised Phi·lisʹtine will become like one of them, for he has taunted[*] the battle lines of the living God.” ^37 Then David added: “Jehovah, who rescued me from the claws of the lion and the bear, he is the one who will rescue me from the hand of this Phi·lisʹtine.” At this Saul said to David: “Go, and may Jehovah be with you.”

^38 Saul now clothed David with his garments. He put a copper helmet on his head, after which he clothed him with a coat of mail. ^39 Then David strapped on his sword over his garments and tried to go but could not, for he was not used to them. David said to Saul: “I am unable to go in these things, for I am not used to them.” So David took them off. ^40 He then took his staff in his hand and chose five smooth stones from the streambed[*] and placed them in the pouch of his shepherd’s bag, and his sling was in his hand. And he began approaching the Phi·lisʹtine.

^41 The Phi·lisʹtine came closer and closer to David, and his shield-bearer was ahead of him. ^42 When the Phi·lisʹtine looked and saw David, he sneered at him in contempt because he was just a ruddy and handsome boy. ^43 So the Phi·lisʹtine said to David: “Am I a dog, so that you are coming against me with sticks?” With that the Phi·lisʹtine cursed David by his gods. ^44 The Phi·lisʹtine said to David: “Just come to me, and I will give your flesh to the birds of the heavens and to the beasts of the field.”

^45 David replied to the Phi·lisʹtine: “You are coming against me with sword and spear and javelin, but I am coming against you in the name of Jehovah of armies, the God of the battle line of Israel, whom you have taunted.[*] ^46 This very day Jehovah will surrender you into my hand, and I will strike you down and cut off your head; and on this day I will give the corpses of the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines to the birds of the heavens and to the wild beasts of the earth; and people of all the earth will know that there is a God in Israel. ^47 And all those gathered here[*] will know that it is not with the sword or the spear that Jehovah saves, for the battle belongs to Jehovah, and he will give all of you into our hand.”

^48 Then the Phi·lisʹtine rose and drew steadily closer to meet David, but David ran quickly toward the battle line to meet the Phi·lisʹtine. ^49 David thrust his hand into his bag and took a stone from there and slung it. He struck the Phi·lisʹtine in the forehead, and the stone sank into his forehead and he fell facedown on the ground. ^50 So David prevailed over the Phi·lisʹtine with a sling and a stone; he struck down the Phi·lisʹtine and put him to death, though there was no sword in David’s hand. ^51 David continued running and stood over him. Then he took hold of the Phi·lisʹtine’s sword and pulled it out of its sheath and made sure that he was dead by cutting off his head with it. When the Phi·lisʹtines saw that their mighty one had died, they fled.

^52 At that the men of Israel and of Judah rose and broke into shouting and pursued the Phi·lisʹtines all the way from the valley to the gates of Ekʹron, and the slain of the Phi·lisʹtines lay fallen along the road from Shaʹa·raʹim, as far as Gath and Ekʹron. ^53 After the Israelites returned from hotly pursuing the Phi·lisʹtines, they pillaged their camps.

^54 Then David took the head of the Phi·lisʹtine and brought it to Jerusalem, but he put the Phi·lisʹtine’s weapons in his own tent.

^55 At the moment that Saul saw David go out to meet the Phi·lisʹtine, he said to Abʹner, the chief of the army: “Whose son is this boy, Abʹner?” Abʹner replied: “As surely as you live,[*] O king, I do not know!” ^56 The king said: “Find out whose son the young man is.” ^57 So as soon as David returned from striking down the Phi·lisʹtine, Abʹner took him and brought him before Saul with the head of the Phi·lisʹtine in his hand. ^58 Saul now said to him: “Whose son are you, boy?” to which David said: “The son of your servant Jesʹse the Bethʹle·hem·ite.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:1 Lit., “camps.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:2 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:4 His height was about 2.9 m (9 ft 5.75 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:5 About 57 kg (125 lb). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:7 About 6.84 kg (15 lb). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:10 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:17 About 22 L (20 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 17:18 Lit., “milk.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:19 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:25 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:26 Or “challenge.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:32 Or “courage.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:33 Or “a man of war.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:35 Or “by the jaw.” Lit., “by its beard.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:36 Or “challenged.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:40 Or “wadi.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:45 Or “challenged.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:47 Lit., “all this congregation.”

^ 1 Sam. 17:55 Or “By the life of your soul.”

1 Samuel  18 : 1 - 30

18 As soon as David had finished speaking to Saul, Jonʹa·than and David became bound together in close friendship,[*] and Jonʹa·than began to love him as himself.[*] ^2 From that day, Saul kept David with him, and he did not allow him to return to his father’s house. ^3 And Jonʹa·than and David made a covenant, because he loved him as himself.[*] ^4 Jonʹa·than took off the sleeveless coat that he wore and gave it to David, along with his gear, his sword, his bow, and his belt. ^5 David began going out and was successful[*] wherever Saul would send him. So Saul put him in charge of the fighting men, and this pleased all the people and the servants of Saul.

^6 When David and the others would return from striking down the Phi·lisʹtines, the women would come out from all the cities of Israel with song and dances to meet King Saul with tambourines, with rejoicing, and with lutes. ^7 The women who were celebrating would sing:

“Saul has struck down his thousands,

And David his tens of thousands.”

^8 Saul became very angry, and this song displeased him, for he said: “They have credited David with tens of thousands, but to me they have credited thousands. The only thing left to give him is the kingship!” ^9 From that day on, Saul was always looking at David suspiciously.

^10 The next day a bad spirit from God gripped Saul, and he started to act strangely[*] inside the house, while David was playing music on the harp as on other occasions. Saul had a spear in his hand, ^11 and he hurled the spear, saying to himself: ‘I will pin David to the wall!’ But David escaped from him twice. ^12 Then Saul was afraid of David because Jehovah was with him but had departed from Saul. ^13 So Saul removed him from his presence and appointed him as chief of a thousand, and David would lead the army into battle.[*] ^14 David continued to have success[*] in all he did, and Jehovah was with him. ^15 And when Saul saw that he was very successful, he became afraid of him. ^16 But all Israel and Judah loved David, because he would lead them in their campaigns.

^17 Saul later said to David: “Here is my oldest daughter Meʹrab. I will give her to you as a wife. However, you should continue to display your courage for me and fight the wars of Jehovah.” For Saul said to himself: ‘Do not let my hand come against him. Let the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines strike him.’ ^18 At this David said to Saul: “Who am I and who are my relatives, my father’s family in Israel, for me to become son-in-law to the king?” ^19 However, when the time came to give Saul’s daughter Meʹrab to David, she had already been given to be the wife of Aʹdri·el the Me·holʹath·ite.

^20 Now Saul’s daughter Miʹchal was in love with David, and it was reported to Saul, and this pleased him. ^21 So Saul said: “I will give her to him to serve as a snare to him, so that the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines may come upon him.” Saul then said to David a second time: “You will form a marriage alliance with me[*] today.” ^22 Further, Saul ordered his servants: “Speak to David secretly and say, ‘Look! The king is pleased with you, and all his servants are fond of you. So now form a marriage alliance with the king.’” ^23 When Saul’s servants told David these things, David said: “Is it a trivial matter to you to form a marriage alliance with the king when I am a man poor and lightly esteemed?” ^24 Then Saul’s servants reported to him: “These are the words that David spoke.”

^25 At that Saul said: “This is what you should say to David, ‘The king does not want any bride price except 100 foreskins of the Phi·lisʹtines, to take revenge on the enemies of the king.’” For Saul was scheming to have David fall by the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines. ^26 So his servants reported these words to David, and it was pleasing to David to form a marriage alliance with the king. Before the allotted time, ^27 David went with his men and struck down 200 Phi·lisʹtine men, and David brought the full number of their foreskins to the king, to form a marriage alliance with the king. Therefore, Saul gave him his daughter Miʹchal as a wife. ^28 Saul realized that Jehovah was with David and that his daughter Miʹchal loved him. ^29 This made Saul even more afraid of David, and Saul became an enemy of David for the rest of his life.

^30 The princes of the Phi·lisʹtines would go out to battle, but as often as they went out, David was more successful[*] than all the servants of Saul; and his name was highly esteemed.

^ 1 Sam. 18:1 Or “Jonathan’s soul became bound with David’s soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:1 Or “as his own soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:3 Or “as his own soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:5 Or “acted wisely.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:10 Or “behaved like a prophet.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:13 Lit., “and he went out and came in before the people.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:14 Or “act wisely.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:21 Or “will become my son-in-law.”

^ 1 Sam. 18:30 Or “acted more wisely.”

1 Samuel  19 : 1 - 24

19 Saul later spoke to Jonʹa·than his son and to all his servants about putting David to death. ^2 Since Saul’s son Jonʹa·than was very fond of David, Jonʹa·than told David: “My father Saul wants to have you put to death. Please be on your guard in the morning, and go to a secret place and remain hidden. ^3 I will go out and stand next to my father in the field where you will be. I will talk about you to my father, and if I learn anything, I will be sure to tell you.”

^4 So Jonʹa·than spoke well of David to his father Saul. He said to him: “The king should not sin against his servant David, for he has not sinned against you and what he has done for you has benefited you. ^5 He risked his life[*] to strike down the Phi·lisʹtine, so that Jehovah brought about a great victory[*] for all Israel. You saw it, and you were overjoyed. So why should you sin against innocent blood in having David put to death for no reason?” ^6 Saul listened to Jonʹa·than, and Saul swore: “As surely as Jehovah is living, he will not be put to death.” ^7 Afterward Jonʹa·than called David and told him all these things. So Jonʹa·than brought David to Saul, and he continued to serve him as before.

^8 In time war broke out again, and David went out and fought against the Phi·lisʹtines and struck them down with a great slaughter, and they fled from before him.

^9 And a bad spirit from Jehovah came upon Saul when he was sitting in his house with his spear in his hand, while David was playing music on the harp. ^10 Saul tried to pin David to the wall with the spear, but he eluded Saul, who drove the spear into the wall. David fled and escaped during that night. ^11 Saul later sent messengers to David’s house to watch it and to kill him in the morning, but David’s wife Miʹchal told him: “If you do not escape[*] tonight, tomorrow you will be a dead man.” ^12 Immediately Miʹchal let David down through the window, so that he could run away and escape. ^13 Miʹchal took the teraphim statue[*] and placed it on the bed, and she put a net of goat hair at the place of his head, and she covered it with a garment.

^14 Saul now sent messengers to take David, but she said: “He is sick.” ^15 So Saul sent the messengers to see David and told them: “Bring him to me on his bed to have him put to death.” ^16 When the messengers came in, there was the teraphim statue[*] on the bed and a net of goat hair where his head would have been. ^17 Saul said to Miʹchal: “Why did you trick me like this and send my enemy away so that he could escape?” Miʹchal replied to Saul: “He said to me, ‘Send me away, or I will kill you!’”

^18 Now David had run away and escaped, and he came to Samuel at Raʹmah. He told him all that Saul had done to him. Then he and Samuel went away, and they stayed in Naiʹoth. ^19 In time it was reported to Saul: “Look! David is in Naiʹoth in Raʹmah.” ^20 At once Saul sent messengers to seize David. When they saw the elderly ones of the prophets prophesying and Samuel standing and presiding over them, the spirit of God came to be upon Saul’s messengers, and they began behaving as prophets as well.

^21 When they told it to Saul, he immediately sent other messengers, and they too began behaving as prophets. So Saul sent messengers again, a third group, and they too began behaving as prophets. ^22 Finally he also went to Raʹmah. When he reached the great cistern that is in Seʹcu, he asked: “Where are Samuel and David?” They replied: “There in Naiʹoth in Raʹmah.” ^23 While Saul was on his way from there to Naiʹoth in Raʹmah, the spirit of God came upon him as well, and he walked along behaving as a prophet until he came into Naiʹoth in Raʹmah. ^24 He also stripped off his garments, and he too behaved as a prophet before Samuel, and he lay there naked[*] all that day and all that night. That is why they say: “Is Saul also among the prophets?”

^ 1 Sam. 19:5 Or “put his soul in his hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 19:5 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 19:11 Or “If you do not let your soul escape.”

^ 1 Sam. 19:13 Or “the household god; the idol.”

^ 1 Sam. 19:16 Or “the household god; the idol.”

^ 1 Sam. 19:24 Or “lightly clad.”

1 Samuel  20 : 1 - 42

20 Then David ran away from Naiʹoth in Raʹmah. However, he came to Jonʹa·than and said: “What have I done? What is my offense, and how have I sinned against your father for him to seek my life?”[*] ^2 At this Jonʹa·than said to him: “It is unthinkable! You will not die. Look! My father will not do anything, great or small, without disclosing it to me. Why should my father hide this matter from me? This will not happen.” ^3 But David swore further and said: “Your father surely knows that I have found favor in your eyes and would say, ‘Do not let Jonʹa·than know this or he will be upset.’ But as surely as Jehovah is living and as surely as you are[*] living, there is only a step between me and death!”

^4 Then Jonʹa·than said to David: “Whatever you say,[*] I will do for you.” ^5 David said to Jonʹa·than: “Tomorrow is the new moon, and I am certainly expected to sit with the king to eat; you must send me away, and I will hide in the field until the evening on the third day. ^6 If your father misses me at all, then say, ‘David begged me for permission to go quickly to his city Bethʹle·hem, because there is a yearly sacrifice there for all the family.’ ^7 If his response is, ‘That is fine,’ it means peace to your servant. But if he becomes angry, you can be sure that he is determined to harm me. ^8 Show loyal love to your servant, for you have brought your servant into Jehovah’s covenant with you. But if I am guilty, put me to death yourself. Why turn me over to your father?”

^9 To this Jonʹa·than said: “It is unthinkable to suggest that about you! If I learn that my father is determined to harm you, would I not tell you?” ^10 Then David said to Jonʹa·than: “Who will tell me whether your father gives you a harsh answer?” ^11 Jonʹa·than said to David: “Come, let us go out into the field.” So both of them went out into the field. ^12 And Jonʹa·than said to David: “Let Jehovah the God of Israel be a witness that I will sound out my father about this time tomorrow or by the third day. If he is favorably disposed toward David, will I not then send you word and disclose it to you? ^13 But if my father intends to harm you, may Jehovah do that and more to Jonʹa·than if I do not disclose it to you and send you away in peace. May Jehovah be with you, just as he was with my father. ^14 And will you not show me the loyal love of Jehovah while I am alive and even when I die? ^15 Never withdraw your loyal love from my household, even when Jehovah wipes out all the enemies of David from the face of the earth.” ^16 So Jonʹa·than made a covenant with the house of David, saying, “Jehovah will require it and call David’s enemies to account.” ^17 So Jonʹa·than had David swear again by his love for him, for he loved him as he loved himself.[*]

^18 Jonʹa·than then said to him: “Tomorrow is the new moon, and you will be missed, for your seat will be vacant. ^19 By the third day, you will be missed even more, and you must go to the place where you hid the other day[*] and stay near the stone here. ^20 I will then shoot three arrows to one side of it, as though I were shooting at a target. ^21 When I send the attendant, I will say, ‘Go, find the arrows.’ If I say to the attendant, ‘Look! The arrows are on this side of you, get them,’ then you may come back, for as surely as Jehovah is living, it means everything is peaceful for you and there is no danger. ^22 But if I should say to the boy, ‘Look! The arrows are beyond you,’ then go, for Jehovah has sent you away. ^23 As for the promise that we have made, you and I, may Jehovah be between us forever.”

^24 So David hid in the field. When the new moon came, the king took his seat at the meal to eat. ^25 The king was sitting in his usual seat by the wall. Jonʹa·than was facing him, and Abʹner was sitting at Saul’s side, but David’s place was vacant. ^26 Saul did not say anything that day, for he said to himself: ‘Something has happened so that he is not clean. Yes, he must be unclean.’ ^27 And the day after the new moon, on the second day, David’s place continued vacant. Saul then said to Jonʹa·than his son: “Why has the son of Jesʹse not come to the meal either yesterday or today?” ^28 Jonʹa·than answered Saul: “David begged me for permission to go to Bethʹle·hem. ^29 He said, ‘Please permit me to go, because we have a family sacrifice in the city, and my own brother summoned me. So if I have found favor in your eyes, please let me slip away to see my brothers.’ That is why he has not come to the king’s table.” ^30 Then Saul became enraged with Jonʹa·than, and he said to him: “You son of a rebellious woman, do you think I do not know that you are choosing to side with the son of Jesʹse, to your own shame and to the shame of your mother?[*] ^31 As long as the son of Jesʹse is alive on the earth, you and your kingship will not be firmly established. So now send someone to bring him to me, for he must die.”[*]

^32 However, Jonʹa·than said to Saul his father: “Why should he be put to death? What has he done?” ^33 At that Saul hurled the spear at him to strike him, so Jonʹa·than knew that his father was determined to put David to death. ^34 Jonʹa·than immediately rose up from the table in the heat of anger, and he did not eat any food on the second day after the new moon, for he was upset over David and his own father had humiliated him.

^35 In the morning Jonʹa·than went out to the field for the appointment with David, and a young attendant was with him. ^36 And he said to his attendant: “Please run and find the arrows that I shoot.” The attendant ran, and Jonʹa·than shot the arrow beyond him. ^37 When the attendant reached the place where Jonʹa·than had shot the arrow, Jonʹa·than called out to the attendant: “Is not the arrow beyond you?” ^38 Jonʹa·than called out to the attendant: “Hurry! Go quickly! Do not delay!” And Jonʹa·than’s attendant picked up the arrows and came back to his master. ^39 The attendant did not understand anything about the matter; only Jonʹa·than and David knew what was meant. ^40 Then Jonʹa·than gave his weapons to his attendant and told him: “Go, take them to the city.”

^41 When the attendant left, David rose up from a place nearby that was to the south. Then he fell with his face to the ground and bowed three times, and they kissed each other and wept for each other, but David wept the most. ^42 Jonʹa·than said to David: “Go in peace, since we have both sworn in the name of Jehovah, saying, ‘May Jehovah be between you and me and between your offspring[*] and my offspring[*] forever.’”

Then David rose up and left, and Jonʹa·than went back to the city.

^ 1 Sam. 20:1 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:3 Or “your soul is.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:4 Or “your soul says.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:17 Or “his own soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:19 Lit., “on the working day.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:30 Lit., “to the shame of your mother’s nakedness?”

^ 1 Sam. 20:31 Lit., “for he is a son of death.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:42 Lit., “seed.”

^ 1 Sam. 20:42 Lit., “seed.”

1 Samuel  21 : 1 - 15

21 David later came to Nob to A·himʹe·lech the priest. A·himʹe·lech began to tremble when he met David, and he said to him: “Why are you by yourself and no one is with you?” ^2 David replied to A·himʹe·lech the priest: “The king instructed me to do something, but he said, ‘Do not let anyone know anything about the mission on which I am sending you and about the instructions I have given you.’ I made an appointment with my young men to meet at a certain place. ^3 Now if there are five loaves of bread at your disposal, just give them to me, or whatever is available.” ^4 But the priest answered David: “There is no ordinary bread on hand, but there is holy bread—provided that the young men have kept away from women.”[*] ^5 David answered the priest: “Women have certainly been kept away from us as on previous occasions when I went out on a campaign. If the bodies of the young men are holy even when the mission is ordinary, how much more so today should they be holy!” ^6 So the priest gave him the holy bread, because there was no bread there except the showbread, which had been removed from Jehovah’s presence to be replaced by fresh bread on the day it was taken away.

^7 Now one of Saul’s servants was there on that day, detained before Jehovah. His name was Doʹeg the Eʹdom·ite, the chief of Saul’s shepherds.

^8 David then said to A·himʹe·lech: “Is there a spear or a sword here at your disposal? I did not take my own sword or my weapons with me, because the king’s mission was urgent.” ^9 To this the priest said: “The sword of Go·liʹath the Phi·lisʹtine, whom you struck down in the Valley[*] of Eʹlah, is here, wrapped up in a cloth behind the ephʹod. If you want to take it for yourself, take it, because it is the only one here.” David said: “There is none like it. Give it to me.”

^10 That day David rose up and continued his flight from Saul, and he eventually came to King Aʹchish of Gath. ^11 The servants of Aʹchish said to him: “Is this not David, the king of the land? Is he not the one they sang about when they danced, saying,

‘Saul has struck down his thousands,

And David his tens of thousands’?”

^12 David took these words to heart, and he became very much afraid of King Aʹchish of Gath. ^13 So he disguised his sanity in their presence and acted insane while among them.[*] He was making marks on the doors of the gate and letting his saliva run down his beard. ^14 Finally Aʹchish said to his servants: “You see that this man is crazy! Why bring him to me? ^15 Do I have a shortage of crazy men that I need to have this one acting crazy before me? Should this man enter my house?”

^ 1 Sam. 21:4 Or “have abstained from sexual relations.”

^ 1 Sam. 21:9 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 21:13 Lit., “in their hand.”

1 Samuel  22 : 1 - 23

22 So David went from there, escaping to the cave of A·dulʹlam. When his brothers and his father’s entire house heard of it, they went down there to him. ^2 And all those who were in trouble and in debt and who had a grievance[*] gathered to him, and he became their chief. There were about 400 men with him.

^3 David later went from there to Mizʹpeh in Moʹab and said to the king of Moʹab: “Please let my father and mother stay with you until I know what God will do for me.” ^4 So he left them with the king of Moʹab, and they stayed with him the whole time that David was in the stronghold.

^5 In time Gad the prophet said to David: “Do not stay in the stronghold. Go from there into the land of Judah.” So David left and went into the forest of Heʹreth.

^6 Saul heard that David and the men with him had been found. Saul was then sitting in Gibʹe·ah under the tamarisk tree on the high place with his spear in his hand, and all his servants were stationed around him. ^7 Then Saul said to his servants stationed around him: “Listen, please, you Benʹja·min·ites. Will the son of Jesʹse also give fields and vineyards to all of you? Will he appoint all of you as chiefs of thousands and chiefs of hundreds? ^8 All of you have conspired against me! No one informed me when my own son made a covenant with the son of Jesʹse! Not one of you has sympathy for me and informs me that my own son has incited my own servant against me to ambush me, as is now the case.”

^9 Then Doʹeg the Eʹdom·ite, who was stationed there over the servants of Saul, answered: “I saw the son of Jesʹse come to Nob to A·himʹe·lech the son of A·hiʹtub. ^10 And he inquired of Jehovah for him and gave him provisions. He even gave him the sword of Go·liʹath the Phi·lisʹtine.” ^11 At once the king sent for A·himʹe·lech son of A·hiʹtub the priest and all the priests of his father’s house, who were in Nob. So all of them came to the king.

^12 Saul now said: “Listen, please, you son of A·hiʹtub!” to which he replied: “Here I am, my lord.” ^13 Saul said to him: “Why have you conspired against me, you and the son of Jesʹse, by giving him bread and a sword and by making an inquiry of God for him? He opposes me and waits in ambush, as is now the case.” ^14 At this A·himʹe·lech answered the king: “Who among all your servants is as trustworthy[*] as David? He is the king’s son-in-law and a chief over your bodyguard and honored in your house. ^15 Was today the first time I inquired of God for him? What you are saying is unthinkable on my part! Do not let the king hold anything against his servant and against my father’s entire house, for your servant did not know a single thing about any of this.”

^16 But the king said: “You will surely die, A·himʹe·lech, you along with all your father’s house.” ^17 With that the king said to the guards[*] stationed around him: “Turn and kill the priests of Jehovah, because they have sided with David! They knew that he was a runaway, and they did not inform me!” But the king’s servants did not want to lift their hands to assault the priests of Jehovah. ^18 Then the king said to Doʹeg: “You turn and assault the priests!” Immediately Doʹeg the Eʹdom·ite went and assaulted the priests himself. He killed on that day 85 men wearing the linen ephʹod. ^19 He also struck Nob, the city of the priests, with the sword; man as well as woman, child as well as infant, bull, donkey, and sheep, he put to the sword.

^20 However, one son of A·himʹe·lech the son of A·hiʹtub, whose name was A·biʹa·thar, escaped and ran away to follow David. ^21 A·biʹa·thar told David: “Saul has killed the priests of Jehovah.” ^22 At this David said to A·biʹa·thar: “I knew on that day, when Doʹeg the Eʹdom·ite was there, that he would be sure to tell Saul. I am personally responsible for the death of everyone[*] in your father’s house. ^23 Stay with me. Do not be afraid, for whoever seeks your life[*] seeks my life;[*] you are under my protection.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:2 Or “were bitter of soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:14 Or “faithful.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:17 Lit., “runners.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:22 Or “every soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:23 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 22:23 Or “soul.”

1 Samuel  23 : 1 - 29

23 In time David was told: “The Phi·lisʹtines are fighting against Keiʹlah, and they are raiding the threshing floors.” ^2 So David inquired of Jehovah: “Should I go and strike down these Phi·lisʹtines?” Jehovah said to David: “Go, strike down the Phi·lisʹtines and rescue Keiʹlah.” ^3 But the men of David said to him: “Look! We are afraid while here in Judah; how much more so if we go to Keiʹlah against the battle line of the Phi·lisʹtines!” ^4 So David inquired once again of Jehovah. Jehovah now answered him: “Rise up; go down to Keiʹlah because I will give the Phi·lisʹtines into your hand.” ^5 So David went with his men to Keiʹlah and fought against the Phi·lisʹtines; he carried off their livestock and struck them down with a great slaughter, and David rescued the inhabitants of Keiʹlah.

^6 Now when A·biʹa·thar the son of A·himʹe·lech ran away to David at Keiʹlah, he had an ephʹod with him. ^7 Saul was told: “David has come to Keiʹlah.” Then Saul said: “God has handed him over to me,[*] for he has trapped himself by entering a city with gates and bars.” ^8 So Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Keiʹlah and besiege David and his men. ^9 When David learned that Saul was plotting against him, he said to A·biʹa·thar the priest: “Bring the ephʹod here.” ^10 Then David said: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, your servant has indeed heard that Saul intends to come to Keiʹlah to destroy the city because of me. ^11 Will the leaders[*] of Keiʹlah surrender me into his hand? Will Saul come down as your servant has heard? O Jehovah the God of Israel, please tell your servant.” To this Jehovah said: “He will come down.” ^12 David asked: “Will the leaders of Keiʹlah surrender me and my men into Saul’s hand?” Jehovah replied: “They will surrender you.”

^13 At once David rose up with his men, about 600 in number, and they left Keiʹlah and moved about wherever they could. When Saul was told that David had escaped from Keiʹlah, he did not go out after him. ^14 David stayed in the wilderness in places difficult to approach, in the mountainous region of the wilderness of Ziph. Saul searched for him constantly, but Jehovah did not give him into his hand. ^15 David was aware that[*] Saul had gone out to seek his life[*] while David was in the wilderness of Ziph at Hoʹresh.

^16 Jonʹa·than the son of Saul now went out to David at Hoʹresh, and he helped him find strength[*] in Jehovah. ^17 He said to him: “Do not be afraid, for my father Saul will not find you; you will be king over Israel, and I will become second to you; and my father Saul also knows that.” ^18 Then the two of them made a covenant before Jehovah, and David stayed in Hoʹresh, and Jonʹa·than went to his home.

^19 The men of Ziph later went up to Saul at Gibʹe·ah and said: “Is not David hiding near us in the places difficult to approach at Hoʹresh, on the hill of Hach·iʹlah, which is south[*] of Je·shiʹmon?[*] ^20 Whenever it pleases you[*] to come down, O king, come, and we will surrender him into the hand of the king.” ^21 At this Saul said: “May you be blessed by Jehovah, for you have shown compassion to me. ^22 Please go and try to find out exactly where he is and who saw him there, for I have been told that he is very cunning. ^23 Carefully ascertain where all his hiding places are and return to me with the evidence. I will then go with you, and if he is in the land, I will search him out among all the thousands[*] of Judah.”

^24 So they left and went to Ziph ahead of Saul, while David and his men were in the wilderness of Maʹon, in the Arʹa·bah to the south of Je·shiʹmon. ^25 Then Saul came with his men to look for him. When David was told, he at once went down to the crag and stayed in the wilderness of Maʹon. When Saul heard this, he chased after David into the wilderness of Maʹon. ^26 As Saul came to one side of the mountain, David and his men were on the other side of the mountain. David was hurrying to get away from Saul, but Saul and his men were closing in on David and his men to capture them. ^27 But a messenger came to Saul, saying: “Come quickly, for the Phi·lisʹtines have made a raid on the land!” ^28 At that Saul stopped chasing after David and went to confront the Phi·lisʹtines. That is why that place was named the Crag of the Divisions.

^29 Then David made his way up from there and stayed in the places difficult to approach at En-gedʹi.

^ 1 Sam. 23:7 Lit., “sold him into my hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:11 Or possibly, “landowners.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:15 Or possibly, “was fearful because.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:15 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:16 Lit., “he strengthened his hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:19 Lit., “on the right side.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:19 Or possibly, “the desert; the wilderness.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:20 Or “your soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 23:23 Or “clans.”

1 Samuel  24 : 1 - 22

24 As soon as Saul returned from pursuing the Phi·lisʹtines, they told him: “Look! David is in the wilderness of En-gedʹi.”

^2 So Saul took 3,000 men chosen from all Israel and went to look for David and his men on the rocky cliffs of the mountain goats. ^3 Saul came to the stone sheepfolds along the road, where there was a cave, and he went in to relieve himself[*] while David and his men were sitting in the recesses at the back of the cave. ^4 David’s men said to him: “This is the day on which Jehovah is saying to you, ‘Look! I am giving your enemy into your hand, and you can do to him whatever seems good to you.’” So David rose up and quietly cut off the edge of Saul’s sleeveless coat. ^5 But afterward David’s heart[*] kept striking him because he had cut off the edge of Saul’s sleeveless coat. ^6 He said to his men: “It is unthinkable from Jehovah’s standpoint that I should do such a thing to my lord, the anointed of Jehovah, by lifting my hand against him, for he is the anointed of Jehovah.” ^7 So David restrained[*] his men with these words, and he did not allow them to attack Saul. As for Saul, he rose up from the cave and went on his way.

^8 Then David got up and went out from the cave and called out after Saul: “My lord the king!” When Saul looked behind him, David bowed down low with his face to the ground and prostrated himself. ^9 David said to Saul: “Why do you listen to the words of men who say, ‘Look! David is seeking to harm you’? ^10 This very day your own eyes have seen how Jehovah gave you into my hand in the cave. But when someone said to kill you, I had pity on you and said, ‘I will not lift my hand against my lord, for he is the anointed of Jehovah.’ ^11 And look, my father, yes, see the edge of your sleeveless coat in my hand; for when I cut off the edge of your sleeveless coat, I did not kill you. You can now see and understand that I do not intend to harm you or to rebel, and I have not sinned against you, whereas you are hunting me down to take my life.[*] ^12 May Jehovah judge between you and me, and may Jehovah take vengeance on you for me, but my hand will not come against you. ^13 Just as the ancient proverb says, ‘From the wicked comes wickedness,’ but my hand will not come against you. ^14 After whom has the king of Israel gone out? Whom are you chasing? A dead dog? A single flea? ^15 May Jehovah be the judge, and he will judge between you and me, and he will see and will plead my case and judge me and rescue me from your hand.”

^16 At the moment that David finished speaking these words to him, Saul said: “Is this your voice, my son David?” And Saul began to weep loudly. ^17 He said to David: “You are more righteous than I am, for you have treated me well and I have repaid you with evil. ^18 Yes, today you have told me of the good you did by not killing me when Jehovah surrendered me into your hand. ^19 For what man finds his enemy and sends him on his way unharmed? Jehovah will reward you with good because of what you have done for me today. ^20 And now look! I know that you will surely rule as king and that in your hand the kingdom of Israel will endure. ^21 Now swear to me by Jehovah that you will not wipe out my descendants[*] after me and that you will not annihilate my name out of my father’s house.” ^22 So David swore to Saul, after which Saul went home. But David and his men went up to the stronghold.

^ 1 Sam. 24:3 Lit., “to cover his feet.”

^ 1 Sam. 24:5 Or “conscience.”

^ 1 Sam. 24:7 Or possibly, “dispersed.”

^ 1 Sam. 24:11 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 24:21 Lit., “seed.”

1 Samuel  25 : 1 - 44

25 In time Samuel died; and all Israel gathered together to mourn for him and to bury him at his house in Raʹmah. Then David rose and went down to the wilderness of Paʹran.

^2 Now there was a man in Maʹon whose work was in Carʹmel.[*] The man was very wealthy; he had 3,000 sheep and 1,000 goats, and he was then shearing his sheep at Carʹmel. ^3 The man’s name was Naʹbal, and his wife’s name was Abʹi·gail. The wife was discerning and beautiful, but the husband, a Caʹleb·ite, was harsh, and he behaved badly. ^4 David heard in the wilderness that Naʹbal was shearing his sheep. ^5 So David sent ten young men to him, and David told the young men: “Go up to Carʹmel, and when you come to Naʹbal, ask him in my name about his welfare. ^6 Then say, ‘May you live long and may you be well[*] and may your household be well and may all that you have be well. ^7 Now I hear that you are doing your shearing. When your shepherds were with us, we did not harm them, and they found nothing missing the whole time they were in Carʹmel. ^8 Ask your young men, and they will tell you. May my young men find favor in your eyes, because we have come at a joyous time.[*] Please give to your servants and to your son David whatever you can spare.’”

^9 So David’s young men went and told all of this to Naʹbal in David’s name. When they finished, ^10 Naʹbal answered David’s servants: “Who is David, and who is the son of Jesʹse? Nowadays many servants are breaking away from their masters. ^11 Do I have to take my bread and my water and the meat that I butchered for my shearers and give it to men who come from who knows where?”

^12 At that David’s young men returned and reported all these words to him. ^13 David immediately said to his men: “Everyone strap on your sword!” So they all strapped on their swords, and David also strapped on his own sword, and about 400 men went up with David, while 200 men stayed with the baggage.

^14 Meanwhile, one of the servants reported to Abʹi·gail, Naʹbal’s wife: “Look! David sent messengers from the wilderness to wish our master well, but he screamed insults at them. ^15 Those men were very good to us. They never harmed us, and we did not miss a single thing the whole time we were together with them in the fields. ^16 They were like a protective wall around us, both by night and by day, the whole time we were with them shepherding the flock. ^17 Now decide what you are going to do, for disaster has been determined against our master and against all his house, and he is such a worthless[*] man that no one can speak to him.”

^18 So Abʹi·gail quickly took 200 loaves of bread, two large jars of wine, five dressed sheep, five seah measures[*] of roasted grain, 100 cakes of raisins, and 200 cakes of pressed figs and put all of it on the donkeys. ^19 Then she said to her servants: “Go on ahead of me; I will follow you.” But she said nothing to her husband Naʹbal.

^20 While she was riding on the donkey and going down under cover of the mountain, just then David and his men were coming down toward her, and she met them. ^21 Now David had been saying: “It was for nothing that I guarded everything that belongs to this fellow in the wilderness. Not a single thing belonging to him went missing, and yet he repays me evil for good. ^22 May God do the same and more to the enemies of David[*] if I allow a single male[*] of his to survive until the morning.”

^23 When Abʹi·gail caught sight of David, she hurried down off the donkey and threw herself facedown before David, bowing to the ground. ^24 She then fell at his feet and said: “My lord, let the blame be on me; let your servant girl speak to you, and listen to the words of your servant girl. ^25 Please, do not let my lord pay attention to this worthless Naʹbal, for he is just like his name. Naʹbal[*] is his name, and senselessness is with him. But I, your servant girl, did not see my lord’s young men whom you sent. ^26 And now, my lord, as surely as Jehovah is living and as you are[*] living, it is Jehovah who has held you back from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge[*] with your own hand. May your enemies and those seeking injury to my lord become like Naʹbal. ^27 Now let this gift[*] that your servant girl has brought to my lord be given to the young men who are following my lord. ^28 Pardon, please, the transgression of your servant girl, for Jehovah will without fail make for my lord a lasting house, because my lord is fighting the wars of Jehovah, and no evil has been found in you all your days. ^29 When someone rises up to pursue you and seeks your life,[*] the life[*] of my lord will be wrapped securely in the bag of life with Jehovah your God, but the lives[*] of your enemies he will hurl away like stones from a sling.[*] ^30 And when Jehovah has done for my lord all the good things he has promised and he appoints you as leader over Israel, ^31 you will have no remorse or regret[*] in your heart for shedding blood without cause and for letting the hand of my lord take revenge.[*] When Jehovah confers good upon my lord, remember your servant girl.”

^32 At this David said to Abʹi·gail: “Praise Jehovah the God of Israel, who sent you this day to meet me! ^33 And blessed be your good sense! May you be blessed for restraining me this day from incurring bloodguilt and from taking revenge[*] with my own hands. ^34 Otherwise, as surely as Jehovah the God of Israel who held me back from harming you is living, if you had not come quickly to meet me, by morning there would not have remained a single male[*] belonging to Naʹbal.” ^35 With that David accepted from her what she had brought him and said to her: “Go up in peace to your house. See, I have listened to you, and I will grant your request.”

^36 Abʹi·gail later went back to Naʹbal, who was feasting like a king in his house, and Naʹbal[*] was in a good mood and was as drunk as could be. She did not tell him a single thing until the morning light. ^37 In the morning, when Naʹbal was sober, his wife told him these things. And his heart became like a dead man’s, and he lay paralyzed like a stone. ^38 About ten days later, Jehovah struck Naʹbal, and he died.

^39 When David heard that Naʹbal had died, he said: “Praise Jehovah, who has pleaded my case of reproach from Naʹbal and has kept his servant from doing anything bad, and Jehovah has brought the badness of Naʹbal back on his own head!” Then David sent word to propose to Abʹi·gail to take her as his wife. ^40 So David’s servants came to Abʹi·gail at Carʹmel and said to her: “David has sent us to you to take you as his wife.” ^41 She immediately rose up and bowed with her face to the ground and said: “Here is your slave as a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.” ^42 Then Abʹi·gail quickly rose up and rode on her donkey with five of her female servants walking behind her; she accompanied the messengers of David and became his wife.

^43 David had also married A·hinʹo·am from Jezʹre·el, and both women became his wives.

^44 But Saul had given his daughter Miʹchal, David’s wife, to Palʹti the son of Laʹish, who was from Galʹlim.

^ 1 Sam. 25:2 A city in Judah; not the same as Mount Carmel.

^ 1 Sam. 25:6 Or “may you have peace.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:8 Lit., “a good day.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:17 Or “good-for-nothing.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:18 A seah equaled 7.33 L (6.66 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Sam. 25:22 Or possibly, “to David.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:22 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Sam. 25:25 Meaning “Senseless; Stupid.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:26 Or “your soul is.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:26 Or “bringing salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:27 Lit., “blessing.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:29 Or “as from the hollow of a sling.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:31 Lit., “staggering or stumbling.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:31 Or “bring salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:33 Or “bringing salvation.”

^ 1 Sam. 25:34 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Sam. 25:36 Lit., “Nabal’s heart.”

1 Samuel  26 : 1 - 25

26 In time the men of Ziph came to Saul at Gibʹe·ah, saying: “Is David not hiding on the hill of Hach·iʹlah facing Je·shiʹmon?”[*] ^2 So Saul rose up and went down to the wilderness of Ziph with 3,000 chosen men of Israel to look for David in the wilderness of Ziph. ^3 Saul camped on the hill of Hach·iʹlah, which faces Je·shiʹmon, by the road. David was then living in the wilderness, and he learned that Saul had come into the wilderness after him. ^4 So David sent spies to verify that Saul had indeed come. ^5 David later went to the place where Saul had encamped, and David saw the place where Saul and Abʹner the son of Ner, the chief of his army, were lying asleep; Saul lay asleep in the camp enclosure with the troops camping all around him. ^6 Then David said to A·himʹe·lech the Hitʹtite and A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah, the brother of Joʹab: “Who will go down with me into the camp to Saul?” A·bishʹai replied: “I will go down with you.” ^7 So David and A·bishʹai made their way to the troops by night, and they found Saul lying asleep in the camp enclosure with his spear stuck into the ground next to his head; Abʹner and the troops were lying all around him.

^8 A·bishʹai now said to David: “Today God has surrendered your enemy into your hand. And now, please, let me pin him to the ground with the spear just once, and I will not need to do it twice.” ^9 However, David said to A·bishʹai: “Do not harm him, for who can lift his hand against the anointed of Jehovah and remain innocent?” ^10 David continued: “As surely as Jehovah is living, Jehovah himself will strike him down, or his day will come and he will die, or he will go down into battle and perish. ^11 It is unthinkable from Jehovah’s standpoint for me to lift my hand against the anointed of Jehovah! So now take, please, the spear next to his head and the water jug, and let us be on our way.” ^12 So David took the spear and the water jug from next to Saul’s head, and they went away. No one saw or noticed them or woke up, for they were all asleep, because a deep sleep from Jehovah had fallen upon them. ^13 Then David crossed to the other side and stood on the top of the mountain some distance away, with a considerable space between them.

^14 David called out to the troops and to Abʹner the son of Ner, saying: “Abʹner, will you not answer?” Abʹner answered: “Who are you who calls to the king?” ^15 David said to Abʹner: “Are you not a man? And who is like you in Israel? So why did you not keep watch over your lord the king? For one of the soldiers came in to do away with your lord the king. ^16 What you have done is not good. As surely as Jehovah is living, you deserve to die, because you have not kept watch over your lord, the anointed of Jehovah. Now look around! Where are the king’s spear and the water jug that were next to his head?”

^17 Then Saul recognized the voice of David and said: “Is this your voice, my son David?” David replied: “It is my voice, my lord the king.” ^18 He added: “Why is my lord chasing after his servant, for what have I done, and what am I guilty of? ^19 My lord the king, please, listen to the words of his servant: If it is Jehovah who incited you against me, let him accept[*] my grain offering. But if men have incited you, they are cursed before Jehovah, because they have driven me away today from being united with Jehovah’s inheritance, saying, ‘Go, serve other gods!’ ^20 And now do not let my blood fall to the ground away from the presence of Jehovah, for the king of Israel has gone out to look for a single flea, as if he were chasing a partridge on the mountains.”

^21 In turn Saul said: “I have sinned. Come back, my son David, for I will do you no more harm, because you regarded my life[*] as precious this day. Yes, I have acted foolishly and have made a terrible mistake.” ^22 David answered: “Here is the spear of the king. Let one of the young men come over and take it. ^23 It is Jehovah who will repay each one for his own righteousness and his own faithfulness, for today Jehovah gave you into my hand, but I was unwilling to lift my hand against the anointed of Jehovah. ^24 Look! Just as your life[*] was precious to me this day, so may my life[*] be precious in the eyes of Jehovah, and may he rescue me out of all distress.” ^25 Saul replied to David: “May you be blessed, my son David. You will surely do great things, and you will surely prevail.” Then David went on his way, and Saul returned to his place.

^ 1 Sam. 26:1 Or possibly, “the desert; the wilderness.”

^ 1 Sam. 26:19 Lit., “smell.”

^ 1 Sam. 26:21 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 26:24 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 26:24 Or “soul.”

1 Samuel  27 : 1 - 12

27 However, David said in his heart: “One day I will perish by Saul’s hand. The best thing for me is to escape to the land of the Phi·lisʹtines; then Saul will give up looking for me in all the territory of Israel, and I will escape from his hand.” ^2 So David rose up with the 600 men who were with him and went over to Aʹchish the son of Maʹoch, the king of Gath. ^3 David stayed with Aʹchish in Gath, he and his men, each man with his household. With David were his two wives, A·hinʹo·am of Jezʹre·el and Abʹi·gail the Carʹmel·ite, Naʹbal’s widow. ^4 When report was made to Saul that David had run away to Gath, he stopped searching for him.

^5 Then David said to Aʹchish: “If I have found favor in your eyes, let them give me a place in one of the cities of the countryside, so that I may live there. Why should your servant live in the royal city with you?” ^6 So Aʹchish gave him Zikʹlag on that day. That is why Zikʹlag belongs to the kings of Judah down to this day.

^7 The length of time[*] that David lived in the countryside of the Phi·lisʹtines was a year and four months. ^8 David would go up with his men to raid the Geshʹur·ites, the Girʹzites, and the A·malʹek·ites, for they were inhabiting the land that extended from Teʹlam as far as Shur and down to the land of Egypt. ^9 When David would attack the land, he preserved neither man nor woman alive, but he took the flocks, herds, donkeys, camels, and clothing, after which he would return to Aʹchish. ^10 Then Aʹchish would ask: “Where did you make a raid today?” David would reply: “Against the south[*] of Judah” or “Against the south of the Je·rahʹme·el·ites” or “Against the south of the Kenʹites.” ^11 David did not spare alive any man or woman to be brought to Gath, saying: “That they may not tell them about us and say, ‘This is what David did.’” (And that was his practice the whole time he lived in the countryside of the Phi·lisʹtines.) ^12 So Aʹchish believed David, saying to himself: ‘He has certainly become a stench among his people Israel, so he will always be my servant.’

^ 1 Sam. 27:7 Lit., “number of days.”

^ 1 Sam. 27:10 Or “the Negeb.”

1 Samuel  28 : 1 - 25

28 In those days the Phi·lisʹtines assembled their armies for war against Israel. So Aʹchish said to David: “You know, of course, that you and your men will go out into battle with me.” ^2 At that David said to Aʹchish: “You surely know what your servant will do.” Aʹchish said to David: “That is why I will appoint you as my permanent bodyguard.”[*]

^3 Now Samuel had died, and all Israel had mourned him and had buried him in Raʹmah, his own city. And Saul had removed the spirit mediums and the fortune-tellers from the land.

^4 The Phi·lisʹtines assembled and went and set up camp in Shuʹnem. So Saul assembled all Israel, and they set up camp in Gil·boʹa. ^5 When Saul saw the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines, he was afraid, and his heart trembled greatly. ^6 Although Saul would inquire of Jehovah, Jehovah never answered him, either in dreams or by the Uʹrim or through the prophets. ^7 Finally Saul said to his servants: “Find me a woman who is a spirit medium, and I will go and consult her.” His servants replied: “Look! There is a woman who is a spirit medium in En-dor.”

^8 So Saul disguised himself and put on other garments and went to the woman by night with two of his men. He said: “Use divination, please, by acting as a spirit medium, and bring up for me the one whom I designate to you.” ^9 However, the woman said to him: “You must know what Saul did, how he removed the spirit mediums and the fortune-tellers from the land. Why, then, are you trying to trap me[*] to have me put to death?” ^10 Saul then swore to her by Jehovah, saying: “As surely as Jehovah is alive, you will not incur any guilt in this matter!” ^11 At this the woman said: “Whom should I bring up for you?” He replied: “Bring up Samuel for me.” ^12 When the woman saw “Samuel,”[*] she cried out at the top of her voice and said to Saul: “Why did you trick me? You are Saul!” ^13 The king said to her: “Do not be afraid, but what do you see?” The woman replied to Saul: “I see one like a god coming up out of the earth.” ^14 At once he asked her: “What does he look like?” to which she said: “It is an old man coming up, and he is clothed in a sleeveless coat.” At that Saul realized that it was “Samuel,” and he bowed low with his face to the ground and prostrated himself.

^15 Then “Samuel” said to Saul: “Why have you disturbed me by having me brought up?” Saul replied: “I am in great trouble. The Phi·lisʹtines are fighting against me, and God has departed from me and no longer answers me, either through the prophets or in dreams; so that is why I am calling on you to let me know what I should do.”

^16 And “Samuel” said: “Why do you inquire of me now that Jehovah has departed from you and has become your adversary? ^17 Jehovah will do for himself what he foretold through me: Jehovah will rip the kingdom out of your hands and give it to one of your fellow men, David. ^18 Because you did not obey the voice of Jehovah and you did not execute his burning anger against the A·malʹek·ites, that is why Jehovah is doing this to you this day. ^19 Jehovah will also give both Israel and you into the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines, and tomorrow you and your sons will be with me. Jehovah will also give the army of Israel into the hands of the Phi·lisʹtines.”

^20 At once Saul fell full length on the ground and became very much afraid because of “Samuel’s” words. And there was no strength left in him, because he had not eaten food all day and all night. ^21 When the woman came to Saul and saw that he had been greatly disturbed, she said to him: “Here your servant has obeyed what you said, and I risked my life[*] and did what you told me to do. ^22 Now, please, listen to what your servant has to say. Let me set before you a piece of bread; then eat so that you will have some strength to go on your way.” ^23 But he refused and said: “I am not going to eat.” However, his servants and also the woman kept urging him. Finally he listened to them and got up from the ground and sat on the bed. ^24 The woman had a fattened calf in the house, so she quickly slaughtered[*] it and took flour and kneaded dough and baked it into unleavened bread. ^25 She served them to Saul and his servants, and they ate. After that they rose up and left during the night.

^ 1 Sam. 28:2 Lit., “as guardian of my head all the days.”

^ 1 Sam. 28:9 Or “my soul.”

^ 1 Sam. 28:12 Or “what appeared to be Samuel.”

^ 1 Sam. 28:21 Or “took my soul in my hand.”

^ 1 Sam. 28:24 Or “sacrificed.”

1 Samuel  29 : 1 - 11

29 The Phi·lisʹtines assembled all their armies at Aʹphek, while the Israelites were camping by the spring in Jezʹre·el. ^2 And the lords of the Phi·lisʹtines were passing by with their hundreds and their thousands, and David and his men were marching at the rear with Aʹchish. ^3 But the princes of the Phi·lisʹtines said: “Why are these Hebrews here?” Aʹchish replied to the princes of the Phi·lisʹtines: “This is David, the servant of King Saul of Israel, who has been with me for a year or more. I have not found any fault in him from the day he deserted to me until today.” ^4 But the princes of the Phi·lisʹtines became indignant at him, and they said to him: “Make the man go back. Let him return to the place where you assigned him. Do not let him go down with us into the battle, so that he will not turn against us during the battle. For what better way to put himself in favor with his lord than with the heads of our men? ^5 Is this not the David about whom they sang when they danced, saying:

‘Saul has struck down his thousands,

And David his tens of thousands’?”

^6 So Aʹchish summoned David and said to him: “As surely as Jehovah is living, you are upright, and I am pleased to have you go on the campaign with my army, for I have not found any fault with you from the day you came to me until today. But the lords do not trust you. ^7 So return in peace, and do not do anything to displease the lords of the Phi·lisʹtines.” ^8 However, David said to Aʹchish: “Why, what have I done? What fault have you found in your servant from the day that I came to you until today? Why should I not come with you and fight against the enemies of my lord the king?” ^9 Aʹchish answered David: “From my standpoint, you have been as good as an angel of God. But the princes of the Phi·lisʹtines have said, ‘Do not let him go up with us into the battle.’ ^10 Now get up early in the morning with the servants of your lord who came with you; rise up and leave early in the morning as soon as it is light.”

^11 So David and his men rose up early in the morning to return to the land of the Phi·lisʹtines, and the Phi·lisʹtines went up to Jezʹre·el.

1 Samuel  30 : 1 - 31

30 When David and his men came to Zikʹlag on the third day, the A·malʹek·ites had made a raid on the south[*] and on Zikʹlag, and they had attacked Zikʹlag and burned it with fire. ^2 They had taken captive the women and all who were in it, from the smallest to the greatest. They had not killed anyone, but they had carried them off and gone on their way. ^3 When David and his men came to the city, they found it burned down, and their wives and their sons and their daughters had been carried off captive. ^4 So David and the men with him began weeping loudly until they had no strength left to weep. ^5 David’s two wives had also been carried off captive, A·hinʹo·am of Jezʹre·el and Abʹi·gail the widow of Naʹbal the Carʹmel·ite. ^6 David was very distressed, because the men were talking of stoning him, for all the men[*] had become very bitter over the loss of their sons and daughters. But David strengthened himself by Jehovah his God.

^7 David then said to A·biʹa·thar the priest, the son of A·himʹe·lech: “Please bring the ephʹod here.” So A·biʹa·thar brought the ephʹod to David. ^8 David inquired of Jehovah: “Should I chase after this marauder band? Will I overtake them?” At this He said to him: “Go in pursuit, for you will certainly overtake them, and you will make the rescue.”

^9 David immediately set out with the 600 men who were with him, and they went on as far as the Wadi[*] Beʹsor, where some of the men stayed behind. ^10 David kept up the chase with 400 men, but the 200 men who were too tired to cross the Wadi Beʹsor stayed behind.

^11 They found an Egyptian man in the field and took him to David. They gave him food to eat and water to drink, ^12 as well as a slice of a cake of pressed figs and two cakes of raisins. After he ate, he regained his strength,[*] for he had not eaten any food or drunk any water for three days and three nights. ^13 David now asked him: “To whom do you belong, and where are you from?” to which he said: “I am an Egyptian attendant, a slave of an A·malʹek·ite man, but my master left me because I got sick three days ago. ^14 We made a raid on the south[*] of the Cherʹe·thites and on the territory of Judah and on the south[*] of Caʹleb, and Zikʹlag we burned with fire.” ^15 At this David said to him: “Will you lead me down to this marauder band?” He replied: “If you swear to me by God that you will not put me to death and that you will not hand me over to my master, I will lead you down to this marauder band.”

^16 So he led him down to where they were spread out all over the land, eating and drinking and celebrating because of all the great spoil that they had taken from the land of the Phi·lisʹtines and the land of Judah. ^17 Then David struck them down from the morning darkness until the following evening; not a man escaped except 400 men who fled on camels. ^18 David recovered all that the A·malʹek·ites had taken, and David rescued his two wives. ^19 Nothing of theirs was missing, from the smallest to the greatest. They recovered their sons and daughters and the spoil; David recovered everything that they had taken. ^20 So David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drove before their own livestock. They said: “This is David’s spoil.”

^21 Then David came to the 200 men who had been too tired to go along with David and who had stayed behind by the Wadi Beʹsor, and they came out to meet David and the people with him. When David came near to the men, he asked them how they were. ^22 However, every bad and worthless man among those who had gone with David said: “Since they did not go with us, we will not give them any of the spoil that we recovered except that each one may take his wife and his sons and go away.” ^23 But David said: “You must not do this, my brothers, with what Jehovah has given us. He protected us and gave into our hand the marauder band that came against us. ^24 Who would agree with you on this? The share of the one who went down into the battle will be the same as the share of the one who sat by the baggage. All will have a share together.” ^25 And from that day forward, he kept it set as a regulation and a rule for Israel down to this day.

^26 When David returned to Zikʹlag, he sent some of the spoil to the elders of Judah who were his friends, saying: “Here is a gift[*] for you from the spoil of Jehovah’s enemies.” ^27 He sent it to those who were in Bethʹel, to those in Raʹmoth of the Negʹeb,[*] to those in Jatʹtir, ^28 to those in A·roʹer, to those in Siphʹmoth, to those in Esh·te·moʹa, ^29 to those in Raʹcal, to those in the cities of the Je·rahʹme·el·ites, to those in the cities of the Kenʹites, ^30 to those in Horʹmah, to those in Borʹa·shan, to those in Aʹthach, ^31 to those in Hebʹron, and to all the places that David and his men had frequented.

^ 1 Sam. 30:1 Or “the Negeb.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:6 Or “for the souls of all the people.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:9 See Glossary.

^ 1 Sam. 30:12 Lit., “his spirit returned to him.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:14 Or “the Negeb.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:14 Or “the Negeb.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:26 Lit., “blessing.”

^ 1 Sam. 30:27 Or “the south.”

1 Samuel  31 : 1 - 13

31 Now the Phi·lisʹtines were fighting against Israel. And the men of Israel fled from before the Phi·lisʹtines, and many fell slain on Mount Gil·boʹa. ^2 The Phi·lisʹtines kept in close range of Saul and his sons, and the Phi·lisʹtines struck down Jonʹa·than, A·binʹa·dab, and Malʹchi-shuʹa, Saul’s sons. ^3 The fighting grew fierce against Saul, and the archers found him, and he was severely wounded by the archers. ^4 Then Saul said to his armor-bearer: “Draw your sword and run me through with it, so that these uncircumcised men may not come and run me through and deal ruthlessly[*] with me.” But his armor-bearer was unwilling, because he was very much afraid. So Saul took the sword and fell on it. ^5 When his armor-bearer saw that Saul was dead, he too fell on his own sword and died with him. ^6 Thus Saul, his three sons, his armor-bearer, and all his men died together on that day. ^7 When the people of Israel who were in the region of the valley[*] and in the region of the Jordan saw that the men of Israel had fled and that Saul and his sons had died, they began to abandon the cities and flee; the Phi·lisʹtines then came and occupied them.

^8 The next day, when the Phi·lisʹtines came to strip the slain, they found Saul and his three sons fallen on Mount Gil·boʹa. ^9 So they cut off his head and stripped off his armor and sent word throughout the land of the Phi·lisʹtines to spread the news in the houses[*] of their idols and among the people. ^10 Then they put his armor in the house of the Ashʹto·reth images and fastened his corpse to the wall of Beth-shan. ^11 When the inhabitants of Jaʹbesh-gilʹe·ad heard what the Phi·lisʹtines had done to Saul, ^12 all the warriors rose and traveled all night and took the bodies of Saul and his sons off the wall of Beth-shan. They returned to Jaʹbesh and burned them there. ^13 Then they took their bones and buried them under the tamarisk tree in Jaʹbesh, and they fasted for seven days.

^ 1 Sam. 31:4 Or “abusively.”

^ 1 Sam. 31:7 Or “low plain.”

^ 1 Sam. 31:9 Or “temples.”

2 Samuel  1 : 1 - 27

THE SECOND OF SAMUEL

1 After Saul’s death, when David had returned from defeating[*] the A·malʹek·ites, David stayed at Zikʹlag for two days. ^2 On the third day, a man came from the camp of Saul with his garments ripped apart and dirt on his head. When he approached David, he fell down to the ground and prostrated himself.

^3 David asked him: “Where are you coming from?” He replied: “I have escaped from the camp of Israel.” ^4 David asked him: “How did things turn out? Please tell me.” To this he said: “The people have fled from the battle and many have fallen and died. Even Saul and his son Jonʹa·than have died.” ^5 Then David asked the young man who brought him the news: “How do you know that Saul and his son Jonʹa·than are dead?” ^6 The young man replied: “By chance I was on Mount Gil·boʹa, and there was Saul supporting himself on his spear, and the chariots and horsemen had caught up with him. ^7 When he turned around and saw me, he called me, and I said, ‘Here I am!’ ^8 He asked me, ‘Who are you?’ I replied, ‘I am an A·malʹek·ite.’ ^9 Then he said, ‘Please stand over me and put me to death, for I am in great agony, but I am still alive.’[*] ^10 So I stood over him and put him to death, for I knew that he could not survive after he had fallen down wounded. Then I took the crown[*] that was on his head and the bracelet that was on his arm, and I brought them here to my lord.”

^11 At this David took hold of his garments and ripped them apart, and so did all the men who were with him. ^12 And they wailed and wept and fasted until evening for Saul, for his son Jonʹa·than, for the people of Jehovah, and for the house of Israel, because they had fallen by the sword.

^13 David asked the young man who brought him the news: “Where are you from?” He said: “I am the son of a foreign resident, an A·malʹek·ite.” ^14 Then David said to him: “Why did you not fear to lift your hand to do away with the anointed of Jehovah?” ^15 With that David called one of the young men and said: “Step forward and strike him.” So he struck him down, and he died. ^16 David said to him: “Your blood is on your own head, because your own mouth testified against you by saying, ‘I myself put the anointed of Jehovah to death.’”

^17 Then David chanted this dirge[*] over Saul and his son Jonʹa·than ^18 and said that the people of Judah should be taught the dirge called “The Bow,” which is written in the book of Jaʹshar:

^19 “The beauty, O Israel, lies slain upon your high places.

How the mighty have fallen!

^20 Do not tell it in Gath;

Do not announce it in the streets of Ashʹke·lon,

Or the daughters of the Phi·lisʹtines will rejoice,

Or the daughters of the uncircumcised men will exult.

^21 You mountains of Gil·boʹa,

May there be no dew or rain upon you,

Nor fields producing holy contributions,

Because there the shield of mighty ones was defiled,

The shield of Saul is no longer anointed with oil.

^22 From the blood of the slain, from the fat of mighty ones,

The bow of Jonʹa·than did not turn back,

And the sword of Saul would not return without success.

^23 Saul and Jonʹa·than, beloved and cherished[*] during their life,

And in death they were not separated.

Swifter than the eagles they were,

Mightier than the lions.

^24 O daughters of Israel, weep over Saul,

Who clothed you in scarlet and finery,

Who put gold ornaments upon your clothing.

^25 How the mighty have fallen in battle!

Jonʹa·than lies slain upon your high places!

^26 I am distressed over you, my brother Jonʹa·than;

You were very dear to me.

More wonderful was your love to me than the love of women.

^27 How the mighty have fallen

And the weapons of war have perished!”

^ 2 Sam. 1:1 Or “striking down.”

^ 2 Sam. 1:9 Or “because all my soul is still in me.”

^ 2 Sam. 1:10 Or “diadem.”

^ 2 Sam. 1:17 Or “song of mourning.”

^ 2 Sam. 1:23 Or “pleasant.”

2 Samuel  2 : 1 - 32

2 Afterward David inquired of Jehovah, saying: “Should I go up into one of the cities of Judah?” Jehovah said to him: “Go up.” David then asked: “Where should I go?” He replied: “To Hebʹron.” ^2 So David went up there with his two wives, A·hinʹo·am of Jezʹre·el and Abʹi·gail the widow of Naʹbal the Carʹmel·ite. ^3 David also brought the men who were with him, each with his household, and they settled in the cities around Hebʹron. ^4 Then the men of Judah came, and there they anointed David as king over the house of Judah.

They told David: “The men of Jaʹbesh-gilʹe·ad were the ones who buried Saul.” ^5 So David sent messengers to the men of Jaʹbesh-gilʹe·ad and said to them: “May you be blessed by Jehovah, because you showed loyal love to your lord Saul by burying him. ^6 May Jehovah show loyal love and faithfulness to you. I will also show you kindness because you have done this. ^7 Now let your hands be strong and be courageous men, for your lord Saul is dead, and the house of Judah has anointed me as king over them.”

^8 But Abʹner the son of Ner, the chief of Saul’s army, had taken Saul’s son Ish-boʹsheth and brought him across to Ma·ha·naʹim ^9 and made him king over Gilʹe·ad, the Ashʹur·ites, Jezʹre·el, Eʹphra·im, Benjamin, and over all Israel. ^10 Ish-boʹsheth, Saul’s son, was 40 years old when he became king over Israel, and he reigned for two years. The house of Judah, however, supported David. ^11 The time[*] that David was king in Hebʹron over the house of Judah was seven years and six months.

^12 In time Abʹner the son of Ner and the servants of Ish-boʹsheth, Saul’s son, went out from Ma·ha·naʹim to Gibʹe·on. ^13 Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah and the servants of David also went out and encountered them at the pool of Gibʹe·on; and one group sat on this side of the pool, and the other group on that side of the pool. ^14 Finally Abʹner said to Joʹab: “Let the young men get up and engage in combat[*] before us.” To this Joʹab said: “Let them get up.” ^15 So they got up and crossed over by number, 12 for Benjamin and Saul’s son Ish-boʹsheth and 12 from the servants of David. ^16 They grabbed one another by the head and each of them thrust his sword into the side of his opponent, and they all fell down together. So that place, which is in Gibʹe·on, was called Helʹkath-haz·zuʹrim.

^17 The fighting that ensued was extremely fierce that day, and Abʹner and the men of Israel were finally defeated before the servants of David. ^18 Now the three sons of Ze·ruʹiah were there—Joʹab, A·bishʹai, and Asʹa·hel; and Asʹa·hel was as swift on his feet as a gazelle in the open field. ^19 Asʹa·hel chased after Abʹner, and he would not veer to the right or to the left in his pursuit of Abʹner. ^20 When Abʹner looked behind, he asked, “Is that you, Asʹa·hel?” to which he replied, “Yes, it is.” ^21 Then Abʹner said to him: “Veer to your right or to your left and capture one of the young men, and take whatever you strip off him for yourself.” But Asʹa·hel did not want to stop chasing him. ^22 So Abʹner said to Asʹa·hel once again: “Stop chasing me. Why should I strike you down? How could I look your brother Joʹab in the face?” ^23 But he kept refusing to stop, so Abʹner struck him in the abdomen with the butt end of the spear, and the spear came out from his back; and he fell there and died on the spot. Everyone who came to the place where Asʹa·hel fell and died would stop and pause there.

^24 Then Joʹab and A·bishʹai went in pursuit of Abʹner. As the sun was setting, they came to the hill of Amʹmah, which faces Giʹah on the way to the wilderness of Gibʹe·on. ^25 And the Benʹja·min·ites gathered together behind Abʹner, and they formed one company and made a stand on the top of a certain hill. ^26 Then Abʹner called out to Joʹab: “Is the sword going to devour endlessly? Do you not know that the outcome will only be bitterness? How long, then, will it be before you tell the people to turn back from pursuing their brothers?” ^27 At that Joʹab said: “As surely as the true God is living, if you had not spoken, then only by the morning would the people have stopped pursuing their brothers.” ^28 Joʹab now blew the horn, and his men stopped chasing after Israel, and the fighting ceased.

^29 Abʹner and his men then marched through the Arʹa·bah all that night and crossed the Jordan and marched through the entire ravine[*] and finally came to Ma·ha·naʹim. ^30 After Joʹab turned back from pursuing Abʹner, he gathered all the people together. Of David’s servants, 19 were missing, in addition to Asʹa·hel. ^31 But the servants of David had defeated the Benʹja·min·ites and the men of Abʹner, and 360 of their men had died. ^32 They took Asʹa·hel and buried him in his father’s tomb, which is at Bethʹle·hem. Then Joʹab and his men marched all night long, and they reached Hebʹron at daybreak.

^ 2 Sam. 2:11 Lit., “The number of days.”

^ 2 Sam. 2:14 Or “put on a competition.”

^ 2 Sam. 2:29 Or possibly, “through all of Bithron.”

2 Samuel  3 : 1 - 39

3 The war between the house of Saul and the house of David dragged on; and David kept getting stronger, and the house of Saul grew steadily weaker.

^2 Meanwhile, sons were born to David in Hebʹron. His firstborn was Amʹnon by A·hinʹo·am of Jezʹre·el. ^3 His second was Chilʹe·ab by Abʹi·gail, the widow of Naʹbal the Carʹmel·ite; and the third was Abʹsa·lom the son of Maʹa·cah, the daughter of Talʹmai the king of Geshʹur. ^4 The fourth was Ad·o·niʹjah the son of Hagʹgith, and the fifth was Sheph·a·tiʹah the son of A·biʹtal. ^5 The sixth was Ithʹre·am by David’s wife Egʹlah. These were born to David in Hebʹron.

^6 While the war between the house of Saul and the house of David continued, Abʹner kept strengthening his position in the house of Saul. ^7 Now Saul had had a concubine whose name was Rizʹpah, the daughter of Aʹiah. Ish-boʹsheth later said to Abʹner: “Why did you have relations with the concubine of my father?” ^8 Abʹner grew very angry over the words of Ish-boʹsheth and said: “Am I a dog’s head from Judah? Until this very day, I have shown loyal love toward the house of your father Saul and to his brothers and his friends, and I have not betrayed you into the hand of David; yet today you call me to account for an error concerning a woman. ^9 May God do so to Abʹner and add to it if I do not do for David just as Jehovah swore to him: ^10 to transfer the kingdom from the house of Saul and to establish the throne of David over Israel and over Judah, from Dan to Beʹer-sheʹba.” ^11 He was not able to say one more word in reply to Abʹner, for he was afraid of him.

^12 Abʹner immediately sent messengers to David, saying: “To whom does the land belong?” He added: “Make a covenant with me, and I will do whatever I can[*] to turn all Israel to your side.” ^13 To this he replied: “Good! I will make a covenant with you. The only thing I ask of you is that you do not try to see my face unless first you bring Miʹchal, Saul’s daughter, when you come to see me.” ^14 Then David sent messengers to Ish-boʹsheth, Saul’s son, saying: “Give me my wife Miʹchal, to whom I became engaged for 100 foreskins of the Phi·lisʹtines.” ^15 So Ish-boʹsheth sent to take her from her husband, Palʹti·el the son of Laʹish. ^16 But her husband kept walking with her, weeping as he followed her as far as Ba·huʹrim. Then Abʹner said to him: “Go, return!” At that he returned.

^17 Meanwhile, Abʹner sent word to the elders of Israel, saying: “For some time you wanted to have David as king over you. ^18 Now act, for Jehovah said to David: ‘By the hand of my servant David I will save my people Israel from the hand of the Phi·lisʹtines and from the hand of all their enemies.’” ^19 Then Abʹner spoke to the people of Benjamin. Abʹner also went to speak privately to David at Hebʹron to tell him what Israel and the whole house of Benjamin had agreed upon.

^20 When Abʹner came to David at Hebʹron with 20 men, David held a feast for Abʹner and for the men with him. ^21 Then Abʹner said to David: “Let me go and gather all Israel together to my lord the king, so that they may make a covenant with you, and you will become king over all that you desire.”[*] So David sent Abʹner off, and he went his way in peace.

^22 Just then, David’s servants and Joʹab returned from a raid, bringing a great quantity of spoil back with them. Abʹner was no longer with David in Hebʹron, for he had sent him on his way in peace. ^23 When Joʹab and all the army that was with him arrived, Joʹab was told: “Abʹner the son of Ner came to the king, and he sent him off, and he went his way in peace.” ^24 So Joʹab went in to the king and said: “What have you done? Here Abʹner came to you. Why did you send him off so that he successfully got away? ^25 You know Abʹner the son of Ner! He came here to fool you and to get to know your every move and to find out everything that you are doing.”

^26 So Joʹab left David and sent messengers after Abʹner, and they brought him back from the cistern of Siʹrah; but David did not know anything about it. ^27 When Abʹner returned to Hebʹron, Joʹab took him aside inside the gate to speak with him privately. However, there he stabbed him in the abdomen, and he died; this was for killing[*] his brother Asʹa·hel. ^28 When David heard about it later, he said: “I and my kingdom are forever innocent before Jehovah of the bloodguilt for Abʹner the son of Ner. ^29 May it turn back on the head of Joʹab and on the entire house of his father. May Joʹab’s house never be without a man suffering from a discharge or a leper or a man working at the spindle[*] or one falling by the sword or one in need of food!” ^30 So Joʹab and his brother A·bishʹai killed Abʹner because he had put Asʹa·hel their brother to death in the battle at Gibʹe·on.

^31 Then David said to Joʹab and all the people with him: “Rip your garments apart and tie on sackcloth and wail over Abʹner.” King David himself was walking behind the funeral bier. ^32 They buried Abʹner in Hebʹron; and the king wept loudly at Abʹner’s tomb, and all the people gave way to weeping. ^33 The king chanted over Abʹner and said:

“Should Abʹner die the death of a senseless person?

^34 Your hands had not been bound,

And your feet were not in fetters.[*]

You fell like one falling before criminals.”[*]

At that all the people wept over him again.

^35 Later all the people came to give David bread for consolation[*] while it was still daytime, but David swore: “May God do so to me and add to it if before the sun sets I taste bread or anything at all!” ^36 All the people took notice, and it pleased them. Like everything that the king did, it pleased all the people. ^37 So all the people and all Israel knew on that day that the king was not responsible for having Abʹner the son of Ner put to death. ^38 Then the king said to his servants: “Do you not know that a prince and a great man has fallen this day in Israel? ^39 Today I am weak, although anointed as king, and these men, the sons of Ze·ruʹiah, are too brutal for me. May Jehovah repay the evildoer according to his own evil.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:12 Lit., “and look! my hand is with you.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:21 Or “your soul desires.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:27 Lit., “for the blood of.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:29 Perhaps referring to a crippled man required to do women’s work.

^ 2 Sam. 3:34 Lit., “copper.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:34 Lit., “the sons of unrighteousness.”

^ 2 Sam. 3:35 Or “bread of mourning.”

2 Samuel  4 : 1 - 12

4 When Saul’s son Ish-boʹsheth[*] heard that Abʹner had died in Hebʹron, his courage failed him[*] and all the Israelites were disturbed. ^2 There were two men in charge of the marauder bands that belonged to the son of Saul: one was named Baʹa·nah and the other Reʹchab. They were sons of Rimʹmon the Be·erʹoth·ite, of the tribe of Benjamin. (For Be·erʹoth too used to be counted as part of Benjamin. ^3 The Be·erʹoth·ites ran away to Gitʹta·im, and they are foreign residents there down to this day.)

^4 Now Saul’s son Jonʹa·than had a son whose feet were crippled.[*] He was five years old when the report about Saul and Jonʹa·than came from Jezʹre·el, and his nurse picked him up and fled, but as she was fleeing in panic, he fell and was crippled. His name was Me·phibʹo·sheth.

^5 The sons of Rimʹmon the Be·erʹoth·ite, Reʹchab and Baʹa·nah, went to the house of Ish-boʹsheth during the hot part of the day, as he was taking his midday rest. ^6 They went into the house as if they were getting wheat, and they struck him in the abdomen; then Reʹchab and his brother Baʹa·nah escaped. ^7 When they had entered the house, he was lying on his bed in his bedroom, and they struck him and put him to death, after which they cut off his head. Then they took his head and walked all night long on the road to the Arʹa·bah. ^8 And they brought the head of Ish-boʹsheth to David at Hebʹron and said to the king: “Here is the head of Ish-boʹsheth the son of Saul your enemy who sought your life.[*] This day Jehovah gives to my lord the king revenge on Saul and his descendants.”

^9 However, David answered Reʹchab and his brother Baʹa·nah, the sons of Rimʹmon the Be·erʹoth·ite, and said to them: “As surely as Jehovah is living, the one who rescued me[*] out of all distress, ^10 when someone reported to me, ‘Here Saul is dead,’ and he thought he was bringing me good news, I took hold of him and killed him in Zikʹlag. That was the messenger’s reward he received from me! ^11 How much more so when wicked men have killed a righteous man in his own house on his bed! Should I not require his blood from your hands and rid the earth of you?” ^12 David then ordered the young men to kill them. They cut off their hands and feet and hung them by the pool in Hebʹron. But they took the head of Ish-boʹsheth and buried it in the burial place of Abʹner in Hebʹron.

^ 2 Sam. 4:1 Lit., “the son of Saul.”

^ 2 Sam. 4:1 Lit., “his hands became feeble.”

^ 2 Sam. 4:4 Or “lame.”

^ 2 Sam. 4:8 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 4:9 Or “redeemed my soul.”

2 Samuel  5 : 1 - 25

5 In time all the tribes of Israel came to David at Hebʹron and said: “Look! We are your own bone and flesh.[*] ^2 In times past while Saul was our king, you were the one who was leading Israel on its campaigns.[*] And Jehovah said to you: ‘You will shepherd my people Israel, and you will become leader over Israel.’” ^3 So all the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebʹron, and King David made a covenant with them in Hebʹron before Jehovah. Then they anointed David as king over Israel.

^4 David was 30 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 40 years. ^5 In Hebʹron he reigned over Judah for 7 years and 6 months, and in Jerusalem he reigned for 33 years over all Israel and Judah. ^6 And the king and his men set out for Jerusalem against the Jebʹu·sites who were inhabiting the land. They taunted David: “You will never come in here! Even the blind and the lame will drive you away.” They thought, ‘David will never get in here.’ ^7 However, David captured the stronghold of Zion, which is now the City of David. ^8 So David said on that day: “Those who attack the Jebʹu·sites should go through the water tunnel to strike down both ‘the lame and the blind,’ who are hateful to David!”[*] That is why it is said: “The blind and the lame will never enter the house.” ^9 Then David took up residence in the stronghold, and it was called[*] the City of David; and David began to build all around from the Mound[*] inward. ^10 Thus David became greater and greater, and Jehovah the God of armies was with him.

^11 King Hiʹram of Tyre sent messengers to David, also cedar timbers, woodworkers, and stonemasons for building walls, and they began to build a house[*] for David. ^12 And David knew that Jehovah had firmly established him as king over Israel and had exalted his kingdom for the sake of His people Israel.

^13 David took more concubines and wives in Jerusalem after he came from Hebʹron, and more sons and daughters were born to David. ^14 These are the names of those born to him in Jerusalem: Sham·muʹa, Shoʹbab, Nathan, Solʹo·mon, ^15 Ibʹhar, E·liʹshu·a, Neʹpheg, Ja·phiʹa, ^16 E·lishʹa·ma, E·liʹa·da, and E·liphʹe·let.

^17 When the Phi·lisʹtines heard that David had been anointed as king over Israel, all the Phi·lisʹtines came up to search for David. When David heard about it, he went down to the stronghold. ^18 Then the Phi·lisʹtines came in and spread out in the Valley[*] of Rephʹa·im. ^19 David inquired of Jehovah, saying: “Should I go up against the Phi·lisʹtines? Will you give them into my hand?” At this Jehovah said to David: “Go up, for I will surely give the Phi·lisʹtines into your hand.” ^20 So David came to Baʹal-pe·raʹzim, and David struck them down there. At that he said: “Jehovah has broken through my enemies before me, like a breach made by waters.” That is why he named that place Baʹal-pe·raʹzim.[*] ^21 The Phi·lisʹtines abandoned their idols there, and David and his men took them away.

^22 Later the Phi·lisʹtines came up once again and spread out in the Valley[*] of Rephʹa·im. ^23 David inquired of Jehovah, but He said: “Do not go directly up. Instead, go around behind them, and come against them in front of the baʹca bushes. ^24 And when you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the baʹca bushes, then act decisively, for Jehovah will have gone out before you to strike down the army of the Phi·lisʹtines.” ^25 So David did just as Jehovah commanded him, and he struck down the Phi·lisʹtines from Geʹba all the way to Geʹzer.

^ 2 Sam. 5:1 Or “your blood relatives.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:2 Lit., “the one bringing out and the one bringing in Israel.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:8 Or “the soul of David.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:9 Or possibly, “and he called it.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:9 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:11 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:18 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:20 Meaning “Master of Breakings Through.”

^ 2 Sam. 5:22 Or “Low Plain.”

2 Samuel  6 : 1 - 23

6 David again gathered all the best troops in Israel, 30,000 men. ^2 Then David and all the men with him set out for Baʹal·e-juʹdah to bring up from there the Ark of the true God, before which people call on the name of Jehovah of armies, who sits enthroned above[*] the cherubs. ^3 However, they placed the Ark of the true God on a new wagon to transport it from the house of A·binʹa·dab, which was on the hill; and Uzʹzah and A·hiʹo, the sons of A·binʹa·dab, were leading the new wagon.

^4 So they transported the Ark of the true God from A·binʹa·dab’s house on the hill, and A·hiʹo was walking ahead of the Ark. ^5 David and all the house of Israel were celebrating before Jehovah with all sorts of juniper-wood instruments, harps, other stringed instruments, tambourines, sistrums, and cymbals. ^6 But when they came to the threshing floor of Naʹcon, Uzʹzah thrust his hand out to the Ark of the true God and grabbed hold of it, for the cattle nearly upset it. ^7 At that Jehovah’s anger blazed against Uzʹzah, and the true God struck him down there for his irreverent act, and he died there beside the Ark of the true God. ^8 But David became angry[*] because Jehovah’s wrath had broken through against Uzʹzah; and that place has been called Peʹrez-uzʹzah[*] down to this day. ^9 So David became fearful of Jehovah on that day and said: “How can the Ark of Jehovah come to me?” ^10 David was not willing to bring the Ark of Jehovah to where he was in the City of David. Instead, David had it taken to the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom the Gitʹtite.

^11 The Ark of Jehovah remained at the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom the Gitʹtite for three months, and Jehovah kept blessing Oʹbed-eʹdom and all his household. ^12 The report was made to King David: “Jehovah has blessed the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom and all that belongs to him because of the Ark of the true God.” So David went to bring the Ark of the true God from the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom up to the City of David with rejoicing. ^13 When the carriers of the Ark of Jehovah had marched six steps, he sacrificed a bull and a fattened animal.

^14 David was dancing around before Jehovah with all his might; all the while David wore[*] a linen ephʹod. ^15 David and all the house of Israel were bringing up the Ark of Jehovah with joyful shouting and with the sound of the horn. ^16 But when the Ark of Jehovah came into the City of David, Saul’s daughter Miʹchal looked down through the window and saw King David leaping and dancing around before Jehovah; and she began to despise him in her heart. ^17 So they brought the Ark of Jehovah in and set it in its place inside the tent that David had pitched for it. Then David offered up burnt offerings and communion sacrifices before Jehovah. ^18 When David finished offering up the burnt offerings and the communion sacrifices, he blessed the people in the name of Jehovah of armies. ^19 Further, he distributed to all the people, to the whole multitude of Israel, to each man and woman, a ring-shaped loaf of bread, a date cake, and a raisin cake, and then all the people left, each to his own house.

^20 When David returned to bless his own household, Saul’s daughter Miʹchal came out to meet him. She said: “How glorious the king of Israel made himself when he uncovered himself today before the eyes of the slave girls of his servants, just as an empty-headed man openly uncovers himself!” ^21 At this David said to Miʹchal: “My celebration was before Jehovah, who chose me rather than your father and all his household and who appointed me as leader over Jehovah’s people, Israel. Therefore, I will celebrate before Jehovah, ^22 and I will humble myself even more than this and become low even in my own eyes. But by the slave girls whom you mentioned, I will be glorified.” ^23 So Saul’s daughter Miʹchal had no children down to the day of her death.

^ 2 Sam. 6:2 Or possibly, “between.”

^ 2 Sam. 6:8 Or “upset.”

^ 2 Sam. 6:8 Meaning “Breach Against Uzzah.”

^ 2 Sam. 6:14 Lit., “was girded with.”

2 Samuel  7 : 1 - 29

7 When the king was settled in his own house[*] and Jehovah had given him rest from all his surrounding enemies, ^2 the king said to Nathan the prophet: “Here I am living in a house of cedars while the Ark of the true God sits in the midst of tent cloths.” ^3 Nathan replied to the king: “Go and do whatever is in your heart, for Jehovah is with you.”

^4 On that very night, the word of Jehovah came to Nathan, saying: ^5 “Go and say to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Should you build me a house to dwell in? ^6 For I have not dwelled in a house from the day I brought the people of Israel out of Egypt to this day, but I have been moving[*] about in a tent and in a tabernacle. ^7 During all the time that I went with all the Israelites,[*] did I ever say one word to any of the tribal leaders of Israel whom I appointed to shepherd my people Israel, saying, ‘Why did you not build a house of cedars for me?’”’ ^8 Now say this to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “I took you from the pastures, from following the flock, to become a leader over my people Israel. ^9 And I will be with you wherever you go, and I will do away with[*] all your enemies from before you; and I will make a great name for you like the name of the great men of the earth. ^10 I will appoint a place for my people Israel and settle them, and they will live there and not be disturbed anymore; and wicked men will not oppress them again as they did in the past, ^11 from the day that I appointed judges over my people Israel. And I will give you rest from all your enemies.

“‘“Also, Jehovah has told you that Jehovah will make a house[*] for you. ^12 When your days come to an end and you are laid to rest with your forefathers, then I will raise up your offspring[*] after you, your own son,[*] and I will firmly establish his kingdom. ^13 He is the one who will build a house for my name, and I will firmly establish the throne of his kingdom forever. ^14 I will become his father, and he will become my son. When he does wrong, I will reprove him with the rod of men and with the strokes of the sons of men.[*] ^15 My loyal love will not be taken away from him the way I took it away from Saul, whom I removed from before you. ^16 Your house and your kingdom will be secure forever before you; your throne will be firmly established forever.”’”

^17 Nathan told David all these words and this entire vision.

^18 At that King David came in and sat down before Jehovah and said: “Who am I, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah? And what is my house that you have brought me this far? ^19 As if this were not enough, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, you also speak about the house of your servant down to a distant future time; and this is instruction[*] for all mankind, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ^20 What more can your servant David say to you when you know me so well, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah? ^21 For the sake of your word and in agreement with your heart[*] you have done all these great things and have revealed them to your servant. ^22 That is why you are truly great, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah. There is no one like you, and there is no God except you; everything we have heard with our ears confirms this. ^23 And what other nation on earth is like your people Israel? God went and redeemed them as his people, making a name for himself by doing great and awe-inspiring things for them. You drove out the nations and their gods in behalf of your people, whom you redeemed to yourself from Egypt. ^24 You established your people Israel as your own people for all time; and you, O Jehovah, have become their God.

^25 “Now, O Jehovah God, carry out the promise you have made concerning your servant and his house for all time, and may you do just as you have promised. ^26 May your name be exalted forever, so that people may say, ‘Jehovah of armies is God over Israel,’ and may the house of your servant David be firmly established before you. ^27 For you, Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, have made a revelation to your servant by saying, ‘I will build a house[*] for you.’ That is why your servant has the courage[*] to pray this prayer to you. ^28 And now, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, you are the true God, and your words are truth, and you have promised these good things to your servant. ^29 So may it please you to bless the house of your servant, and may it continue forever before you; for you, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, have promised, and with your blessing may the house of your servant be blessed forever.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:1 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:6 Lit., “walking.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:7 Lit., “sons of Israel.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:9 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:11 Or “dynasty.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:12 Lit., “seed.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:12 Lit., “one who will come out of your inward parts.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:14 Or possibly, “Adam.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:19 Or “law.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:21 Or “in harmony with your will.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:27 Or “dynasty.”

^ 2 Sam. 7:27 Lit., “has found his heart.”

2 Samuel  8 : 1 - 18

8 Some time later, David defeated the Phi·lisʹtines and subdued them, and David took Methʹeg-amʹmah out of the hands of the Phi·lisʹtines.

^2 He defeated the Moʹab·ites and made them lie down on the ground and measured them with a line. He measured out two lines to be put to death, and one full line to be kept alive. And the Moʹab·ites became David’s servants and brought tribute.

^3 David defeated Had·ad·eʹzer the son of Reʹhob the king of Zoʹbah as he was on his way to restore his authority at the Eu·phraʹtes River. ^4 David captured 1,700 horsemen and 20,000 foot soldiers from him. Then David hamstrung all but 100 of the chariot horses.

^5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help King Had·ad·eʹzer of Zoʹbah, David struck down 22,000 of the Syrians. ^6 David then established garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians became David’s servants and brought tribute. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. ^7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold from the servants of Had·ad·eʹzer and brought them to Jerusalem. ^8 From Beʹtah and Be·roʹthai, cities of Had·ad·eʹzer, King David took a great quantity of copper.

^9 Now King Toʹi of Haʹmath heard that David had defeated the entire army of Had·ad·eʹzer. ^10 So Toʹi sent his son Joʹram to King David to ask about his welfare and to congratulate him because he had fought and defeated Had·ad·eʹzer (for Had·ad·eʹzer had often fought against Toʹi), and he brought articles of silver, gold, and copper. ^11 King David sanctified these to Jehovah, along with the silver and the gold that he had sanctified from all the nations that he had subdued: ^12 from Syria and Moʹab, from the Amʹmon·ites, the Phi·lisʹtines, the A·malʹek·ites, and from the spoil of Had·ad·eʹzer the son of Reʹhob the king of Zoʹbah. ^13 David also made a name for himself when he came back from striking down 18,000 Eʹdom·ites in the Valley of Salt. ^14 He established garrisons in Eʹdom. In all Eʹdom he established garrisons, and all the Eʹdom·ites became David’s servants. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went.

^15 David kept reigning over all Israel, and David was administering justice and righteousness for all his people. ^16 Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah was over the army, and Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of A·hiʹlud was recorder. ^17 Zaʹdok the son of A·hiʹtub and A·himʹe·lech the son of A·biʹa·thar were priests, and Se·raiʹah was secretary. ^18 Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was over the Cherʹe·thites and the Pelʹe·thites. And David’s sons became chief ministers.[*]

^ 2 Sam. 8:6 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 8:14 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 8:18 Lit., “became priests.”

2 Samuel  9 : 1 - 13

9 David then said: “Is there anyone still left of the house of Saul to whom I may show loyal love for the sake of Jonʹa·than?” ^2 Now there was a servant of the house of Saul named Ziʹba. So they called him to David, and the king asked him: “Are you Ziʹba?” He replied: “I am your servant.” ^3 The king continued: “Is there anyone left of the house of Saul to whom I may extend God’s loyal love?” Ziʹba replied to the king: “There is still one son of Jonʹa·than; he is crippled[*] in both feet.” ^4 The king asked him: “Where is he?” Ziʹba replied to the king: “He is in the house of Maʹchir the son of Amʹmi·el at Lo-deʹbar.”

^5 King David immediately sent for him and took him from the house of Maʹchir the son of Amʹmi·el at Lo-deʹbar. ^6 When Me·phibʹo·sheth the son of Jonʹa·than the son of Saul came in to David, he at once fell facedown and prostrated himself. Then David said: “Me·phibʹo·sheth!” to which he replied: “Here is your servant.” ^7 David said to him: “Do not be afraid, for I will certainly show loyal love to you for the sake of your father Jonʹa·than, and I will return to you all the land of Saul your grandfather, and you will always dine[*] at my table.”

^8 At that he prostrated himself and said: “What is your servant, that you have turned your attention[*] to a dead dog like me?” ^9 The king now sent for Ziʹba, Saul’s attendant, and said to him: “Everything that belonged to Saul and to all his house I give to the grandson of your master. ^10 You will cultivate the land for him—you and your sons and your servants—and you will gather its produce to provide food for those who belong to the grandson of your master to eat. But Me·phibʹo·sheth, the grandson of your master, will always dine at my table.”

Now Ziʹba had 15 sons and 20 servants. ^11 Then Ziʹba said to the king: “Your servant will do all that my lord the king commands his servant to do.” So Me·phibʹo·sheth ate at David’s[*] table like one of the sons of the king. ^12 Now Me·phibʹo·sheth also had a young son named Miʹca; and all those who lived in Ziʹba’s house became servants of Me·phibʹo·sheth. ^13 And Me·phibʹo·sheth lived in Jerusalem, for he always ate at the table of the king; and he was crippled in both feet.

^ 2 Sam. 9:3 Or “lame.”

^ 2 Sam. 9:7 Lit., “eat bread.”

^ 2 Sam. 9:8 Lit., “face.”

^ 2 Sam. 9:11 Or possibly, “my.”

2 Samuel  10 : 1 - 19

10 Later the king of the Amʹmon·ites died, and his son Haʹnun became king in his place. ^2 At that David said: “I will show loyal love toward Haʹnun the son of Naʹhash as his father showed loyal love toward me.” So David sent his servants to offer him comfort over the loss of his father. But when David’s servants came into the land of the Amʹmon·ites, ^3 the princes of the Amʹmon·ites said to Haʹnun their lord: “Do you think that David is honoring your father by sending comforters to you? Is it not to search through the city and to spy it out and to overthrow it that David has sent his servants to you?” ^4 So Haʹnun took the servants of David and shaved off half their beards and cut their garments in half at their buttocks and sent them away. ^5 When David was told, he at once sent men to meet them, because the men had been deeply humiliated; and the king told them: “Stay in Jerʹi·cho until your beards grow back, and then return.”

^6 In time the Amʹmon·ites saw that they had become a stench to David, so the Amʹmon·ites sent and hired Syrians of Beth-reʹhob and Syrians of Zoʹbah, 20,000 foot soldiers; and the king of Maʹa·cah, with 1,000 men; and from Ishʹtob,[*] 12,000 men. ^7 When David heard about it, he sent Joʹab and the entire army, including his mightiest warriors. ^8 And the Amʹmon·ites went out and drew up in battle formation at the entrance of the city gate while the Syrians of Zoʹbah and of Reʹhob, along with Ishʹtob[*] and Maʹa·cah, were by themselves in the open field.

^9 When Joʹab saw that the battle charges were coming against him from the front and the rear, he chose some of the best troops in Israel and drew them up in battle formation to meet the Syrians. ^10 He put the rest of the men under the command[*] of his brother A·bishʹai, in order to draw them up in battle formation to meet the Amʹmon·ites. ^11 Then he said: “If the Syrians become too strong for me, then you must come to my rescue; but if the Amʹmon·ites become too strong for you, I will come to your rescue. ^12 We must be strong and courageous for our people and for the cities of our God, and Jehovah will do what is good in his eyes.”

^13 Then Joʹab and his men advanced to meet the Syrians in battle, and they fled from before him. ^14 When the Amʹmon·ites saw that the Syrians had fled, they fled from A·bishʹai and went into the city. After that Joʹab returned from the Amʹmon·ites and came to Jerusalem.

^15 When the Syrians saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they regrouped. ^16 So Had·ad·eʹzer sent for the Syrians in the region of the River,[*] and then they came to Heʹlam, with Shoʹbach the chief of the army of Had·ad·eʹzer leading them.

^17 When the report was made to David, he immediately gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan and came to Heʹlam. The Syrians then drew up in battle formation to meet David and fought against him. ^18 But the Syrians fled from Israel; and David killed 700 charioteers and 40,000 horsemen of the Syrians, and he struck down Shoʹbach the chief of their army, who died there. ^19 When all the kings, the servants of Had·ad·eʹzer, saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they promptly made peace with Israel and became their subjects; and the Syrians were afraid to help the Amʹmon·ites anymore.

^ 2 Sam. 10:6 Or “the men of Tob.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:8 Or “the men of Tob.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:10 Lit., “in the hand.”

^ 2 Sam. 10:16 That is, the Euphrates.

2 Samuel  11 : 1 - 27

11 At the start of the year,[*] at the time when kings go on campaigns, David sent Joʹab and his servants and the entire army of Israel to bring the Amʹmon·ites to ruin, and they besieged Rabʹbah, while David stayed in Jerusalem.

^2 One evening[*] David got up from his bed and walked around on the rooftop of the king’s house.[*] From the rooftop he saw a woman bathing, and the woman was very beautiful. ^3 David sent someone to inquire about the woman, and he reported: “Is this not Bath-sheʹba the daughter of E·liʹam and the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite?” ^4 Then David sent messengers to bring her. So she came in to him, and he lay down with her. (This happened while she was purifying herself from her uncleanness.[*]) Afterward, she returned to her house.

^5 The woman became pregnant, and she sent a message to David: “I am pregnant.” ^6 At this David sent a message to Joʹab: “Send to me U·riʹah the Hitʹtite.” So Joʹab sent U·riʹah to David. ^7 When U·riʹah came to him, David asked him how Joʹab was getting along, how the troops were getting along, and how the war was going. ^8 David then said to U·riʹah: “Go down to your house and relax.”[*] When U·riʹah left the king’s house, the king’s courtesy gift[*] was sent after him. ^9 However, U·riʹah slept at the entrance of the king’s house with all the other servants of his lord, and he did not go down to his own house. ^10 So David was told: “U·riʹah did not go down to his own house.” At that David said to U·riʹah: “Have you not just returned from a journey? Why did you not go down to your own house?” ^11 U·riʹah replied to David: “The Ark and Israel and Judah are dwelling in temporary shelters, and my lord Joʹab and the servants of my lord are camping in the open field. So should I go into my own house to eat and drink and lie down with my wife? As surely as you live and are alive,[*] I will not do this thing!”

^12 Then David said to U·riʹah: “Stay here also today, and tomorrow I will send you away.” So U·riʹah stayed in Jerusalem on that day and the following day. ^13 David then sent for him to come and eat and drink with him, and he got him drunk. But in the evening, he went out to sleep on his bed with the servants of his lord, and he did not go down to his house. ^14 In the morning David wrote a letter to Joʹab and sent it by the hand of U·riʹah. ^15 He wrote in the letter: “Put U·riʹah in the front lines where the fighting is fiercest. Then retreat from behind him, so that he will be struck down and die.”

^16 Joʹab had been carefully watching the city, and he stationed U·riʹah where he knew there were mighty warriors. ^17 When the men of the city came out and fought against Joʹab, some of David’s servants fell, and U·riʹah the Hitʹtite was among those who died. ^18 Joʹab now reported to David all the news about the war. ^19 He instructed the messenger: “When you finish speaking to the king about all the news of the war, ^20 the king may become angry and say to you, ‘Why did you have to go so near to the city to fight? Did you not know that they would shoot from the top of the wall? ^21 Who struck down A·bimʹe·lech the son of Je·rubʹbe·sheth? Was it not a woman who threw an upper millstone on him from the top of the wall, causing his death at Theʹbez? Why did you have to go so close to the wall?’ Then say, ‘Your servant U·riʹah the Hitʹtite also died.’”

^22 So the messenger went and told David everything that Joʹab had sent him to tell. ^23 Then the messenger told David: “Their men overpowered us, and they came out against us in the field; but we drove them back to the entrance of the city gate. ^24 And the archers were shooting at your servants from the top of the wall, and some of the servants of the king died; your servant U·riʹah the Hitʹtite also died.” ^25 At that David said to the messenger: “Say this to Joʹab: ‘Do not let this matter trouble you, for the sword devours one as well as another. Intensify your battle against the city and conquer it.’ And encourage him.”

^26 When U·riʹah’s wife heard that her husband U·riʹah had died, she began to mourn her husband. ^27 As soon as the mourning period was over, David sent for her and brought her to his house, and she became his wife and bore him a son. But what David had done was very displeasing to[*] Jehovah.

^ 2 Sam. 11:1 That is, in the spring.

^ 2 Sam. 11:2 Or “Late one afternoon.”

^ 2 Sam. 11:2 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 11:4 Possibly her menstrual uncleanness.

^ 2 Sam. 11:8 Lit., “wash your feet.”

^ 2 Sam. 11:8 Or “the king’s portion,” that is, the portion sent by the host to the honored guest.

^ 2 Sam. 11:11 Or “and as your soul is living.”

^ 2 Sam. 11:27 Lit., “was bad in the eyes of.”

2 Samuel  12 : 1 - 31

12 So Jehovah sent Nathan to David. He came in to him and said: “There were two men in one city, the one rich and the other poor. ^2 The rich man had very many sheep and cattle; ^3 but the poor man had nothing but one small female lamb, which he had bought. He cared for it, and it grew up together with him and his sons. It would eat from the little food he had and drink from his cup and sleep in his arms. It became as a daughter to him. ^4 Later a visitor came to the rich man, but he would not take any of his own sheep and cattle to prepare a meal for the traveler who had come to him. Instead, he took the poor man’s lamb and prepared it for the man who had come to him.”

^5 At this David grew very angry against the man, and he said to Nathan: “As surely as Jehovah is living, the man who did this deserves to die! ^6 And he should pay for the lamb four times over, because he did this and showed no compassion.”

^7 Then Nathan said to David: “You are the man! This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘I myself anointed you as king over Israel, and I rescued you from the hand of Saul. ^8 I was willing to give you your master’s house and put your master’s wives in your arms, and I gave you the house of Israel and of Judah. And as if that were not enough, I was willing to do much more for you. ^9 Why did you despise the word of Jehovah by doing what is bad in his eyes? You struck down U·riʹah the Hitʹtite with the sword! Then you took his wife as your wife after you killed him by the sword of the Amʹmon·ites. ^10 Now a sword will never depart from your own house, because you despised me by taking the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite as your wife.’ ^11 This is what Jehovah says: ‘Here I am bringing against you calamity from within your own house; and before your own eyes, I will take your wives and give them to another man,[*] and he will lie down with your wives in broad daylight.[*] ^12 Although you acted in secret, I will do this in front of all Israel and in broad daylight.’”[*]

^13 David then said to Nathan: “I have sinned against Jehovah.” Nathan replied to David: “Jehovah, in turn, forgives your sin.[*] You will not die. ^14 Nevertheless, because you have treated Jehovah with utter disrespect in this matter, the son just born to you will certainly die.”

^15 Then Nathan went to his own house.

And Jehovah struck the child whom U·riʹah’s wife had borne to David, and he became sick. ^16 David pleaded with the true God in behalf of the boy. David went on a strict fast and would go in and spend the night lying on the ground. ^17 So the elders of his house stood over him and tried to raise him up from the ground, but he refused and would not eat with them. ^18 On the seventh day the child died, but David’s servants were afraid to tell him that the child was dead. They said: “While the child was alive we spoke to him, and he did not listen to us. So how can we tell him that the child has died? He may do something terrible.”

^19 When David saw that his servants were whispering to one another, he discerned that the child had died. David said to his servants: “Has the child died?” They replied: “He has died.” ^20 So David got up from the ground. He washed, rubbed himself with oil, changed his clothing, and went to the house of Jehovah and prostrated himself. Afterward, he went to his house[*] and asked for food to be brought to him, and he ate. ^21 His servants asked him: “Why have you acted in this way? While the child was alive, you fasted and kept weeping; but as soon as the child died, you got up and ate food.” ^22 He replied: “While the child was alive, I fasted and kept weeping because I said to myself, ‘Who knows whether Jehovah may show me favor and let the child live?’ ^23 Now that he has died, why should I fast? Can I bring him back? I will go to him, but he will not return to me.”

^24 Then David comforted his wife Bath-sheʹba. He went in to her and lay down with her. In time she bore a son, and he was named Solʹo·mon.[*] And Jehovah loved him, ^25 and he sent word through Nathan the prophet to name him Jed·i·diʹah,[*] for the sake of Jehovah.

^26 Joʹab continued fighting against Rabʹbah of the Amʹmon·ites, and he captured the royal city.[*] ^27 So Joʹab sent messengers to David and said: “I have fought against Rabʹbah, and I have captured the city of waters.[*] ^28 Now gather the rest of the troops and encamp against the city and capture it. Otherwise, I will be the one to capture the city, and it will be credited to me.”[*]

^29 So David gathered all the troops and went to Rabʹbah and fought against it and captured it. ^30 Then he took the crown of Malʹcam from its head. The weight of it was a talent[*] of gold, along with precious stones, and it was placed on David’s head. He also took a vast amount of spoil from the city. ^31 And he brought out the people who were in it and put them to work at sawing stones, at working with sharp iron instruments and with iron axes, and at brickmaking. That was what he did to all the cities of the Amʹmon·ites. Finally David and all the troops returned to Jerusalem.

^ 2 Sam. 12:11 Or “to your fellow man.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:11 Lit., “to the eyes of this sun.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:12 Lit., “before the sun.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:13 Or “lets your sin pass by.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:20 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:24 From a Hebrew word meaning “Peace.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:25 Meaning “Beloved of Jah.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:26 Or “the city of the kingdom.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:27 Possibly referring to the water resources of the city.

^ 2 Sam. 12:28 Lit., “and my name will be called upon it.”

^ 2 Sam. 12:30 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

2 Samuel  13 : 1 - 39

13 Now David’s son Abʹsa·lom had a beautiful sister named Taʹmar, and David’s son Amʹnon fell in love with her. ^2 Amʹnon was so distressed that he became sick because of his sister Taʹmar, for she was a virgin and it seemed impossible for Amʹnon to do anything to her. ^3 Now Amʹnon had a companion named Je·honʹa·dab, the son of Shimʹe·ah, David’s brother; and Je·honʹa·dab was a very clever man. ^4 So he said to him: “Why are you, the king’s son, so depressed every morning? Why not tell me?” Amʹnon replied to him: “I am in love with Taʹmar, the sister of my brother Abʹsa·lom.” ^5 Je·honʹa·dab replied to him: “Lie down on your bed and pretend to be sick. When your father comes to see you, say to him, ‘Please, let my sister Taʹmar come and serve me some food. If she prepares the food given to the sick[*] before my eyes, I will eat it from her hand.’”

^6 So Amʹnon lay down and pretended to be sick, and the king came in to see him. Then Amʹnon said to the king: “Please, let my sister Taʹmar come in and bake two heart-shaped cakes before my eyes so that I may take food from her hand.” ^7 At that David sent a message to Taʹmar at the house, saying: “Please go to the house of your brother Amʹnon and prepare food[*] for him.” ^8 So Taʹmar went to the house of her brother Amʹnon, where he was lying down. She took the dough and kneaded it into cakes before his eyes and cooked the cakes. ^9 Then she took the pan and served him. But Amʹnon refused to eat and said: “Have everybody leave me!” So everybody left him.

^10 Amʹnon now said to Taʹmar: “Bring the food[*] into the bedroom, so that I may eat it from your hand.” So Taʹmar took the heart-shaped cakes that she had made and brought them to her brother Amʹnon in the bedroom. ^11 When she brought them for him to eat, he grabbed her and said: “Come, lie down with me, my sister.” ^12 But she said to him: “No, my brother! Do not humiliate me, for such a thing is not done in Israel. Do not do this disgraceful thing. ^13 How could I live down my shame? And you will be regarded as one of the disgraceful men in Israel. Now speak, please, to the king, for he will not withhold me from you.” ^14 But he refused to listen to her, and he overpowered her and humiliated her by raping her. ^15 Then Amʹnon began hating her with a very intense hatred, so that his hatred for her became greater than the love he had felt for her. Amʹnon said to her: “Get up; go away!” ^16 At this she said to him: “No, my brother, for sending me away now is worse than what you have done with me!” But he refused to listen to her.

^17 With that he called his young attendant and said: “Get this person out of my presence, please, and lock the door behind her.” ^18 (Now she was wearing a special[*] robe, for those were the garments that the virgin daughters of the king wore.) So his attendant led her outside, and he locked the door behind her. ^19 Then Taʹmar put ashes on her head, and she ripped apart the fine robe she was wearing; and she kept her hands on her head and walked off, crying out as she walked.

^20 At this her brother Abʹsa·lom asked her: “Was it your brother Amʹnon who was with you? And now keep silent, my sister. He is your brother. Do not let your heart dwell on this matter.” Then Taʹmar lived in isolation at the house of her brother Abʹsa·lom. ^21 When King David heard about all these things, he became very angry. But he would not hurt the feelings of Amʹnon his son, because he loved him, for he was his firstborn. ^22 And Abʹsa·lom said nothing to Amʹnon, either bad or good; for Abʹsa·lom hated Amʹnon because he had humiliated his sister Taʹmar.

^23 After two full years, Abʹsa·lom’s sheepshearers were at Baʹal-haʹzor, near Eʹphra·im, and Abʹsa·lom invited all the sons of the king. ^24 So Abʹsa·lom came in to the king and said: “Your servant is having his sheep sheared. Please let the king and his servants go with me.” ^25 But the king said to Abʹsa·lom: “No, my son. If all of us go, we will be a burden to you.” Although he kept urging him, he did not consent to go, but he blessed him. ^26 Abʹsa·lom then said: “If not you, please let my brother Amʹnon go with us.” The king replied to him: “Why should he go with you?” ^27 But Abʹsa·lom urged him, so he sent Amʹnon and all the king’s sons with him.

^28 Then Abʹsa·lom ordered his attendants: “Watch, and when Amʹnon’s heart is in a cheerful mood from the wine, I will say to you, ‘Strike down Amʹnon!’ You must then put him to death. Do not be afraid. Is it not I who command you? Be strong and courageous.” ^29 So Abʹsa·lom’s attendants did to Amʹnon exactly as Abʹsa·lom had ordered; then all the other sons of the king got up, and each one mounted his mule and fled. ^30 While they were on the way, the report reached David: “Abʹsa·lom has struck down all the sons of the king, and not one of them survived.” ^31 At this the king got up and ripped his clothes apart and lay on the ground, and all his servants were standing by with their garments ripped apart.

^32 However, Je·honʹa·dab the son of Shimʹe·ah, David’s brother, said: “Do not let my lord think that they have killed all the young sons of the king, for only Amʹnon has died. This is by the order of Abʹsa·lom, who decided to do this from the day that Amʹnon humiliated his sister Taʹmar. ^33 Now do not let my lord the king pay attention to[*] the report that says, ‘All the king’s sons have died’; only Amʹnon has died.”

^34 Meanwhile, Abʹsa·lom ran away. Later the watchman raised his eyes and saw that there were many people coming from the road behind him next to the mountain. ^35 At this Je·honʹa·dab said to the king: “Look! The king’s sons have returned. It is just as your servant said.” ^36 As he finished speaking, the king’s sons came in, weeping loudly; also the king and all his servants wept very bitterly. ^37 But Abʹsa·lom fled and went to Talʹmai the son of Am·miʹhud the king of Geshʹur. David mourned his son for many days. ^38 After Abʹsa·lom fled and went to Geshʹur, he stayed there for three years.

^39 Finally King David longed to go to Abʹsa·lom, for he had become reconciled to[*] the death of Amʹnon.

^ 2 Sam. 13:5 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:7 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:10 Or “the bread of consolation.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:18 Or “an ornamented.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:33 Lit., “take to his heart.”

^ 2 Sam. 13:39 Or “had found consolation over.”

2 Samuel  14 : 1 - 33

14 Now Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah learned that the king’s heart longed for Abʹsa·lom. ^2 So Joʹab sent to Te·koʹa and summoned from there a clever woman and told her: “Act like you are in mourning, please, and put on garments of mourning, and do not rub yourself with oil. Behave like a woman who has been mourning over someone dead for a long time. ^3 Then go in and speak to the king like this.” With that Joʹab put the words in her mouth.[*]

^4 The Te·koʹite woman went in to the king and fell with her face to the ground and prostrated herself and said: “Help me, O king!” ^5 The king replied to her: “What is the matter?” To this she said: “Alas, I am a widow; my husband is dead. ^6 And I, your servant, had two sons, and the two of them fought with each other in the field. There was no one to separate them, and one struck the other down and killed him. ^7 Now the whole family has risen up against me, your servant, and they are saying, ‘Hand over the one who struck his brother, so that we may put him to death for the life[*] of his brother whom he killed, even if it means wiping out the heir!’ They would extinguish the last glowing coal that I have left[*] and leave to my husband neither a name nor a survivor[*] on the surface of the earth.”

^8 Then the king said to the woman: “Go to your home, and I will issue an order regarding you.” ^9 At this the Te·koʹite woman said to the king: “O my lord the king, let the guilt be on me and on my father’s house, while the king and his throne are innocent.” ^10 The king then said: “If anyone speaks further to you, bring him to me, and he will never trouble you again.” ^11 But she said: “Please, let the king remember Jehovah your God, so that the avenger of blood does not bring ruin and annihilate my son.” To this he said: “As surely as Jehovah is living, not one of your son’s hairs will fall to the ground.” ^12 The woman now said: “Let your servant, please, speak a word to my lord the king.” So he said: “Speak!”

^13 The woman said: “Why, then, have you thought to do something like this against the people of God? When the king speaks this way, he makes himself guilty, for the king does not bring back his own banished son. ^14 We will surely die and be like waters that are poured out on the ground, which cannot be recovered. But God would not take away a life,[*] and he considers reasons why the banished one should not always be banished from him. ^15 I have come in to say this to my lord the king because the people made me afraid. So your servant said, ‘Let me speak, please, to the king. Perhaps the king will act on the request of his slave. ^16 The king may listen and rescue his slave from the hand of the man seeking to annihilate me and my only son from the inheritance God gave us.’ ^17 Then your servant said, ‘May the word of my lord the king please give me relief,’ for my lord the king is just like an angel of the true God in distinguishing what is good from what is bad. May Jehovah your God be with you.”

^18 The king now answered the woman: “Please do not hide from me anything I ask you.” The woman replied: “Let my lord the king speak, please.” ^19 The king then asked: “Did Joʹab put you up to all of this?” The woman answered: “As surely as you are[*] living, O my lord the king, it is just as[*] my lord the king says, for it was your servant Joʹab who instructed me and put all these words in the mouth of your servant. ^20 Your servant Joʹab has done this to change the appearance of things, but my lord has wisdom like that of the angel of the true God and knows all that is happening in the land.”

^21 The king then said to Joʹab: “All right, I will do this thing. Go and bring back the young man Abʹsa·lom.” ^22 At this Joʹab fell with his face to the ground and prostrated himself and praised the king. Joʹab said: “Today your servant knows that I have found favor in your eyes, O my lord the king, because the king has acted on the request of his servant.” ^23 Then Joʹab got up and went to Geshʹur and brought Abʹsa·lom to Jerusalem. ^24 However, the king said: “Let him return to his own house, but he may not see my face.” So Abʹsa·lom returned to his own house, and he did not see the face of the king.

^25 Now in all Israel, no man was as highly praised for his handsome appearance as Abʹsa·lom. From the sole of his foot to the crown of his head, there was no flaw in him. ^26 When he shaved his head—he had to shave it at the end of every year because it was so heavy for him—the hair of his head weighed 200 shekels[*] by the royal stone weight.[*] ^27 To Abʹsa·lom were born three sons and one daughter, whose name was Taʹmar. She was a very beautiful woman.

^28 And Abʹsa·lom continued living in Jerusalem for two full years, but he did not see the face of the king. ^29 So Abʹsa·lom summoned Joʹab in order to send him to the king, but Joʹab would not come to him. Then he sent for him again, a second time, and he still refused to come. ^30 Finally he said to his servants: “Joʹab’s plot of land is next to mine, and he has some barley there. Go and set it on fire.” So the servants of Abʹsa·lom set the plot of land on fire. ^31 At this Joʹab got up and came to Abʹsa·lom’s house and said to him: “Why did your servants set my plot of land on fire?” ^32 Abʹsa·lom replied to Joʹab: “Look! I sent this message to you, ‘Come and let me send you to the king to ask: “Why have I come from Geshʹur? It would have been better for me to stay there. Now let me see the face of the king, and if there is guilt in me, then he should put me to death.”’”

^33 So Joʹab went in to the king and told him. Then he called Abʹsa·lom, who came in to the king and prostrated himself before him, falling with his face to the ground before the king. Then the king kissed Abʹsa·lom.

^ 2 Sam. 14:3 Or “told her what to say.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:7 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:7 That is, the last hope for descendants.

^ 2 Sam. 14:7 Lit., “remnant.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:14 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:19 Or “your soul is.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:19 Or “no one can go to the left or right from what.”

^ 2 Sam. 14:26 About 2.3 kg (5 lb). See App. B14.

^ 2 Sam. 14:26 This may have been a standard weight kept at the royal palace or a “royal” shekel that was different from the common shekel.

2 Samuel  15 : 1 - 37

15 After all these things, Abʹsa·lom acquired for himself a chariot and horses and 50 men to run before him. ^2 Abʹsa·lom would rise up early and stand at the side of the road to the city gate. Whenever any man had a legal case that was to come to the king for judgment, Abʹsa·lom would call him and say: “From what city are you?” and he would say: “Your servant is from one of the tribes of Israel.” ^3 Abʹsa·lom would say to him: “See, your claims are right and proper, but there is no one from the king to hear your case.” ^4 Abʹsa·lom would say: “If only I were appointed judge in the land! Then every man who has a legal case or judgment could come to me, and I would see that he receives justice.”

^5 And when a man came near to bow down to him, Abʹsa·lom would extend his hand and grab hold of him and kiss him. ^6 Abʹsa·lom would do this to all the Israelites who would come in to the king for judgment; so Abʹsa·lom kept stealing the hearts of the men of Israel.

^7 At the end of four years,[*] Abʹsa·lom said to the king: “Let me go, please, to Hebʹron to pay my vow that I made to Jehovah. ^8 For your servant made this solemn vow when I was dwelling in Geshʹur in Syria: ‘If Jehovah will bring me back to Jerusalem, I will make an offering to[*] Jehovah.’” ^9 So the king said to him: “Go in peace.” With that he rose up and went to Hebʹron.

^10 Abʹsa·lom now sent spies through all the tribes of Israel, saying: “As soon as you hear the sound of the horn, announce, ‘Abʹsa·lom has become king in Hebʹron!’” ^11 Now 200 men from Jerusalem had gone there with Abʹsa·lom; they were invited and went unsuspectingly, unaware of what was happening. ^12 Further, when he offered the sacrifices, Abʹsa·lom sent for A·hithʹo·phel the Giʹlon·ite, David’s adviser,[*] from his city Giʹloh. The conspiracy kept gaining momentum, and the people who supported Abʹsa·lom were growing in number.

^13 In time an informer came to David, saying: “The heart of the men of Israel has turned to Abʹsa·lom.” ^14 At once David said to all his servants with him in Jerusalem: “Get up, and let us run away, for none of us will escape from Abʹsa·lom! Hurry, for fear he may quickly overtake us and bring disaster on us and strike the city with the sword!” ^15 The king’s servants replied to the king: “Whatever my lord the king decides, your servants are ready to do.” ^16 So the king went out with all his household following him, but the king left ten concubines to take care of the house.[*] ^17 And the king continued on his way out with all the people following, and they stopped at Beth-merʹhak.

^18 All his servants leaving with him[*] and all the Cherʹe·thites, the Pelʹe·thites, and the Gitʹtites, 600 men who had followed him from Gath, were passing by as the king reviewed them.[*] ^19 Then the king said to Itʹtai the Gitʹtite: “Why should you also go with us? Go back and dwell with the new king, for you are a foreigner and also an exile from your place. ^20 Yesterday you came, so today should I make you wander with us, to go when I must go and where I must go? Go back and take your brothers with you, and may Jehovah show you loyal love and faithfulness!” ^21 But Itʹtai answered the king: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as surely as my lord the king is living, wherever my lord the king may be, whether for death or for life, there your servant will be!” ^22 At that David said to Itʹtai: “Go and cross over.” So Itʹtai the Gitʹtite crossed over, together with all his men and children.

^23 Everyone in the land was weeping loudly while all these people crossed over, and the king was standing by the Kidʹron Valley; all the people were crossing over to the road leading to the wilderness. ^24 Zaʹdok was also there and with him were all the Levites carrying the ark of the covenant of the true God; and they set the Ark of the true God down; and A·biʹa·thar went up, while all the people completed crossing over from the city. ^25 But the king said to Zaʹdok: “Take the Ark of the true God back to the city. If I find favor in the eyes of Jehovah, he will also bring me back and let me see it and its dwelling place. ^26 But if he should say, ‘I have found no pleasure in you,’ then let him do to me whatever seems good in his eyes.” ^27 The king said to Zaʹdok the priest: “Are you not a seer? Return to the city in peace, and take the two sons of you men with you, A·himʹa·az your own son and Jonʹa·than the son of A·biʹa·thar. ^28 See, I will linger by the fords of the wilderness until word comes from you to inform me.” ^29 So Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar took the Ark of the true God back to Jerusalem, and they remained there.

^30 As David was going up the Mount[*] of Olives, he was weeping as he went up; his head was covered, and he was walking barefoot. All the people with him also covered their heads and were weeping as they went up. ^31 David was then told: “A·hithʹo·phel is among those conspiring with Abʹsa·lom.” At this David said: “Turn, please, the advice[*] of A·hithʹo·phel into foolishness, O Jehovah!”

^32 When David came to the summit where people used to bow down to God, Huʹshai the Arʹchite was there to meet him, with his robe ripped apart and dirt on his head. ^33 However, David said to him: “If you go across with me, you will be a load on me. ^34 But if you return to the city and you say to Abʹsa·lom, ‘I am your servant, O King. I was the servant of your father in the past, but now I am your servant,’ you can then frustrate the advice of A·hithʹo·phel for me. ^35 Are not Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar the priests there with you? You must tell Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar the priests everything that you hear from the house of the king. ^36 Look! There with them are their two sons, A·himʹa·az the son of Zaʹdok and Jonʹa·than the son of A·biʹa·thar, and through them send to me everything that you hear.” ^37 So Huʹshai, David’s friend,[*] went into the city as Abʹsa·lom was entering into Jerusalem.

^ 2 Sam. 15:7 Or possibly, “40 years.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:8 Or “worship.” Lit., “render service to.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:12 Or “counselor.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:16 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:18 Or “crossing at his side.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:18 Or “crossing before the king’s face.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:30 Or “ascent.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:31 Or “counsel.”

^ 2 Sam. 15:37 Or “confidant.”

2 Samuel  16 : 1 - 23

16 When David had passed a little beyond the summit, Ziʹba, the attendant of Me·phibʹo·sheth, was there to meet him with a couple of saddled donkeys, and on them were 200 loaves of bread, 100 cakes of raisins, 100 cakes of summer fruit,[*] and a large jar of wine. ^2 Then the king said to Ziʹba: “Why have you brought these things?” Ziʹba replied: “The donkeys are for the household of the king to ride, the bread and the summer fruit are for the young men to eat, and the wine is for those who get exhausted in the wilderness to drink.” ^3 The king now said: “And where is the son[*] of your master?” At this Ziʹba said to the king: “He is staying in Jerusalem, for he said, ‘Today the house of Israel will give back the royal rule of my father to me.’” ^4 The king then said to Ziʹba: “Look! Everything that belongs to Me·phibʹo·sheth is yours.” Ziʹba replied: “I bow down before you. May I find favor in your eyes, my lord the king.”

^5 When King David reached Ba·huʹrim, a man of the family of Saul’s house named Shimʹe·i, the son of Geʹra, came out shouting curses as he approached. ^6 He was throwing stones at David and at all the servants of King David, as well as at all the people and the mighty men on his right and on his left. ^7 Shimʹe·i said as he cursed: “Get out, get out, you bloodguilty man! You worthless man! ^8 Jehovah has brought back on you all the bloodguilt for the house of Saul, in whose place you have ruled as king, but Jehovah gives the kingship into the hand of Abʹsa·lom your son. Now calamity has overtaken you because you are a bloodguilty man!”

^9 Then A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah said to the king: “Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? Let me go over, please, and take off his head.” ^10 But the king said: “What do I have to do with you, you sons of Ze·ruʹiah? Let him curse me, for Jehovah has said to him, ‘Curse David!’ So who should say, ‘Why are you doing this?’” ^11 David then said to A·bishʹai and all his servants: “Here my own son, who came from my own body, is seeking my life,[*] and how much more now a Benʹja·min·ite! Leave him alone so that he may curse me, for Jehovah told him to! ^12 Perhaps Jehovah will see my affliction, and Jehovah will restore goodness to me instead of the curses shouted at me this day.” ^13 With that David and his men kept going down the road while Shimʹe·i was walking alongside the mountain abreast of him, shouting curses and throwing stones and a lot of dust.

^14 At length the king and all the people with him arrived at their destination exhausted, and they refreshed themselves.

^15 Meanwhile, Abʹsa·lom and all the men of Israel arrived in Jerusalem, and A·hithʹo·phel was with him. ^16 When Huʹshai the Arʹchite, David’s friend,[*] came in to Abʹsa·lom, Huʹshai said to Abʹsa·lom: “Long live the king! Long live the king!” ^17 At this Abʹsa·lom said to Huʹshai: “Is this your loyal love toward your friend? Why did you not go with your friend?” ^18 So Huʹshai said to Abʹsa·lom: “No, I am on the side of the one who has been chosen by Jehovah, this people, and all the men of Israel. I will stay with him. ^19 And again I say, Whom should I serve? Should it not be his son? Just as I served your father, so I will serve you.”

^20 Abʹsa·lom then said to A·hithʹo·phel: “Give me your advice.[*] What should we do?” ^21 At that A·hithʹo·phel said to Abʹsa·lom: “Have relations with your father’s concubines, those whom he left behind to take care of the house.[*] Then all Israel will hear that you have made yourself a stench to your father, and those who support you will be strengthened.” ^22 So they pitched a tent for Abʹsa·lom on the roof, and Abʹsa·lom had relations with the concubines of his father before the eyes of all Israel.

^23 In those days the advice that A·hithʹo·phel gave was considered as[*] the word of the true God. That was how all the advice of A·hithʹo·phel was esteemed, both by David and by Abʹsa·lom.

^ 2 Sam. 16:1 Especially figs and perhaps also dates.

^ 2 Sam. 16:3 Or “grandson.”

^ 2 Sam. 16:11 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 16:16 Or “confidant.”

^ 2 Sam. 16:20 Or “counsel.”

^ 2 Sam. 16:21 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 16:23 Or “was as if someone were inquiring of.”

2 Samuel  17 : 1 - 29

17 A·hithʹo·phel then said to Abʹsa·lom: “Please let me choose 12,000 men and rise up and chase after David tonight. ^2 I will come upon him when he is weary and powerless,[*] and I will throw him into a panic; and all the people who are with him will flee, and I will strike down only the king. ^3 Then I will bring all the people back to you. The return of all the people depends on what happens with the man you are seeking. Then all the people will be at peace.” ^4 The proposal was just right in the eyes of Abʹsa·lom and all the elders of Israel.

^5 However, Abʹsa·lom said: “Please call Huʹshai the Arʹchite as well, and let us hear what he has to say.” ^6 So Huʹshai came in to Abʹsa·lom. Then Abʹsa·lom said to him: “This is the advice A·hithʹo·phel gave. Should we act on his advice? If not, you tell us.” ^7 At this Huʹshai said to Abʹsa·lom: “The advice that A·hithʹo·phel gave is not good in this instance!”

^8 Huʹshai continued: “You well know that your father and his men are mighty, and they are desperate,[*] like a bear that has lost her cubs in the field. Moreover, your father is a warrior, and he will not spend the night with the people. ^9 At this very moment he is hiding in one of the caves[*] or in some other place; and if he attacks first, those hearing of it will say, ‘The people following Abʹsa·lom have been defeated!’ ^10 Even the courageous man whose heart is like that of a lion will surely melt in fear, for all Israel knows that your father is a mighty man and that the men with him are courageous. ^11 I give this advice: Let all Israel be gathered to you, from Dan to Beʹer-sheʹba, as many as the grains of sand by the sea, and you should lead them into the fight. ^12 We will come against him wherever he is found, and we will come upon him just like the dew that falls on the ground; and not one of them will survive, not he nor any of the men with him. ^13 If he retreats into a city, all Israel will carry ropes to that city, and we will drag it down into the valley until not even a pebble is left.”

^14 Then Abʹsa·lom and all the men of Israel said: “The advice of Huʹshai the Arʹchite is better than the advice of A·hithʹo·phel!” For Jehovah had determined[*] to frustrate the sound advice of A·hithʹo·phel, so that Jehovah could bring disaster on Abʹsa·lom.

^15 Huʹshai later said to Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar the priests: “This is what A·hithʹo·phel has advised Abʹsa·lom and the elders of Israel, and this is what I have advised. ^16 Now quickly send word to David and warn him: ‘Do not stay at the fords[*] of the wilderness tonight, but cross over without fail, or the king and all the people with him may be wiped out.’”[*]

^17 Jonʹa·than and A·himʹa·az were staying at En-roʹgel; so a servant girl went off and told them and they went to tell King David, for they did not dare to be seen entering the city. ^18 However, a young man saw them and told Abʹsa·lom. So the two of them quickly went off and came to the house of a man in Ba·huʹrim who had a well in his courtyard. They went down into it, ^19 and the man’s wife spread a covering over the top of the well and covered it with cracked grain; no one knew about it. ^20 The servants of Abʹsa·lom came to the woman at her house and asked: “Where are A·himʹa·az and Jonʹa·than?” The woman replied: “They passed by toward the water.” Then the men searched for them but did not find them, so they returned to Jerusalem.

^21 After the men were gone, they came up out of the well and went and informed King David. They said to him: “Rise up and quickly cross the water, for this is what A·hithʹo·phel advised against you.” ^22 Immediately David and all the people with him rose up and crossed the Jordan. By daybreak, there was no one left who had not crossed the Jordan.

^23 When A·hithʹo·phel saw that his advice had not been acted on, he saddled a donkey and went to his house in his hometown. After he gave instructions to his household, he hanged[*] himself. So he died and was buried in the burial place of his forefathers.

^24 Meanwhile, David went to Ma·ha·naʹim, and Abʹsa·lom crossed the Jordan with all the men of Israel. ^25 Abʹsa·lom put A·maʹsa in charge of the army in place of Joʹab; A·maʹsa was the son of a man named Ithʹra the Israelite, who had relations with Abʹi·gail the daughter of Naʹhash, the sister of Ze·ruʹiah, Joʹab’s mother. ^26 Israel and Abʹsa·lom camped in the land of Gilʹe·ad.

^27 As soon as David came to Ma·ha·naʹim, Shoʹbi the son of Naʹhash from Rabʹbah of the Amʹmon·ites, Maʹchir the son of Amʹmi·el from Lo-deʹbar, and Bar·zilʹlai the Gilʹe·ad·ite from Ro·geʹlim ^28 brought beds, basins, clay pots, wheat, barley, flour, roasted grain, broad beans, lentils, parched grain, ^29 honey, butter, sheep, and cheese.[*] They brought all of this out for David and the people with him to eat, for they said: “The people are hungry and tired and thirsty in the wilderness.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:2 Or “feeble in both hands.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:8 Or “bitter of soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:9 Or “pits; ravines.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:14 Or “commanded.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:16 Or possibly, “the desert plains.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:16 Lit., “swallowed up.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:23 Or “strangled.”

^ 2 Sam. 17:29 Lit., “curds of cattle.”

2 Samuel  18 : 1 - 33

18 Then David numbered the men who were with him and placed over them chiefs of thousands and chiefs of hundreds. ^2 And David sent one third of the men under the command[*] of Joʹab, one third under the command of Joʹab’s brother A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah, and one third under the command of Itʹtai the Gitʹtite. The king then said to the men: “I will also go out with you.” ^3 But they said: “You must not go out, for if we flee, they would not care about[*] us; and if half of us would die, they would not care about us, because you are worth 10,000 of us. Therefore, it would be better if you would send us help from the city.” ^4 The king said to them: “Whatever seems best to you, I will do.” So the king stood next to the city gate, and all the men went out by hundreds and by thousands. ^5 Then the king gave Joʹab and A·bishʹai and Itʹtai this order: “Deal gently with the young man Abʹsa·lom for my sake.” All the men heard it when the king gave all the chiefs the order about Abʹsa·lom.

^6 The men went out to the field to meet Israel, and the battle took place in the forest of Eʹphra·im. ^7 There the people of Israel were defeated by the servants of David, and a great slaughter took place on that day—20,000 men. ^8 The battle spread through the whole region. Furthermore, the forest devoured more of the people than the sword did on that day.

^9 Abʹsa·lom eventually found himself facing the servants of David. Abʹsa·lom was riding on a mule, and the mule went under the thick branches of a large tree, and his head got entangled in the big tree, so that he was suspended in midair[*] while the mule he had been riding kept going. ^10 Then someone saw it and told Joʹab: “Look! I have seen Abʹsa·lom hanging in a big tree.” ^11 Joʹab replied to the man who told him: “If you saw it, why did you not strike him down to the ground on the spot? Then I would have gladly given you ten pieces of silver and a belt.” ^12 But the man said to Joʹab: “Even if I were handed[*] 1,000 pieces of silver, I could not lift my hand against the king’s son, for we heard the king order you and A·bishʹai and Itʹtai, ‘Whoever you are, watch over the young man Abʹsa·lom.’ ^13 If I had disobeyed and taken his life,[*] it could never have remained hidden from the king, and you would not have protected me.” ^14 To this Joʹab said: “I am not going to waste any more time with you!” So he took three spikes[*] in his hand and drove them through the heart of Abʹsa·lom while he was still alive in the midst of the big tree. ^15 Then ten attendants who carried Joʹab’s weapons came and struck Abʹsa·lom until he was dead. ^16 Joʹab now blew the horn, and the men returned from chasing after Israel; Joʹab called for them to halt. ^17 They took Abʹsa·lom and threw him into a big pit in the forest and piled up over him a very big heap of stones. And all Israel fled to their homes.

^18 Now Abʹsa·lom, while he was alive, had taken and set up for himself a pillar in the Valley[*] of the King, for he said: “I have no son to preserve the memory of my name.” So he named the pillar after himself, and it is called Abʹsa·lom’s Monument to this day.

^19 A·himʹa·az the son of Zaʹdok said: “Let me run, please, and break the news to the king, for Jehovah has given him justice by freeing him from his enemies.” ^20 But Joʹab said to him: “You will not be a bearer of news this day. You may break the news on another day, but today you will not break the news, because the king’s own son has died.” ^21 Then Joʹab said to a Cushʹite: “Go, tell the king what you have seen.” At that the Cushʹite bowed to Joʹab and ran off. ^22 A·himʹa·az the son of Zaʹdok said once again to Joʹab: “Whatever happens, please let me also run behind the Cushʹite.” However, Joʹab said: “Why should you run, my son, when there is no news for you to tell?” ^23 Still he said: “Whatever happens, let me run.” So Joʹab said to him: “Run!” And A·himʹa·az ran by the way of the district of the Jordan,[*] and he eventually overtook the Cushʹite.

^24 Now David was sitting between the two city gates, and the watchman went up to the roof of the gate by the wall. He looked up and saw a man running by himself. ^25 So the watchman called out and told the king. The king said: “If he is by himself, he has news to tell.” As he came steadily nearer, ^26 the watchman saw another man running. The watchman then called to the gatekeeper: “Look! Another man running by himself!” The king said: “This one is also bringing news.” ^27 The watchman said: “I can see that the first man runs like A·himʹa·az the son of Zaʹdok,” so the king said: “He is a good man, and he comes with good news.” ^28 A·himʹa·az then called out to the king: “All is well!” With that he bowed to the king with his face to the ground. Then he said: “May Jehovah your God be praised, who has surrendered the men who rebelled[*] against my lord the king!”

^29 However, the king said: “Is everything all right with the young man Abʹsa·lom?” To this A·himʹa·az said: “I saw the great commotion when Joʹab sent the king’s servant and your servant, but I did not know what it was.” ^30 So the king said: “Step aside, stand here.” At that he stepped aside and stood there.

^31 Then the Cushʹite arrived, and the Cushʹite said: “Let my lord the king accept this news: Today Jehovah has brought justice by freeing you from the hand of all those who rebelled against you.” ^32 But the king said to the Cushʹite: “Is everything all right with the young man Abʹsa·lom?” To this the Cushʹite said: “May all the enemies of my lord the king and all those who rebelled against you to harm you become like the young man!”

^33 This disturbed the king, and he went up to the roof chamber over the gateway and wept, saying as he walked: “My son Abʹsa·lom, my son, my son Abʹsa·lom! If only I had died instead of you, Abʹsa·lom my son, my son!”

^ 2 Sam. 18:2 Lit., “hand.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:3 Lit., “set heart toward.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:9 Lit., “between the heavens and the earth.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:12 Lit., “were weighing upon my palms.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:13 Or “If I had dealt treacherously against his soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:14 Or possibly, “darts; spears.” Lit., “rods.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:18 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:23 Lit., “the district.”

^ 2 Sam. 18:28 Lit., “lifted up their hand.”

2 Samuel  19 : 1 - 43

19 It was reported to Joʹab: “The king is weeping and mourning for Abʹsa·lom.” ^2 So the victory[*] on that day was turned into mourning for all the people, because they heard that the king was grieving over his son. ^3 The people quietly returned to the city that day like people who are ashamed because they fled in the battle. ^4 The king covered his face and kept crying out with a loud voice: “My son Abʹsa·lom! Abʹsa·lom my son, my son!”

^5 Then Joʹab went in to the king at the house and said: “Today you have put to shame all your servants who this day saved your life[*] and the lives[*] of your sons, your daughters, your wives, and your concubines. ^6 You love those who hate you and hate those who love you, for you have made it clear today that your chiefs and servants mean nothing to you, because I am sure that if only Abʹsa·lom were alive today and the rest of us were dead, it would be all right with you. ^7 Now get up, go out and reassure[*] your servants, because by Jehovah I swear that if you do not go out, not a man will remain with you tonight. This will be worse for you than all the injury that has come upon you from your youth until now.” ^8 So the king rose up and sat in the city gate, and all the people were informed: “Now the king is sitting in the gate.” Then all the people came before the king.

But Israel had fled, each to his home. ^9 All the people in all the tribes of Israel were disputing, saying: “The king saved us from our enemies, and he rescued us from the Phi·lisʹtines; but now he has fled the land because of Abʹsa·lom. ^10 And Abʹsa·lom, whom we anointed over us, has died in the battle. So now, why are you doing nothing to bring the king back?”

^11 King David sent this message to Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar the priests: “Speak to the elders of Judah, saying, ‘Why should you be the last ones to bring the king back to his house, when the word of all Israel has come to the king at his house? ^12 You are my brothers; you are my own bone and flesh.[*] Why should you be the last ones to bring the king back?’ ^13 And you should say to A·maʹsa, ‘Are you not my own bone and flesh? So may God do to me and add to it if you will not become my army chief from now on instead of Joʹab.’”

^14 So he won over[*] the hearts of all the men of Judah as one man, and they sent word to the king: “Come back, you and all your servants.”

^15 The king started back and reached the Jordan, and the people of Judah came to Gilʹgal to meet the king and to escort him across the Jordan. ^16 Then Shimʹe·i the son of Geʹra, the Benʹja·min·ite from Ba·huʹrim, hurried down with the men of Judah to meet King David, ^17 and there were 1,000 men from Benjamin with him. Also Ziʹba, the attendant of the house of Saul, with his 15 sons and 20 servants, rushed down to the Jordan ahead of the king. ^18 He[*] crossed the ford to bring the king’s household across and to do whatever he desired. But Shimʹe·i the son of Geʹra fell down before the king when he was about to cross the Jordan. ^19 He said to the king: “Do not let my lord hold me guilty, and do not remember the wrong your servant did on the day that my lord the king went out of Jerusalem. May the king not take it to heart, ^20 for your servant well knows that I have sinned; so today I have been the first of all the house of Joseph to come down to meet my lord the king.”

^21 At once A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah said: “Should not Shimʹe·i be put to death for this, because he cursed the anointed of Jehovah?” ^22 But David said: “What does this have to do with you, you sons of Ze·ruʹiah, that you should act against me today? Should anyone be put to death today in Israel? For do I not know that today I am king over Israel?” ^23 Then the king said to Shimʹe·i: “You will not die.” And the king gave him his oath.

^24 Me·phibʹo·sheth, the grandson of Saul, also came down to meet the king. He had not cared for his feet or trimmed his mustache or washed his garments from the day the king left until the day he returned in peace. ^25 When he came to[*] Jerusalem to meet the king, the king said to him: “Why did you not go with me, Me·phibʹo·sheth?” ^26 To this he said: “My lord the king, my servant tricked me. For your servant had said, ‘Let me get my donkey saddled so that I may ride on it and go with the king,’ for your servant is crippled. ^27 But he slandered your servant to my lord the king. However, my lord the king is like an angel of the true God, so do whatever seems good to you. ^28 All the household of my father could have been doomed to death by my lord the king, and yet you placed your servant among those eating at your table. So what right do I have to cry out further to the king?”

^29 However, the king said to him: “Why keep on speaking like this? I have decided that you and Ziʹba should share the field.” ^30 At this Me·phibʹo·sheth said to the king: “Let him take it all, now that my lord the king has come to his house in peace.”

^31 Then Bar·zilʹlai the Gilʹe·ad·ite came down from Ro·geʹlim to the Jordan to escort the king to the Jordan. ^32 Bar·zilʹlai was very old, 80 years of age, and he supplied the king with food while he was staying in Ma·ha·naʹim, for he was a very wealthy man. ^33 So the king said to Bar·zilʹlai: “Cross over with me, and I will supply you with food in Jerusalem.” ^34 But Bar·zilʹlai said to the king: “How many days[*] of my life are left that I should go up with the king to Jerusalem? ^35 I am 80 years old today. Can I discern between good and bad? Can I, your servant, taste what I eat and drink? Can I still listen to the voice of male and female singers? So why should your servant be an added burden to my lord the king? ^36 It is enough that your servant could bring the king to the Jordan. Why should the king repay me with this reward? ^37 Let your servant return, please, and let me die in my city near the burial place of my father and my mother. But here is your servant Chimʹham. Let him cross over with my lord the king, and you may do for him what seems good to you.”

^38 So the king said: “Chimʹham will go across with me, and I will do for him what seems good to you; whatever you ask of me I will do for you.” ^39 All the people now began to cross the Jordan, and when the king crossed, the king kissed Bar·zilʹlai and blessed him; and Bar·zilʹlai returned home. ^40 When the king went across to Gilʹgal, Chimʹham crossed with him. All the people of Judah and half the people of Israel brought the king across.

^41 Then all the men of Israel approached the king and said to him: “Why did our brothers the men of Judah steal you away and bring the king and his household over the Jordan, along with all of David’s men?” ^42 All the men of Judah answered the men of Israel: “Because the king is related to us. Why are you angry over this? Have we eaten anything at the king’s expense, or has a gift been given to us?”

^43 However, the men of Israel answered the men of Judah: “We have ten parts in the king, so that we have a greater claim in David than you have. Why, then, have you treated us with contempt? Should we not have been first to bring our king back?” But the word of the men of Judah prevailed over[*] that of the men of Israel.

^ 2 Sam. 19:2 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:5 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:5 Or “souls.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:7 Lit., “speak to the heart of.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:12 Or “my blood relatives.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:14 Lit., “he bent.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:18 Or possibly, “They.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:25 Or possibly, “from.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:34 Lit., “days of years.”

^ 2 Sam. 19:43 Or “was more severe than.”

2 Samuel  20 : 1 - 26

20 Now there was a troublemaker named Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri, a Benʹja·min·ite. He blew the horn and said: “We have no share in David, and we have no inheritance in the son of Jesʹse. Everyone to his gods,[*] O Israel!” ^2 At that all the men of Israel quit following David to follow Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri; but the men of Judah stuck to their king, from the Jordan to Jerusalem.

^3 When David came to his house[*] at Jerusalem, the king took the ten concubines he had left behind to take care of the house, and he put them in a house under guard. He supplied food to them, but he did not have any relations with them. They remained in confinement until the day of their death, living as if they were widows, even though they had a living husband.

^4 The king now said to A·maʹsa: “Call the men of Judah together to me within three days, and you also should be here.” ^5 So A·maʹsa went to call Judah together, but he came later than the set time that had been appointed for him. ^6 Then David said to A·bishʹai: “Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri may do us more harm than Abʹsa·lom did. Take the servants of your lord and chase after him, so that he may not find fortified cities and escape from us.” ^7 So the men of Joʹab, the Cherʹe·thites, the Pelʹe·thites, and all the mighty men went out after him; they left Jerusalem to chase after Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri. ^8 When they were near the great stone in Gibʹe·on, A·maʹsa came to meet them. Now Joʹab was wearing his battle clothing, and he had a sword in its sheath strapped to his hip. When he stepped forward, the sword fell out.

^9 Joʹab said to A·maʹsa: “Are you all right, my brother?” Then with his right hand, Joʹab took hold of A·maʹsa’s beard as if to kiss him. ^10 A·maʹsa was not on guard against the sword that was in Joʹab’s hand, and Joʹab stabbed him with it in the abdomen, and his intestines spilled out on the ground. He did not have to stab him again; once was enough to kill him. Then Joʹab and his brother A·bishʹai chased after Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri.

^11 One of Joʹab’s young men stood by him and was saying: “Whoever is on Joʹab’s side and whoever belongs to David, let him follow Joʹab!” ^12 All the while A·maʹsa was wallowing in his blood in the middle of the road. When the man saw that all the people were stopping, he moved A·maʹsa from the road to the field. Then he threw a garment over him, because he saw that everyone was stopping when they came up to him. ^13 After he had removed him from the road, all the men followed Joʹab to chase after Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri.

^14 Sheʹba passed through all the tribes of Israel to Abel of Beth-maʹa·cah. The Bichʹrites gathered together and also went in after him.

^15 Joʹab and his men[*] came and besieged him in Abel of Beth-maʹa·cah and raised up a siege rampart against the city, as it was standing within a rampart. And all the men with Joʹab were undermining the wall to knock it down. ^16 And a wise woman called out from the city: “Listen, men, listen! Please tell Joʹab, ‘Come here, and let me speak to you.’” ^17 So he went near to her, and the woman said: “Are you Joʹab?” He replied: “I am.” At this she said to him: “Listen to the words of your servant.” He said: “I am listening.” ^18 She continued: “They would always say in the past, ‘Let them inquire in Abel, and that was the end of the matter.’ ^19 I represent the peaceable and faithful ones of Israel. You are seeking to destroy a city that is like a mother in Israel. Why should you do away with[*] the inheritance of Jehovah?” ^20 Joʹab answered: “It is unthinkable for me to do away with it and destroy it. ^21 That is not the case at all. Rather, a man named Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri from the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im has rebelled[*] against King David. If you hand over this one man, I will withdraw from the city.” Then the woman said to Joʹab: “Look! His head will be thrown over the wall to you!”

^22 At once the wise woman went in to all the people, and they cut off the head of Sheʹba the son of Bichʹri and threw it to Joʹab. At that he blew the horn, and they dispersed from the city, each one to his home; and Joʹab returned to Jerusalem to the king.

^23 Now Joʹab was in charge of all the army of Israel; Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was over the Cherʹe·thites and the Pelʹe·thites. ^24 A·doʹram was over those conscripted for forced labor; Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of A·hiʹlud was the recorder. ^25 Sheʹva was the secretary; Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar were priests. ^26 And Iʹra the Jaʹir·ite also became a chief minister[*] for David.

^ 2 Sam. 20:1 Or possibly, “tents.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:3 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:15 Lit., “They.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:19 Lit., “swallow up.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:21 Lit., “lifted up his hand.”

^ 2 Sam. 20:26 Lit., “became a priest.”

2 Samuel  21 : 1 - 22

21 Now there was a famine in the days of David for three consecutive years, so David consulted Jehovah, and Jehovah said: “There is bloodguilt on Saul and on his house, because he put the Gibʹe·on·ites to death.” ^2 So the king called the Gibʹe·on·ites and spoke to them. (Incidentally, the Gibʹe·on·ites were not Israelites but Amʹor·ites who remained, and the Israelites had sworn to spare them, but Saul sought to strike them down in his zeal for the people of Israel and Judah.) ^3 David said to the Gibʹe·on·ites: “What should I do for you, and how can I make atonement, so that you will bless the inheritance of Jehovah?” ^4 The Gibʹe·on·ites said to him: “It is not a matter of silver or gold for us in connection with Saul and his household; nor can we put any man to death in Israel.” At that he said: “Whatever you say, I will do for you.” ^5 They said to the king: “The man who exterminated us and schemed to annihilate us from living anywhere in the territory of Israel— ^6 let seven of his sons be given to us. We will hang their dead bodies[*] before Jehovah in Gibʹe·ah of Saul, the chosen one of Jehovah.” The king then said: “I will hand them over.”

^7 However, the king showed compassion for Me·phibʹo·sheth, the son of Jonʹa·than the son of Saul, because of the oath made before Jehovah between David and Jonʹa·than, the son of Saul. ^8 So the king took Ar·moʹni and Me·phibʹo·sheth, the two sons of Rizʹpah the daughter of Aʹiah whom she bore to Saul, and the five sons of Miʹchal[*] the daughter of Saul whom she bore to Aʹdri·el the son of Bar·zilʹlai the Me·holʹath·ite. ^9 Then he handed them over to the Gibʹe·on·ites, and they hung their dead bodies on the mountain before Jehovah. All seven of them died together; they were put to death in the first days of harvest, at the start of the barley harvest. ^10 Then Rizʹpah the daughter of Aʹiah took sackcloth and spread it out on the rock from the start of harvest until rain poured down from the heavens on the bodies; she did not allow the birds of the heavens to land on them by day nor the wild beasts of the field to come near by night.

^11 David was told what Saul’s concubine Rizʹpah the daughter of Aʹiah had done. ^12 So David went and took the bones of Saul and the bones of his son Jonʹa·than from the leaders[*] of Jaʹbesh-gilʹe·ad, who had stolen them from the public square of Beth-shan, where the Phi·lisʹtines had hung them on the day that the Phi·lisʹtines struck down Saul on Gil·boʹa. ^13 He brought the bones of Saul and the bones of his son Jonʹa·than up from there, and they also gathered the bones of the men who had been executed.[*] ^14 Then they buried the bones of Saul and of Jonʹa·than his son in the land of Benjamin in Zeʹla in the tomb of Kish his father. After they did everything that the king had commanded, God listened to their entreaties for the land.

^15 Once again there was war between the Phi·lisʹtines and Israel. So David and his servants went down and fought the Phi·lisʹtines, but David became exhausted. ^16 A descendant of the Rephʹa·im named Ishʹbi-beʹnob, whose copper spear weighed 300 shekels[*] and who was armed with a new sword, intended to strike David down. ^17 At once A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah came to his aid and struck the Phi·lisʹtine down and put him to death. At that time the men of David swore this oath to him: “You must not go out with us to battle anymore! You must not extinguish the lamp of Israel!”

^18 After this, war broke out again with the Phi·lisʹtines at Gob. At that time Sibʹbe·cai the Huʹshath·ite struck down Saph, who was a descendant of the Rephʹa·im.

^19 And war broke out again with the Phi·lisʹtines at Gob, and El·haʹnan the son of Jaʹa·re-orʹe·gim the Bethʹle·hem·ite struck down Go·liʹath the Gitʹtite, whose spear had a shaft like the beam of loom workers.

^20 War broke out yet again at Gath, where there was a man of extraordinary size, with 6 fingers on each hand and 6 toes on each foot, 24 in all; and he too was a descendant of the Rephʹa·im. ^21 He kept taunting Israel. So Jonʹa·than the son of Shimʹe·i, David’s brother, struck him down.

^22 These four were descendants of the Rephʹa·im in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.

^ 2 Sam. 21:6 Lit., “will expose them,” that is, with arms and legs broken.

^ 2 Sam. 21:8 Or possibly, “Merab.”

^ 2 Sam. 21:12 Or possibly, “landowners.”

^ 2 Sam. 21:13 Lit., “exposed.”

^ 2 Sam. 21:16 About 3.42 kg (7.5 lb). See App. B14.

2 Samuel  23 : 1 - 39

23 These are the last words of David:

“The word of David the son of Jesʹse,

And the word of the man who was raised on high,

The anointed of the God of Jacob,

The pleasant singer[*] of the songs of Israel.

 ^2 The spirit of Jehovah spoke through me;

His word was on my tongue.

 ^3 The God of Israel spoke;

To me the Rock of Israel said:

‘When the one ruling over mankind is righteous,

Ruling in the fear of God,

 ^4 It is like the morning light when the sun shines,

A morning without clouds.

It is like the brightness after the rain,

Making grass sprout from the earth.’

 ^5 Is not my house like that before God?

For he has made an eternal covenant with me,

Arranged in every detail and secured.

Because it means my complete salvation and all my delight,

Is that not why he makes it flourish?

 ^6 But worthless men are all thrown away like thornbushes,

For they cannot be taken with the hand.

 ^7 When a man touches them,

He should be fully armed with iron and the shaft of a spear,

And they should be completely burned up with fire in their place.”

^8 These are the names of David’s mighty warriors: Joʹsheb-bas·sheʹbeth a Tah·cheʹmo·nite, the head of the three. He brandished his spear over 800 slain at one time. ^9 Next to him, El·e·aʹzar the son of Doʹdo the son of A·hoʹhi was among the three mighty warriors with David when they taunted the Phi·lisʹtines. They had gathered there for the battle, and when the men of Israel retreated, ^10 he stood his ground and kept striking down the Phi·lisʹtines until his arm grew weary and his hand became stiff from gripping the sword. So Jehovah brought about a great victory[*] on that day; and the people returned behind him to strip the slain.

^11 Next to him was Shamʹmah the son of Aʹgee the Harʹa·rite. The Phi·lisʹtines gathered together at Leʹhi, where there was a plot of land full of lentils; and the people fled because of the Phi·lisʹtines. ^12 But he took his stand in the middle of the field and defended it and kept striking down the Phi·lisʹtines, so that Jehovah brought about a great victory.[*]

^13 Three of the 30 headmen went down during the harvest to David at the cave of A·dulʹlam, and a company[*] of the Phi·lisʹtines was camped in the Valley[*] of Rephʹa·im. ^14 David was then in the stronghold, and an outpost of the Phi·lisʹtines was in Bethʹle·hem. ^15 Then David expressed his longing: “If only I could have a drink of the water from the cistern by the gate of Bethʹle·hem!” ^16 At that the three mighty warriors forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines and drew water from the cistern by the gate of Bethʹle·hem and brought it to David; but he refused to drink it and poured it out to Jehovah. ^17 He said: “It is unthinkable on my part, O Jehovah, that I should do this! Should I drink the blood of the men going at the risk of their lives?”[*] So he refused to drink it. These are the things that his three mighty warriors did.

^18 A·bishʹai the brother of Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah was the head of another three; he brandished his spear over 300 slain, and he had a reputation like the three. ^19 Although he was the most distinguished of the other three and he was their chief, he did not attain to the rank of the first three.

^20 Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was a courageous man[*] who performed many exploits in Kabʹze·el. He struck down the two sons of Arʹi·el of Moʹab, and he descended into a waterpit on a snowy day and killed a lion. ^21 He also struck down an Egyptian man of extraordinary size. Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand, he went against him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. ^22 These things Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da did, and he had a reputation like that of the three mighty warriors. ^23 Although he was distinguished even more than the thirty, he did not attain to the rank of the three. However, David appointed him over his own bodyguard.

^24 Asʹa·hel the brother of Joʹab was among the thirty: El·haʹnan the son of Doʹdo of Bethʹle·hem, ^25 Shamʹmah the Haʹrod·ite, E·liʹka the Haʹrod·ite, ^26 Heʹlez the Palʹtite, Iʹra the son of Ikʹkesh the Te·koʹite, ^27 Abi-eʹzer the Anʹa·thoth·ite, Me·bunʹnai the Huʹshath·ite, ^28 Zalʹmon the A·hoʹhite, Maʹha·rai the Ne·tophʹa·thite, ^29 Heʹleb the son of Baʹa·nah the Ne·tophʹa·thite, Itʹtai the son of Riʹbai of Gibʹe·ah of the Benʹja·min·ites, ^30 Be·naiʹah a Pirʹa·thon·ite, Hidʹdai of the wadis[*] of Gaʹash, ^31 Aʹbi-alʹbon the Arʹbath·ite, Azʹma·veth the Bar-huʹmite, ^32 E·liʹah·ba the Sha·alʹbo·nite, the sons of Jaʹshen, Jonʹa·than, ^33 Shamʹmah the Harʹa·rite, A·hiʹam the son of Shaʹrar the Harʹa·rite, ^34 E·liphʹe·let the son of A·hasʹbai the son of the Ma·acʹa·thite, E·liʹam the son of A·hithʹo·phel the Giʹlon·ite, ^35 Hezʹro the Carʹmel·ite, Paʹa·rai the Arʹbite, ^36 Iʹgal the son of Nathan of Zoʹbah, Baʹni the Gadʹite, ^37 Zeʹlek the Amʹmon·ite, Naʹha·rai the Be·erʹoth·ite, the armor-bearer of Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah, ^38 Iʹra the Ithʹrite, Gaʹreb the Ithʹrite, ^39 and U·riʹah the Hitʹtite—37 in all.

^ 2 Sam. 23:1 Or “The pleasant one.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:10 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:12 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:13 Or “tent village.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:13 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:17 Or “souls?”

^ 2 Sam. 23:20 Lit., “the son of a man of valor.”

^ 2 Sam. 23:30 See Glossary.

2 Samuel  24 : 1 - 25

24 The anger of Jehovah again blazed against Israel when one incited David[*] against them, saying: “Go, take a count of Israel and Judah.” ^2 So the king said to Joʹab the chief of the army who was with him: “Please go through all the tribes of Israel, from Dan to Beʹer-sheʹba, and register the people, so that I may know the number of the people.” ^3 But Joʹab said to the king: “May Jehovah your God multiply the people 100 times, and may the eyes of my lord the king see it, but why does my lord the king want to do such a thing?”

^4 But the king’s word prevailed over Joʹab and the chiefs of the army. So Joʹab and the chiefs of the army went out from before the king to register the people of Israel. ^5 They crossed the Jordan and camped at A·roʹer, to the right[*] of the city in the middle of the valley,[*] and they went toward the Gadʹites and on to Jaʹzer. ^6 After that they went on to Gilʹe·ad and the land of Tahʹtim-hodʹshi and continued to Dan-jaʹan and went around to Siʹdon. ^7 Then they went to the fortress of Tyre and all the cities of the Hiʹvites and of the Caʹnaan·ites, and finally they ended up in the Negʹeb of Judah at Beʹer-sheʹba. ^8 Thus they went through all the land and came to Jerusalem at the end of nine months and 20 days. ^9 Joʹab now gave to the king the number of the people who were registered. Israel amounted to 800,000 warriors armed with swords, and the men of Judah were 500,000.

^10 But David’s heart[*] was struck with remorse after he had numbered the people. David then said to Jehovah: “I have sinned greatly by doing this. And now, Jehovah, please forgive your servant’s error, for I have acted very foolishly.” ^11 When David got up in the morning, Jehovah’s word came to Gad the prophet, David’s visionary, saying: ^12 “Go and say to David, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I am giving you three options. Choose the one that I should bring on you.”’” ^13 So Gad came in to David and told him: “Should seven years of famine come on your land? Or should you flee for three months from your adversaries while they pursue you? Or should there be three days of pestilence in your land? Now consider carefully what I should reply to the One who sent me.” ^14 So David said to Gad: “It is very distressing to me. Let us fall, please, into the hand of Jehovah, for his mercy is great; but do not let me fall into the hand of man.”

^15 Then Jehovah sent a pestilence on Israel from the morning until the designated time, so that 70,000 of the people from Dan to Beʹer-sheʹba died. ^16 When the angel stretched out his hand toward Jerusalem to destroy it, Jehovah felt regret[*] over the calamity, and he said to the angel bringing destruction among the people: “It is enough! Now let your hand drop.” Jehovah’s angel was close to the threshing floor of A·rauʹnah the Jebʹu·site.

^17 When David saw the angel who was striking the people down, he said to Jehovah: “I am the one who sinned, and I am the one who did wrong; but these sheep—what have they done? Let your hand, please, come against me and my father’s house.”

^18 So Gad came in to David on that day and said to him: “Go up, set up for Jehovah an altar on the threshing floor of A·rauʹnah the Jebʹu·site.” ^19 So David went up at the word of Gad, as Jehovah had commanded. ^20 When A·rauʹnah looked down and saw the king and his servants coming toward him, A·rauʹnah immediately went out and bowed down to the king with his face to the ground. ^21 A·rauʹnah asked: “Why has my lord the king come to his servant?” David replied: “To buy from you the threshing floor in order to build an altar to Jehovah, so that the scourge against the people may be halted.” ^22 But A·rauʹnah said to David: “Let my lord the king take it and offer up what seems good to him.[*] Here are cattle for the burnt offering and the threshing sledge and the equipment of the cattle for the wood. ^23 All of this, O king, A·rauʹnah gives to the king.” Then A·rauʹnah said to the king: “May Jehovah your God show you favor.”

^24 However, the king said to A·rauʹnah: “No, I must buy it from you for a price. I will not offer up to Jehovah my God burnt sacrifices that cost me nothing.” So David bought the threshing floor and the cattle for 50 silver shekels.[*] ^25 And David built an altar there to Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices. Jehovah then responded to the entreaty for the land, and the scourge against Israel was halted.

^ 2 Sam. 24:1 Or “when David was incited.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:5 Or “the south.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:5 Or “wadi.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:10 Or “conscience.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:16 Or “grieved.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:22 Lit., “what is good in his eyes.”

^ 2 Sam. 24:24 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

1 Kings  1 : 1 - 53

THE FIRST OF KINGS

1 Now King David was old, advanced in years,[*] and although they would cover him with garments, he could not get warm. ^2 So his servants said to him: “Let a girl, a virgin, be found for my lord the king, and she will wait on the king as his nurse. She will lie in your arms so that my lord the king may feel warm.” ^3 They searched throughout all the territory of Israel for a beautiful girl, and they found Abʹi·shag the Shuʹnam·mite and brought her in to the king. ^4 The girl was extremely beautiful, and she became the king’s nurse and waited on him, but the king did not have sexual relations with her.

^5 Meanwhile, Ad·o·niʹjah the son of Hagʹgith was exalting himself, saying: “I am going to be king!” He had a chariot made for himself with horsemen and 50 men to run before him. ^6 But his father had never confronted him[*] by saying: “Why have you done this?” He was also very handsome, and his mother had given birth to him after Abʹsa·lom. ^7 He conferred with Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah and A·biʹa·thar the priest, and they offered Ad·o·niʹjah help and support. ^8 But Zaʹdok the priest, Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, Nathan the prophet, Shimʹe·i, Reʹi, and David’s mighty warriors did not support Ad·o·niʹjah.

^9 Eventually Ad·o·niʹjah held a sacrifice of sheep, cattle, and fattened animals by the stone of Zoʹhe·leth, which is near En-roʹgel, and he invited all his brothers the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah the king’s servants. ^10 But he did not invite Nathan the prophet, Be·naiʹah and the mighty warriors, or Solʹo·mon his brother. ^11 Nathan then said to Bath-sheʹba, Solʹo·mon’s mother: “Have you not heard that Ad·o·niʹjah the son of Hagʹgith has become king, and our lord David does not know anything about it? ^12 So now come, please, and let me advise you, so that you may save your own life and the life of[*] your son Solʹo·mon. ^13 Go in to King David and say to him, ‘Was it not you, my lord the king, who swore to your servant, saying: “Your son Solʹo·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne”? So why has Ad·o·niʹjah become king?’ ^14 While you are still there speaking with the king, I will come in after you and confirm your words.”

^15 So Bath-sheʹba went in to the king, into his private room. The king was very old, and Abʹi·shag the Shuʹnam·mite was waiting on the king. ^16 Then Bath-sheʹba bowed low and prostrated herself to the king, and the king said: “What is your request?” ^17 She replied: “My lord, it was you who swore by Jehovah your God to your servant, ‘Your son Solʹo·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne.’ ^18 But look! Ad·o·niʹjah has become king, and my lord the king does not know anything about it. ^19 He sacrificed bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity and invited all the sons of the king and A·biʹa·thar the priest and Joʹab the chief of the army; but he did not invite your servant Solʹo·mon. ^20 And now, my lord the king, the eyes of all Israel are upon you to tell them who will sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. ^21 Otherwise, as soon as my lord the king is laid to rest with his forefathers, I and also my son Solʹo·mon will be considered traitors.”

^22 And while she was still speaking to the king, Nathan the prophet came in. ^23 At once the king was told: “Here is Nathan the prophet!” He came in before the king and prostrated himself to the king with his face to the ground. ^24 Then Nathan said: “My lord the king, did you say, ‘Ad·o·niʹjah will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne’? ^25 For today he has gone down to sacrifice bulls, fattened animals, and sheep in great quantity, and he has invited all the sons of the king and the chiefs of the army and A·biʹa·thar the priest. They are there eating and drinking with him, and they keep saying, ‘Long live King Ad·o·niʹjah!’ ^26 But he did not invite me, your servant, or Zaʹdok the priest, or Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, or your servant Solʹo·mon. ^27 Has my lord the king authorized this without telling your servant who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?”

^28 King David now answered: “Call Bath-sheʹba for me.” At that she came in and stood before the king. ^29 The king then swore an oath: “As surely as Jehovah is living, the one who rescued me[*] out of all distress, ^30 just as I swore to you by Jehovah the God of Israel, saying, ‘Your son Solʹo·mon will become king after me, and he is the one who will sit on my throne in my place!’ that is what I will bring about this day.” ^31 Then Bath-sheʹba bowed low with her face to the ground and prostrated herself to the king and said: “May my lord King David live forever!”

^32 Immediately King David said: “Call for me Zaʹdok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da.” So they came in before the king. ^33 The king said to them: “Take with you the servants of your lord, and have my son Solʹo·mon ride on my own mule,[*] and lead him down to Giʹhon. ^34 Zaʹdok the priest and Nathan the prophet will anoint him there as king over Israel; then blow the horn and say, ‘Long live King Solʹo·mon!’ ^35 Then follow him back, and he will come in and sit on my throne; and he will be king in my place, and I will commission him as leader over Israel and over Judah.” ^36 At once Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da said to the king: “Amen! May Jehovah the God of my lord the king confirm it. ^37 Just as Jehovah was with my lord the king, so let him be with Solʹo·mon, and may He make his throne greater than the throne of my lord King David.”

^38 Then Zaʹdok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, and the Cherʹe·thites and the Pelʹe·thites went down and had Solʹo·mon ride on the mule of King David, and they brought him to Giʹhon. ^39 Zaʹdok the priest now took the horn of oil out of the tent and anointed Solʹo·mon, and they began to blow the horn, and all the people began shouting: “Long live King Solʹo·mon!” ^40 After that all the people followed him and went up, playing flutes and rejoicing greatly, so that the earth was split open by their noise.

^41 Ad·o·niʹjah and all those invited by him heard it when they had finished eating. As soon as Joʹab heard the sound of the horn, he said: “Why is there such a noisy uproar in the city?” ^42 While he was still speaking, Jonʹa·than the son of A·biʹa·thar the priest came. Then Ad·o·niʹjah said: “Come in, for you are a good[*] man, and you must bring good news.” ^43 But Jonʹa·than answered Ad·o·niʹjah: “No! Our lord King David has made Solʹo·mon king. ^44 The king sent with him Zaʹdok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, and the Cherʹe·thites and the Pelʹe·thites, and they had him ride on the mule of the king. ^45 Then Zaʹdok the priest and Nathan the prophet anointed him as king in Giʹhon. After that they came up from there rejoicing, and the city is in an uproar. That was the noise that you heard. ^46 Moreover, Solʹo·mon has sat down on the royal throne. ^47 Another thing, the servants of the king have come in to congratulate our lord King David, saying, ‘May your God make Solʹo·mon’s name more splendid than your name, and may He make his throne greater than your throne!’ At that the king bowed down on the bed. ^48 And the king also said, ‘May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, who today has granted someone to sit on my throne and has allowed my own eyes to see it!’”

^49 And all those invited by Ad·o·niʹjah became terrified, and each of them rose up and went his own way. ^50 Ad·o·niʹjah was also afraid because of Solʹo·mon, so he got up and went and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar. ^51 The report was made to Solʹo·mon: “Here Ad·o·niʹjah has become afraid of King Solʹo·mon; and he has taken hold of the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let King Solʹo·mon first swear to me that he will not put his servant to death by the sword.’” ^52 To this Solʹo·mon said: “If he behaves in a worthy manner, not a single hair of his will fall to the ground; but if what is bad is found in him, he will have to die.” ^53 So King Solʹo·mon sent for him to be brought down from the altar. Then he came in and bowed down to King Solʹo·mon, after which Solʹo·mon said to him: “Go to your own house.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:1 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:6 Or “hurt his feelings; rebuked him.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:12 Or “your own soul and the soul of.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:29 Or “redeemed my soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:33 Or “she-mule.”

^ 1 Ki. 1:42 Or “worthy.”

1 Kings  2 : 1 - 46

2 When the time of David’s death drew near, he gave his son Solʹo·mon these instructions: ^2 “I am about to die.[*] Therefore, be strong and prove yourself a man. ^3 You must keep your obligation to Jehovah your God by walking in his ways and by observing his statutes, his commandments, his judgments, and his reminders as they are written in the Law of Moses; then you will succeed[*] in everything you do and everywhere you turn. ^4 And Jehovah will carry out his promise that he made concerning me: ‘If your sons pay attention to their way by walking faithfully before me with all their heart and soul,[*] there will never fail to be a man of your line[*] sitting on the throne of Israel.’

^5 “You also well know what Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah did to me, what he did to two chiefs of the armies of Israel—Abʹner the son of Ner and A·maʹsa the son of Jeʹther. He killed them, shedding the blood of war in peacetime, and he put the blood of war on the belt around his waist and on the sandals on his feet. ^6 You must act according to your wisdom and not let his gray hairs go down in peace to the Grave.[*]

^7 “But toward the sons of Bar·zilʹlai the Gilʹe·ad·ite, you should show loyal love, and they should be among those eating at your table, for that was how they stood by me when I ran away from your brother Abʹsa·lom.

^8 “There is also with you Shimʹe·i the son of Geʹra the Benʹja·min·ite from Ba·huʹrim. He was the one who cursed me with a vicious curse on the day that I was going to Ma·ha·naʹim; but when he came down to meet me at the Jordan, I swore to him by Jehovah: ‘I will not put you to death by the sword.’ ^9 Now do not leave him unpunished, for you are a wise man and you know what you should do to him; you must bring his gray hairs down to the Grave[*] with blood.”

^10 Then David was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David. ^11 The length[*] of David’s reign over Israel was 40 years. In Hebʹron he reigned for 7 years, and in Jerusalem he reigned for 33 years.

^12 Solʹo·mon then sat down on the throne of David his father, and gradually his kingship became firmly established.

^13 In time Ad·o·niʹjah the son of Hagʹgith came to Bath-sheʹba, Solʹo·mon’s mother. She asked: “Is your coming peaceable?” He replied: “It is peaceable.” ^14 He then said: “I have something to say to you.” So she said: “Speak.” ^15 He continued: “You well know that the kingship was to become mine, and all Israel expected[*] me to become king; but the kingship eluded me and became my brother’s, for it was from Jehovah that it became his. ^16 But now there is just one request that I am making of you. Do not turn me away.” So she said to him: “Speak.” ^17 He then said: “Please, ask Solʹo·mon the king—for he will not turn you away—to give me Abʹi·shag the Shuʹnam·mite as a wife.” ^18 To this Bath-sheʹba said: “Very well! I will speak for you to the king.”

^19 So Bath-sheʹba went in to King Solʹo·mon to speak to him for Ad·o·niʹjah. At once the king rose to meet her and bowed down to her. Then he sat down on his throne and had a throne set for the king’s mother, so that she could sit at his right. ^20 She then said: “There is one small request that I am making of you. Do not turn me away.” So the king said to her: “Make it, my mother; for I will not turn you away.” ^21 She said: “Let Abʹi·shag the Shuʹnam·mite be given as a wife to your brother Ad·o·niʹjah.” ^22 At this King Solʹo·mon answered his mother: “Why are you requesting Abʹi·shag the Shuʹnam·mite for Ad·o·niʹjah? You may as well request the kingship for him, for he is my older brother, and supporting him are A·biʹa·thar the priest and Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah.”

^23 With that King Solʹo·mon swore by Jehovah: “So may God do to me and add to it if it was not at the cost of his own life[*] that Ad·o·niʹjah made this request. ^24 And now, as surely as Jehovah is living, who has firmly established me and seated me on the throne of David my father and who made a house[*] for me, just as he promised, Ad·o·niʹjah will be put to death today.” ^25 King Solʹo·mon immediately sent Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, who went out and struck Ad·o·niʹjah down,[*] and he died.

^26 To A·biʹa·thar the priest, the king said: “Go to your fields in Anʹa·thoth! You deserve to die, but on this day I will not put you to death because you carried the Ark of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah before David my father and because you shared in all the hardships that my father suffered.” ^27 So Solʹo·mon drove A·biʹa·thar out from serving as a priest of Jehovah, to fulfill Jehovah’s word against the house of Eʹli in Shiʹloh.

^28 When the news reached Joʹab—for Joʹab had supported Ad·o·niʹjah but he had not supported Abʹsa·lom—Joʹab fled to the tent of Jehovah and grabbed hold of the horns of the altar. ^29 Then King Solʹo·mon was told: “Joʹab has fled to the tent of Jehovah, and he is there beside the altar.” So Solʹo·mon sent Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, saying: “Go, strike him down!” ^30 So Be·naiʹah went to the tent of Jehovah and said to him: “This is what the king says, ‘Come out!’” But he said: “No! I will die here.” Be·naiʹah brought word back to the king: “This is what Joʹab said, and this is what he answered me.” ^31 Then the king said to him: “Do just as he said; strike him down and bury him and remove from me and from the house of my father the blood that Joʹab spilled without just cause. ^32 Jehovah will bring his blood back on his own head, for without my father David’s knowledge, he struck down and killed with the sword two men more righteous and better than he was: Abʹner the son of Ner, the chief of the army of Israel, and A·maʹsa the son of Jeʹther, the chief of the army of Judah. ^33 Their blood will come back on the head of Joʹab and on the head of his offspring[*] forever; but for David, his offspring,[*] his house, and his throne, may there be peace from Jehovah forever.” ^34 Then Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da went up and struck Joʹab down and put him to death, and he was buried at his own house in the wilderness. ^35 Then the king appointed Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da over the army in his place, and the king appointed Zaʹdok the priest in place of A·biʹa·thar.

^36 Then the king summoned Shimʹe·i and said to him: “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem, and live there; do not go out from there to any other place. ^37 On the day you go out and cross the Kidʹron Valley, you can be sure that you will die. Your blood will be on your own head.” ^38 Shimʹe·i replied to the king: “What you have said is fair. Your servant will do just as my lord the king has said.” So Shimʹe·i stayed in Jerusalem for many days.

^39 But at the end of three years, two of Shimʹe·i’s slaves ran away to Aʹchish the son of Maʹa·cah the king of Gath. When Shimʹe·i was told: “Look! Your slaves are in Gath,” ^40 Shimʹe·i immediately saddled his donkey and went to see Aʹchish in Gath to find his slaves. When Shimʹe·i returned from Gath with his slaves, ^41 Solʹo·mon was told: “Shimʹe·i has gone out of Jerusalem to Gath and has returned.” ^42 At that the king summoned Shimʹe·i and said to him: “Did I not put you under oath by Jehovah and warn you: ‘On the day you go out from here to any other place, you can be sure that you will die’? And did you not say to me, ‘What you are saying is fair; I will obey’? ^43 Why, then, did you not keep the oath of Jehovah and the commandment that I imposed on you?” ^44 The king then said to Shimʹe·i: “You know in your heart all the injury that you did to David my father, and Jehovah will bring back that injury on your own head. ^45 But King Solʹo·mon will be blessed, and the throne of David will be firmly established before Jehovah forever.” ^46 With that the king commanded Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da, who went out and struck him down, and he died.

Thus the kingdom was firmly established in the hand of Solʹo·mon.

^ 1 Ki. 2:2 Lit., “I am going in the way of all the earth.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:3 Or “act wisely.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:4 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 2:4 Lit., “will not be cut off from you a man.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:6 Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 2:9 Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 2:11 Lit., “The days.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:15 Lit., “had set their faces on.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:23 Or “not against his own soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:24 Or “dynasty.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:25 Or “who fell upon Adonijah.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:33 Or “descendants.”

^ 1 Ki. 2:33 Or “descendants.”

1 Kings  3 : 1 - 28

3 Solʹo·mon made a marriage alliance with Pharʹaoh king of Egypt. He married[*] Pharʹaoh’s daughter and brought her to the City of David until he finished building his own house, and the house of Jehovah, and the wall around Jerusalem. ^2 But the people were still sacrificing on the high places, because until that time a house for the name of Jehovah had not yet been built. ^3 Solʹo·mon continued to love Jehovah by walking in the statutes of David his father, except that he was sacrificing and making offerings smoke on the high places.

^4 The king went to Gibʹe·on to sacrifice there, for that was the most prominent[*] high place. Solʹo·mon offered 1,000 burnt sacrifices on that altar. ^5 In Gibʹe·on Jehovah appeared to Solʹo·mon in a dream by night, and God said: “Ask what you would like me to give you.” ^6 At this Solʹo·mon said: “You have shown great loyal love toward your servant David my father as he walked before you in faithfulness and in righteousness and in uprightness of heart. You have continued to show him this great loyal love down to this day by giving him a son to sit on his throne. ^7 And now, Jehovah my God, you have made your servant king in the place of David my father, though I am just a youth[*] and I am inexperienced.[*] ^8 Your servant is among your people whom you have chosen, a people so vast that they cannot be numbered or counted. ^9 So grant your servant an obedient heart to judge your people, to discern between good and bad, for who is able to judge this numerous[*] people of yours?”

^10 It was pleasing to Jehovah that Solʹo·mon had requested this. ^11 God then said to him: “Because you requested this and you did not request for yourself long life[*] or riches or the death[*] of your enemies, but you requested understanding to hear judicial cases, ^12 I will do what you asked. I will give you a wise and understanding heart, so that just as there has never been anyone like you before, there will never be anyone like you again. ^13 Furthermore, what you have not requested I will give you, both riches and glory, so that there will be no other king like you in your lifetime.[*] ^14 And if you walk in my ways by keeping my regulations and my commandments, just as David your father walked, I will also give you a long life.”[*]

^15 When Solʹo·mon awoke, he realized that it had been a dream. Then he went to Jerusalem and stood before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and communion offerings and spread a feast for all his servants.

^16 At that time two prostitutes came in to the king and stood before him. ^17 The first woman said: “Please, my lord, this woman and I live in one house, and I gave birth while she was in the house. ^18 On the third day after I gave birth, this woman also gave birth. We were together, just the two of us; there was no one else with us in the house. ^19 During the night this woman’s son died, because she lay on him. ^20 So she got up in the middle of the night and took my son from my side while your slave girl was asleep and laid him in her arms,[*] and she laid her dead son in my arms. ^21 When I got up in the morning to nurse my son, I saw that he was dead. So I examined him closely in the morning and saw that it was not my son whom I had given birth to.” ^22 But the other woman said: “No, my son is the living one, and your son is the dead one!” But the first woman was saying: “No, your son is the dead one, and my son is the living one.” That is how they argued before the king.

^23 Finally the king said: “This one says, ‘This is my son, the living one, and your son is the dead one!’ and that one says, ‘No, your son is the dead one, and my son is the living one!’” ^24 The king said: “Bring me a sword.” So they brought a sword to the king. ^25 The king then said: “Cut the living child in two, and give half to one woman and half to the other.” ^26 At once the woman whose son was the living one pleaded with the king, for her compassions were stirred toward her son. She said: “Please, my lord! You should give her the living child! By no means put him to death!” But the other woman was saying: “He will be neither mine nor yours! Let them cut him in two!” ^27 At that the king answered: “Give the living child to the first woman! By no means put him to death, for she is his mother.”

^28 So all Israel heard about the judgment that the king had handed down, and they were in awe[*] of the king, for they saw that the wisdom of God was with him to execute justice.

^ 1 Ki. 3:1 Or “took.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:4 Lit., “the great.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:7 Or “little boy.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:7 Lit., “and I do not know going out and coming in.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:9 Or possibly, “difficult.” Lit., “heavy.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:11 Lit., “many days.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:11 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:13 Lit., “all your days.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:14 Lit., “lengthen your days.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:20 Lit., “her bosom.”

^ 1 Ki. 3:28 Lit., “fear.”

1 Kings  4 : 1 - 34

4 King Solʹo·mon ruled over all Israel. ^2 These were his high officials:[*] Az·a·riʹah the son of Zaʹdok was the priest; ^3 El·i·horʹeph and A·hiʹjah the sons of Shiʹsha were secretaries; Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of A·hiʹlud was the recorder; ^4 Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was in charge of the army; Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar were priests; ^5 Az·a·riʹah the son of Nathan was over the deputies; Zaʹbud the son of Nathan was a priest and the king’s friend; ^6 A·hiʹshar was over the household; and Ad·o·niʹram the son of Abʹda was over those conscripted for forced labor.

^7 Solʹo·mon had 12 deputies in charge of all Israel who provided the king and his household with food. Each one was responsible for providing the food for one month of the year. ^8 These were their names: The son of Hur, in the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im; ^9 the son of Deʹker, in Maʹkaz, Sha·alʹbim, Beth-sheʹmesh, and Eʹlon-beth-haʹnan; ^10 the son of Heʹsed, in A·rubʹboth (he had Soʹcoh and all the land of Heʹpher); ^11 the son of A·binʹa·dab, in all the slopes of Dor (Solʹo·mon’s daughter Taʹphath became his wife); ^12 Baʹa·na the son of A·hiʹlud, in Taʹa·nach, Me·gidʹdo, and all Beth-sheʹan, which is beside Zarʹe·than below Jezʹre·el, from Beth-sheʹan to Aʹbel-me·hoʹlah to the region of Jokʹme·am; ^13 the son of Geʹber, in Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad (he had the tent villages of Jaʹir the son of Ma·nasʹseh, which are in Gilʹe·ad; he also had the region of Arʹgob, which is in Baʹshan: 60 large cities with walls and copper bars); ^14 A·hinʹa·dab the son of Idʹdo, in Ma·ha·naʹim; ^15 A·himʹa·az, in Naphʹta·li (he took Basʹe·math, another of Solʹo·mon’s daughters, as his wife); ^16 Baʹa·na the son of Huʹshai, in Ashʹer and Be·aʹloth; ^17 Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of Pa·ruʹah, in Isʹsa·char; ^18 Shimʹe·i the son of Eʹla, in Benjamin; ^19 Geʹber the son of Uʹri, in the land of Gilʹe·ad, the land of Siʹhon king of the Amʹor·ites and of Og king of Baʹshan. There was also one deputy in charge of all these other deputies in the land.

^20 Judah and Israel were as numerous as the grains of sand by the sea; they were eating and drinking and rejoicing.

^21 Solʹo·mon ruled over all the kingdoms from the River[*] to the land of the Phi·lisʹtines and to the boundary of Egypt. They brought tribute and served Solʹo·mon all the days of his life.

^22 Solʹo·mon’s food for each day was 30 cor measures[*] of fine flour and 60 cor measures of flour, ^23 10 fattened cattle, 20 pastured cattle, and 100 sheep, besides some stags, gazelles, roebucks, and fattened cuckoos. ^24 For he controlled everything this side of the River,[*] from Tiphʹsah to Gazʹa, including all the kings on this side of the River; and he enjoyed peace in every region, all around him. ^25 Judah and Israel lived in security, everyone under his own vine and under his own fig tree, from Dan to Beʹer-sheʹba, all the days of Solʹo·mon.

^26 And Solʹo·mon had 4,000[*] stalls of horses for his chariots and 12,000 horses.[*]

^27 These deputies supplied food to King Solʹo·mon and to everyone who ate at the table of King Solʹo·mon. Each was responsible for his month and saw to it that nothing was lacking. ^28 They also brought barley and straw wherever it was needed for the horses and for the teams of horses, each according to his quota.

^29 And God gave Solʹo·mon wisdom and discernment in very great measure and a broadness of heart[*] like the sand on the seashore. ^30 Solʹo·mon’s wisdom surpassed the wisdom of all the people of the East and all the wisdom of Egypt. ^31 He was wiser than any other man, wiser than Eʹthan the Ezʹra·hite and Heʹman, Calʹcol, and Darʹda, the sons of Maʹhol; his fame spread among all the surrounding nations. ^32 He composed[*] 3,000 proverbs and his songs numbered 1,005. ^33 He would speak about the trees, from the cedar in Lebʹa·non to the hyssop that grows on the wall; he would speak about the animals, the birds,[*] the creeping things,[*] and the fish. ^34 People from all the nations came to hear Solʹo·mon’s wisdom, including kings from all over the earth who had heard about his wisdom.

^ 1 Ki. 4:2 Or “his princes.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:21 That is, the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 4:22 A cor equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 4:24 That is, west of the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 4:26 This figure is found in some manuscripts and in the parallel account. Other manuscripts say 40,000.

^ 1 Ki. 4:26 Or “horsemen.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:29 Or “heart with understanding.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:32 Or “spoke.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:33 Or “flying creatures.”

^ 1 Ki. 4:33 Possibly including reptiles and insects.

1 Kings  5 : 1 - 18

5 When Hiʹram the king of Tyre heard that Solʹo·mon had been anointed as king in place of his father, he sent his servants to Solʹo·mon, for Hiʹram had always been a friend of David’s.[*] ^2 In turn Solʹo·mon sent word to Hiʹram: ^3 “You well know that David my father was not able to build a house for the name of Jehovah his God because of the wars waged against him from every side until Jehovah put his enemies under the soles of his feet. ^4 But now Jehovah my God has given me rest on all sides. There is no one opposing me and nothing bad happening. ^5 So I intend to build a house for the name of Jehovah my God, just as Jehovah promised to David my father, saying: ‘Your son whom I will put on your throne in your place, he is the one who will build the house for my name.’ ^6 Now command your people to cut cedars of Lebʹa·non for me. My servants will work with your servants, and I will pay the wages of your servants according to the rate you set, for you are aware that not one of us knows how to cut trees like the Si·doʹni·ans.”

^7 When Hiʹram heard Solʹo·mon’s words, he rejoiced greatly and said: “May Jehovah be praised today, for he has given David a wise son over this great[*] people!” ^8 So Hiʹram sent word to Solʹo·mon: “I have heard the message you sent to me. I will do all you desire in providing the cedar and juniper timbers. ^9 My servants will bring them down from Lebʹa·non to the sea, and I will make them into log rafts to go by sea to the place that you designate to me. I will have them broken up there, and you can carry them away. In exchange, you will provide the food that I request for my household.”

^10 So Hiʹram supplied all the timbers of cedar and juniper that Solʹo·mon desired. ^11 And Solʹo·mon gave Hiʹram 20,000 cor measures[*] of wheat as food supplies for his household and 20 cor measures of very fine olive oil.[*] That was what Solʹo·mon gave Hiʹram year after year. ^12 And Jehovah gave Solʹo·mon wisdom, just as He had promised him. And there was peace between Hiʹram and Solʹo·mon, and the two of them made a treaty.[*]

^13 King Solʹo·mon conscripted men for forced labor out of all Israel; 30,000 men were conscripted. ^14 He would send them to Lebʹa·non in shifts of 10,000 each month. They would spend a month in Lebʹa·non and two months at their homes; and Ad·o·niʹram was over those conscripted for forced labor. ^15 Solʹo·mon had 70,000 common laborers[*] and 80,000 stonecutters in the mountains, ^16 as well as Solʹo·mon’s 3,300 princely deputies who served as foremen to supervise the workmen. ^17 At the king’s order, they quarried large stones, expensive stones, to lay the foundation of the house with hewn stones. ^18 So Solʹo·mon’s builders and Hiʹram’s builders and the Geʹbal·ites did the cutting, and they prepared the timbers and the stones to build the house.

^ 1 Ki. 5:1 Or “had always loved David.”

^ 1 Ki. 5:7 Or “numerous.”

^ 1 Ki. 5:11 A cor equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 5:11 Lit., “of beaten oil.”

^ 1 Ki. 5:12 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 5:15 Or “burden bearers.”

1 Kings  7 : 1 - 51

7 And it took Solʹo·mon 13 years to build his own house,[*] until his whole house was completed.

^2 And he built the House of the Forest of Lebʹa·non 100 cubits[*] long, 50 cubits wide, and 30 cubits high on four rows of cedar pillars; and there were cedar beams on the pillars. ^3 It was paneled above with cedar on the girders that rested on the pillars; they numbered 45, with 15 to a row. ^4 There were three rows of framed windows, and each window was opposite another window in three tiers. ^5 All the entrances and the doorposts had square[*] frames, as did the front of the windows that were opposite each other in three tiers.

^6 And he built the Hall[*] of Pillars 50 cubits long and 30 cubits wide, and there was a porch in front of it with pillars and a canopy.

^7 He also built the Hall[*] of the Throne, where he would judge—the Hall of Judgment—and they paneled it with cedar from the floor to the rafters.

^8 The house[*] where he was to live, at the other courtyard, was set back from the Hall,[*] and it was similar in workmanship. He also built a house similar to this Hall for Pharʹaoh’s daughter, whom Solʹo·mon had taken as a wife.

^9 All of these were made of expensive stones hewn according to measure, trimmed with stonesaws inside and out, from the foundation up to the coping, and outside as far as the great courtyard. ^10 And the foundation was laid with very large, expensive stones; some stones measured ten cubits, and other stones, eight cubits. ^11 And above these were expensive stones, hewn according to measure, as well as cedar. ^12 Around the great courtyard were three rows of hewn stone and a row of cedar beams, like that for the inner courtyard of the house of Jehovah and the porch of the house.

^13 King Solʹo·mon sent for Hiʹram and brought him from Tyre. ^14 He was the son of a widow from the tribe of Naphʹta·li, and his father was a Tyrʹi·an coppersmith; and he had great skill, understanding, and experience for all kinds of work in copper.[*] So he came to King Solʹo·mon and did all his work.

^15 He cast the two pillars of copper; each pillar was 18 cubits high, and it took a measuring cord 12 cubits long to encircle each of the two pillars.[*] ^16 And he made two capitals cast in copper to put on the tops of the pillars. One capital was five cubits high, and the other capital was five cubits high. ^17 The capital on top of each pillar had mesh network with wreathed chains; seven for the one capital and seven for the other capital. ^18 And he made pomegranates in two rows around the one network to cover the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; he did the same for both capitals. ^19 The capitals on top of the pillars at the porch were of a lily pattern four cubits high. ^20 The capitals were on the two pillars, just above the rounded portion adjoining the network; and there were 200 pomegranates in rows all around on each capital.

^21 He set up the pillars of the porch of the temple.[*] He set up the right-hand[*] pillar and named it Jaʹchin,[*] and then he set up the left-hand[*] pillar and named it Boʹaz.[*] ^22 And the top of the pillars were of a lily pattern. So the work of the pillars was completed.

^23 Then he made the Sea[*] of cast metal. It was circular in shape, 10 cubits from brim to brim and 5 cubits high, and it took a measuring line 30 cubits long to encircle it.[*] ^24 And there were ornamental gourds below its brim, completely encircling it, ten to a cubit all around the Sea, with two rows of the gourds cast in one piece with it. ^25 It stood on 12 bulls, 3 facing north, 3 facing west, 3 facing south, and 3 facing east; and the Sea rested on them, and all their hindquarters were toward the center. ^26 And its thickness was a handbreadth;[*] and its brim was made like the brim of a cup, like a lily blossom. It would hold 2,000 bath measures.[*]

^27 Then he made the ten carriages[*] of copper. Each carriage was four cubits long, four cubits wide, and three cubits high. ^28 And this was how the carriages were constructed: They had side panels, and the side panels were between the crossbars. ^29 And on the side panels between the crossbars were lions, bulls, and cherubs, and the same design was on the crossbars. Above and beneath the lions and the bulls were wreaths in relief. ^30 And each carriage had four copper wheels and copper axles, and its four cornerpieces served as supports for them. Beneath the basin were the supports, cast with wreaths at the side of each. ^31 Its opening was inside the crown, extending upward one cubit; and its opening was round, making up a stand of one and a half cubits, and on its mouth were engravings. And their side panels were square, not round. ^32 The four wheels were below the side panels, and the supports of the wheels were attached to the carriage, and the height of each wheel was one and a half cubits. ^33 And the wheels were made like chariot wheels. Their supports, rims,[*] spokes, and hubs were all of cast metal. ^34 There were four supports on the four corners of each carriage; its supports were cast as part of[*] the carriage. ^35 On top of the carriage was a circular band half a cubit high, and on the top of the carriage, its framing pieces and its side panels were cast as part of[*] it. ^36 On the surfaces of its framing pieces and on its side panels he engraved cherubs, lions, and palm trees according to the amount of space on each, with wreaths all around. ^37 This is how he made the ten carriages; they were all cast alike, with the same measure and shape.

^38 He made ten copper basins; each could hold 40 bath measures. Each basin measured four cubits.[*] There was one basin for each of the ten carriages. ^39 Then he put five carriages on the right side of the house and five on the left side of the house, and he placed the Sea on the right side of the house, toward the southeast.

^40 Hiʹram also made the basins, the shovels, and the bowls.

So Hiʹram finished all the work that he did for King Solʹo·mon on the house of Jehovah: ^41 the two pillars and the bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the two pillars; the two networks to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on top of the pillars; ^42 the 400 pomegranates for the two networks, two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowl-shaped capitals that were on the two pillars; ^43 the ten carriages and the ten basins on the carriages; ^44 the Sea and the 12 bulls beneath the Sea; ^45 and the cans, the shovels, the bowls, and all the utensils, which Hiʹram made of polished copper for King Solʹo·mon for the house of Jehovah. ^46 The king cast them in clay molds in the district of the Jordan, between Sucʹcoth and Zarʹe·than.

^47 Solʹo·mon left all the utensils unweighed because they were in such great quantities. The weight of the copper was not ascertained. ^48 Solʹo·mon made all the utensils for the house of Jehovah: the altar of gold; the gold table on which to put the showbread; ^49 the lampstands of pure gold, five on the right and five on the left before the innermost room; and the blossoms, the lamps, and the snuffers,[*] of gold; ^50 the basins, the extinguishers, the bowls, the cups, and the fire holders, of pure gold; and the sockets for the doors of the inner house, that is, the Most Holy, and for the doors of the house of the temple, of gold.

^51 So King Solʹo·mon completed all the work he had to do for the house of Jehovah. Solʹo·mon then brought in the things that David his father had made holy, and he put the silver, the gold, and the articles into the treasuries of the house of Jehovah.

^ 1 Ki. 7:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:2 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:5 Or “four-sided; rectangular.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:6 Or “Porch.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:7 Or “Porch.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:8 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:8 Lit., “house of the Hall.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:14 Or “bronze,” here and in subsequent occurrences in this chapter.

^ 1 Ki. 7:15 Or “each of the two pillars was 12 cubits in circumference.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Here referring to the Holy.

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Or “southern.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Meaning “May He [that is, Jehovah] Firmly Establish.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Or “northern.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:21 Possibly meaning “In Strength.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:23 Or “reservoir.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:23 Or “it was 30 cubits in circumference.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:26 About 7.4 cm (2.9 in.). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:26 A bath equaled 22 L (5.81 gal). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 7:27 Or “water carts.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:33 Or “fellies.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:34 Or “were one piece with.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:35 Or “were one piece with.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:38 Or “four cubits in diameter.”

^ 1 Ki. 7:49 Or “tongs.”

1 Kings  8 : 1 - 66

8 At that time Solʹo·mon congregated the elders of Israel, all the heads of the tribes, the chieftains of the paternal houses of Israel. They came to King Solʹo·mon at Jerusalem to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah from the City of David, that is, Zion. ^2 All the men of Israel assembled before King Solʹo·mon at the festival[*] in the month of Ethʹa·nim,[*] that is, the seventh month. ^3 So all the elders of Israel came, and the priests lifted up the Ark. ^4 They brought up the Ark of Jehovah, the tent of meeting, and all the holy utensils that were in the tent. The priests and the Levites brought them up. ^5 King Solʹo·mon and the entire assembly of Israel, who had been summoned to meet with him, were before the Ark. So many sheep and cattle were being sacrificed that they could not be counted or numbered.

^6 Then the priests brought the ark of the covenant of Jehovah to its place, into the innermost room of the house, the Most Holy, underneath the wings of the cherubs.

^7 Thus the wings of the cherubs were spread out over the place of the Ark, so that the cherubs overshadowed the Ark and its poles. ^8 The poles were so long that the tips of the poles were visible from the Holy in front of the innermost room, but they were not visible from outside. And they are there to this day. ^9 There was nothing in the Ark but the two stone tablets that Moses placed there at Horʹeb, when Jehovah made a covenant with the people of Israel while they were coming out of the land of Egypt.

^10 When the priests came out from the holy place, the cloud filled the house of Jehovah. ^11 The priests were not able to stand to minister because of the cloud, for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah. ^12 At that time Solʹo·mon said: “Jehovah said he would reside in the thick gloom. ^13 I have successfully built a lofty house for you, an established place for you to dwell in forever.”

^14 Then the king turned around and began to bless all the congregation of Israel while all the congregation of Israel stood. ^15 He said: “May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, the one who by his own mouth promised my father David, and by his own hand has given fulfillment, saying, ^16 ‘From the day I brought my people Israel out of Egypt, I have not chosen a city out of all the tribes of Israel in which to build a house for my name to remain there, but I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.’ ^17 And it was the heart’s desire of my father David to build a house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel. ^18 But Jehovah said to my father David, ‘It was your heart’s desire to build a house for my name, and you did well to desire this in your heart. ^19 However, you will not build the house, but your own son who is to be born to you[*] is the one who will build the house for my name.’ ^20 Jehovah has carried out the promise that he made, for I have succeeded my father David and I sit on the throne of Israel, just as Jehovah promised. I have also built the house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel ^21 and have set up a place there for the Ark containing the covenant that Jehovah made with our forefathers when he was bringing them out of the land of Egypt.”

^22 Then Solʹo·mon stood before the altar of Jehovah in front of all the congregation of Israel, and he spread his hands out to the heavens, ^23 and he said: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, there is no God like you in the heavens above or on the earth beneath, keeping the covenant and showing loyal love to your servants who are walking before you with all their heart. ^24 You have kept the promise that you made to your servant David my father. You made the promise with your own mouth, and this day you have fulfilled it with your own hand. ^25 And now, O Jehovah the God of Israel, keep the promise you made to your servant David my father when you said: ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line before me to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your sons will pay attention to their way by walking before me, just as you have walked before me.’ ^26 And now, O God of Israel, let the promise that you made to your servant David my father prove trustworthy, please.

^27 “But will God really dwell on the earth? Look! The heavens, yes, the heaven of the heavens, cannot contain you; how much less, then, this house that I have built! ^28 Now pay attention to the prayer of your servant and to his request for favor, O Jehovah my God, and listen to the cry for help and to the prayer that your servant is praying before you today. ^29 May your eyes be open toward this house night and day, toward the place of which you said, ‘My name will be there,’ to listen to the prayer that your servant prays toward this place. ^30 And listen to your servant’s request for favor and to the request by your people Israel that they pray toward this place, and may you hear from your dwelling place in the heavens; yes, may you hear and forgive.

^31 “When a man sins against his fellow man and is made to take an oath[*] and is brought under liability to the oath,[*] and while under the oath[*] he comes before your altar in this house, ^32 may you then hear from the heavens and act and judge your servants by pronouncing the wicked one guilty[*] and bringing what he did on his own head, and by pronouncing the righteous one innocent[*] and rewarding him according to his own righteousness.

^33 “When your people Israel are defeated by an enemy because they kept sinning against you, and they return to you and glorify your name and pray and beg you for favor in this house, ^34 may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your people Israel and bring them back to the land that you gave to their forefathers.

^35 “When the heavens are shut up and there is no rain because they kept sinning against you, and they pray toward this place and glorify your name and turn back from their sin because you humbled[*] them, ^36 may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your servants, of your people Israel, for you will instruct them about the good way in which they should walk; and bring rain on your land that you gave to your people as an inheritance.

^37 “If a famine occurs in the land, or a pestilence, a scorching blight, mildew, swarming locusts, or voracious locusts;[*] or if their enemy besieges them in any of the cities of the land[*] or if any other sort of plague or disease occurs, ^38 whatever prayer, whatever request for favor may be made by any man or by all your people Israel (for each one knows the plague of his own heart) when they spread out their hands toward this house, ^39 then may you hear from the heavens, your dwelling place, and may you forgive and take action; and reward each one according to all his ways, for you know his heart (you alone truly know every human heart), ^40 so that they may fear you all the days they live on the land that you gave to our forefathers.

^41 “Also concerning the foreigner who is not part of your people Israel and who comes from a distant land because of your name[*] ^42 (for they will hear about your great name and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm), and he comes and prays toward this house, ^43 may you then listen from the heavens, your dwelling place, and do all that the foreigner asks of you, so that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you, as your people Israel do, and may know that your name has been called on this house that I have built.

^44 “If your people go to war against their enemy in the way that you send them, and they pray to Jehovah in the direction of the city that you have chosen and toward the house that I have built for your name, ^45 then hear from the heavens their prayer and their request for favor and execute judgment for them.

^46 “If they sin against you (for there is no man who does not sin), and you are furious with them and you abandon them to an enemy, and their captors carry them off captive to the land of the enemy, far or near; ^47 and they come to their senses in the land where they were carried off captive, and they return to you and beg you for favor in the land of their captors, saying, ‘We have sinned and done wrong; we have acted wickedly,’ ^48 and they return to you with all their heart and all their soul[*] in the land of their enemies who carried them off captive, and they pray to you in the direction of their land that you gave to their forefathers and of the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built for your name, ^49 then hear from the heavens, your dwelling place, their prayer and their request for favor, and execute judgment for them ^50 and forgive your people who have sinned against you, forgiving all their transgressions they committed against you. You will make them objects of pity before their captors, and they will pity them ^51 (for they are your people and your inheritance, whom you brought out of Egypt, from inside the iron-smelting furnace). ^52 May your eyes be opened to your servant’s request for favor and to the request for favor by your people Israel by listening whenever they call to you.[*] ^53 For you set them apart as your inheritance out of all the peoples of the earth, just as you declared through Moses your servant when you were bringing our forefathers out of Egypt, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

^54 And as soon as Solʹo·mon finished offering to Jehovah this entire prayer and request for favor, he rose up from before the altar of Jehovah, where he had been kneeling with his hands spread out to the heavens. ^55 He then stood and blessed all the congregation of Israel with a loud voice, saying: ^56 “Praised be Jehovah, who has given a resting-place to his people Israel, just as he promised. Not one word of all his good promise that he made through Moses his servant has failed. ^57 May Jehovah our God be with us just as he was with our forefathers. May he not abandon us nor forsake us. ^58 May he draw our heart toward himself, to walk in all his ways and to keep his commandments, his regulations, and his judgments, which he commanded our forefathers to observe. ^59 And may these words of mine with which I have begged Jehovah for favor be near to Jehovah our God by day and night, that he may execute judgment for his servant and for his people Israel as each day requires, ^60 so that all the peoples of the earth may know that Jehovah is the true God. There is no other! ^61 So let your heart be complete with[*] Jehovah our God by walking in his regulations and by keeping his commandments as on this day.”

^62 Now the king and all Israel with him offered a grand sacrifice before Jehovah. ^63 Solʹo·mon offered the communion sacrifices to Jehovah: He offered 22,000 cattle and 120,000 sheep. Thus the king and all the Israelites inaugurated the house of Jehovah. ^64 On that day the king had to sanctify the middle of the courtyard that is before the house of Jehovah, for there he had to offer up the burnt sacrifices, the grain offerings, and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices, because the copper altar that is before Jehovah was too small to contain the burnt sacrifices, the grain offerings, and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices. ^65 At that time Solʹo·mon held the festival together with all Israel, a great congregation from Leʹbo-haʹmath[*] down to the Wadi[*] of Egypt, before Jehovah our God for 7 days and then another 7 days, 14 days in all. ^66 On the following[*] day, he sent the people away, and they blessed the king and went to their homes rejoicing and feeling glad of heart over all the goodness that Jehovah had shown to David his servant and Israel his people.

^ 1 Ki. 8:2 That is, the Festival of Booths.

^ 1 Ki. 8:2 See App. B15.

^ 1 Ki. 8:19 Lit., “your son, the one coming out of your loins.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:31 Or “and the latter lays a cursing on him.” That is, an oath that carried with it a curse as its penalty if sworn falsely or violated.

^ 1 Ki. 8:31 Lit., “curse.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:31 Lit., “curse.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:32 Lit., “wicked.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:32 Lit., “righteous.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:35 Or “afflicted.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:37 Or “grasshoppers.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:37 Lit., “in the land of his gates.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:41 Or “reputation.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:48 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 8:52 Or “listening to them whatever they ask of you.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:61 Or “completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:65 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ 1 Ki. 8:65 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 8:66 Lit., “eighth,” that is, the day after the second seven-day period.

1 Kings  9 : 1 - 28

9 As soon as Solʹo·mon had finished building the house of Jehovah, the house[*] of the king, and everything Solʹo·mon desired to make, ^2 Jehovah appeared to Solʹo·mon a second time, just as he had appeared to him in Gibʹe·on. ^3 Jehovah said to him: “I have heard your prayer and your request for favor that you made before me. I have sanctified this house that you built by permanently putting my name there, and my eyes and my heart will always be there. ^4 And you, if you walk before me as your father David walked, with integrity of heart and with uprightness, by doing everything I have commanded you, and you obey my regulations and my judgments, ^5 then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, just as I promised your father David, saying, ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line sitting on the throne of Israel.’ ^6 But if you and your sons turn away from following me and do not keep my commandments and my statutes that I have put before you, and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, ^7 I will cut Israel off from the surface of the land that I have given to them, and the house that I have sanctified for my name I will cast out of my sight, and Israel will become an object of scorn[*] and a cause for ridicule among all the peoples. ^8 And this house will become heaps of ruins. Everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and will whistle and say, ‘Why did Jehovah do that to this land and this house?’ ^9 Then they will say, ‘It was because they abandoned Jehovah their God, who had brought their forefathers out of the land of Egypt, and they embraced other gods and bowed down to them and served them. That is why Jehovah brought all this calamity on them.’”

^10 At the end of 20 years, during which Solʹo·mon built the two houses, the house of Jehovah and the house[*] of the king, ^11 Hiʹram the king of Tyre had supplied Solʹo·mon with cedar and juniper timbers and with as much gold as he desired, and King Solʹo·mon gave to Hiʹram 20 cities in the land of Galʹi·lee. ^12 So Hiʹram went out from Tyre to see the cities that Solʹo·mon had given him, but he was not satisfied with them.[*] ^13 He said: “What sort of cities are these that you have given me, my brother?” So they came to be called the Land of Caʹbul[*] down to this day. ^14 In the meantime, Hiʹram sent to the king 120 talents[*] of gold.

^15 This is the account of those whom King Solʹo·mon conscripted for forced labor to build the house of Jehovah, his own house,[*] the Mound,[*] the wall of Jerusalem, Haʹzor, Me·gidʹdo, and Geʹzer. ^16 (Pharʹaoh king of Egypt had come up and captured Geʹzer and had burned it with fire, and he had also killed the Caʹnaan·ites dwelling in the city. So he gave it as a parting gift[*] to his daughter, the wife of Solʹo·mon.) ^17 Solʹo·mon built up[*] Geʹzer, Lower Beth-hoʹron, ^18 Baʹal·ath, and Taʹmar in the wilderness, within the land, ^19 as well as all of Solʹo·mon’s storage cities, the chariot cities, the cities for the horsemen, and whatever Solʹo·mon desired to build in Jerusalem, in Lebʹa·non, and in all the land of his dominion. ^20 As for all the people who were left from the Amʹor·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Hiʹvites, and the Jebʹu·sites, who were not part of the people of Israel, ^21 their descendants who were left in the land—those whom the Israelites had been unable to devote to destruction—were conscripted by Solʹo·mon for forced labor as slaves until this day. ^22 But Solʹo·mon did not make any of the Israelites slaves, for they were his warriors, servants, princes, adjutants, and the chiefs of his charioteers and horsemen. ^23 There were 550 chiefs of the deputies who were over the work of Solʹo·mon, the foremen over the people who were doing the work.

^24 But Pharʹaoh’s daughter came up from the City of David to her own house that he had built for her; then he built the Mound.[*]

^25 Three times a year Solʹo·mon offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices on the altar that he had built for Jehovah, also making sacrificial smoke on the altar, which was before Jehovah, so he completed the house.

^26 King Solʹo·mon also made a fleet of ships in Eʹzi·on-geʹber, which is by Eʹloth, on the shore of the Red Sea in the land of Eʹdom. ^27 Hiʹram sent his own servants with the fleet of ships, experienced seamen, to serve along with the servants of Solʹo·mon. ^28 They went to Oʹphir and took from there 420 talents of gold and brought it to King Solʹo·mon.

^ 1 Ki. 9:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:7 Lit., “a proverb.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:10 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:12 Lit., “they were not right in his eyes.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:13 Or possibly, “the Land as Good as Nothing.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:14 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 9:15 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:15 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:16 Or “a wedding gift; a dowry.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:17 Or “fortified.”

^ 1 Ki. 9:24 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

1 Kings  10 : 1 - 29

10 Now the queen of Sheʹba heard the report about Solʹo·mon in connection with the name of Jehovah, so she came to test him with perplexing questions.[*] ^2 She arrived in Jerusalem with a very impressive entourage,[*] with camels carrying balsam oil and great quantities of gold and precious stones. She went in to Solʹo·mon and spoke to him about everything that was close to her heart. ^3 Solʹo·mon then answered all her questions. There was nothing too difficult for[*] the king to explain to her.

^4 When the queen of Sheʹba had seen all the wisdom of Solʹo·mon, the house that he built, ^5 the food of his table, the seating of his servants, the table service of his waiters and their attire, his cupbearers, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, she was left completely breathless.[*] ^6 So she said to the king: “The report that I heard in my own land about your achievements[*] and about your wisdom was true. ^7 But I did not put faith in the reports until I had come and had seen it with my own eyes. And look! I had not been told the half. You have far surpassed in wisdom and prosperity the report that I heard. ^8 Happy are your men, and happy are your servants who stand before you constantly, listening to your wisdom! ^9 May Jehovah your God be praised, who has taken pleasure in you by putting you on the throne of Israel. Because of Jehovah’s everlasting love for Israel, he appointed you as king to administer justice and righteousness.”

^10 Then she gave the king 120 talents[*] of gold and a great amount of balsam oil and precious stones. Never again was such a quantity of balsam oil brought in as what the queen of Sheʹba gave to King Solʹo·mon.

^11 Hiʹram’s fleet of ships that carried gold from Oʹphir also brought from Oʹphir algum timbers in very great quantity, and precious stones. ^12 The king made from the algum timbers supports for the house of Jehovah and for the king’s house,[*] as well as harps and stringed instruments for the singers. Such algum timbers have never again been brought in or seen down to this day.

^13 King Solʹo·mon also gave the queen of Sheʹba whatever she desired and asked for, in addition to what he gave her out of his own generosity.[*] After that she left and returned to her own land, together with her servants.

^14 And the weight of the gold that came to Solʹo·mon in one year amounted to 666 talents of gold, ^15 besides that from the merchants and the profit from the traders and from all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land.

^16 King Solʹo·mon made 200 large shields of alloyed gold (600 shekels[*] of gold went on each shield) ^17 and 300 bucklers[*] of alloyed gold (three miʹnas[*] of gold went on each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebʹa·non.

^18 The king also made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with refined gold. ^19 There were six steps to the throne, and the throne had a round canopy behind it, and there were armrests on both sides of the seat, and two lions were standing beside the armrests. ^20 And there were 12 lions standing on the six steps, one at each end of the six steps. No other kingdom had made anything like it.

^21 All the drinking vessels of King Solʹo·mon were of gold, and all the utensils of the House of the Forest of Lebʹa·non were of pure gold. There was nothing made of silver, for silver was considered as nothing in the days of Solʹo·mon. ^22 For the king had a fleet of ships of Tarʹshish on the sea along with Hiʹram’s fleet. Once every three years, the fleet of ships of Tarʹshish would come loaded with gold and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.

^23 So King Solʹo·mon was greater than all the other kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. ^24 And people of all the earth sought an audience with[*] Solʹo·mon to hear his wisdom that God had put in his heart. ^25 They would each bring a gift—articles of silver, articles of gold, garments, armor, balsam oil, horses, and mules—and this continued year after year.

^26 And Solʹo·mon kept accumulating chariots and horses;[*] he had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horses,[*] and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem.

^27 The king made the silver in Jerusalem as plentiful as the stones, and cedarwood as plentiful as the sycamore trees in the She·pheʹlah.

^28 The horses of Solʹo·mon had been imported from Egypt, and the company of the king’s merchants would obtain the horses in droves[*] for one price. ^29 Each chariot imported from Egypt cost 600 silver pieces, and a horse cost 150; in turn, they would export them to all the kings of the Hitʹtites and the kings of Syria.

^ 1 Ki. 10:1 Or “with riddles.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:2 Or “train.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:3 Lit., “nothing hidden from.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:5 Lit., “there was no more spirit in her.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:6 Or “words.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:10 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 10:12 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:13 Lit., “according to the hand of King Solomon.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:16 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 10:17 A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ 1 Ki. 10:17 A mina in the Hebrew Scriptures equaled 570 g (18.35 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 10:24 Lit., “sought the face of.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:26 Or “horsemen.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:26 Or “horsemen.”

^ 1 Ki. 10:28 Or possibly, “from Egypt and from Kue; the king’s merchants would buy them from Kue,” perhaps referring to Cilicia.

1 Kings  11 : 1 - 43

11 But King Solʹo·mon loved many foreign women besides the daughter of Pharʹaoh: Moʹab·ite, Amʹmon·ite, Eʹdom·ite, Si·doʹni·an, and Hitʹtite women. ^2 They were from the nations about whom Jehovah had said to the Israelites: “You must not go in among them,[*] and they should not come in among you, for they will surely incline your heart to follow their gods.” But Solʹo·mon clung to them and loved them. ^3 And he had 700 wives who were princesses and 300 concubines, and his wives gradually inclined his heart.[*] ^4 In Solʹo·mon’s old age, his wives inclined[*] his heart to follow other gods, and his heart was not complete with[*] Jehovah his God like the heart of David his father. ^5 And Solʹo·mon followed after Ashʹto·reth, the goddess of the Si·doʹni·ans, and Milʹcom, the disgusting god of the Amʹmon·ites. ^6 And Solʹo·mon did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not follow Jehovah completely[*] as David his father had done.

^7 It was then that Solʹo·mon built a high place to Cheʹmosh, the disgusting god of Moʹab, on the mountain in front of Jerusalem and to Moʹlech, the disgusting god of the Amʹmon·ites. ^8 That was what he did for all his foreign wives who were making sacrificial smoke and sacrificing to their gods.

^9 Jehovah became furious at Solʹo·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice ^10 and had warned him about this very thing, that he should not go after other gods. But he did not obey what Jehovah had commanded. ^11 Jehovah now said to Solʹo·mon: “Because you have done this and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes as I commanded you, I will surely rip the kingdom away from you, and I will give it to one of your servants. ^12 However, for the sake of your father David, I will not do it in your lifetime. I will rip it out of the hand of your son, ^13 but I will not rip away the entire kingdom. One tribe I will give to your son, for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem, which I have chosen.”

^14 Jehovah then raised up a resister against Solʹo·mon, Haʹdad the Eʹdom·ite, of the royal family of Eʹdom. ^15 When David defeated Eʹdom, Joʹab the chief of the army went up to bury the slain, and he tried to strike down every male in Eʹdom. ^16 (For Joʹab and all Israel stayed there for six months until he had done away with[*] every male in Eʹdom.) ^17 But Haʹdad fled with some of his father’s Eʹdom·ite servants, and they went to Egypt; Haʹdad was then a young boy. ^18 So they set out from Midʹi·an and came to Paʹran. They took men with them from Paʹran and came to Egypt, to Pharʹaoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, assigned him a food allowance, and gave him land. ^19 Haʹdad found favor in the eyes of Pharʹaoh, so much so that he gave him in marriage the sister of his own wife, Tahʹpe·nes the queen.[*] ^20 In time the sister of Tahʹpe·nes bore him a son, Ge·nuʹbath, and Tahʹpe·nes brought him up[*] in the house of Pharʹaoh, and Ge·nuʹbath remained in the house of Pharʹaoh among the sons of Pharʹaoh.

^21 Haʹdad heard in Egypt that David had been laid to rest with his forefathers and that Joʹab the chief of the army had died. So Haʹdad said to Pharʹaoh: “Send me away, so that I may go to my own land.” ^22 But Pharʹaoh said to him: “What have you lacked with me that you now seek to go to your own land?” To this he said: “Nothing, but please send me away.”

^23 God also raised up against Solʹo·mon another resister, Reʹzon the son of E·liʹa·da, who had fled from his lord, Had·ad·eʹzer the king of Zoʹbah. ^24 He gathered men to himself and became chief of a marauder band when David defeated[*] them. So they went to Damascus and settled there and began reigning in Damascus. ^25 And he became a resister of Israel all the days of Solʹo·mon, adding to the harm done by Haʹdad, and he abhorred Israel while he reigned over Syria.

^26 And there was Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat, an Eʹphra·im·ite from Zerʹe·dah, a servant of Solʹo·mon’s whose mother’s name was Ze·ruʹah, a widow. He too began to rebel[*] against the king. ^27 This is why he rebelled against the king: Solʹo·mon had built the Mound[*] and had closed up the gap of the City of David his father. ^28 Now this Jer·o·boʹam was a capable man. When Solʹo·mon saw that the young man was a hard worker, he made him overseer over all the compulsory service of the house of Joseph. ^29 During that time Jer·o·boʹam went out from Jerusalem, and the prophet A·hiʹjah the Shiʹlo·nite found him on the road. A·hiʹjah was wearing a new garment, and the two of them were by themselves in the field. ^30 A·hiʹjah took hold of the new garment he was wearing and ripped it into 12 pieces. ^31 Then he said to Jer·o·boʹam:

“Take ten pieces for yourself, for this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Here I am ripping the kingdom out of the hand of Solʹo·mon, and I will give you ten tribes. ^32 But one tribe will remain his for the sake of my servant David and for the sake of Jerusalem, the city I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel. ^33 I will do this because they have left me and are bowing down to Ashʹto·reth the goddess of the Si·doʹni·ans, to Cheʹmosh the god of Moʹab, and to Milʹcom the god of the Amʹmon·ites, and they have not walked in my ways by doing what is right in my eyes and observing my statutes and my judgments as his father David did. ^34 But I will not take the entire kingdom out of his hand, and I will keep him as a chieftain for all the days of his life, for the sake of David my servant whom I chose, because he obeyed my commandments and my statutes. ^35 But I will take the kingship out of the hand of his son and give it to you, that is, ten tribes. ^36 To his son I will give one tribe, so that David my servant may always have a lamp before me in Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen for myself as the place to put my name. ^37 I will take you, and you will reign over all that you desire,[*] and you will become king over Israel. ^38 And if you obey all that I command you and walk in my ways and do what is right in my eyes by obeying my statutes and my commandments, just as David my servant did, I will also be with you. I will build you a lasting house, just as I have built for David, and I will give you Israel. ^39 And I will humiliate the offspring of David because of this, but not always.’”

^40 So Solʹo·mon tried to put Jer·o·boʹam to death, but Jer·o·boʹam fled to Egypt, to Shiʹshak the king of Egypt, and he remained in Egypt until Solʹo·mon’s death.

^41 As for the rest of the history of Solʹo·mon, all that he did and his wisdom, is it not written in the book of the history of Solʹo·mon? ^42 The length[*] of Solʹo·mon’s reign in Jerusalem over all Israel was 40 years. ^43 Then Solʹo·mon was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David his father; and his son Re·ho·boʹam became king in his place.

^ 1 Ki. 11:2 Or “You must not intermarry with them.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:3 Or “his wives had a powerful influence over him.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:4 Or “turned away.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:4 Or “completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:6 Lit., “fully.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:16 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:19 Not a ruling queen.

^ 1 Ki. 11:20 Or possibly, “weaned him.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:24 Lit., “killed.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:26 Lit., “lift his hand.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:27 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:37 Or “your soul desires.”

^ 1 Ki. 11:42 Lit., “The days.”

1 Kings  12 : 1 - 33

12 Re·ho·boʹam went to Sheʹchem, for all Israel had come to Sheʹchem to make him king. ^2 As soon as Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat heard of it (he was still in Egypt because he had run off on account of King Solʹo·mon and was living in Egypt), ^3 they sent for him. After that Jer·o·boʹam and all the congregation of Israel came to Re·ho·boʹam and said: ^4 “Your father made our yoke harsh. But if you make the harsh service of your father easier and you lighten the heavy[*] yoke he put on us, we will serve you.”

^5 At this he said to them: “Go away for three days; then return to me.” So the people went away. ^6 King Re·ho·boʹam then consulted with the older men[*] who had served his father Solʹo·mon while he was alive, saying: “What advice would you give on how to reply to this people?” ^7 They answered him: “If today you would become a servant to this people and submit to their request and give them a favorable answer, they will always be your servants.”

^8 However, he rejected the advice that the older men[*] gave him, and he consulted with the young men who had grown up with him and who were now his attendants. ^9 He asked them: “What advice do you offer on how we should reply to this people who have said to me, ‘Make the yoke your father put on us lighter’?” ^10 The young men who had grown up with him said to him: “This is what you should say to this people who have said to you, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but you should make it lighter for us’; this is what you should tell them, ‘My little finger will be thicker than my father’s hips. ^11 My father imposed a heavy yoke on you, but I will add to your yoke. My father punished you with whips, but I will punish you with scourges.’”

^12 Jer·o·boʹam and all the people came to Re·ho·boʹam on the third day, just as the king had said: “Return to me on the third day.” ^13 But the king answered the people harshly, rejecting the advice that the older men[*] had given him. ^14 He spoke to them according to the advice of the young men, saying: “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to your yoke. My father punished you with whips, but I will punish you with scourges.” ^15 So the king did not listen to the people, for this turn of events was caused by Jehovah, in order to carry out the word that Jehovah had spoken through A·hiʹjah the Shiʹlo·nite to Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat.

^16 When all Israel saw that the king refused to listen to them, the people replied to the king: “What share do we have in David? We have no inheritance in the son of Jesʹse. To your gods, O Israel. Now look after your own house, O David!” With that Israel returned to their homes.[*] ^17 But Re·ho·boʹam continued to reign over the Israelites living in the cities of Judah.

^18 Then King Re·ho·boʹam sent A·doʹram, who was in charge of those conscripted for forced labor, but all Israel stoned him to death. King Re·ho·boʹam managed to mount his chariot to flee to Jerusalem. ^19 And the Israelites have been in revolt against the house of David down to this day.

^20 As soon as all Israel heard that Jer·o·boʹam had returned, they summoned him to the assembly and made him king over all Israel. None of the people followed the house of David except the tribe of Judah.

^21 When Re·ho·boʹam arrived in Jerusalem, he immediately congregated all the house of Judah and the tribe of Benjamin, 180,000 trained[*] warriors, to fight against the house of Israel in order to restore the kingship to Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon. ^22 Then the word of the true God came to She·maiʹah the man of the true God, saying: ^23 “Say to Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon the king of Judah and to all the house of Judah and Benjamin and the rest of the people, ^24 ‘This is what Jehovah says: “You must not go up and fight against your Israelite brothers. Each one of you must return to his house, for I have caused this to happen.”’” So they obeyed the word of Jehovah and went back home, as Jehovah had told them.

^25 Jer·o·boʹam then built up[*] Sheʹchem in the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im and lived there. From there he went out and built up[*] Pe·nuʹel. ^26 Jer·o·boʹam said in his heart: “Now the kingdom will return to the house of David. ^27 If this people continues to go up to offer sacrifices at the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem, the heart of this people will also return to their lord, King Re·ho·boʹam of Judah. Yes, they will kill me and return to King Re·ho·boʹam of Judah.” ^28 After consultation, the king made two golden calves and said to the people: “It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem. Here is your God, O Israel, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt.” ^29 Then he placed one in Bethʹel, and the other he put in Dan. ^30 And this caused them to sin, and the people went as far as Dan to worship the one there.

^31 And he made houses of worship on the high places and appointed priests from the people in general, those who were not Levites. ^32 Jer·o·boʹam also established a festival in the eighth month, on the 15th day of the month, like the festival in Judah. On the altar that he made at Bethʹel, he sacrificed to the calves he had made, and at Bethʹel he assigned priests for the high places that he had made. ^33 And he began to make offerings on the altar that he had made at Bethʹel on the 15th day in the eighth month, in the month that he had devised on his own; and he established a festival for the people of Israel, and he ascended the altar to make offerings and sacrificial smoke.

^ 1 Ki. 12:4 Or “oppressive.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:6 Or “the elders.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:8 Or “the elders.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:13 Or “the elders.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:16 Lit., “tents.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:21 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:25 Or “fortified.”

^ 1 Ki. 12:25 Or “fortified.”

1 Kings  13 : 1 - 34

13 By the word of Jehovah, a man of God came from Judah to Bethʹel while Jer·o·boʹam was standing by the altar to make sacrificial smoke. ^2 Then he called out against the altar by the word of Jehovah and said: “O altar, altar! This is what Jehovah says: ‘Look! A son named Jo·siʹah will be born to the house of David! He will sacrifice on you the priests of the high places, those making sacrificial smoke on you, and he will burn human bones on you.’” ^3 He gave a sign[*] on that day, saying: “This is the sign[*] that Jehovah has declared: Look! The altar will be ripped apart, and the ashes[*] that are on it will be spilled out.”

^4 As soon as the king heard the word that the man of the true God had called out against the altar at Bethʹel, Jer·o·boʹam stretched out his hand from the altar and said: “Seize him!” Immediately, the hand that he had stretched out against him dried up,[*] and he could not draw it back. ^5 Then the altar was ripped apart and the ashes were spilled out from the altar according to the sign[*] that the man of the true God had given by the word of Jehovah.

^6 The king now said to the man of the true God: “Please, beg for the favor[*] of Jehovah your God, and pray in my behalf that my hand may be restored to me.” At this the man of the true God begged for the favor of Jehovah, and the king’s hand was restored to its former condition. ^7 The king then said to the man of the true God: “Come home with me and take some food, and let me give you a gift.” ^8 But the man of the true God said to the king: “Even if you gave me half your house, I would not come with you and eat bread or drink water in this place. ^9 For this is what I was commanded by the word of Jehovah: ‘You must not eat bread or drink water, and you must not return by the way you came.’” ^10 So he left by another way, and he did not return by the way he had come to Bethʹel.

^11 There was a certain old prophet dwelling in Bethʹel, and his sons came home and related to him all the things that the man of the true God had done that day in Bethʹel and the words he had spoken to the king. After they related this to their father, ^12 their father asked them: “Which way did he go?” So his sons showed him the way that the man of the true God from Judah had gone. ^13 He now said to his sons: “Saddle the donkey for me.” They saddled the donkey for him, and he mounted it.

^14 He followed the man of the true God and found him sitting under a big tree. Then he said to him: “Are you the man of the true God who came from Judah?” He replied: “I am.” ^15 He said to him: “Come home with me and eat bread.” ^16 But he said: “I cannot go back with you or accept your invitation, nor may I eat bread or drink water with you in this place. ^17 For I was told by the word of Jehovah, ‘You must not eat bread or drink water there. You must not return by the way you came.’” ^18 At this he said to him: “I too am a prophet like you, and an angel told me by the word of Jehovah, ‘Have him come back with you to your house so that he may eat bread and drink water.’” (He deceived him.) ^19 So he went back with him to eat bread and drink water in his house.

^20 While they were sitting at the table, the word of Jehovah came to the prophet who had brought him back, ^21 and he called out to the man of the true God from Judah, saying, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Because you rebelled against the order of Jehovah and did not keep the commandment that Jehovah your God gave you, ^22 but you went back to eat bread and drink water in the place about which you were told, “Do not eat bread or drink water,” your dead body will not come into the tomb of your forefathers.’”

^23 After the man of the true God ate bread and drank, the old prophet saddled the donkey for the prophet whom he had brought back. ^24 Then he got on his way, but a lion came across him on the road and killed him. His dead body was thrown onto the road, and the donkey stood beside it; the lion was also standing beside the dead body. ^25 There were men passing by who saw the dead body thrown onto the road and the lion standing beside the dead body. They came in and told about it in the city where the old prophet lived.

^26 When the prophet who had brought him back from the road heard of it, he immediately said: “It is the man of the true God who rebelled against the order of Jehovah; so Jehovah gave him over to the lion, to maul and to kill him, according to the word of Jehovah that he spoke to him.” ^27 He then said to his sons: “Saddle the donkey for me.” So they saddled it. ^28 Then he went on his way and found the dead body thrown onto the road, with the donkey and the lion standing beside it. The lion had not eaten the dead body, nor had it mauled the donkey. ^29 The prophet lifted up the dead body of the man of the true God and put him on the donkey, and he brought him back into his own city to mourn and bury him. ^30 So he laid the dead body in his own tomb, and they kept crying out over him: “Too bad, my brother!” ^31 After burying him, he told his sons: “When I die, you must bury me in the place where the man of the true God is buried. Lay my bones next to his bones. ^32 The word that he called out by the word of Jehovah against the altar in Bethʹel and against all the houses of worship on the high places in the cities of Sa·marʹi·a is sure to take place.”

^33 Even after this happened, Jer·o·boʹam did not turn back from his bad way, but he kept appointing priests for the high places from the people in general. He would install as priests[*] anyone who so desired, saying: “Let him become one of the priests for the high places.” ^34 This sin on the part of the household of Jer·o·boʹam led to their destruction and annihilation from the face of the earth.

^ 1 Ki. 13:3 Or “portent.”

^ 1 Ki. 13:3 Or “portent.”

^ 1 Ki. 13:3 Or “fatty ashes,” that is, ashes soaked with the fat of the sacrifices.

^ 1 Ki. 13:4 Or “was paralyzed.”

^ 1 Ki. 13:5 Or “portent.”

^ 1 Ki. 13:6 Or “soften the face.”

^ 1 Ki. 13:33 Lit., “fill the hand of.”

1 Kings  14 : 1 - 31

14 At that time A·biʹjah the son of Jer·o·boʹam fell sick. ^2 So Jer·o·boʹam said to his wife: “Rise up, please, and disguise yourself so that they will not know that you are Jer·o·boʹam’s wife, and go to Shiʹloh. Look! A·hiʹjah the prophet is there. He is the one who spoke of me becoming king over this people. ^3 Take with you ten loaves of bread, sprinkled cakes, and a flask of honey, and go to him. He will then tell you what is going to happen to the boy.”

^4 Jer·o·boʹam’s wife did what he said. She rose up and went to Shiʹloh and came to the house of A·hiʹjah. A·hiʹjah’s eyes stared straight ahead, and he could not see because of his age.

^5 But Jehovah had told A·hiʹjah: “Here is the wife of Jer·o·boʹam coming to inquire of you regarding her son, for he is sick. I will tell you what to say to her.[*] When she arrives, she will conceal her identity.”

^6 As soon as A·hiʹjah heard the sound of her footsteps as she was coming into the entrance, he said: “Come in, wife of Jer·o·boʹam. Why are you concealing your identity? I have been assigned to give you a harsh message. ^7 Go, tell Jer·o·boʹam, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “I raised you up from among your people to make you a leader over my people Israel. ^8 Then I ripped the kingdom away from the house of David and gave it to you. But you have not become like my servant David, who kept my commandments and who walked after me with all his heart, doing only what was right in my eyes. ^9 But you have done worse than all those who were prior to you, and you made for yourself another god and metal images[*] to offend me, and it is I whom you have turned your back on. ^10 For that reason I am bringing calamity on the house of Jer·o·boʹam, and I will annihilate[*] from Jer·o·boʹam every male,[*] including the helpless and weak in Israel, and I will make a clean sweep of the house of Jer·o·boʹam, just as one clears away the dung until it is all gone! ^11 Anyone belonging to Jer·o·boʹam who dies in the city, the dogs will eat; and anyone who dies in the field, the birds of the heavens will eat, for Jehovah has spoken it.”’

^12 “Now rise up; go to your house. When you set foot in the city, the child will die. ^13 All Israel will mourn him and bury him, for he alone of Jer·o·boʹam’s family will be laid in a grave, because he is the only one of the house of Jer·o·boʹam in whom Jehovah the God of Israel has found something good. ^14 Jehovah will raise up for himself a king over Israel who will do away with[*] the house of Jer·o·boʹam from that day forward, yes, even now. ^15 Jehovah will strike Israel down like a reed that sways in the water, and he will uproot Israel off this good land that he gave to their forefathers, and he will scatter them beyond the River,[*] because they made their sacred poles,[*] offending Jehovah. ^16 And he will abandon Israel because of the sins that Jer·o·boʹam has committed and has caused Israel to commit.”

^17 At that Jer·o·boʹam’s wife rose up and went on her way and came to Tirʹzah. As she came to the threshold of the house, the boy died. ^18 So they buried him, and all Israel mourned him, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hiʹjah the prophet.

^19 And the rest of the history of Jer·o·boʹam, how he waged war and how he reigned, is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. ^20 And the length[*] of Jer·o·boʹam’s reign was 22 years, after which he was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Naʹdab became king in his place.

^21 Meanwhile, Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon had become king in Judah. Re·ho·boʹam was 41 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 17 years in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel as the place to put his name. The name of Re·ho·boʹam’s mother was Naʹa·mah the Amʹmon·it·ess. ^22 And Judah was doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and by the sins they committed they provoked him more than their forefathers had done. ^23 They too kept building for themselves high places, sacred pillars, and sacred poles[*] on every high hill and under every luxuriant tree. ^24 There were also male temple prostitutes in the land. They acted according to all the detestable things of the nations that Jehovah had driven out before the Israelites.

^25 In the fifth year of King Re·ho·boʹam, King Shiʹshak of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. ^26 He took the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.[*] He took everything, including all the gold shields that Solʹo·mon had made. ^27 So King Re·ho·boʹam made copper shields to replace them, and he entrusted them to the chiefs of the guard,[*] who guarded the entrance of the king’s house. ^28 Whenever the king came to the house of Jehovah, the guards would carry them, and then they would return them to the guard chamber.

^29 And the rest of the history of Re·ho·boʹam, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^30 There was constant warfare between Re·ho·boʹam and Jer·o·boʹam. ^31 Then Re·ho·boʹam was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. His mother’s name was Naʹa·mah the Amʹmon·it·ess. And his son A·biʹjam[*] became king in his place.

^ 1 Ki. 14:5 Or “You should tell her such and such.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:9 Or “molten statues.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:10 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:10 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Ki. 14:14 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:15 That is, the Euphrates.

^ 1 Ki. 14:15 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 14:20 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:23 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 14:26 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:27 Lit., “runners.”

^ 1 Ki. 14:31 Also called Abijah.

1 Kings  15 : 1 - 34

15 In the 18th year of King Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat, A·biʹjam became king over Judah. ^2 He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Maʹa·cah the granddaughter of A·bishʹa·lom. ^3 He went on walking in all the sins that his father committed prior to him, and his heart was not complete with[*] Jehovah his God like the heart of David his forefather. ^4 However, on account of David, Jehovah his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem by raising up his son after him and keeping Jerusalem in existence. ^5 For David did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not turn aside from anything that He had commanded him all the days of his life, except in the matter of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite. ^6 And there was warfare between Re·ho·boʹam and Jer·o·boʹam all the days of his life.

^7 As for the rest of the history of A·biʹjam, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? There was also war between A·biʹjam and Jer·o·boʹam. ^8 Then A·biʹjam was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the City of David; and his son Aʹsa became king in his place.

^9 In the 20th year of King Jer·o·boʹam of Israel, Aʹsa began to reign over Judah. ^10 He reigned in Jerusalem for 41 years. His grandmother’s name was Maʹa·cah the granddaughter of A·bishʹa·lom. ^11 Aʹsa did what was right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his forefather. ^12 He expelled the male temple prostitutes from the land and removed all the disgusting idols[*] that his forefathers had made. ^13 He even removed Maʹa·cah his grandmother from her position as queen mother,[*] because she had made an obscene idol for the worship of the sacred pole.[*] Aʹsa cut down her obscene idol and burned it in the Kidʹron Valley. ^14 But the high places were not removed. Nevertheless, Aʹsa’s heart was complete with[*] Jehovah all his life.[*] ^15 And he brought the things that he and his father had made holy into the house of Jehovah—silver, gold, and various utensils.

^16 There was constant warfare between Aʹsa and Baʹa·sha the king of Israel. ^17 So King Baʹa·sha of Israel came up against Judah and began to build up[*] Raʹmah to prevent anyone from going out or coming in to[*] King Aʹsa of Judah. ^18 At that Aʹsa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah and the treasuries of the house[*] of the king and handed them over to his servants. King Aʹsa then sent them to Ben-haʹdad the son of Tab·rimʹmon the son of Heʹzi·on, the king of Syria, who was dwelling in Damascus, saying: ^19 “There is a treaty[*] between me and you and between my father and your father. I am sending you a gift of silver and gold. Come, break your treaty[*] with King Baʹa·sha of Israel, so that he will withdraw from me.” ^20 Ben-haʹdad listened to King Aʹsa and sent the chiefs of his armies against the cities of Israel, and they struck down Iʹjon, Dan, Aʹbel-beth-maʹa·cah, all Chinʹne·reth, and all the land of Naphʹta·li. ^21 When Baʹa·sha heard of it, he immediately quit building[*] Raʹmah and continued dwelling in Tirʹzah. ^22 King Aʹsa then summoned all Judah—no one was exempt—and they carried off the stones and timbers of Raʹmah that Baʹa·sha had been building with, and with them King Aʹsa built up[*] Geʹba in Benjamin, and Mizʹpah.

^23 As for all the rest of the history of Aʹsa, all his mightiness and all that he did and the cities that he built,[*] is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? But in his old age he suffered from a disease in his feet. ^24 Then Aʹsa was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with them in the City of David his forefather; and his son Je·hoshʹa·phat became king in his place.

^25 Naʹdab the son of Jer·o·boʹam became king over Israel in the second year of King Aʹsa of Judah, and he reigned over Israel for two years. ^26 He kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah and walked in the way of his father and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit. ^27 Baʹa·sha the son of A·hiʹjah of the house of Isʹsa·char conspired against him, and Baʹa·sha struck him down at Gibʹbe·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lisʹtines, while Naʹdab and all Israel were besieging Gibʹbe·thon. ^28 So Baʹa·sha put him to death in the third year of King Aʹsa of Judah and became king in his place. ^29 And as soon as he became king, he struck down all the house of Jer·o·boʹam. He did not let remain anyone breathing who belonged to Jer·o·boʹam; he had them annihilated according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servant A·hiʹjah the Shiʹlo·nite. ^30 This was because of the sins that Jer·o·boʹam had committed and had caused Israel to commit and because he had greatly offended Jehovah the God of Israel. ^31 As for the rest of the history of Naʹdab, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^32 And there was constant warfare between Aʹsa and King Baʹa·sha of Israel.

^33 In the third year of King Aʹsa of Judah, Baʹa·sha the son of A·hiʹjah became king in Tirʹzah over all Israel and reigned for 24 years. ^34 But he kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he walked in the way of Jer·o·boʹam and in his sin that he caused Israel to commit.

^ 1 Ki. 15:3 Or “not completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:12 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 1 Ki. 15:13 Or “as lady.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:13 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 15:14 Or “was completely devoted to.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:14 Lit., “days.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:17 Or “fortify; rebuild.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:17 Or “leaving or entering the territory of.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:18 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:19 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:19 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:21 Or “fortifying; rebuilding.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:22 Or “fortified; rebuilt.”

^ 1 Ki. 15:23 Or “fortified; rebuilt.”

1 Kings  16 : 1 - 34

16 The word of Jehovah against Baʹa·sha then came to Jeʹhu the son of Ha·naʹni, saying: ^2 “I raised you up out of the dust and made you leader over my people Israel, but you kept walking in the way of Jer·o·boʹam and caused my people Israel to sin so that they offended me with their sins. ^3 So I am making a clean sweep of Baʹa·sha and his house, and I will make his house like the house of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat. ^4 Anyone belonging to Baʹa·sha who dies in the city the dogs will eat; and anyone belonging to him who dies in the field the birds of the heavens will eat.”

^5 As for the rest of the history of Baʹa·sha, what he did and his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^6 Then Baʹa·sha was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Tirʹzah; and Eʹlah his son became king in his place. ^7 Also through the prophet Jeʹhu the son of Ha·naʹni, Jehovah’s word came against Baʹa·sha and his house, both because of all the badness that he committed in the eyes of Jehovah by offending him with the work of his hands, becoming like the house of Jer·o·boʹam, and also because of his striking him[*] down.

^8 In the 26th year of King Aʹsa of Judah, Eʹlah the son of Baʹa·sha became king over Israel in Tirʹzah, and he reigned for two years. ^9 His servant Zimʹri, the chief of half of his chariot forces, conspired against him while he was in Tirʹzah drinking himself drunk at the house of Arʹza, who was over the household in Tirʹzah. ^10 Zimʹri came in and struck him down and put him to death in the 27th year of King Aʹsa of Judah, and he became king in his place. ^11 When he became king, as soon as he sat down on his throne, he struck down all the house of Baʹa·sha. He did not spare a single male,[*] whether of his relatives[*] or of his friends. ^12 Thus Zimʹri annihilated the whole house of Baʹa·sha, according to the word that Jehovah had spoken against Baʹa·sha through Jeʹhu the prophet. ^13 This was for all the sins that Baʹa·sha and his son Eʹlah had committed and the sins they had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols. ^14 As for the rest of the history of Eʹlah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?

^15 In the 27th year of King Aʹsa of Judah, Zimʹri became king for seven days in Tirʹzah while the troops were camped against Gibʹbe·thon, which belonged to the Phi·lisʹtines. ^16 In time the troops who were encamped heard it being said: “Zimʹri has conspired and has also struck down the king.” So all Israel made Omʹri, the chief of the army, king over Israel on that day in the camp. ^17 Omʹri and all Israel with him went up from Gibʹbe·thon and laid siege to Tirʹzah. ^18 When Zimʹri saw that the city had been captured, he went into the fortified tower of the king’s house[*] and burned the house down over himself, and he died. ^19 This was for his own sins that he had committed by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah by walking in the way of Jer·o·boʹam and for the sin he had caused Israel to commit. ^20 As for the rest of the history of Zimʹri and his conspiracy, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?

^21 It was then that the people of Israel were divided into two factions. One part of the people became followers of Tibʹni the son of Giʹnath, wanting to make him king, and the other part followed Omʹri. ^22 But the people who were following Omʹri prevailed over the people following Tibʹni the son of Giʹnath. So Tibʹni died, and Omʹri became king.

^23 In the 31st year of King Aʹsa of Judah, Omʹri became king over Israel, and he reigned for 12 years. In Tirʹzah he reigned for six years. ^24 He bought the mountain of Sa·marʹi·a from Sheʹmer for two talents[*] of silver, and he built a city on the mountain. He named the city that he built Sa·marʹi·a,[*] after Sheʹmer the owner[*] of the mountain. ^25 Omʹri kept doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he was worse than all who were prior to him. ^26 He walked in all the ways of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat and in the sin he had caused Israel to commit by offending Jehovah the God of Israel with their worthless idols. ^27 As for the rest of the history of Omʹri, what he did and his mighty exploits, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^28 Then Omʹri was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·marʹi·a; and his son Aʹhab became king in his place.

^29 Aʹhab the son of Omʹri became king over Israel in the 38th year of King Aʹsa of Judah, and Aʹhab the son of Omʹri reigned over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a for 22 years. ^30 Aʹhab the son of Omʹri was worse in the eyes of Jehovah than all those who were prior to him. ^31 As if it were a trivial thing for him to walk in the sins of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat, he also took as wife Jezʹe·bel the daughter of Eth·baʹal, the king of the Si·doʹni·ans, and began to serve Baʹal and to bow down to him. ^32 Further, he set up an altar to Baʹal at the house[*] of Baʹal that he built in Sa·marʹi·a. ^33 Aʹhab also made the sacred pole.[*] Aʹhab did more to offend Jehovah the God of Israel than all the kings of Israel prior to him.

^34 In his days, Hiʹel the Bethʹel·ite rebuilt Jerʹi·cho. At the cost of A·biʹram his firstborn he laid its foundation, and at the cost of Seʹgub his youngest he put up its doors, according to the word of Jehovah spoken through Joshua the son of Nun.

^ 1 Ki. 16:7 That is, Nadab, the son of Jeroboam.

^ 1 Ki. 16:11 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Ki. 16:11 Or “his avengers of blood.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:18 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 Meaning “Belonging to the Clan Shemer.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:24 Lit., “lord.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:32 Or “temple.”

^ 1 Ki. 16:33 See Glossary.

1 Kings  17 : 1 - 24

17 Now E·liʹjah[*] the Tishʹbite, an inhabitant of Gilʹe·ad, said to Aʹhab: “As surely as Jehovah the God of Israel whom I serve[*] is living, during these years there will be no dew or rain except by my word!”

^2 The word of Jehovah came to him, saying: ^3 “Leave here, and turn eastward and hide at the Valley of Cheʹrith,[*] east of the Jordan. ^4 You should drink from the stream, and I will command the ravens to supply you food there.” ^5 He immediately went and did according to the word of Jehovah; he went and stayed by the Valley of Cheʹrith,[*] east of the Jordan. ^6 And the ravens were bringing him bread and meat in the morning and bread and meat in the evening, and he drank from the stream. ^7 But after some days, the stream ran dry, because there was no rain in the land.

^8 The word of Jehovah then came to him: ^9 “Rise up, go to Zarʹe·phath, which belongs to Siʹdon, and stay there. Look! I will command a widow there to supply you with food.” ^10 So he rose up and went to Zarʹe·phath. When he came to the entrance of the city, there was a widow gathering pieces of wood. So he called to her and said: “Please, bring me a little water in a cup so that I may drink.” ^11 As she went to get it, he called to her: “Please, bring me a piece of bread in your hand.” ^12 At this she said: “As surely as Jehovah your God is living, I have no bread, only a handful of flour in the large jar and a little oil in the small jar. Now I am gathering a few pieces of wood, and I will go in and make something for me and my son. After we have eaten, we will die.”

^13 Then E·liʹjah said to her: “Do not be afraid. Go in and do as you said. But first make me a small round loaf of bread with what is there, and bring it out to me. Then you can make something afterward for you and your son. ^14 For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘The large jar of flour will not run out, and the small jar of oil will not run dry until the day Jehovah makes it rain on the surface of the ground.’” ^15 So she went and did as E·liʹjah said, and she together with him and her household ate for many days. ^16 The large jar of flour did not run out, and the small jar of oil did not run dry, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through E·liʹjah.

^17 After these things, the son of the woman who owned the house fell sick, and his sickness became so severe that he stopped breathing. ^18 At this she said to E·liʹjah: “What do you have against me,[*] O man of the true God? Have you come to remind me of my guilt and to put my son to death?” ^19 But he said to her: “Give me your son.” Then he took him from her arms and carried him up to the roof chamber, where he was staying, and he laid him on his own bed. ^20 He called out to Jehovah: “O Jehovah my God, are you also bringing harm to the widow with whom I am staying by putting her son to death?” ^21 Then he stretched himself out over the child three times and called out to Jehovah: “O Jehovah my God, please, let this child’s life[*] come back into him.” ^22 Jehovah listened to E·liʹjah’s request, and the life[*] of the child came back into him, and he revived.[*] ^23 E·liʹjah took the child and brought him down from the roof chamber into the house and gave him to his mother; and E·liʹjah said: “See, your son is alive.” ^24 At that the woman said to E·liʹjah: “Now I know that you truly are a man of God and that Jehovah’s word in your mouth is truth.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:1 Meaning “My God Is Jehovah.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:1 Lit., “before whom I stand.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:3 Or “Wadi Cherith.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:5 Or “Wadi Cherith.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:18 Or “What do I have to do with you, . . .?”

^ 1 Ki. 17:21 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:22 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 17:22 Or “came to life.”

1 Kings  18 : 1 - 46

18 After some time, in the third year, Jehovah’s word came to E·liʹjah, saying: “Go, present yourself to Aʹhab, and I will send rain on the surface of the ground.” ^2 So E·liʹjah went to present himself to Aʹhab, while the famine was severe in Sa·marʹi·a.

^3 Meanwhile, Aʹhab called O·ba·diʹah, who was over the household. (Now O·ba·diʹah greatly feared Jehovah, ^4 and when Jezʹe·bel was doing away with[*] Jehovah’s prophets, O·ba·diʹah took 100 prophets and hid them 50 to a cave, and he supplied them with bread and water.) ^5 Aʹhab then said to O·ba·diʹah: “Go through the land to all the springs of water and to all the valleys.[*] Perhaps we can find enough grass to keep the horses and mules alive and not have all our animals die.” ^6 So they divided between themselves the land they were going to pass through. Aʹhab went alone by one way, and O·ba·diʹah went alone by another way.

^7 As O·ba·diʹah was on his way, E·liʹjah was there to meet him. At once he recognized him and fell facedown and said: “Is this you, my lord E·liʹjah?” ^8 He replied to him: “It is I. Go and tell your lord: ‘E·liʹjah is here.’” ^9 But he said: “What sin have I committed that you should hand your servant over to Aʹhab to put me to death? ^10 As surely as Jehovah your God is living, there is not a nation or a kingdom where my lord has not sent to look for you. After they said, ‘He is not here,’ he made the kingdom and the nation swear that they could not find you. ^11 Now you are saying, ‘Go and tell your lord: “E·liʹjah is here.”’ ^12 When I depart from you, the spirit of Jehovah will carry you away to a place I will not know, and when I tell Aʹhab and he does not find you, he will surely kill me. Yet, your servant has feared Jehovah from his youth. ^13 Has my lord not been told what I did when Jezʹe·bel was killing the prophets of Jehovah, how I hid 100 of the prophets of Jehovah by groups of 50 in a cave and kept supplying them bread and water? ^14 But now you are saying, ‘Go and tell your lord: “E·liʹjah is here.”’ He will certainly kill me.” ^15 However, E·liʹjah said: “As surely as Jehovah of armies whom I serve[*] is living, today I will present myself to him.”

^16 So O·ba·diʹah went off to meet Aʹhab and told him, and Aʹhab went to meet E·liʹjah.

^17 As soon as Aʹhab saw E·liʹjah, he said to him: “Is this you, the one bringing great trouble[*] on Israel?”

^18 To this he said: “I have not brought trouble on Israel, but you and the house of your father have, by abandoning the commandments of Jehovah and by following the Baʹals. ^19 And now summon all Israel to me at Mount Carʹmel, as well as the 450 prophets of Baʹal and the 400 prophets of the sacred pole,[*] who are eating at the table of Jezʹe·bel.” ^20 So Aʹhab sent word among all the people of Israel and collected the prophets together at Mount Carʹmel.

^21 Then E·liʹjah approached all the people and said: “How long will you be limping between two different opinions?[*] If Jehovah is the true God, follow him; but if Baʹal is, follow him!” But the people did not say a word in answer to him. ^22 E·liʹjah then said to the people: “I am the only prophet of Jehovah left, while the prophets of Baʹal are 450 men. ^23 Let them give us two young bulls, and let them choose one young bull and cut it into pieces and put it on the wood, but they should not put fire to it. I will prepare the other young bull, and I will place it on the wood, but I will not put fire to it. ^24 Then you must call on the name of your god, and I will call on the name of Jehovah. The God who answers by fire will show that he is the true God.” To this all the people answered: “What you say is good.”

^25 E·liʹjah now said to the prophets of Baʹal: “Choose one young bull and prepare it first, because you are the majority. Then call on the name of your god, but you must not put fire to it.” ^26 So they took the young bull that was given to them, prepared it, and kept calling on the name of Baʹal from morning until noon, saying: “O Baʹal, answer us!” But there was no voice and no one answering. They kept limping around the altar that they had made. ^27 About noon E·liʹjah began to mock them and say: “Call out at the top of your voice! After all, he is a god! Perhaps he is deep in thought or he has gone to relieve himself.[*] Or maybe he is asleep and someone needs to wake him up!” ^28 They were calling out at the top of their voice and cutting themselves with daggers and lances, according to their custom, until their blood gushed out all over them. ^29 Noon was past and they continued in a frenzy[*] until the time the evening grain offering is presented, but there was no voice and no one answering; no one was paying attention.

^30 At length E·liʹjah said to all the people: “Approach me.” So all the people approached him. Then he repaired the altar of Jehovah that had been torn down. ^31 E·liʹjah then took 12 stones, corresponding to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom Jehovah’s word had come, saying: “Israel will be your name.” ^32 With the stones he built an altar in the name of Jehovah. Then he made a trench all around the altar, an area large enough to sow with two seah measures[*] of seed. ^33 After that he put the pieces of wood in order, cut the young bull into pieces, and placed it on the wood. He now said: “Fill four large jars with water and pour it on the burnt offering and on the pieces of wood.” ^34 Then he said: “Do it again.” So they did it again. Once more he said: “Do it a third time.” So they did it a third time. ^35 And the water ran all around the altar, and he also filled the trench with water.

^36 About the time when the evening grain offering is presented, E·liʹjah the prophet stepped forward and said: “O Jehovah, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, today let it be known that you are God in Israel and that I am your servant and that it is by your word that I have done all these things. ^37 Answer me, O Jehovah! Answer me so that this people may know that you, Jehovah, are the true God and that you are turning their hearts back to you.”

^38 At that the fire of Jehovah fell from above and consumed the burnt offering, the pieces of wood, the stones, and the dust, and it licked up the water from the trench. ^39 When all the people saw it, they immediately fell facedown and said: “Jehovah is the true God! Jehovah is the true God!” ^40 Then E·liʹjah said to them: “Seize the prophets of Baʹal! Do not let a single one of them escape!” At once they seized them, and E·liʹjah brought them down to the stream[*] of Kiʹshon and slaughtered them there.

^41 E·liʹjah now said to Aʹhab: “Go up, eat and drink, for there is the sound of a heavy downpour.” ^42 So Aʹhab went up to eat and drink, while E·liʹjah went up to the top of Carʹmel and crouched on the ground, keeping his face between his knees. ^43 Then he said to his attendant: “Go up, please, and look toward the sea.” So he went up and looked and said: “There is nothing at all.” Seven times E·liʹjah said, “Go back.” ^44 The seventh time his attendant said: “Look! There is a small cloud like a man’s hand ascending out of the sea.” He now said: “Go, say to Aʹhab, ‘Hitch up the chariot! Go down so that the downpour may not detain you!’” ^45 Meanwhile, the sky grew dark with clouds, the wind blew, and a heavy downpour fell; and Aʹhab kept riding and made his way to Jezʹre·el. ^46 But the hand of Jehovah came on E·liʹjah, and he wrapped his garment around[*] his hips and ran ahead of Aʹhab all the way to Jezʹre·el.

^ 1 Ki. 18:4 Lit., “cutting off.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:5 Or “wadis.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:15 Lit., “before whom I stand.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:17 Or “bringing ostracism.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:19 See Glossary.

^ 1 Ki. 18:21 Or “on two crutches.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:27 Or possibly, “he has gone on a journey.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:29 Or “behaving like prophets.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:32 A seah equaled 7.33 L (6.66 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 18:40 Or “wadi.”

^ 1 Ki. 18:46 Or “he girded.”

1 Kings  19 : 1 - 21

19 Then Aʹhab told Jezʹe·bel all that E·liʹjah had done and how he had killed all the prophets with the sword. ^2 At that Jezʹe·bel sent a messenger to E·liʹjah, saying: “So may the gods do to me and add to it if by this time tomorrow I do not make you like each one[*] of them!” ^3 At that he became afraid, so he got up and ran for his life.[*] He came to Beʹer-sheʹba, which belongs to Judah, and he left his attendant there. ^4 He went a day’s journey into the wilderness and came and sat down under a broom tree, and he asked that he[*] might die. He said: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life[*] away, for I am no better than my forefathers.”

^5 Then he lay down and fell asleep under the broom tree. But suddenly an angel touched him and said to him: “Get up and eat.” ^6 When he looked, there at his head was a round loaf on heated stones and a jug of water. He ate and drank and lay down again. ^7 Later the angel of Jehovah came back a second time and touched him and said: “Get up and eat, for the journey will be too much for you.” ^8 So he got up and ate and drank, and in the strength of that nourishment he went on for 40 days and 40 nights until he reached Horʹeb, the mountain of the true God.

^9 There he entered a cave and spent the night; and look! Jehovah’s word came to him, telling him: “What are you doing here, E·liʹjah?” ^10 To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life[*] away.” ^11 But He said: “Go out and stand on the mountain before Jehovah.” And look! Jehovah was passing by, and a great and strong wind was splitting mountains and breaking crags before Jehovah, but Jehovah was not in the wind. After the wind, there was an earthquake, but Jehovah was not in the earthquake. ^12 After the earthquake, there was a fire, but Jehovah was not in the fire. After the fire, there was a calm, low voice. ^13 As soon as E·liʹjah heard it, he wrapped his face in his official garment and went out and stood at the entrance of the cave. Then a voice asked him: “What are you doing here, E·liʹjah?” ^14 To this he said: “I have been absolutely zealous for Jehovah the God of armies; for the people of Israel have forsaken your covenant, your altars they have torn down, and your prophets they have killed with the sword, and I am the only one left. Now they are seeking to take my life[*] away.”

^15 Jehovah said to him: “Return, and go to the wilderness of Damascus. When you arrive, anoint Hazʹa·el as king over Syria. ^16 And you should anoint Jeʹhu the grandson of Nimʹshi as king over Israel, and you should anoint E·liʹsha[*] the son of Shaʹphat from Aʹbel-me·hoʹlah as prophet to take your place. ^17 Anyone escaping from Hazʹa·el’s sword, Jeʹhu will put to death; and anyone escaping from Jeʹhu’s sword, E·liʹsha will put to death. ^18 And I still have left 7,000 in Israel, all whose knees have not bent down to Baʹal and whose mouths have not kissed him.”

^19 So he went from there and found E·liʹsha the son of Shaʹphat while he was plowing with 12 pairs of bulls ahead of him, and he was with the 12th pair. So E·liʹjah went over to him and threw his official garment on him. ^20 At that he left the bulls and ran after E·liʹjah and said: “Please, let me kiss my father and my mother. Then I will follow you.” He replied to him: “Go, return, for what have I done to stop you?” ^21 So he went back and took a pair of bulls and sacrificed them, and he used the plowing gear to boil the meat of the bulls and gave it to the people, and they ate. After that he rose up and followed E·liʹjah and began to minister to him.

^ 1 Ki. 19:2 Or “make your soul like the soul of each one.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:3 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:4 Or “his soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:4 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:10 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:14 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 19:16 Meaning “God Is Salvation.”

1 Kings  20 : 1 - 43

20 Now King Ben-haʹdad of Syria gathered his whole army together along with 32 other kings and their horses and chariots; he went up and laid siege to Sa·marʹi·a and fought against it. ^2 Then he sent messengers to King Aʹhab of Israel at the city and said to him: “This is what Ben-haʹdad says, ^3 ‘Your silver and your gold are mine, as well as the best of your wives and your sons.’” ^4 To this the king of Israel answered: “According to your word, my lord the king, I am yours along with all that belongs to me.”

^5 The messengers later came back and said: “This is what Ben-haʹdad says, ‘I sent this message to you: “Your silver, your gold, your wives, and your sons you will give me.” ^6 But about this time tomorrow I will send my servants to you, and they will carefully search your house and the houses of your servants, and all your desirable things they will seize and take away.’”

^7 At that the king of Israel called all the elders of the land and said: “Take note, please, and see that this man is bent on bringing calamity, for he demanded my wives, my sons, my silver, and my gold, and I did not refuse him.” ^8 Then all the elders and all the people said to him: “Do not obey, and do not consent.” ^9 So he said to the messengers of Ben-haʹdad: “Say to my lord the king, ‘All that you first demanded of your servant I will do, but this I cannot do.’” With that the messengers went off and brought word back to him.

^10 Ben-haʹdad now sent him this message: “So may the gods do to me and add to it if there is enough dust in Sa·marʹi·a to give each of the people following me a handful!” ^11 The king of Israel answered: “Tell him, ‘The one who puts on his armor should not boast about himself like one who takes it off.’” ^12 As soon as he heard this reply, while he and the kings were drinking in their tents,[*] he said to his servants: “Get ready to attack!” So they got ready to attack the city.

^13 But a prophet approached King Aʹhab of Israel and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Have you seen all this large crowd? Here I am giving it into your hand today, and then you will know that I am Jehovah.’” ^14 Aʹhab asked: “By whom?” to which he said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘By the attendants of the princes of the provinces.’”[*] So he asked: “Who will start the battle?” to which he said: “You!”

^15 Aʹhab then counted the attendants of the princes of the provinces, and they were 232; after that, he counted all the Israelite men, 7,000. ^16 They went out at noon while Ben-haʹdad was drinking himself drunk in the tents[*] along with the 32 kings who were helping him. ^17 When the attendants of the princes of the provinces came out first, Ben-haʹdad at once sent messengers. They reported to him: “Men have come out from Sa·marʹi·a.” ^18 At that he said: “If they have come out for peace, take them alive; or if they have come out for battle, you should still take them alive.” ^19 But when these came out of the city—the attendants of the princes of the provinces and the armies that were following them— ^20 each one struck down his opponent. Then the Syrians fled, and Israel pursued them, but King Ben-haʹdad of Syria escaped on a horse with some of the horsemen. ^21 But the king of Israel went out and kept striking down the horses and the chariots, and he inflicted a great defeat[*] on the Syrians.

^22 Later the prophet approached the king of Israel and said to him: “Go, strengthen yourself and consider what you are going to do, for at the start of the next year[*] the king of Syria will come up against you.”

^23 Now the servants of the king of Syria said to him: “Their God is a God of mountains. That is why they overpowered us. But if we fight against them on level land, we will overpower them. ^24 Also do this: Remove all the kings from their places, and replace them with governors. ^25 Then gather[*] an army equal to the army you lost, horse for horse and chariot for chariot. Let us fight against them on level land, and we will surely overpower them.” So he listened to their advice and did just that.

^26 At the start of the year,[*] Ben-haʹdad mustered the Syrians and went up to Aʹphek for battle against Israel. ^27 The people of Israel were also mustered and supplied, and they went out to meet them. When the people of Israel camped in front of them, they were like two tiny flocks of goats, while the Syrians filled the whole land. ^28 Then the man of the true God approached the king of Israel and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Because the Syrians have said: “Jehovah is a God of mountains, and he is not a God of plains,” I will give all this large crowd into your hand, and you will certainly know that I am Jehovah.’”

^29 They remained encamped opposite each other for seven days, and on the seventh day the battle began. The people of Israel struck down 100,000 Syrian foot soldiers in one day. ^30 And the rest fled to Aʹphek, into the city. But the wall fell down on 27,000 of the men who were left. Ben-haʹdad also fled and came into the city, and he hid in an inner room.

^31 So his servants said to him: “Look, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are merciful kings.[*] Please, let us wear sackcloth on our hips and put ropes on our heads and go out to the king of Israel. Perhaps he will spare your life.”[*] ^32 So they wore sackcloth around their hips and ropes on their heads and came in to the king of Israel and said: “Your servant Ben-haʹdad says, ‘Please, let me[*] live.’” He replied: “Is he still alive? He is my brother.” ^33 The men took it as an omen and quickly took him at his word, so they said: “Ben-haʹdad is your brother.” At that he said: “Go and get him.” Then Ben-haʹdad went out to him, and he had him get up into the chariot.

^34 Ben-haʹdad now said to him: “The cities that my father took from your father I will return, and you may establish markets[*] for yourself in Damascus, just as my father did in Sa·marʹi·a.”

Aʹhab replied: “On the basis of this agreement,[*] I will let you go.”

With that he made an agreement with him and let him go.

^35 By the word of Jehovah, one of the sons of the prophets[*] said to his companion: “Strike me, please.” But the man refused to strike him. ^36 So he said to him: “Because you did not listen to the voice of Jehovah, as soon as you leave me, a lion will kill you.”[*] After he left him, a lion came upon him and killed him.

^37 He found another man and said: “Strike me, please.” So the man struck him and wounded him.

^38 Then the prophet went and waited for the king by the road, disguising himself with a bandage over his eyes. ^39 As the king was passing by, he cried out to the king: “Your servant went into the thick of the battle, and there was a man coming out who brought a man to me and said, ‘Guard this man. If he is found missing, your life will have to take the place of his life,[*] or else you will pay a talent[*] of silver.’ ^40 And while your servant was busy here and there, suddenly the man was gone.” The king of Israel said to him: “So your own judgment will be; you have decided it yourself.” ^41 Then he quickly removed the bandage from his eyes, and the king of Israel recognized that he was one of the prophets. ^42 He said to him: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Because you have let the man who I said should be destroyed escape from your hand, your life must take the place of his life,[*] and your people the place of his people.’” ^43 At that the king of Israel went home to Sa·marʹi·a, sullen and dejected.

^ 1 Ki. 20:12 Or “booths.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:14 Or “the jurisdictional districts.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:16 Or “booths.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:21 Or “slaughter.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:22 That is, next spring.

^ 1 Ki. 20:25 Lit., “number.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:26 That is, in the spring.

^ 1 Ki. 20:31 Or “are kings of loyal love.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:31 Or “soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:32 Or “my soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:34 Or “assign streets.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:34 Or “covenant.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:35 “The sons of the prophets” seems to refer to a school of instruction for prophets or to an association of prophets.

^ 1 Ki. 20:36 Or “strike you down.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:39 Or “your soul will be in place of his soul.”

^ 1 Ki. 20:39 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Ki. 20:42 Or “your soul will be in place of his soul.”

1 Kings  21 : 1 - 29

21 After these things, an incident took place concerning a vineyard that belonged to Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite; it was in Jezʹre·el, next to the palace of Aʹhab the king of Sa·marʹi·a. ^2 Aʹhab said to Naʹboth: “Give me your vineyard for me to use as a vegetable garden, for it is near my house. Then I will give you a better vineyard to replace it. Or if you prefer, I will give you its value in money.” ^3 But Naʹboth said to Aʹhab: “It is unthinkable, from Jehovah’s standpoint, for me to give you the inheritance of my forefathers.” ^4 So Aʹhab came into his house, sullen and dejected over the answer that Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite had given him when he said: “I will not give you the inheritance of my forefathers.” Then he lay down on his bed, kept his face turned away, and refused to eat.

^5 His wife Jezʹe·bel came in to him and asked him: “Why are you[*] so sad that you refuse to eat?” ^6 He replied to her: “Because I said to Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite, ‘Give me your vineyard for money. Or if you prefer, let me give you another vineyard to replace it.’ But he said, ‘I will not give you my vineyard.’” ^7 His wife Jezʹe·bel said to him: “Are you not the one ruling as king over Israel? Get up, eat something, and let your heart be cheerful. I will give you the vineyard of Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite.” ^8 So she wrote letters in Aʹhab’s name and sealed them with his seal and sent the letters to the elders and the nobles who lived in Naʹboth’s city. ^9 She wrote in the letters: “Proclaim a fast, and have Naʹboth sit at the head of the people. ^10 And have two good-for-nothing men sit in front of him and testify against him, saying, ‘You have cursed God and the king!’ Then bring him out and stone him to death.”

^11 So the men of his city, the elders and the nobles who lived in his city, did just as was written in the letters that Jezʹe·bel sent to them. ^12 They proclaimed a fast and had Naʹboth sit at the head of the people. ^13 Then two of the good-for-nothing men came in and sat down in front of him and began to testify against Naʹboth in front of the people, saying: “Naʹboth has cursed God and the king!” After that they brought him to the outskirts of the city and stoned him to death. ^14 They now sent word to Jezʹe·bel, saying: “Naʹboth has been stoned to death.”

^15 As soon as Jezʹe·bel heard that Naʹboth had been stoned to death, she said to Aʹhab: “Get up, take possession of the vineyard of Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite, which he refused to give you for money, for Naʹboth is no longer alive. He is dead.” ^16 As soon as Aʹhab heard that Naʹboth was dead, Aʹhab got up to go down to the vineyard of Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite to take possession of it.

^17 But Jehovah’s word came to E·liʹjah the Tishʹbite, saying: ^18 “Get up, go down to meet Aʹhab the king of Israel, who is in Sa·marʹi·a. There he is in the vineyard of Naʹboth, where he has gone to take possession of it. ^19 You must tell him, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Have you murdered a man and also taken his property?”’[*] Then say to him, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “In the place where the dogs licked up the blood of Naʹboth, the dogs will lick up your own blood.”’”

^20 Aʹhab said to E·liʹjah: “So you have found me, O my enemy!” He replied: “I have found you. ‘Because you are determined[*] to do what is bad in the eyes of Jehovah, ^21 here I am bringing calamity upon you, and I will make a clean sweep after you and will annihilate from Aʹhab every male,[*] including the helpless and weak in Israel. ^22 And I will make your house like the house of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat and like the house of Baʹa·sha the son of A·hiʹjah, for you have provoked my anger and have caused Israel to sin.’ ^23 Also concerning Jezʹe·bel, Jehovah has said: ‘The dogs will eat up Jezʹe·bel in the plot of land of Jezʹre·el. ^24 Anyone belonging to Aʹhab who dies in the city the dogs will eat up, and anyone who dies in the field the birds of the heavens will eat up. ^25 Indeed, there has never been anyone like Aʹhab, who was so determined[*] to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, egged on by his wife Jezʹe·bel. ^26 He acted in the most detestable way by going after the disgusting idols,[*] just as all the Amʹor·ites had done, whom Jehovah drove out from before the Israelites.’”

^27 As soon as Aʹhab heard these words, he ripped his garments apart and put sackcloth on his body; and he went on a fast and kept lying down in sackcloth and walking despondently. ^28 Jehovah’s word then came to E·liʹjah the Tishʹbite: ^29 “Have you seen how Aʹhab has humbled himself on my account? Because he has humbled himself before me, I will not bring the calamity during his lifetime. I will bring the calamity upon his house in the days of his son.”

^ 1 Ki. 21:5 Lit., “is your spirit.”

^ 1 Ki. 21:19 Lit., “taken possession?”

^ 1 Ki. 21:20 Lit., “you have sold yourself.”

^ 1 Ki. 21:21 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 1 Ki. 21:25 Lit., “who sold himself.”

^ 1 Ki. 21:26 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

1 Kings  22 : 1 - 53

22 For three years there was no war between Syria and Israel. ^2 In the third year King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah went down to the king of Israel. ^3 Then the king of Israel said to his servants: “Do you know that Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad belongs to us? And yet we are hesitating to take it back from the king of Syria.” ^4 He then said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “Will you go with me to fight at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad?” Je·hoshʹa·phat replied to the king of Israel: “I am the same as you. My people are the same as your people. My horses are the same as your horses.”

^5 But Je·hoshʹa·phat said to the king of Israel: “First inquire, please, for the word of Jehovah.” ^6 So the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, about 400 men, and said to them: “Should I go to war against Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, or should I refrain?” They said: “Go up, and Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”

^7 Je·hoshʹa·phat then said: “Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah? Let us also inquire through him.” ^8 At that the king of Israel said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “There is still one more man through whom we can inquire of Jehovah; but I hate him, for he never prophesies good things concerning me, only bad. He is Mi·caiʹah the son of Imʹlah.” However, Je·hoshʹa·phat said: “The king should not say such a thing.”

^9 So the king of Israel called a court official and said: “Bring Mi·caiʹah the son of Imʹlah quickly.” ^10 Now the king of Israel and Je·hoshʹa·phat the king of Judah were each sitting on his throne, dressed in royal attire, at the threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Sa·marʹi·a, and all the prophets were prophesying before them. ^11 Then Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Che·naʹa·nah made for himself iron horns and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘With these you will gore[*] the Syrians until you exterminate them.’” ^12 All the other prophets were prophesying the same way, saying: “Go up to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad and you will be successful; Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”

^13 So the messenger who went to call Mi·caiʹah said to him: “Look! The words of the prophets are unanimously favorable to the king. Let your word, please, become like their words, and speak favorably.” ^14 But Mi·caiʹah said: “As surely as Jehovah is living, whatever Jehovah says to me is what I will speak.” ^15 Then he came in to the king, and the king asked him: “Mi·caiʹah, should we go to war against Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, or should we refrain?” At once he replied: “Go up and you will be successful; Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.” ^16 At that the king said to him: “How many times must I put you under oath not to speak to me anything but the truth in the name of Jehovah?” ^17 So he said: “I see all the Israelites scattered on the mountains, like sheep that have no shepherd. Jehovah said: ‘These have no master. Let each one go back to his house in peace.’”

^18 Then the king of Israel said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “Did I not tell you, ‘He will not prophesy good things concerning me, only bad’?”

^19 Mi·caiʹah then said: “Therefore, hear the word of Jehovah: I saw Jehovah sitting on his throne and all the army of the heavens standing by him, to his right and to his left. ^20 Jehovah then said, ‘Who will fool Aʹhab, so that he will go up and fall at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad?’ And one was saying one thing while another said something else. ^21 Then a spirit[*] came forward and stood before Jehovah and said, ‘I will fool him.’ Jehovah asked him, ‘How will you do it?’ ^22 He replied, ‘I will go out and become a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ So he said, ‘You will fool him, and what is more, you will be successful. Go out and do that.’ ^23 And now Jehovah has put a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all these prophets of yours, but Jehovah has declared calamity for you.”

^24 Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Che·naʹa·nah now approached and struck Mi·caiʹah on the cheek and said: “Which way did the spirit of Jehovah pass from me to speak with you?” ^25 Mi·caiʹah replied: “Look! You will see which way on the day when you will enter the innermost room to hide.” ^26 Then the king of Israel said: “Take Mi·caiʹah and turn him over to Aʹmon the chief of the city and to Joʹash the king’s son. ^27 Tell them, ‘This is what the king says: “Put this fellow in the prison and feed him with a reduced allowance of bread and water until I return in peace.”’” ^28 But Mi·caiʹah said: “If you do return in peace, Jehovah has not spoken with me.” Then he added: “Take note, all you peoples.”

^29 So the king of Israel and Je·hoshʹa·phat the king of Judah went up to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad. ^30 The king of Israel now said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “I will disguise myself and will go into the battle, but you should put on your royal attire.” So the king of Israel disguised himself and entered the battle. ^31 Now the king of Syria had ordered his 32 chariot commanders: “Do not fight with anyone, small or great, except the king of Israel.” ^32 And as soon as the chariot commanders saw Je·hoshʹa·phat, they said to themselves: “Surely it is the king of Israel.” So they turned to fight against him; and Je·hoshʹa·phat began to cry for help. ^33 When the chariot commanders saw that it was not the king of Israel, they immediately turned back from following him.

^34 But one man shot his bow at random,[*] and he struck the king of Israel between the joints of his coat of mail. So the king said to his charioteer: “Turn around and take me out of the battle,[*] for I have been badly wounded.” ^35 The fighting raged throughout that day, and the king had to be propped up in the chariot, facing the Syrians. The blood of the wound poured out into the interior of the war chariot, and he died in the evening. ^36 Around sunset a cry passed through the camp, saying: “Everyone to his city! Everyone to his land!” ^37 Thus the king died, and he was brought to Sa·marʹi·a; they buried the king in Sa·marʹi·a. ^38 When they washed off the war chariot by the pool of Sa·marʹi·a, the dogs licked up his blood and the prostitutes bathed there,[*] according to the word that Jehovah had spoken.

^39 As for the rest of the history of Aʹhab, all that he did and the house[*] of ivory that he built and all the cities that he built, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^40 Then Aʹhab was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son A·ha·ziʹah became king in his place.

^41 Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of Aʹsa had become king over Judah in the fourth year of King Aʹhab of Israel. ^42 Je·hoshʹa·phat was 35 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 25 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A·zuʹbah the daughter of Shilʹhi. ^43 He kept walking in all the way of Aʹsa his father. He did not deviate from it, and he did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes. However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. ^44 Je·hoshʹa·phat kept peaceful relations with the king of Israel. ^45 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoshʹa·phat, his mighty exploits and how he waged war, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^46 He also cleared out of the land the rest of the male temple prostitutes who had been left over in the days of Aʹsa his father.

^47 Then there was no king in Eʹdom; a deputy was acting as king.

^48 Je·hoshʹa·phat also made Tarʹshish ships[*] to go to Oʹphir for gold, but they did not go because the ships were wrecked at Eʹzi·on-geʹber. ^49 It was then that A·ha·ziʹah the son of Aʹhab said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “Let my servants go with your servants in the ships,” but Je·hoshʹa·phat did not consent.

^50 Then Je·hoshʹa·phat was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather; and his son Je·hoʹram became king in his place.

^51 A·ha·ziʹah the son of Aʹhab became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a in the 17th year of King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah, and he reigned over Israel for two years. ^52 And he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes and walking in the way of his father and his mother and in the way of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat, who had caused Israel to sin. ^53 He continued serving Baʹal and bowing down to him and kept offending Jehovah the God of Israel, just as his father had done.

^ 1 Ki. 22:11 Or “push.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:21 Or “an angel.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:34 Or “in his innocence.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:34 Lit., “camp.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:38 Or possibly, “where the prostitutes bathed, the dogs licked up his blood.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:39 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Ki. 22:48 See Glossary.

2 Kings  1 : 1 - 18

THE SECOND OF KINGS

1 After the death of Aʹhab, Moʹab revolted against Israel.

^2 It was then that A·ha·ziʹah fell down through the grating in his roof chamber in Sa·marʹi·a and was injured. So he sent messengers and said to them: “Go, inquire of Baʹal-zeʹbub the god of Ekʹron to find out whether I will recover from this injury.” ^3 But the angel of Jehovah said to E·liʹjah[*] the Tishʹbite: “Rise up, go to meet the messengers of the king of Sa·marʹi·a and say to them, ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are going to inquire of Baʹal-zeʹbub the god of Ekʹron? ^4 Therefore this is what Jehovah says: “You will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.”’” With that E·liʹjah went off.

^5 When the messengers returned to him, he immediately said to them: “Why have you come back?” ^6 They replied to him: “There was a man who came up to meet us, and he said to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent you and tell him, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel that you are sending to inquire of Baʹal-zeʹbub the god of Ekʹron? Therefore, you will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.’”’” ^7 At this he asked them: “What did the man look like who came up to meet you and spoke these words to you?” ^8 So they said to him: “He was a man with a garment of hair and a leather belt around his waist.” Immediately he said: “It was E·liʹjah the Tishʹbite.”

^9 The king then sent to him a chief of 50 with his 50 men. When he went up to him, he was sitting on the top of the mountain. He said to him: “Man of the true God, the king says, ‘Come down.’” ^10 But E·liʹjah answered the chief of the 50: “Well, if I am a man of God, let fire come down from the heavens and consume you and your 50 men.” And fire came down from the heavens and consumed him and his 50 men.

^11 So the king sent again to him another chief of 50 with his 50 men. He went and said to him: “Man of the true God, this is what the king says, ‘Come down quickly.’” ^12 But E·liʹjah answered them: “If I am a man of the true God, let fire come down from the heavens and consume you and your 50 men.” And fire of God came down from the heavens and consumed him and his 50 men.

^13 Then the king sent again a third chief of 50 and his 50 men. But the third chief of 50 went up and bowed down on his knees in front of E·liʹjah and began to beg for favor and say to him: “Man of the true God, please, let my life and the lives of[*] these 50 servants of yours be precious in your eyes. ^14 Fire has already come down from the heavens and consumed the two former chiefs of 50 and their groups of 50, but now let my life[*] be precious in your eyes.”

^15 At that the angel of Jehovah told E·liʹjah: “Go down with him. Do not be afraid of him.” So he rose and went down with him to the king. ^16 E·liʹjah then said to the king, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘You sent messengers to inquire of Baʹal-zeʹbub the god of Ekʹron. Is it because there is no God in Israel? Why did you not inquire of his word? Therefore, you will not leave the bed on which you are lying, for you will certainly die.’” ^17 So he died, according to the word of Jehovah that E·liʹjah had spoken; and because he did not have a son, Je·hoʹram[*] became king in his place, in the second year of Je·hoʹram the son of Je·hoshʹa·phat the king of Judah.

^18 As for the rest of the history of A·ha·ziʹah, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel?

^ 2 Ki. 1:3 Meaning “My God Is Jehovah.”

^ 2 Ki. 1:13 Or “let my soul and the souls of.”

^ 2 Ki. 1:14 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Ki. 1:17 That is, Ahaziah’s brother.

2 Kings  2 : 1 - 25

2 When Jehovah was about to take E·liʹjah up to the heavens[*] in a windstorm, E·liʹjah and E·liʹsha went out from Gilʹgal. ^2 E·liʹjah said to E·liʹsha: “Stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to Bethʹel.” But E·liʹsha said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are[*] living, I will not leave you.” So they went down to Bethʹel. ^3 Then the sons of the prophets[*] in Bethʹel came out to E·liʹsha and said to him: “Do you know that today Jehovah is taking your master away from headship over you?” At this he said: “I already know it. Be silent.”

^4 E·liʹjah now said to him: “E·liʹsha, stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to Jerʹi·cho.” But he said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are[*] living, I will not leave you.” So they came to Jerʹi·cho. ^5 Then the sons of the prophets who were in Jerʹi·cho approached E·liʹsha and said to him: “Do you know that today Jehovah is taking your master away from headship over you?” At this he said: “I already know it. Be silent.”

^6 E·liʹjah now said to him: “Stay here, please, because Jehovah has sent me on to the Jordan.” But he said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you are[*] living, I will not leave you.” So both of them went on. ^7 And 50 of the sons of the prophets also went and stood watching from a distance while the two of them stood by the Jordan. ^8 Then E·liʹjah took his official garment and rolled it up and struck the waters, and they were divided to the left and to the right, so that both of them went across on the dry ground.

^9 As soon as they had gone across, E·liʹjah said to E·liʹsha: “Ask what you want me to do for you before I am taken from you.” So E·liʹsha said: “Please, may I receive a double portion[*] of your spirit?” ^10 He replied: “You have asked a difficult thing. If you see me when I am taken from you, it will happen for you that way; but if you do not, it will not happen.”

^11 As they were walking along, speaking as they walked, suddenly a fiery chariot and fiery horses made a separation between the two of them, and E·liʹjah ascended to the heavens[*] in the windstorm. ^12 While E·liʹsha was watching, he was crying out: “My father, my father! The chariot of Israel and his horsemen!” When he could no longer see him, he took hold of his own garments and ripped them into two pieces. ^13 After that he picked up the official garment of E·liʹjah that had fallen off him and went back and stood by the bank of the Jordan. ^14 Then he took the official garment of E·liʹjah that had fallen off him and struck the waters and said: “Where is Jehovah, the God of E·liʹjah?” When he struck the waters, they were divided to the left and to the right, so that E·liʹsha went across.

^15 When the sons of the prophets at Jerʹi·cho saw him from a distance, they said: “The spirit of E·liʹjah has settled down on E·liʹsha.” So they went to meet him and bowed down to the ground before him. ^16 They said to him: “Here are 50 capable men with your servants. Let them go, please, to look for your master. Perhaps the spirit[*] of Jehovah has lifted him up and then thrown him on one of the mountains or in one of the valleys.” But he said: “Do not send them.” ^17 However, they kept urging him until he was embarrassed, so he said: “Send them.” They sent the 50 men, who kept looking for three days but did not find him. ^18 When they returned to him, he was staying in Jerʹi·cho. Then he said to them: “Did I not tell you not to go?”

^19 In time the men of the city said to E·liʹsha: “My master can see that the city is well-situated; but the water is bad, and the land is barren.”[*] ^20 At that he said: “Bring me a small new bowl and put salt in it.” So they brought it to him. ^21 Then he went out to the source of the water and threw salt into it and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘I have healed this water. No more will it cause death or barrenness.’”[*] ^22 And the water has been healed down to this day, according to the word spoken by E·liʹsha.

^23 He went up from there to Bethʹel. As he was going along the way, some young boys came out from the city and began to jeer at him, and they kept saying to him: “Go up, you baldhead! Go up, you baldhead!” ^24 Finally he turned around and looked at them and cursed them in the name of Jehovah. Then two she-bears came out of the forest and tore 42 of the children to pieces. ^25 He kept going from there to Mount Carʹmel, and from there he returned to Sa·marʹi·a.

^ 2 Ki. 2:1 Or “sky.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:2 Or “your soul is.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:3 “The sons of the prophets” seems to refer to a school of instruction for prophets or to an association of prophets.

^ 2 Ki. 2:4 Or “your soul is.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:6 Or “your soul is.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:9 Or “two parts.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:11 Or “sky.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:16 Or “wind.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:19 Or possibly, “causing miscarriages.”

^ 2 Ki. 2:21 Or possibly, “miscarriages.”

2 Kings  3 : 1 - 27

3 Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a in the 18th year of King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah, and he reigned for 12 years. ^2 He kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, but not to the extent of his father or his mother, for he removed the sacred pillar of Baʹal that his father had made. ^3 However, he clung to the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. He did not depart from them.

^4 Now Meʹsha the king of Moʹab was a sheep raiser, and he used to pay 100,000 lambs and 100,000 unshorn rams as tribute to the king of Israel. ^5 As soon as Aʹhab died, the king of Moʹab revolted against the king of Israel. ^6 So King Je·hoʹram went out on that day from Sa·marʹi·a and mustered all Israel. ^7 He also sent a message to King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah, saying: “The king of Moʹab has revolted against me. Will you go with me to war against Moʹab?” To this he said: “I will go. I am the same as you. My people are the same as your people. My horses are the same as your horses.” ^8 Then he asked: “By which way should we go up?” He replied: “By the way of the wilderness of Eʹdom.”

^9 The king of Israel then set out with the king of Judah and the king of Eʹdom. After they journeyed roundabout for seven days, there was no water for the camp and for the domestic animals that were following behind them. ^10 The king of Israel said: “How terrible! Jehovah has called these three kings, only to give them into the hand of Moʹab!” ^11 At that Je·hoshʹa·phat said: “Is there no prophet of Jehovah here through whom we may inquire of Jehovah?” So one of the servants of the king of Israel answered: “There is E·liʹsha the son of Shaʹphat, who used to pour out water on the hands of E·liʹjah.”[*] ^12 Then Je·hoshʹa·phat said: “The word of Jehovah is with him.” So the king of Israel and Je·hoshʹa·phat and the king of Eʹdom went down to him.

^13 E·liʹsha said to the king of Israel: “What do I have to do with you?[*] Go to the prophets of your father and to the prophets of your mother.” But the king of Israel said to him: “No, for it is Jehovah who has called these three kings to give them into the hand of Moʹab.” ^14 To this E·liʹsha said: “As surely as Jehovah of armies whom I serve[*] is living, if I did not have regard for King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah, I would not look at you or take notice of you. ^15 Now bring me a harpist.”[*] As soon as the harpist started playing, the hand of Jehovah came on him. ^16 He said, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Dig trench after trench in this valley,[*] ^17 for this is what Jehovah says: “You will not see wind, and you will not see rain; yet this valley[*] will be filled with water, and you will drink from it, you, your livestock, and your other animals.”’ ^18 But this is a trivial thing in the eyes of Jehovah, for he will also give Moʹab into your hand. ^19 You must strike down every fortified city and every choice city, you should cut down every good tree, you should stop up all the springs of water, and you should ruin every good plot of land with stones.”

^20 And in the morning, at the time of the morning grain offering, water was suddenly coming from the direction of Eʹdom, and the land became filled with the water.

^21 All the Moʹab·ites heard that the kings had come up to fight against them, so they called together all the men who could bear arms,[*] and they stationed themselves at the border. ^22 When they got up early in the morning, the sun was shining on the water, and to the Moʹab·ites on the opposite side, the water looked red like blood. ^23 They said: “This is blood! The kings have surely slaughtered one another with the sword. So, then, to the spoil, O Moʹab!” ^24 When they came into the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and began striking down the Moʹab·ites, who fled from them. They advanced into Moʹab, striking the Moʹab·ites down as they went. ^25 They tore down the cities, and each man threw a stone into every good plot of land, filling it with stones; they stopped up every spring of water, and they cut down every good tree. Finally only the stone walls of Kir-harʹe·seth remained standing, and the slingers surrounded it and struck it down.

^26 When the king of Moʹab saw that the battle was lost, he took with him 700 men armed with swords to break through to the king of Eʹdom; but they were not able to. ^27 So he took his firstborn son who was going to reign in his place and offered him up as a burnt sacrifice on the wall. And there came to be great indignation against Israel, so they withdrew from against him and returned to their land.

^ 2 Ki. 3:11 Or “who was Elijah’s servant.”

^ 2 Ki. 3:13 Lit., “What to me and to you?”

^ 2 Ki. 3:14 Lit., “before whom I stand.”

^ 2 Ki. 3:15 Or “musician.”

^ 2 Ki. 3:16 Or “wadi.”

^ 2 Ki. 3:17 Or “wadi.”

^ 2 Ki. 3:21 Or “all who girded on a belt.”

2 Kings  4 : 1 - 44

4 Now one of the wives of the sons of the prophets cried out to E·liʹsha, saying: “Your servant my husband is dead, and you well know that your servant had always feared Jehovah. Now a creditor has come to take both of my children as his slaves.” ^2 At this E·liʹsha said to her: “What can I do for you? Tell me, what do you have in the house?” She replied: “Your servant has nothing at all in the house but a jar[*] of oil.” ^3 Then he said: “Go outside, ask for containers from all your neighbors, empty containers. Do not limit yourself to a few. ^4 Then go in and close the door behind you and your sons. Fill all these containers, and set the full ones aside.” ^5 So she left him.

When she closed the door behind her and her sons, they passed the containers to her, and she kept pouring. ^6 When the containers were full, she said to one of her sons: “Bring another container to me.” But he said to her: “There are no more containers.” At that the oil stopped. ^7 So she came in and told the man of the true God, and he said: “Go, sell the oil and pay off your debts, and you and your sons can live from what is left.”

^8 One day E·liʹsha went to Shuʹnem, where there was a prominent woman, and she urged him to eat a meal there. As often as he would pass by, he would stop there to eat. ^9 So she said to her husband: “I know that it is a holy man of God who comes this way regularly. ^10 Please, let us make a small room on the roof and put there for him a bed, a table, a chair, and a lampstand. Then, whenever he comes to us, he can stay there.”

^11 One day he came there, and he went to the room on the roof to lie down. ^12 He then said to Ge·haʹzi his attendant: “Call this Shuʹnam·mite woman.” So he called her, and she stood before him. ^13 Then he said to Ge·haʹzi: “Please tell her, ‘Here you have gone to all this trouble for us. What can be done for you? Should I speak in your behalf to the king or to the chief of the army?’” But her reply was: “I am living among my own people.” ^14 So he said: “Then what can be done for her?” Ge·haʹzi now said: “Well, she does not have a son, and her husband is old.” ^15 Immediately he said: “Call her.” So he called her, and she stood at the doorway. ^16 Then he said: “At this time next year, you will be embracing a son.” But she said: “No, my master, man of the true God! Do not tell lies to your servant.”

^17 However, the woman became pregnant and gave birth to a son at the same time the next year, just as E·liʹsha had told her. ^18 The child grew up, and one day he went out to his father, who was with the reapers. ^19 He kept saying to his father: “My head, O my head!” Then his father said to the attendant: “Carry him to his mother.” ^20 So he carried him back to his mother, and he sat on her lap until noon, and then he died. ^21 Then she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of the true God, and she shut the door behind her and left. ^22 She now called her husband and said: “Send me, please, one of the attendants and one of the donkeys, and let me go quickly to the man of the true God and return.” ^23 But he said: “Why are you going to see him today? It is not a new moon or a sabbath.” However, she said: “Everything is all right.” ^24 So she saddled the donkey and said to her attendant: “Go quickly. Do not slow down for me unless I tell you to.”

^25 So she went to the man of the true God at Mount Carʹmel. As soon as the man of the true God saw her from afar, he said to Ge·haʹzi his attendant: “Look! The Shuʹnam·mite woman is over there. ^26 Please run to meet her and ask her, ‘Are you well? Is your husband well? Is your child well?’” To this she said: “All is well.” ^27 When she came to the man of the true God at the mountain, she at once grabbed hold of his feet. At this Ge·haʹzi came near to push her away, but the man of the true God said: “Let her alone, for she is in bitter distress,[*] and Jehovah has hidden it from me and has not told me.” ^28 She then said: “Did I ask my lord for a son? Did I not say, ‘You must not give me a false hope’?”

^29 He immediately said to Ge·haʹzi: “Wrap your garments around your waist and take my staff in your hand and go. If you encounter anyone, do not greet him; and if anyone should greet you, do not answer him. Go and place my staff on the boy’s face.” ^30 At this the boy’s mother said: “As surely as Jehovah is living and as you yourself are[*] living, I will not leave you.” So he got up and went with her. ^31 Ge·haʹzi went before them and put the staff on the boy’s face, but there was no sound or response. He went back to meet E·liʹsha and told him: “The boy did not wake up.”

^32 When E·liʹsha came into the house, the boy was lying dead on his bed. ^33 He went in and closed the door behind them both and began to pray to Jehovah. ^34 Then he got up on the bed and lay down on the child and put his own mouth on the boy’s mouth, his own eyes on his eyes, and his own palms on his palms and kept bent over him, and the child’s body started to grow warm. ^35 He walked back and forth in the house, and he got up on the bed and bent over him again. The boy sneezed seven times, after which he opened his eyes. ^36 E·liʹsha now called Ge·haʹzi and said: “Call the Shuʹnam·mite woman.” So he called her and she came in to him. Then he said: “Pick up your son.” ^37 And she came in and fell at his feet and bowed down to the ground before him, after which she picked up her son and went out.

^38 When E·liʹsha returned to Gilʹgal, there was famine in the land. The sons of the prophets were sitting before him, and he said to his attendant: “Put the large pot on and boil stew for the sons of the prophets.” ^39 So one of them went out to the field to pick mallows, and he found a wild vine and picked wild gourds from it, filling his garment. He then returned and sliced them into the stewpot, not knowing what they were. ^40 They later served it to the men to eat, but as soon as they ate from the stew, they cried out: “There is death in the pot, O man of the true God.” And they could not eat it. ^41 So he said: “Bring some flour.” After he threw it into the pot, he said: “Serve it to the people.” And nothing harmful was in the pot.

^42 A man came from Baʹal-shalʹi·shah, and he brought the man of the true God 20 loaves of barley bread made from the first ripe fruits, as well as a bag of new grain. Then E·liʹsha said: “Give it to the people so that they may eat.” ^43 However, his attendant said: “How can I set this before 100 men?” To this he said: “Give it to the people so that they may eat, for this is what Jehovah says, ‘They will eat and have some left over.’” ^44 At that he put it before them, and they ate and they had some left over, according to the word of Jehovah.

^ 2 Ki. 4:2 Or “spouted jar.”

^ 2 Ki. 4:27 Or “for her soul is bitter within her.”

^ 2 Ki. 4:30 Or “your soul is.”

2 Kings  5 : 1 - 27

5 Now Naʹa·man the army chief of the king of Syria was a prominent man who was held in esteem by his lord, because through him Jehovah had given victory[*] to Syria. He was a mighty warrior, although he was a leper.[*] ^2 On one of their raids, the Syrians had taken captive from the land of Israel a little girl who became a servant to Naʹa·man’s wife. ^3 She said to her mistress: “If only my lord would visit the prophet in Sa·marʹi·a! Then he would cure him of his leprosy.” ^4 So he[*] went and reported to his lord, telling him what the girl from Israel had said.

^5 Then the king of Syria said: “Go now! And I will send a letter to the king of Israel.” So he went, taking with him ten talents[*] of silver, 6,000 pieces of gold, and ten changes of garments. ^6 He brought to the king of Israel the letter, which read: “Along with this letter that has come to you, I send my servant Naʹa·man so that you may cure him of his leprosy.” ^7 As soon as the king of Israel read the letter, he ripped his garments apart and said: “Am I God, to put to death and to keep alive? For he is sending this man to me, telling me to cure him of his leprosy! You can see for yourselves that he is seeking a quarrel with me.”

^8 But when E·liʹsha the man of the true God heard that the king of Israel had ripped his garments apart, he at once sent word to the king: “Why did you rip your garments apart? Please let him come to me so that he may know that there is a prophet in Israel.” ^9 So Naʹa·man came with his horses and his war chariots and stood at the entrance of the house of E·liʹsha. ^10 However, E·liʹsha sent a messenger to tell him: “Go, wash seven times in the Jordan, and your flesh will be restored, and you will be clean.” ^11 At this Naʹa·man became indignant and started to leave, saying: “Here I said to myself, ‘He will come out to me and stand here and call on the name of Jehovah his God, moving his hand back and forth over the leprosy to cure it.’ ^12 Are not the A·baʹnah and the Pharʹpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? Can I not wash in them and become clean?” With that he turned and went away in a rage.

^13 His servants now approached him and said: “My father, if the prophet had told you to do something extraordinary, would you not do it? How much more, then, since he only said to you, ‘Wash and be clean’?” ^14 At that he went down and plunged into[*] the Jordan seven times, according to the word of the man of the true God. Then his flesh was restored like the flesh of a little boy, and he became clean.

^15 After that he went back to the man of the true God, he and all his entourage,[*] and he stood before him and said: “Now I know that there is no God anywhere in all the earth but in Israel. Now accept, please, a gift[*] from your servant.” ^16 However, E·liʹsha said: “As surely as Jehovah whom I serve[*] is living, I will not accept it.” He urged him to accept it, but he kept refusing. ^17 Finally Naʹa·man said: “If not, please, let your servant be given two mule-loads of soil from this land, for your servant will no longer offer a burnt offering or a sacrifice to any gods other than Jehovah. ^18 But may Jehovah forgive your servant for this one thing: When my lord goes into the house[*] of Rimʹmon to bow down there, he supports himself on my arm, so I have to bow down at the house of Rimʹmon. When I bow down at the house of Rimʹmon, may Jehovah, please, forgive your servant for this.” ^19 At this he said to him: “Go in peace.” After he departed from him and had traveled for some distance, ^20 Ge·haʹzi the attendant of E·liʹsha the man of the true God said to himself: ‘Here my master has spared this Syrian Naʹa·man by not accepting from him what he brought. As surely as Jehovah is living, I will run after him and take something from him.’ ^21 So Ge·haʹzi chased after Naʹa·man. When Naʹa·man saw someone running after him, he got down from his chariot to meet him and said: “Is everything all right?” ^22 To this he said: “All is well. My master has sent me, saying, ‘Look! Just now two young men from the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im from the sons of the prophets came to me. Give them, please, a talent of silver and two changes of garments.’” ^23 Naʹa·man said: “Go on, take two talents.” He kept urging him, and he wrapped up two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of garments, and gave them to two of his attendants, who carried them before him.

^24 When he reached Oʹphel,[*] he took them from their hand and put them in the house and sent the men away. After they left, ^25 he went in and stood by his master. E·liʹsha now said to him: “Where did you come from, Ge·haʹzi?” But he said: “Your servant did not go anywhere.” ^26 E·liʹsha said to him: “Was my heart not there with you when the man got down from his chariot to meet you? Is it a time to accept silver or to accept garments or olive groves or vineyards or sheep or cattle or male or female servants? ^27 Now Naʹa·man’s leprosy will stick to you and your descendants forever.” Immediately he went out from before him a leper, white as snow.

^ 2 Ki. 5:1 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:1 Or “struck with a skin disease.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:4 Possibly referring to Naaman.

^ 2 Ki. 5:5 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 5:14 Or “immersed himself in.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:15 Lit., “camp.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:15 Lit., “blessing.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:16 Lit., “before whom I stand.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:18 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Ki. 5:24 A location in Samaria, possibly a hill or a fortification.

2 Kings  6 : 1 - 33

6 The sons of the prophets said to E·liʹsha: “Look! The place where we are staying with you is too cramped for us. ^2 Please let us go to the Jordan. Let each of us take a log from there and make a place there where we can dwell.” He said: “Go.” ^3 One of them said: “Will you please come along with your servants?” At that he said: “I will come.” ^4 So he went with them, and they came to the Jordan and began to cut down the trees. ^5 As one of them was cutting down a tree, the axhead fell into the water, and he cried out: “Alas, my master, it was borrowed!” ^6 The man of the true God said: “Where did it fall?” So he showed him the place. He then cut off a piece of wood and threw it there and made the axhead float. ^7 He said: “Lift it out.” So he reached out his hand and took it.

^8 Now the king of Syria went to war against Israel. He consulted with his servants and said: “I will encamp at such and such a place with you.” ^9 Then the man of the true God sent word to the king of Israel, saying: “Beware of passing by this place, because that is where the Syrians are coming down.” ^10 So the king of Israel sent word to the place that the man of the true God had warned him about. He kept warning him, and he stayed away from there on several occasions.[*]

^11 This enraged the king[*] of Syria, so he summoned his servants and said to them: “Tell me! Who among us is on the side of the king of Israel?” ^12 Then one of his servants said: “None of us, my lord the king! It is E·liʹsha the prophet in Israel who tells the king of Israel the things that you say in your own bedroom.” ^13 He said: “Go and find out where he is, so that I may send men to capture him.” Later the report was made to him: “He is in Doʹthan.” ^14 He immediately sent horses and war chariots there, as well as a large army; they came by night and surrounded the city.

^15 When the attendant[*] of the man of the true God rose early and went outside, he saw that an army with horses and war chariots was surrounding the city. At once the attendant said to him: “Alas, my master! What are we to do?” ^16 But he said: “Do not be afraid! For there are more who are with us than those who are with them.” ^17 Then E·liʹsha began to pray and say: “O Jehovah, open his eyes, please, that he may see.” Immediately Jehovah opened the attendant’s eyes and he saw, and look! the mountainous region was full of horses and war chariots of fire all around E·liʹsha.

^18 When the Syrians came down to him, E·liʹsha prayed to Jehovah and said: “Please, strike this nation with blindness.” So he struck them with blindness, just as E·liʹsha had requested. ^19 E·liʹsha now said to them: “This is not the way, and this is not the city. Follow me, and let me lead you to the man you are looking for.” However, he led them to Sa·marʹi·a.

^20 When they arrived in Sa·marʹi·a, E·liʹsha said: “O Jehovah, open their eyes so that they may see.” So Jehovah opened their eyes, and they saw that they were in the middle of Sa·marʹi·a. ^21 When the king of Israel saw them, he said to E·liʹsha: “Should I strike them down, should I strike them down, my father?” ^22 But he said: “You must not strike them down. Do you strike down those whom you have taken captive with your sword and with your bow? Give them bread and water so they may eat and drink and return to their lord.” ^23 So he spread a great feast for them, and they ate and drank, after which he sent them away to return to their lord. And not once did the marauder bands of the Syrians come again into the land of Israel.

^24 Afterward Ben-haʹdad the king of Syria gathered all his army[*] together and went up and besieged Sa·marʹi·a. ^25 So there was a great famine in Sa·marʹi·a, and they besieged it until a donkey’s head was worth 80 silver pieces, and a fourth of a cab measure[*] of dove’s droppings was worth 5 silver pieces. ^26 As the king of Israel was passing by on the wall, a woman cried out to him: “Help us, O my lord the king!” ^27 To this he said: “If Jehovah does not help you, where can I get help for you? From the threshing floor? Or from the wine or oil press?” ^28 The king asked her: “What is the matter with you?” She replied: “This woman said to me, ‘Hand over your son, and we will eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.’ ^29 So we boiled my son and ate him. The next day I said to her, ‘Hand over your son so that we may eat him.’ But she hid her son.”

^30 As soon as the king heard the woman’s words, he ripped his garments apart. When he passed by on the wall, the people saw that he was wearing sackcloth under his clothes.[*] ^31 Then he said: “So may God do to me and add to it if the head of E·liʹsha the son of Shaʹphat remains on him today!”

^32 E·liʹsha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him. The king sent a man ahead of him, but before the messenger arrived, E·liʹsha said to the elders: “Have you seen how this son of a murderer has sent to take off my head? Watch when the messenger comes, close the door, and hold the door shut against him. Is not the sound of his lord’s footsteps behind him?” ^33 While he was still speaking with them, the messenger came to him, and the king said: “This calamity is from Jehovah. Why should I wait any longer for Jehovah?”

^ 2 Ki. 6:10 Or “more than once or twice.”

^ 2 Ki. 6:11 Lit., “the heart of the king.”

^ 2 Ki. 6:15 Or “minister.”

^ 2 Ki. 6:24 Lit., “camp.”

^ 2 Ki. 6:25 A cab equaled 1.22 L (1.11 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 6:30 Or “underneath, next to his skin.”

2 Kings  7 : 1 - 20

7 E·liʹsha now said, “Listen to the word of Jehovah. This is what Jehovah says: ‘Tomorrow about this time at the gate[*] of Sa·marʹi·a, a seah measure[*] of fine flour will be worth a shekel,[*] and two seah measures of barley will be worth a shekel.’” ^2 At that the adjutant whom the king relied on said to the man of the true God: “Even if Jehovah should open floodgates in the heavens, could this[*] possibly take place?” To that he said: “You will see it with your own eyes, but you will not eat from it.”

^3 There were four lepers at the entrance of the city gate, and they said to one another: “Why are we sitting here until we die? ^4 If we say, ‘Let us go into the city,’ while the famine is in the city, we would die there. And if we sit here, we will die anyway. So now let us go over to the camp of the Syrians. If they spare our lives, we will live, but if they put us to death, then we will die.” ^5 They then got up in the evening darkness and entered the camp of the Syrians. When they reached the outskirts of the Syrian camp, there was nobody there.

^6 For Jehovah had caused the Syrian camp to hear the sound of war chariots and horses, the sound of a huge army. So they said to one another: “Look! The king of Israel has hired the kings of the Hitʹtites and the kings of Egypt to come against us!” ^7 They immediately got up and fled in the evening darkness, leaving their tents, horses, donkeys, and the whole camp just as it was, and they fled for their lives.[*]

^8 When these lepers reached the outskirts of the camp, they entered into one of the tents and began to eat and drink. They carried away from there silver, gold, and garments and went and hid them. Then they returned and entered another tent and carried things away from there and went and hid them.

^9 Finally they said to one another: “What we are doing is not right. This day is a day of good news! If we hesitate and wait until dawn, we will deserve to be punished. Let us now go and report this at the king’s house.” ^10 So they went and called out to the gatekeepers of the city and reported to them: “We went into the camp of the Syrians, but nobody was there—we did not hear anyone at all. There were only the horses and donkeys tied and the tents left just as they were.” ^11 At once the gatekeepers called out, and it was reported inside the king’s house.

^12 Immediately the king got up by night and said to his servants: “Please let me tell you what the Syrians have done to us. They know that we are hungry, so they left the camp to hide in the field, saying, ‘They will come out of the city, and we will catch them alive and enter into the city.’” ^13 Then one of his servants said: “Please, let some men take five of the remaining horses that are in the city. Look! They will end up the same as all the crowd of Israel that remain here. Look! They will end up the same as all the crowd of Israel that perished. Let us then send them out and see.” ^14 So they took two chariots with horses, and the king sent them out to the camp of the Syrians, saying: “Go and see.” ^15 They followed them as far as the Jordan, and the entire way was covered with garments and utensils that the Syrians had thrown away as they fled in panic. The messengers returned and reported it to the king.

^16 The people then went out and plundered the camp of the Syrians, so that a seah measure of fine flour came to be worth a shekel, and two seah measures of barley came to be worth a shekel, according to the word of Jehovah. ^17 The king had appointed the adjutant whom he relied on to be in charge of the gate, but the people trampled him to death at the gate, just as the man of the true God had told the king when he came down to him. ^18 It happened just as the man of the true God had said to the king: “Two seah measures of barley will be worth a shekel, and a seah measure of fine flour will be worth a shekel tomorrow at this time at the gate of Sa·marʹi·a.” ^19 But the adjutant had said to the man of the true God: “Even if Jehovah should open floodgates in the heavens, could such a thing[*] take place?” To this E·liʹsha had said: “You will see it with your own eyes, but you will not eat from it.” ^20 That is exactly what happened to him, because the people trampled him to death at the gate.

^ 2 Ki. 7:1 Or “markets.”

^ 2 Ki. 7:1 A seah equaled 7.33 L (6.66 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 7:1 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 7:2 Lit., “this word.”

^ 2 Ki. 7:7 Or “souls.”

^ 2 Ki. 7:19 Lit., “such a word as this.”

2 Kings  8 : 1 - 29

8 E·liʹsha said to the woman whose son he had restored to life:[*] “Rise up and go, you with your household, and live as a foreigner wherever you can, for Jehovah has declared a famine, and it will come on the land for seven years.” ^2 So the woman got up and did what the man of the true God said. She went with her household and settled in the land of the Phi·lisʹtines for seven years.

^3 At the end of seven years, the woman returned from the land of the Phi·lisʹtines and went to appeal to the king for her house and her field. ^4 Now the king was speaking to Ge·haʹzi the attendant of the man of the true God, saying: “Relate to me, please, all the great things that E·liʹsha has done.” ^5 Just as he was relating to the king how he had restored the dead one to life, the woman whose son he had restored to life came to the king, appealing for her house and her field. At once Ge·haʹzi said: “My lord the king, this is the woman, and this is her son, whom E·liʹsha restored to life.” ^6 At that the king asked the woman, and she related the story to him. Then the king assigned her a court official, telling him: “Return all that belongs to her and all the products of the field from the day she left the land until now.”

^7 E·liʹsha came to Damascus when Ben-haʹdad the king of Syria was sick. So the report was made to him: “The man of the true God has come here.” ^8 At that the king said to Hazʹa·el: “Take a gift with you and go and meet the man of the true God. Inquire of Jehovah through him, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” ^9 Hazʹa·el went to meet him and took a gift with him, every sort of good thing of Damascus, the load of 40 camels. He came and stood before him and said: “Your son, Ben-haʹdad the king of Syria, has sent me to you, asking, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’” ^10 E·liʹsha replied to him: “Go and tell him, ‘You will certainly recover,’ but Jehovah has shown me that he will certainly die.” ^11 And he kept staring at him to the point of embarrassment. Then the man of the true God gave way to weeping. ^12 Hazʹa·el asked: “Why is my lord weeping?” He replied: “Because I know what harm you will do to the people of Israel. Their fortified places you will set on fire, their choice men you will kill with the sword, their children you will dash to pieces, and their pregnant women you will rip open.” ^13 Hazʹa·el said: “How could your servant, who is a mere dog, do such a deed?” But E·liʹsha said: “Jehovah has shown me that you will be king over Syria.”

^14 Then he left E·liʹsha and returned to his own lord, who said to him: “What did E·liʹsha say to you?” He replied: “He told me that you will certainly recover.” ^15 But the next day, Hazʹa·el took a coverlet, dipped it in water, and held[*] it over his face until he died. And Hazʹa·el became king in his place.

^16 In the fifth year of Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab the king of Israel, while Je·hoshʹa·phat was king of Judah, Je·hoʹram the son of King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah became king. ^17 He was 32 years old when he became king, and he reigned for eight years in Jerusalem. ^18 He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, just as those of the house of Aʹhab had done, for Aʹhab’s daughter had become his wife; and he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. ^19 But Jehovah did not want to bring Judah to ruin for the sake of David his servant, since he had promised him to give a lamp to him and to his sons always.

^20 In his days Eʹdom revolted against Judah and then set up its own king. ^21 So Je·hoʹram crossed over to Zaʹir with all his chariots, and he rose up by night and defeated the Eʹdom·ites who were surrounding him and the chariot commanders; and the troops fled to their tents. ^22 But Eʹdom has kept up its revolt against Judah to this day. Libʹnah also revolted at that time.

^23 And the rest of the history of Je·hoʹram, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^24 Then Je·hoʹram was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David. And his son A·ha·ziʹah became king in his place.

^25 In the 12th year of Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab the king of Israel, A·ha·ziʹah the son of King Je·hoʹram of Judah became king. ^26 A·ha·ziʹah was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ath·a·liʹah the granddaughter[*] of King Omʹri of Israel. ^27 He walked in the way of the house of Aʹhab and kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of Aʹhab, for he was related to the house of Aʹhab by marriage. ^28 So he went with Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab to wage war against King Hazʹa·el of Syria at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, but the Syrians wounded Je·hoʹram. ^29 So King Je·hoʹram returned to Jezʹre·el to recover from the wounds that the Syrians had inflicted on him at Raʹmah when he fought against King Hazʹa·el of Syria. A·ha·ziʹah the son of Je·hoʹram the king of Judah went down to Jezʹre·el to see Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab, because he had been wounded.[*]

^ 2 Ki. 8:1 Or “had revived.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:15 Or “placed.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:26 Lit., “daughter.”

^ 2 Ki. 8:29 Or “he was sick.”

2 Kings  9 : 1 - 37

9 E·liʹsha the prophet then called one of the sons of the prophets and said to him: “Wrap your garments around your waist, and quickly take this flask of oil with you and go to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad. ^2 When you arrive there, look for Jeʹhu the son of Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of Nimʹshi; go in and have him get up from among his brothers and take him into the innermost room. ^3 Then take the flask of oil and pour it out on his head and say, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I anoint you as king over Israel.”’ Then open the door and flee without delay.”

^4 So the prophet’s attendant got on his way to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad. ^5 When he arrived, the army chiefs were seated there. He said: “I have a message for you, O chief.” Jeʹhu asked: “For which one of us?” He said: “For you, O chief.” ^6 So Jeʹhu got up and went into the house; the attendant poured the oil out on his head and said to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘I anoint you as king over Jehovah’s people, over Israel. ^7 You must strike down the house of Aʹhab your lord, and I will avenge the blood of my servants the prophets and of all the servants of Jehovah who died at the hands of Jezʹe·bel. ^8 And the whole house of Aʹhab will perish; and I will annihilate from Aʹhab every male,[*] including the helpless and weak in Israel. ^9 And I will make the house of Aʹhab like the house of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat and like the house of Baʹa·sha the son of A·hiʹjah. ^10 As for Jezʹe·bel, the dogs will eat her up in the plot of land at Jezʹre·el, and no one will bury her.’” With that he opened the door and fled.

^11 When Jeʹhu went back to the servants of his lord, they asked him: “Is everything all right? Why did this crazy man come to you?” He answered them: “You know that sort of man and his sort of talk.” ^12 But they said: “That is not true! Tell us, please.” Then he said: “This is what he said to me, and then he added, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I anoint you as king over Israel.”’” ^13 At this each of them quickly took his garment and put it under him on the bare steps, and they blew the horn and said: “Jeʹhu has become king!” ^14 Then Jeʹhu the son of Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of Nimʹshi conspired against Je·hoʹram.

Je·hoʹram had been on guard at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, he with all Israel, because of King Hazʹa·el of Syria. ^15 King Je·hoʹram later returned to Jezʹre·el to recover from the wounds that the Syrians inflicted on him when he fought King Hazʹa·el of Syria.

Jeʹhu now said: “If you agree,[*] do not let anyone escape from the city to go and report this in Jezʹre·el.” ^16 Then Jeʹhu mounted his chariot and went to Jezʹre·el, for Je·hoʹram was lying there wounded, and King A·ha·ziʹah of Judah had gone down to see Je·hoʹram. ^17 As the watchman was standing on the tower in Jezʹre·el, he saw the throng of Jeʹhu’s men approaching. At once he said: “I see a throng of men.” Je·hoʹram said: “Take a cavalryman and send him to meet them, and let him say, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” ^18 So a horseman went to meet him and said: “This is what the king says, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” But Jeʹhu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Fall in behind me!”

The watchman then reported: “The messenger reached them, but he has not returned.” ^19 So he sent out a second horseman, who said when he came to them: “This is what the king says, ‘Are you coming in peace?’” But Jeʹhu said: “What do you have to do with ‘peace’? Fall in behind me!”

^20 The watchman then reported: “He reached them, but he has not returned, and the driving is like the driving of Jeʹhu the grandson[*] of Nimʹshi, for he drives like a madman.” ^21 Je·hoʹram said: “Hitch up!” So his war chariot was hitched up and King Je·hoʹram of Israel and King A·ha·ziʹah of Judah each went out in his own war chariot to meet Jeʹhu. They encountered him in the plot of land of Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite.

^22 As soon as Je·hoʹram saw Jeʹhu, he said: “Are you coming in peace, Jeʹhu?” But he said: “What peace could there be as long as there is the prostitution of Jezʹe·bel your mother and her many sorceries?” ^23 At once Je·hoʹram turned his chariot to flee, and he said to A·ha·ziʹah: “We have been tricked, A·ha·ziʹah!” ^24 Jeʹhu took his bow in hand and shot Je·hoʹram between the shoulders, and the arrow came out at his heart, and he collapsed in his war chariot. ^25 He then said to Bidʹkar his adjutant: “Pick him up and throw him into the field of Naʹboth the Jezʹre·el·ite. Remember, you and I were riding together[*] behind Aʹhab his father when Jehovah himself made this pronouncement against him: ^26 ‘“As surely as I saw the blood of Naʹboth and the blood of his sons yesterday,” declares Jehovah, “I will repay you in this very plot of land,” declares Jehovah.’ So now pick him up and throw him into the plot of land, according to the word of Jehovah.”

^27 When King A·ha·ziʹah of Judah saw what was happening, he fled by way of the garden house. (Later Jeʹhu pursued him and said: “Strike him down also!” So they struck him down in the chariot on his way up to Gur, which is by Ibʹle·am. But he continued his flight to Me·gidʹdo and died there. ^28 Then his servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and they buried him in his grave with his forefathers in the City of David. ^29 It was in the 11th year of Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab that A·ha·ziʹah had become king over Judah.)

^30 When Jeʹhu came to Jezʹre·el, Jezʹe·bel heard of it. So she painted her eyes with black paint[*] and adorned her head and looked down through the window. ^31 As Jeʹhu came in through the gate, she said: “Did it go well with Zimʹri, the killer of his lord?” ^32 Looking up to the window, he said: “Who is on my side? Who?” Immediately two or three court officials looked down at him. ^33 He said: “Throw her down!” So they threw her down, and some of her blood splattered on the wall and on the horses, and he trampled her. ^34 After that he went in and ate and drank. He then said: “Please, take care of this accursed woman and bury her. After all, she is the daughter of a king.” ^35 But when they went to bury her, they did not find anything but her skull and her feet and the palms of her hands. ^36 When they returned and told him, he said: “This fulfills the word of Jehovah that he spoke through his servant E·liʹjah the Tishʹbite, saying, ‘In the plot of land of Jezʹre·el, the dogs will eat the flesh of Jezʹe·bel. ^37 And the dead body of Jezʹe·bel will become as manure on the surface of the field in the plot of land of Jezʹre·el, so that they may not say: “This is Jezʹe·bel.”’”

^ 2 Ki. 9:8 Lit., “anyone urinating against a wall.” A Hebrew expression of contempt referring to males.

^ 2 Ki. 9:15 Or “your soul agrees.”

^ 2 Ki. 9:20 Lit., “son.”

^ 2 Ki. 9:25 Lit., “riding teams.”

^ 2 Ki. 9:30 Or “eye shadow.”

2 Kings  10 : 1 - 36

10 Now Aʹhab had 70 sons in Sa·marʹi·a. So Jeʹhu wrote letters and sent them to Sa·marʹi·a, to the princes of Jezʹre·el, the elders, and the guardians of Aʹhab’s children,[*] saying: ^2 “Now when this letter comes to you, the sons of your lord will be with you, as well as the war chariots, the horses, a fortified city, and weapons. ^3 Select the best and most suitable[*] of the sons of your lord and put him on the throne of his father. Then fight for the house of your lord.”

^4 But they were overcome with fear and said: “Look! If two kings could not stand before him, how can we stand?” ^5 So the overseer of the palace,[*] the governor of the city, the elders, and the guardians sent this message to Jeʹhu: “We are your servants, and we will do everything that you tell us. We will not make anyone king. Do whatever seems good in your eyes.”

^6 Then he wrote them a second letter, saying: “If you belong to me and are willing to obey me, bring the heads of the sons of your lord and come to me tomorrow at this time at Jezʹre·el.”

Now the 70 sons of the king were with the distinguished men of the city who were raising them. ^7 As soon as the letter came to them, they took the sons of the king and slaughtered them, 70 men, and they put their heads in baskets and sent them to him at Jezʹre·el. ^8 The messenger came in and told him: “They have brought the heads of the sons of the king.” So he said: “Put them in two heaps at the entrance of the city gate until morning.” ^9 When he went out in the morning, he stood before all the people and said: “You are innocent.[*] Yes, I conspired against my lord, and I killed him, but who struck down all of these? ^10 Know, then, that not a single word of Jehovah’s that Jehovah has spoken against the house of Aʹhab will go unfulfilled,[*] and Jehovah has done what he spoke through his servant E·liʹjah.” ^11 Moreover, Jeʹhu struck down all who were left of the house of Aʹhab in Jezʹre·el, as well as all his distinguished men, his acquaintances, and his priests, until he had left him no survivor.

^12 Then he got up and went on his way to Sa·marʹi·a. The binding house[*] of the shepherds was on the way. ^13 There Jeʹhu encountered the brothers of King A·ha·ziʹah of Judah, and he said to them, “Who are you?” They said: “We are the brothers of A·ha·ziʹah, and we are on our way down to ask if all is well with the sons of the king and the sons of the queen mother.”[*] ^14 Immediately he said: “Capture them alive!” So they captured them alive and slaughtered them at the cistern of the binding house, 42 men. He did not let a single one of them survive.

^15 As he went from there, he encountered Je·honʹa·dab the son of Reʹchab, who was coming to meet him. When he greeted[*] him, he said to him: “Is your heart fully[*] with me, just as my heart is with your heart?”

Je·honʹa·dab replied: “It is.”

“If so, give me your hand.”

So he gave him his hand, and Jeʹhu pulled him up into the chariot with him. ^16 Then he said: “Come along with me, and see my toleration of no rivalry toward[*] Jehovah.” So they had him ride with him in his war chariot. ^17 Then he came to Sa·marʹi·a, and he struck down all who were left over of Aʹhab’s house in Sa·marʹi·a until he had annihilated them, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken to E·liʹjah.

^18 Further, Jeʹhu collected all the people together and said to them: “Aʹhab worshipped Baʹal a little, but Jeʹhu will worship him much more. ^19 So summon all the prophets of Baʹal, all his worshippers, and all his priests to me. Do not let a single one be absent, because I have a great sacrifice for Baʹal. Anyone who is absent will not live.” But Jeʹhu was acting with cunning to destroy the worshippers of Baʹal.

^20 Jeʹhu continued: “Declare[*] a solemn assembly for Baʹal.” So they proclaimed it. ^21 After that Jeʹhu sent word throughout Israel, and all the worshippers of Baʹal came. Not a single one was left out who did not come. They entered the house[*] of Baʹal, and the house of Baʹal was filled from end to end. ^22 He said to the one who was in charge of the wardrobe: “Bring out garments for all the worshippers of Baʹal.” So he brought out the clothing for them. ^23 Then Jeʹhu and Je·honʹa·dab the son of Reʹchab went into the house of Baʹal. He now said to the worshippers of Baʹal: “Search carefully and see that there are no worshippers of Jehovah here, only worshippers of Baʹal.” ^24 Finally they came in to offer up sacrifices and burnt offerings. Jeʹhu had stationed 80 of his men outside and said: “If any one of the men I am putting into your hands escapes, it will be your life for his.”[*]

^25 As soon as he finished offering up the burnt offering, Jeʹhu said to the guards[*] and the adjutants: “Come in and strike them down! Do not let a single one escape!” So the guards and the adjutants struck them down with the sword and threw them out, and they kept going as far as the inner sanctuary[*] of the house of Baʹal. ^26 Then they brought out the sacred pillars of the house of Baʹal and burned each one. ^27 They tore down the sacred pillar of Baʹal, and they tore down the house of Baʹal and turned it into latrines, as it remains to this day.

^28 Thus Jeʹhu annihilated Baʹal out of Israel. ^29 However, Jeʹhu did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit as regards the golden calves that were in Bethʹel and in Dan. ^30 So Jehovah said to Jeʹhu: “Because you have acted well and have done what is right in my eyes by carrying out all that was in my heart to do to the house of Aʹhab, four generations of your sons will sit on the throne of Israel.” ^31 But Jeʹhu did not take care to walk in the Law of Jehovah the God of Israel with all his heart. He did not turn away from the sins that Jer·o·boʹam had caused Israel to commit.

^32 In those days Jehovah started to cut off[*] Israel piece by piece. Hazʹa·el kept attacking them throughout the territory of Israel, ^33 from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gilʹe·ad—of the Gadʹites, the Reuʹben·ites, and the Ma·nasʹsites—from A·roʹer, which is by the Arʹnon Valley,[*] to Gilʹe·ad and Baʹshan.

^34 And the rest of the history of Jeʹhu, all that he did and all his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^35 Then Jeʹhu was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·marʹi·a; and his son Je·hoʹa·haz became king in his place. ^36 The length[*] of Jeʹhu’s reign over Israel was 28 years in Sa·marʹi·a.

^ 2 Ki. 10:1 Lit., “the guardians of Ahab.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:3 Or “upright.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:5 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:9 Or “righteous.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:10 Lit., “will fall to the earth.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:12 Apparently a place where sheep were bound in order to be sheared.

^ 2 Ki. 10:13 Or “the lady.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:15 Or “blessed.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:15 Lit., “upright.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:16 Or “my zeal for.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:20 Lit., “Sanctify.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:21 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:24 Or “it will be your soul for his soul.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:25 Lit., “runners.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:25 Lit., “the city,” perhaps a fortresslike structure.

^ 2 Ki. 10:32 Or “reduce.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:33 Or “Wadi Arnon.”

^ 2 Ki. 10:36 Lit., “The days.”

2 Kings  11 : 1 - 21

11 Now when Ath·a·liʹah, A·ha·ziʹah’s mother, saw that her son had died, she rose up and destroyed the entire royal line.[*] ^2 However, Je·hoshʹe·ba the daughter of King Je·hoʹram, A·ha·ziʹah’s sister, took Je·hoʹash the son of A·ha·ziʹah and stole him away from among the sons of the king who were to be put to death, keeping him and his nurse in an inner bedroom. They managed to keep him concealed from Ath·a·liʹah, so he was not put to death. ^3 He remained with her for six years, hidden at the house of Jehovah, while Ath·a·liʹah was ruling over the land.

^4 In the seventh year, Je·hoiʹa·da sent for the chiefs of hundreds of the Caʹri·an bodyguard and of the palace guards[*] and had them come to him at the house of Jehovah. He made a pact[*] with them and had them swear to it at the house of Jehovah, and then he showed them the son of the king. ^5 He ordered them: “This is what you are to do: One third of you will be on duty on the Sabbath and will keep strict watch over the king’s house,[*] ^6 another third will be at the Gate of the Foundation, and another third will be at the gate behind the palace guards. You will take turns watching over the house. ^7 Your two divisions that are supposed to be off duty on the Sabbath must keep strict watch over the house of Jehovah to protect the king. ^8 You must surround the king on every side, each with his weapons in hand. Anyone entering within the ranks will be put to death. Stay with the king wherever he goes.”[*]

^9 The chiefs of hundreds did exactly what Je·hoiʹa·da the priest had commanded. So each one took his men who were on duty on the Sabbath, together with those who were off duty on the Sabbath, and they came in to Je·hoiʹa·da the priest. ^10 The priest then gave the chiefs of hundreds the spears and the circular shields that had belonged to King David, which were in the house of Jehovah. ^11 And the palace guards took their positions, each with his weapons in hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, by the altar and by the house, all around the king. ^12 Then Je·hoiʹa·da brought the king’s son out and put on him the crown[*] and the Testimony,[*] and they made him king and anointed him. They began to clap their hands and say: “Long live the king!”

^13 When Ath·a·liʹah heard the sound of the people running, she immediately came to the people at the house of Jehovah. ^14 Then she saw the king standing there by the pillar according to the custom. The chiefs and the trumpeters were with the king, and all the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing the trumpets. At this Ath·a·liʹah ripped her garments apart and cried out: “Conspiracy! Conspiracy!” ^15 But Je·hoiʹa·da the priest commanded the chiefs of hundreds, those appointed over the army, and said to them: “Take her out from among the ranks, and if anyone follows her, put him to death with the sword!” For the priest had said: “Do not put her to death in the house of Jehovah.” ^16 So they seized her, and when she reached the place where the horses enter the king’s house,[*] she was put to death there.

^17 Then Je·hoiʹa·da made a covenant between Jehovah and the king and the people, that they would continue as the people of Jehovah, and he also made a covenant between the king and the people. ^18 After that all the people of the land came to the house[*] of Baʹal and tore down his altars, completely smashed his images, and killed Matʹtan the priest of Baʹal in front of the altars.

Then the priest appointed overseers over the house of Jehovah. ^19 Further, he took the chiefs of hundreds, the Caʹri·an bodyguard, the palace guards, and all the people of the land to escort the king down from the house of Jehovah, and they came to the king’s house[*] by the way of the gate of the palace guard. He then sat on the throne of the kings. ^20 So all the people of the land rejoiced and the city was quiet, for they had put Ath·a·liʹah to death with the sword at the king’s house.

^21 Je·hoʹash was seven years old when he became king.

^ 2 Ki. 11:1 Lit., “all seed of the kingdom.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:4 Lit., “the runners.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:4 Or “covenant.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:5 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:8 Lit., “when he goes out and when he comes in.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:12 Or “diadem.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:12 Possibly a scroll containing the Law of God.

^ 2 Ki. 11:16 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:18 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Ki. 11:19 Or “palace.”

2 Kings  12 : 1 - 21

12 In the seventh year of Jeʹhu, Je·hoʹash became king, and he reigned for 40 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zibʹi·ah from Beʹer-sheʹba. ^2 Je·hoʹash continued doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes all the days that Je·hoiʹa·da the priest instructed him. ^3 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places.

^4 Je·hoʹash said to the priests: “Take all the money that is brought to the house of Jehovah for the holy offerings, the money for which each one is assessed, the money given as an estimated value for a person,[*] and all the money that each person’s heart is moved to bring to the house of Jehovah. ^5 The priests will personally take it from their donors[*] and use it to repair the house, wherever any damage is[*] found.”

^6 By the 23rd year of King Je·hoʹash, the priests had not yet repaired the damage to the house. ^7 So King Je·hoʹash called Je·hoiʹa·da the priest and the other priests and said to them: “Why are you not repairing the damage to the house? Therefore, do not take any more money from your donors unless it is used to repair the house.” ^8 At that the priests agreed not to take any more money from the people and not to be responsible for repairing the house.

^9 Je·hoiʹa·da the priest then took a chest and bored a hole in its lid and put it next to the altar on the right as one enters the house of Jehovah. That is where the priests who served as doorkeepers would put all the money that was brought into the house of Jehovah. ^10 Whenever they saw that there was a great deal of money in the chest, the secretary of the king and the high priest would come up and collect[*] and count the money that had been brought to the house of Jehovah. ^11 They would give the money that had been counted to those appointed over the work being done in the house of Jehovah. They, in turn, paid it to the woodworkers and to the builders who were working at the house of Jehovah, ^12 as well as to the masons and the stonecutters. They also bought timbers and hewn stones for repairing the damage to the house of Jehovah and used the money for all the other expenses incurred in repairing the house.

^13 However, none of the money brought to the house of Jehovah was used to make basins of silver, extinguishers, bowls, trumpets, or any sort of gold or silver article for the house of Jehovah. ^14 They would give it only to those who did the work, and with it they repaired the house of Jehovah. ^15 They would not call for an accounting from the men to whom they gave the money to give to the workers, for they were trustworthy. ^16 However, the money for guilt offerings and the money for sin offerings was not brought to the house of Jehovah; it belonged to the priests.

^17 It was then that Hazʹa·el the king of Syria went up to fight against Gath, and he captured it, after which he decided to attack[*] Jerusalem. ^18 At that King Je·hoʹash of Judah took all the holy offerings that his forefathers Je·hoshʹa·phat, Je·hoʹram, and A·ha·ziʹah, the kings of Judah, had sanctified, as well as his own holy offerings and all the gold to be found in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah and the king’s house,[*] and sent them to Hazʹa·el the king of Syria. So he withdrew from Jerusalem.

^19 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoʹash, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^20 However, his servants joined in a conspiracy against him and struck Je·hoʹash down at the house of the Mound,[*] on the way that goes down to Silʹla. ^21 His servants Joʹza·car the son of Shimʹe·ath and Je·hozʹa·bad the son of Shoʹmer were the ones who struck him and put him to death. They buried him with his forefathers in the City of David, and his son Am·a·ziʹah became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 12:4 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:5 Or “acquaintances.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:5 Or “cracks are.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:10 Or “put into bags.” Lit., “bind.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:17 Lit., “Hazael set his face to go up against.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:18 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 12:20 Or “at Beth-millo.”

2 Kings  13 : 1 - 25

13 In the 23rd year of Je·hoʹash the son of A·ha·ziʹah the king of Judah, Je·hoʹa·haz the son of Jeʹhu became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for 17 years. ^2 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and he persisted in the sin that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. He did not turn away from it. ^3 So Jehovah’s anger grew hot against Israel, and he gave them into the hand of King Hazʹa·el of Syria and into the hand of Ben-haʹdad the son of Hazʹa·el all their days.

^4 In time Je·hoʹa·haz begged for the favor[*] of Jehovah, and Jehovah listened to him, for he had seen the oppression the king of Syria had inflicted on Israel. ^5 So Jehovah provided Israel with a savior to free them from Syria’s grip, and the Israelites were able to dwell in their homes as before.[*] ^6 (However, they did not depart from the sin of the house of Jer·o·boʹam that he had caused Israel to commit. They continued in this sin,[*] and the sacred pole[*] continued to stand in Sa·marʹi·a.) ^7 Je·hoʹa·haz was left with an army of only 50 horsemen, 10 chariots, and 10,000 foot soldiers, because the king of Syria had destroyed them, trampling them like the dust at threshing time.

^8 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoʹa·haz, all that he did and his mightiness, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^9 Then Je·hoʹa·haz was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in Sa·marʹi·a; and his son Je·hoʹash became king in his place.

^10 In the 37th year of King Je·hoʹash of Judah, Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for 16 years. ^11 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, not departing from all the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had made Israel commit. He continued[*] in these sins.

^12 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoʹash, all that he did and his mightiness and how he fought against King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^13 Then Je·hoʹash was laid to rest with his forefathers, and Jer·o·boʹam[*] sat on his throne. And Je·hoʹash was buried in Sa·marʹi·a with the kings of Israel.

^14 Now when E·liʹsha became ill with the sickness from which he eventually died, Je·hoʹash the king of Israel came down to him and wept over him, saying: “My father, my father! The chariot of Israel and his horsemen!” ^15 E·liʹsha then said to him: “Take a bow and arrows.” So he took a bow and arrows. ^16 Then he said to the king of Israel: “Put your hand to the bow.” So he put his hand to it, after which E·liʹsha laid his hands on the king’s hands. ^17 Then he said: “Open the window toward the east.” So he opened it. E·liʹsha said: “Shoot!” So he shot. He now said: “Jehovah’s arrow of victory,[*] the arrow of victory over[*] Syria! You will strike down[*] Syria at Aʹphek until you finish it off.”

^18 He continued: “Take the arrows,” and he took them. Then he said to the king of Israel: “Strike the ground.” So he struck the ground three times and stopped. ^19 At that the man of the true God grew indignant at him and said: “You should have struck the ground five or six times! Then you would have struck down Syria until you finished it off, but now you will strike down Syria only three times.”

^20 After that E·liʹsha died and was buried. There were Moʹab·ite marauder bands that would come into the land at the beginning of the year.[*] ^21 As some men were burying a man, they saw the marauder band, so they quickly threw the man into E·liʹsha’s burial place and ran off. When the man touched the bones of E·liʹsha, he came to life and stood on his feet.

^22 Now King Hazʹa·el of Syria oppressed Israel all the days of Je·hoʹa·haz. ^23 However, Jehovah extended favor and mercy to them and showed his concern for them for the sake of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. He did not want to bring them to ruin, and he has not cast them away from his presence to this day. ^24 When King Hazʹa·el of Syria died, his son Ben-haʹdad became king in his place. ^25 Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz then took back from Ben-haʹdad the son of Hazʹa·el the cities that he had taken in war from Je·hoʹa·haz his father. Three times Je·hoʹash struck him down,[*] and he recovered the cities of Israel.

^ 2 Ki. 13:4 Or “softened the face.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:5 That is, in peace and security.

^ 2 Ki. 13:6 Lit., “In it he walked.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:6 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 13:11 Lit., “walked.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:13 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 2 Ki. 13:17 Or “salvation.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:17 Or “salvation against.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:17 Or “defeat.”

^ 2 Ki. 13:20 Lit., “at the coming in of the year,” likely in the spring.

^ 2 Ki. 13:25 Or “defeated him.”

2 Kings  14 : 1 - 29

14 In the second year of Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz the king of Israel, Am·a·ziʹah the son of King Je·hoʹash of Judah became king. ^2 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ho·adʹdin of Jerusalem. ^3 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, but not like David his forefather. He did everything as Je·hoʹash his father had done. ^4 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. ^5 As soon as he had the kingdom firmly in his control, he struck down his servants who had struck down his father the king. ^6 But he did not put the sons of the murderers to death, in harmony with Jehovah’s commandment written in the book of Moses’ Law: “Fathers should not be put to death for their sons, and sons should not be put to death for their fathers; but each one should be put to death for his own sin.” ^7 He struck down the Eʹdom·ites in the Valley of Salt, 10,000 men, and captured Seʹla in the war, and its name became Jokʹthe·el to this day.

^8 Then Am·a·ziʹah sent messengers to Je·hoʹash son of Je·hoʹa·haz son of Jeʹhu the king of Israel, saying: “Come, let us confront each other in battle.”[*] ^9 King Je·hoʹash of Israel sent this message to King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah: “The thorny weed in Lebʹa·non sent a message to the cedar in Lebʹa·non, ‘Give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of Lebʹa·non passed by and trampled down the thorny weed. ^10 True, you have struck down Eʹdom, so your heart has become arrogant. Enjoy your glory, but stay in your own house.[*] Why should you provoke disaster and fall, bringing Judah down with you?” ^11 But Am·a·ziʹah did not listen.

So King Je·hoʹash of Israel went up, and he and King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah confronted each other in battle at Beth-sheʹmesh, which belongs to Judah. ^12 Judah was defeated by Israel, so each one fled to his home.[*] ^13 King Je·hoʹash of Israel captured King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah, son of Je·hoʹash son of A·ha·ziʹah, at Beth-sheʹmesh. Then they came to Jerusalem, and he made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of Eʹphra·im to the Corner Gate, 400 cubits.[*] ^14 He took all the gold and the silver and all the articles that were found in the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the house[*] of the king, as well as hostages. Then he returned to Sa·marʹi·a.

^15 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoʹash, what he did and his mightiness and how he fought against King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^16 Then Je·hoʹash was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in Sa·marʹi·a with the kings of Israel; and his son Jer·o·boʹam[*] became king in his place.

^17 Am·a·ziʹah the son of Je·hoʹash the king of Judah lived for 15 years after the death of Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz the king of Israel. ^18 As for the rest of the history of Am·a·ziʹah, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^19 Later a conspiracy was formed against him at Jerusalem, and he fled to Laʹchish, but they sent men after him to Laʹchish and put him to death there. ^20 So they carried him back on horses, and he was buried in Jerusalem with his forefathers in the City of David. ^21 Then all the people of Judah took Az·a·riʹah,[*] who was 16 years old, and made him king in place of his father Am·a·ziʹah. ^22 He rebuilt Eʹlath and restored it to Judah after the king[*] was laid to rest with his forefathers.

^23 In the 15th year of Am·a·ziʹah the son of Je·hoʹash the king of Judah, Jer·o·boʹam the son of King Je·hoʹash of Israel became king in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for 41 years. ^24 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. ^25 He restored the boundary of Israel from Leʹbo-haʹmath[*] clear to the Sea of the Arʹa·bah,[*] according to the word that Jehovah the God of Israel spoke through his servant Joʹnah the son of A·mitʹtai, the prophet from Gath-heʹpher. ^26 For Jehovah had seen the very bitter affliction of Israel. There was no one left to help Israel, not even the helpless or the weak. ^27 But Jehovah had promised not to wipe out the name of Israel from under the heavens. So he saved them by the hand of Jer·o·boʹam the son of Je·hoʹash.

^28 As for the rest of the history of Jer·o·boʹam, all that he did and his mightiness, how he fought and how he restored Damascus and Haʹmath to Judah in Israel, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^29 Then Jer·o·boʹam was laid to rest with his forefathers, with the kings of Israel; and his son Zech·a·riʹah became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 14:8 Or “meet face-to-face.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:10 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:12 Lit., “tent.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:13 About 178 m (584 ft). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 14:14 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:16 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 2 Ki. 14:21 Meaning “Jehovah Has Helped.” He is called Uzziah at 2Ki 15:13; 2Ch 26:1-23; Isa 6:1; and Zec 14:5.

^ 2 Ki. 14:22 That is, his father Amaziah.

^ 2 Ki. 14:25 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ 2 Ki. 14:25 That is, the Salt Sea, or the Dead Sea.

2 Kings  15 : 1 - 38

15 In the 27th year of King Jer·o·boʹam[*] of Israel, Az·a·riʹah[*] the son of King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah became king. ^2 He was 16 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 52 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·co·liʹah of Jerusalem. ^3 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Am·a·ziʹah had done. ^4 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. ^5 Jehovah afflicted the king, and he remained a leper until the day of his death; and he stayed in a separate house, while the king’s son Joʹtham was in charge of the house,[*] judging the people of the land. ^6 As for the rest of the history of Az·a·riʹah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^7 Then Az·a·riʹah was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Joʹtham became king in his place.

^8 In the 38th year of King Az·a·riʹah of Judah, Zech·a·riʹah the son of Jer·o·boʹam became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for six months. ^9 He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his forefathers had done. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. ^10 Then Shalʹlum the son of Jaʹbesh conspired against him and struck him down at Ibʹle·am. After putting him to death, he became king in his place. ^11 As for the rest of the history of Zech·a·riʹah, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. ^12 That fulfilled Jehovah’s word spoken to Jeʹhu: “Four generations of your sons will sit on the throne of Israel.” And that is how it happened.

^13 Shalʹlum the son of Jaʹbesh became king in the 39th year of King Uz·ziʹah of Judah, and he reigned for a full month in Sa·marʹi·a. ^14 Then Menʹa·hem the son of Gaʹdi came up from Tirʹzah to Sa·marʹi·a and struck down Shalʹlum the son of Jaʹbesh in Sa·marʹi·a. After putting him to death, he became king in his place. ^15 As for the rest of the history of Shalʹlum and the conspiracy that he formed, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel. ^16 It was then that Menʹa·hem came from Tirʹzah and struck down Tiphʹsah and all who were in it and its territory, because it did not open its gates to him. He struck it down and ripped open its pregnant women.

^17 In the 39th year of King Az·a·riʹah of Judah, Menʹa·hem the son of Gaʹdi became king over Israel, and he reigned for ten years in Sa·marʹi·a. ^18 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from all the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit, all his days. ^19 King Pul of As·syrʹi·a came into the land, and Menʹa·hem gave Pul 1,000 talents[*] of silver in return for his support in strengthening his hold on the kingdom. ^20 So Menʹa·hem raised the silver from Israel by exacting it from the prominent, wealthy men. He gave the king of As·syrʹi·a 50 silver shekels[*] for each man. Then the king of As·syrʹi·a turned back and did not stay in the land. ^21 As for the rest of the history of Menʹa·hem, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel? ^22 Then Menʹa·hem was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Pek·a·hiʹah became king in his place.

^23 In the 50th year of King Az·a·riʹah of Judah, Pek·a·hiʹah the son of Menʹa·hem became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for two years. ^24 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. He did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. ^25 Then his adjutant Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah conspired against him and struck him down in Sa·marʹi·a in the fortified tower of the king’s house[*] with Arʹgob and A·riʹeh. He had 50 men of Gilʹe·ad with him; and after he put him to death, he became king in his place. ^26 As for the rest of the history of Pek·a·hiʹah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.

^27 In the 52nd year of King Az·a·riʹah of Judah, Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a, and he reigned for 20 years. ^28 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, and he did not depart from the sins that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had caused Israel to commit. ^29 In the days of King Peʹkah of Israel, King Tigʹlath-pil·eʹser of As·syrʹi·a invaded and captured Iʹjon, Aʹbel-beth-maʹa·cah, Ja·noʹah, Keʹdesh, Haʹzor, Gilʹe·ad, and Galʹi·lee, all the land of Naphʹta·li, and he took the inhabitants into exile in As·syrʹi·a. ^30 Then Ho·sheʹa the son of Eʹlah formed a conspiracy against Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah, and he struck him and put him to death; and he became king in his place in the 20th year of Joʹtham the son of Uz·ziʹah. ^31 As for the rest of the history of Peʹkah, all that he did, it is written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Israel.

^32 In the second year of Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah the king of Israel, Joʹtham the son of King Uz·ziʹah of Judah became king. ^33 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ruʹsha the daughter of Zaʹdok. ^34 He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Uz·ziʹah had done. ^35 However, the high places were not removed, and the people were still sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places. He was the one who built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah. ^36 As for the rest of the history of Joʹtham, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^37 In those days Jehovah began sending Reʹzin the king of Syria and Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah against Judah. ^38 Then Joʹtham was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David his forefather. And his son Aʹhaz became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 15:1 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 2 Ki. 15:1 Meaning “Jehovah Has Helped.” He is called Uzziah at 2Ki 15:13; 2Ch 26:1-23; Isa 6:1; and Zec 14:5.

^ 2 Ki. 15:5 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 15:19 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 15:20 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 15:25 Or “palace.”

2 Kings  16 : 1 - 20

16 In the 17th year of Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah, Aʹhaz the son of King Joʹtham of Judah became king. ^2 Aʹhaz was 20 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. He did not do what was right in the eyes of Jehovah his God as David his forefather had done. ^3 Instead, he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and he even made his own son pass through the fire, following the detestable practices of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the Israelites. ^4 He also kept sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places, on the hills, and under every luxuriant tree.

^5 It was then that King Reʹzin of Syria and Peʹkah son of Rem·a·liʹah the king of Israel came up to wage war against Jerusalem. They laid siege against Aʹhaz but were not able to capture the city. ^6 At that time King Reʹzin of Syria restored Eʹlath to Eʹdom, after which he drove the Jews[*] out of Eʹlath. And the Eʹdom·ites entered Eʹlath, and they have occupied it down to this day. ^7 So Aʹhaz sent messengers to King Tigʹlath-pil·eʹser of As·syrʹi·a, saying: “I am your servant and your son. Come up and save me from the hand of the king of Syria and the hand of the king of Israel, who are attacking me.” ^8 Aʹhaz then took the silver and the gold that was to be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the king’s house[*] and sent the king of As·syrʹi·a a bribe. ^9 The king of As·syrʹi·a responded to his request, and he went up to Damascus and captured it and led its people into exile to Kir, and he put Reʹzin to death.

^10 Then King Aʹhaz went to meet King Tigʹlath-pil·eʹser of As·syrʹi·a at Damascus. When he saw the altar that was in Damascus, King Aʹhaz sent U·riʹjah the priest a plan of the altar, showing its pattern and how it was made. ^11 U·riʹjah the priest built an altar according to all the directions that King Aʹhaz had sent from Damascus. U·riʹjah the priest finished building it before King Aʹhaz returned from Damascus. ^12 When the king returned from Damascus and saw the altar, he approached the altar and made offerings on it. ^13 And on that altar he continued to make his burnt offerings and his grain offerings smoke; he also poured out his drink offerings and sprinkled the blood of his communion sacrifices on it. ^14 Then he moved the copper altar that was before Jehovah from its place in front of the house, from between his own altar and the house of Jehovah, and he put it at the north side of his own altar. ^15 King Aʹhaz commanded U·riʹjah the priest: “Make the morning burnt offering smoke on the great altar, also the evening grain offering, the king’s burnt offering, and his grain offering, as well as the burnt offerings, the grain offerings, and the drink offerings of all the people. You should also sprinkle on it all the blood of the burnt offerings and all the blood of the other sacrifices. As for the copper altar, let me decide what to do with it.” ^16 And U·riʹjah the priest did everything that King Aʹhaz had commanded.

^17 Furthermore, King Aʹhaz cut the side panels of the carriages into pieces and removed the basins from them, and he took the Sea down off the copper bulls that supported it and put it on a stone pavement. ^18 And the covered structure for the Sabbath that had been built in the house and the king’s outer entryway he shifted away from the house of Jehovah; he did so because of the king of As·syrʹi·a.

^19 As for the rest of the history of Aʹhaz, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^20 Then Aʹhaz was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Hez·e·kiʹah[*] became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 16:6 Or “the men of Judah.”

^ 2 Ki. 16:8 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 16:20 Meaning “Jehovah Strengthens.”

2 Kings  17 : 1 - 41

17 In the 12th year of King Aʹhaz of Judah, Ho·sheʹa the son of Eʹlah became king over Israel in Sa·marʹi·a; he ruled for nine years. ^2 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, only not to the extent of the kings of Israel prior to him. ^3 King Shal·man·eʹser of As·syrʹi·a came up against him, and Ho·sheʹa became his servant and began to pay tribute to him. ^4 However, the king of As·syrʹi·a learned that Ho·sheʹa was involved in a conspiracy, for he had sent messengers to King So of Egypt and did not bring the tribute up to the king of As·syrʹi·a as in former years. Therefore, the king of As·syrʹi·a kept him confined and bound in prison.

^5 The king of As·syrʹi·a invaded the entire land, and he came to Sa·marʹi·a and laid siege to it for three years. ^6 In the ninth year of Ho·sheʹa, the king of As·syrʹi·a captured Sa·marʹi·a. He then led the people of Israel into exile in As·syrʹi·a and made them dwell in Haʹlah and in Haʹbor at the river Goʹzan and in the cities of the Medes.

^7 This happened because the people of Israel had sinned against Jehovah their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the control of Pharʹaoh king of Egypt. They worshipped[*] other gods, ^8 they followed the customs of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the Israelites, and they followed the customs that the kings of Israel had established.

^9 The Israelites were pursuing the things that were not right according to Jehovah their God. They kept building high places in all their cities, from watchtower to fortified city.[*] ^10 They kept setting up for themselves sacred pillars and sacred poles[*] on every high hill and under every luxuriant tree; ^11 and on all the high places they would make sacrificial smoke just as the nations did that Jehovah had driven into exile from before them. They kept doing wicked things to offend Jehovah.

^12 They continued to serve disgusting idols,[*] about which Jehovah had told them: “You must not do this!” ^13 Jehovah kept warning Israel and Judah through all his prophets and every visionary, saying: “Turn back from your wicked ways! Keep my commandments and my statutes according to all the law that I commanded your forefathers and that I sent to you through my servants the prophets.” ^14 But they did not listen, and they remained just as stubborn as[*] their forefathers who had not shown faith in Jehovah their God. ^15 They continued rejecting his regulations and his covenant that he had made with their forefathers and his reminders that he had given to warn them, and they kept following worthless idols and became worthless themselves, imitating the nations all around them that Jehovah had commanded them not to imitate.

^16 They kept leaving all the commandments of Jehovah their God, and they made metal statues[*] of two calves and a sacred pole,[*] and they bowed down to all the army of the heavens and served Baʹal. ^17 They also made their sons and their daughters pass through the fire, they practiced divination and looked for omens, and they kept devoting[*] themselves to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, to offend him.

^18 So Jehovah was very angry with Israel, so that he removed them from his sight. He did not let any remain but the tribe of Judah alone.

^19 Even Judah did not keep the commandments of Jehovah their God; they also walked in the customs that Israel followed. ^20 Jehovah rejected all the descendants of Israel and humiliated them and gave them into the hand of plunderers, until he had cast them away from before him. ^21 He ripped Israel away from the house of David, and they made Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat king. But Jer·o·boʹam caused Israel to stray from following Jehovah, and he caused them to commit a great sin. ^22 And the people of Israel kept walking in all the sins that Jer·o·boʹam had committed. They did not depart from them ^23 until Jehovah removed Israel from his sight, just as he had declared through all his servants the prophets. So Israel was taken into exile from its land to As·syrʹi·a, where they remain to this day.

^24 The king of As·syrʹi·a then brought people from Babylon, Cuʹthah, Avʹva, Haʹmath, and Seph·ar·vaʹim and settled them in the cities of Sa·marʹi·a in place of the Israelites; they took possession of Sa·marʹi·a and lived in its cities. ^25 When they first began dwelling there, they did not fear[*] Jehovah. So Jehovah sent lions among them, and they killed some of the people. ^26 It was reported to the king of As·syrʹi·a: “The nations that you have taken into exile and resettled in the cities of Sa·marʹi·a do not know the religion[*] of the God of the land. So he keeps sending lions among them, which are putting them to death, because none of them know the religion of the God of the land.”

^27 At that the king of As·syrʹi·a commanded: “Have one of the priests whom you took into exile from there return to live there and to teach them the religion of the God of the land.” ^28 So one of the priests whom they had taken into exile from Sa·marʹi·a came back to live in Bethʹel, and he began to teach them how they should fear[*] Jehovah.

^29 However, each different nation made their own god,[*] which they placed in the houses of worship on the high places that the Sa·marʹi·tans had made; each different nation did so in their cities where they were living. ^30 So the men of Babylon made Sucʹcoth-beʹnoth, the men of Cuth made Nerʹgal, the men of Haʹmath made A·shiʹma, ^31 and the Avʹvites made Nibʹhaz and Tarʹtak. The Seʹphar·vites would burn their sons in the fire to A·dramʹme·lech and A·namʹme·lech, the gods of Seph·ar·vaʹim. ^32 Although they feared Jehovah, they appointed priests for the high places from the people in general, and these officiated for them at the houses of worship on the high places. ^33 Thus, they feared Jehovah, but they worshipped their own gods according to the religion[*] of the nations from which they had been deported.

^34 To this day they follow their former religions.[*] None of them worship[*] Jehovah, and none follow his statutes, his judgments, the Law, and the commandment that Jehovah gave the sons of Jacob, whose name he changed to Israel. ^35 When Jehovah made a covenant with them, he commanded them: “You must not fear other gods, and you must not bow down to them or serve them or sacrifice to them. ^36 But Jehovah, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt with great power and an outstretched arm, is the One you should fear, and to him you should bow down, and to him you should sacrifice. ^37 And the regulations, the judgments, the Law, and the commandment that he wrote for you, you should always follow carefully, and you must not fear other gods. ^38 And you must not forget the covenant that I made with you, and you must not fear other gods. ^39 But it is Jehovah your God whom you should fear, as he is the one who will rescue you out of the hand of all your enemies.”

^40 But they did not obey, and they followed their former religion.[*] ^41 So these nations came to fear Jehovah, but they were also serving their own graven images. Both their sons and their grandsons have done just as their forefathers did, down to this day.

^ 2 Ki. 17:7 Lit., “feared.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:9 That is, in every place, whether sparsely inhabited or populous.

^ 2 Ki. 17:10 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 17:12 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 2 Ki. 17:14 Lit., “hardened their neck like the neck of.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:16 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:16 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 17:17 Lit., “selling.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:25 Or “worship.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:26 Or “religious customs.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:28 Or “worship.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:29 Or “gods.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:33 Or “religious customs.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:34 Or “religious customs.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:34 Lit., “fear.”

^ 2 Ki. 17:40 Or “religious customs.”

2 Kings  18 : 1 - 37

18 In the third year of Ho·sheʹa the son of Eʹlah the king of Israel, Hez·e·kiʹah the son of King Aʹhaz of Judah became king. ^2 He was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Aʹbi[*] the daughter of Zech·a·riʹah. ^3 He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as David his forefather had done. ^4 He was the one who removed the high places, smashed the sacred pillars, and cut down the sacred pole.[*] He also crushed the copper serpent that Moses had made; for down to that time the people of Israel had been making sacrificial smoke to it and it used to be called the copper serpent-idol.[*] ^5 He trusted in Jehovah the God of Israel; there was no one like him among all the kings of Judah after him nor among those prior to him. ^6 He held fast to Jehovah. He did not turn away from following him; he continued to keep the commandments that Jehovah had given to Moses. ^7 And Jehovah was with him. Wherever he went, he acted wisely. He rebelled against the king of As·syrʹi·a and refused to serve him. ^8 He also defeated the Phi·lisʹtines clear to Gazʹa and its territories, from watchtower to fortified city.[*]

^9 In the fourth year of King Hez·e·kiʹah, that is, the seventh year of Ho·sheʹa the son of Eʹlah the king of Israel, King Shal·man·eʹser of As·syrʹi·a came up against Sa·marʹi·a and began to lay siege to it. ^10 They captured it at the end of three years; in the sixth year of Hez·e·kiʹah, which was the ninth year of King Ho·sheʹa of Israel, Sa·marʹi·a was captured. ^11 Then the king of As·syrʹi·a took Israel into exile in As·syrʹi·a and settled them in Haʹlah and in Haʹbor at the river Goʹzan and in the cities of the Medes. ^12 This was because they had not listened to the voice of Jehovah their God but kept violating his covenant, all that Moses the servant of Jehovah had commanded. They neither listened nor obeyed.

^13 In the 14th year of King Hez·e·kiʹah, Sen·nachʹer·ib the king of As·syrʹi·a came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and captured them. ^14 So King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah sent word to the king of As·syrʹi·a at Laʹchish: “I am at fault. Withdraw from against me, and I will give whatever you may impose on me.” The king of As·syrʹi·a imposed on King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah a fine of 300 silver talents[*] and 30 gold talents. ^15 So Hez·e·kiʹah gave all the silver that could be found at the house of Jehovah and in the treasuries of the king’s house.[*] ^16 At that time Hez·e·kiʹah removed[*] the doors of the temple of Jehovah and the doorposts that King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah himself had overlaid,[*] and he gave them to the king of As·syrʹi·a.

^17 The king of As·syrʹi·a then sent the Tarʹtan,[*] the Rabʹsa·ris,[*] and the Rabʹsha·keh[*] with a vast army from Laʹchish to King Hez·e·kiʹah in Jerusalem. They went up to Jerusalem and took up a position by the conduit of the upper pool, which is at the highway of the laundryman’s field. ^18 When they called for the king to come out, E·liʹa·kim son of Hil·kiʹah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹnah the secretary, and Joʹah son of Aʹsaph the recorder came out to them.

^19 So the Rabʹsha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·kiʹah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syrʹi·a, says: “What is the basis for your confidence? ^20 You are saying, ‘I have a strategy and the power to wage war,’ but these are empty words. In whom have you put your trust, so that you dare to rebel against me? ^21 Look! You trust in the support of this crushed reed, Egypt, which if a man should lean on it would enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Pharʹaoh king of Egypt is to all those who trust in him. ^22 And if you should say to me, ‘We trust in Jehovah our God,’ is he not the one whose high places and altars Hez·e·kiʹah has removed, while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You should bow down before this altar in Jerusalem’?”’ ^23 So now make this wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syrʹi·a: I will give you 2,000 horses if you are able to find enough riders for them. ^24 How, then, could you drive back even one governor who is the least of my lord’s servants, while you put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? ^25 Now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this place to destroy it? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land and destroy it.’”

^26 At this E·liʹa·kim son of Hil·kiʹah, and Shebʹnah and Joʹah said to the Rabʹsha·keh: “Speak to your servants, please, in the Ar·a·maʹic[*] language, for we can understand it; do not speak to us in the language of the Jews in the hearing of the people on the wall.” ^27 But the Rabʹsha·keh said to them: “Is it just to your lord and to you that my lord sent me to speak these words? Is it not also to the men who sit on the wall, those who will eat their own excrement and drink their own urine along with you?”

^28 Then the Rabʹsha·keh stood and called out loudly in the language of the Jews, saying: “Hear the word of the great king, the king of As·syrʹi·a. ^29 This is what the king says, ‘Do not let Hez·e·kiʹah deceive you, for he is not able to rescue you out of my hand. ^30 And do not let Hez·e·kiʹah cause you to trust in Jehovah by saying: “Jehovah will surely rescue us, and this city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a.” ^31 Do not listen to Hez·e·kiʹah, for this is what the king of As·syrʹi·a says: “Make peace with me and surrender,[*] and each of you will eat from his own vine and from his own fig tree and will drink the water of his own cistern, ^32 until I come and take you to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees and honey. Then you will live and not die. Do not listen to Hez·e·kiʹah, for he misleads you by saying, ‘Jehovah will rescue us.’ ^33 Have any of the gods of the nations rescued their land out of the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a? ^34 Where are the gods of Haʹmath and Arʹpad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·vaʹim, Heʹna, and Ivʹvah? Have they rescued Sa·marʹi·a out of my hand? ^35 Who among all the gods of the lands have rescued their land out of my hand, so that Jehovah should rescue Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”

^36 But the people kept silent and did not say a word to him in reply, for the order of the king was, “You must not answer him.” ^37 But E·liʹa·kim son of Hil·kiʹah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹnah the secretary, and Joʹah son of Aʹsaph the recorder came to Hez·e·kiʹah with their garments ripped apart and told him the words of the Rabʹsha·keh.

^ 2 Ki. 18:2 An abbreviated form of Abijah.

^ 2 Ki. 18:4 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 18:4 Or “called Nehushtan.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:8 That is, in every place, whether sparsely inhabited or populous.

^ 2 Ki. 18:14 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 18:15 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:16 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:16 That is, overlaid with gold.

^ 2 Ki. 18:17 Or “the commander.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:17 Or “the chief court official.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:17 Or “the chief cupbearer.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:18 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:26 Or “Syrian.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:31 Lit., “Make a blessing with me and come out to me.”

^ 2 Ki. 18:37 Or “palace.”

2 Kings  19 : 1 - 37

19 As soon as King Hez·e·kiʹah heard this, he ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and went into the house of Jehovah. ^2 Then he sent E·liʹa·kim, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹnah the secretary, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah, the son of Aʹmoz. ^3 They said to him: “This is what Hez·e·kiʹah says, ‘This day is a day of distress, of rebuke,[*] and of disgrace; for the children are ready to be born,[*] but there is no strength to give birth. ^4 Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear all the words of the Rabʹsha·keh, whom the king of As·syrʹi·a his lord sent to taunt the living God, and he will call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. So offer up a prayer in behalf of the remnant who have survived.’”

^5 So the servants of King Hez·e·kiʹah went in to Isaiah, ^6 and Isaiah said to them: “This is what you should say to your lord, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Do not be afraid because of the words that you heard, the words with which the attendants of the king of As·syrʹi·a blasphemed me. ^7 Here I am putting a thought in his mind,[*] and he will hear a report and return to his own land; and I will make him fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

^8 After the Rabʹsha·keh heard that the king of As·syrʹi·a had pulled away from Laʹchish, he returned to him and found him fighting against Libʹnah. ^9 Now the king heard it said about King Tir·haʹkah of E·thi·oʹpi·a: “Here he has come out to fight against you.” So he sent messengers again to Hez·e·kiʹah, saying: ^10 “This is what you should say to King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you trust deceive you by saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a.” ^11 Look! You have heard what the kings of As·syrʹi·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction. Will you alone be rescued? ^12 Did the gods of the nations that my forefathers destroyed rescue them? Where are Goʹzan, Haʹran, Reʹzeph, and the people of Eʹden who were in Tel-asʹsar? ^13 Where is the king of Haʹmath, the king of Arʹpad, and the king of the cities of Seph·ar·vaʹim, and of Heʹna, and of Ivʹvah?’”

^14 Hez·e·kiʹah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them. Hez·e·kiʹah then went up to the house of Jehovah and spread them[*] out before Jehovah. ^15 And Hez·e·kiʹah began to pray before Jehovah and say: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, sitting enthroned above[*] the cherubs, you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You made the heavens and the earth. ^16 Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear! Open your eyes, O Jehovah, and see! Hear the words that Sen·nachʹer·ib has sent to taunt the living God. ^17 It is a fact, O Jehovah, that the kings of As·syrʹi·a have devastated the nations and their lands. ^18 And they have thrown their gods into the fire, because they were not gods but the work of human hands, wood and stone. That is why they could destroy them. ^19 But now, O Jehovah our God, please save us out of his hand, so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone are God, O Jehovah.”

^20 Isaiah son of Aʹmoz then sent this message to Hez·e·kiʹah: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘I have heard your prayer to me concerning King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a. ^21 This is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:

“The virgin daughter of Zion despises you, she scoffs at you.

The daughter of Jerusalem shakes her head at you.

^22 Whom have you taunted and blasphemed?

Against whom have you raised your voice

And lifted your arrogant eyes?

It is against the Holy One of Israel!

^23 Through your messengers you have taunted Jehovah and said,

‘With the multitude of my war chariots

I will ascend the heights of mountains,

The remotest parts of Lebʹa·non.

I will cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.

I will enter its farthest retreats, its densest forests.

^24 I will dig wells and drink foreign waters;

I will dry up all the streams[*] of Egypt with the soles of my feet.’

^25 Have you not heard? From long ago it was determined.[*]

From days gone by I have prepared[*] it.

Now I will bring it about.

You will turn fortified cities into desolate piles of ruins.

^26 Their inhabitants will be helpless;

They will be terrified and put to shame.

They will become as vegetation of the field and green grass,

As grass of the roofs that is scorched by the east wind.

^27 But I well know when you sit, when you go out, when you come in,

And when you are enraged against me,

^28 Because your rage against me and your roaring have reached my ears.

So I will put my hook in your nose and my bridle between your lips,

And I will lead you back the way you came.”

^29 “‘And this will be the sign for you:[*] This year you will eat what grows on its own;[*] and in the second year you will eat grain that sprouts from that; but in the third year you will sow seed and reap, and you will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. ^30 Those of the house of Judah who escape, those who are left, will take root downward and produce fruit upward. ^31 For a remnant will go out of Jerusalem and survivors from Mount Zion. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

^32 “‘Therefore this is what Jehovah says about the king of As·syrʹi·a:

“He will not come into this city

Or shoot an arrow there

Or confront it with a shield

Or cast up a siege rampart against it.

^33 By the way he came he will return;

He will not come into this city,” declares Jehovah.

^34 “I will defend this city and save it for my own sake

And for the sake of my servant David.”’”

^35 On that very night the angel of Jehovah went out and struck down 185,000 men in the camp of the As·syrʹi·ans. When people rose up early in the morning, they saw all the dead bodies. ^36 So King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a departed and returned to Ninʹe·veh and stayed there. ^37 And as he was bowing down at the house[*] of his god Nisʹroch, his own sons A·dramʹme·lech and Shar·eʹzer struck him down with the sword and then escaped to the land of Arʹa·rat. And his son Eʹsar-hadʹdon became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 19:2 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:3 Or “insult.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:3 Lit., “have come to the opening of the womb.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:7 Lit., “a spirit in him.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:14 Lit., “it.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:15 Or possibly, “between.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:24 Or “the Nile canals.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:25 Lit., “done.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:25 Or “formed.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:29 That is, Hezekiah.

^ 2 Ki. 19:29 Or “the growth from spilled kernels of grain.”

^ 2 Ki. 19:37 Or “temple.”

2 Kings  20 : 1 - 21

20 In those days Hez·e·kiʹah became sick and was at the point of death. The prophet Isaiah the son of Aʹmoz came and said to him, “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Give instructions to your household, for you will die; you will not recover.’” ^2 At that he turned his face to the wall and began to pray to Jehovah: ^3 “I beg you, O Jehovah, remember, please, how I have walked before you faithfully and with a complete heart, and I have done what was good in your eyes.” And Hez·e·kiʹah began to weep profusely.

^4 Isaiah had not yet gone out to the middle courtyard when Jehovah’s word came to him, saying: ^5 “Go back and say to Hez·e·kiʹah, the leader of my people, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather says: “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Here I am healing you. On the third day you will go up to the house of Jehovah. ^6 I will add 15 years to your life,[*] and I will rescue you and this city out of the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a, and I will defend this city for my own sake and for the sake of David my servant.”’”

^7 Isaiah then said: “Bring a cake of pressed dried figs.” So they brought it and applied it to the boil, after which he gradually recovered.

^8 Hez·e·kiʹah had asked Isaiah: “What is the sign to show that Jehovah will heal me and that I will go up on the third day to the house of Jehovah?” ^9 Isaiah replied: “This is the sign from Jehovah to show you that Jehovah will carry out the word that he has spoken: Do you want the shadow on the stairway[*] to move forward ten steps or back ten steps?” ^10 Hez·e·kiʹah said: “It is an easy thing for the shadow to extend itself ten steps but not to go back ten steps.” ^11 So Isaiah the prophet called out to Jehovah, and He made the shadow on the stairway of Aʹhaz go back ten steps after it had already descended the steps.

^12 At that time the king of Babylon, Be·roʹdach-balʹa·dan son of Balʹa·dan, sent letters and a gift to Hez·e·kiʹah, for he had heard that Hez·e·kiʹah had been sick. ^13 Hez·e·kiʹah welcomed[*] them and showed them his entire treasure-house—the silver, the gold, the balsam oil and other precious oil, his armory, and everything that was to be found in his treasuries. There was nothing that Hez·e·kiʹah did not show them in his own house[*] and in all his dominion.

^14 After that Isaiah the prophet came in to King Hez·e·kiʹah and asked him: “What did these men say, and where did they come from?” So Hez·e·kiʹah said: “They came from a distant land, from Babylon.” ^15 Next he asked: “What did they see in your house?”[*] Hez·e·kiʹah replied: “They saw everything in my house.[*] There was nothing that I did not show them in my treasuries.”

^16 Isaiah now said to Hez·e·kiʹah: “Hear the word of Jehovah, ^17 ‘Look! Days are coming, and all that is in your house[*] and all that your forefathers have stored up to this day will be carried off to Babylon. Nothing will be left,’ says Jehovah. ^18 ‘And some of your own sons to whom you will become father will be taken and will become court officials in the palace of the king of Babylon.’”

^19 At that Hez·e·kiʹah said to Isaiah: “The word of Jehovah that you have spoken is good.” Then he added: “It is good if there will be peace and stability[*] during my lifetime.”[*]

^20 As for the rest of the history of Hez·e·kiʹah, all his mightiness and how he made the pool and the conduit and brought the water into the city, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^21 Then Hez·e·kiʹah was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Ma·nasʹseh became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 20:6 Lit., “days.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:9 Perhaps these stairs were used to count time, as on a sundial.

^ 2 Ki. 20:13 Or “listened to.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:13 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:15 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:15 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:17 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:19 Or “truth.”

^ 2 Ki. 20:19 Lit., “days.”

2 Kings  21 : 1 - 26

21 Ma·nasʹseh was 12 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 55 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Hephʹzi·bah. ^2 He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, following the detestable practices of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the people of Israel. ^3 He rebuilt the high places that his father Hez·e·kiʹah had destroyed, and he set up altars to Baʹal and made a sacred pole,[*] just as Aʹhab the king of Israel had done. And he bowed down to all the army of the heavens and served them. ^4 He also built altars in the house of Jehovah, about which Jehovah had said: “In Jerusalem, I will put my name.” ^5 And he built altars to all the army of the heavens in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah. ^6 And he made his own son pass through the fire; he practiced magic, looked for omens, and appointed spirit mediums and fortune-tellers. He did on a grand scale what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, to offend him.

^7 He put the carved image of the sacred pole[*] that he made into the house about which Jehovah had said to David and to his son Solʹo·mon: “In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will permanently put my name. ^8 And I will never again make the feet of Israel wander from the land that I gave to their forefathers, provided they carefully observe all that I have commanded them, the entire Law that my servant Moses ordered them to follow.” ^9 But they did not obey, and Ma·nasʹseh kept leading them astray, causing them to do greater evil than the nations that Jehovah had annihilated from before the Israelites.

^10 Jehovah kept speaking through his servants the prophets, saying: ^11 “Ma·nasʹseh the king of Judah has done all these detestable things; he has acted more wickedly than all the Amʹor·ites before him, and he has made Judah sin with his disgusting idols.[*] ^12 Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Here I am bringing such a disaster on Jerusalem and Judah that it will make both ears of anyone who hears about it tingle. ^13 And I will stretch out on Jerusalem the measuring line applied to Sa·marʹi·a and use the leveling tool[*] applied to the house of Aʹhab, and I will wipe Jerusalem clean, just as one wipes a bowl clean, wiping it and turning it upside down. ^14 I will forsake the remnant of my inheritance and give them into the hand of their enemies, and they will become plunder and spoil to all their enemies, ^15 because they did what was bad in my eyes and were continually offending me from the day that their forefathers came out of Egypt to this day.’”

^16 Ma·nasʹseh also shed innocent blood in very great quantity until he had filled Jerusalem from one end to the other, besides his sin of causing Judah to sin by doing what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah. ^17 As for the rest of the history of Ma·nasʹseh and all that he did and the sins that he committed, are they not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^18 Then Ma·nasʹseh was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the garden of his house, in the garden of Uzʹza; and his son Aʹmon became king in his place.

^19 Aʹmon was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Me·shulʹle·meth the daughter of Haʹruz from Jotʹbah. ^20 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Ma·nasʹseh had done. ^21 He kept walking in all the ways that his father walked, and he continued serving and bowing down to the disgusting idols that his father had served. ^22 So he abandoned Jehovah the God of his forefathers, and he did not walk in the way of Jehovah. ^23 Eventually Aʹmon’s servants conspired against him and put the king to death in his own house. ^24 But the people of the land struck down all those who conspired against King Aʹmon, and they made his son Jo·siʹah king in his place. ^25 As for the rest of the history of Aʹmon, what he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^26 So they buried him in his grave in the garden of Uzʹza, and his son Jo·siʹah became king in his place.

^ 2 Ki. 21:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 21:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 21:11 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 2 Ki. 21:13 Or “plumb line.”

2 Kings  22 : 1 - 20

22 Jo·siʹah was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned for 31 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·diʹdah the daughter of A·daiʹah from Bozʹkath. ^2 He did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes and walked in all the ways of David his forefather, and he did not deviate to the right or to the left.

^3 In the 18th year of King Jo·siʹah, the king sent Shaʹphan the secretary, the son of Az·a·liʹah the son of Me·shulʹlam, to the house of Jehovah, saying: ^4 “Go up to Hil·kiʹah the high priest, and let him collect all the money that is being brought into the house of Jehovah, which the doorkeepers have collected from the people. ^5 Have them give it to those appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah who, in turn, will give it to the workers in the house of Jehovah who are to repair the damage to[*] the house, ^6 that is, to the craftsmen, the builders, and the masons; and they are to use it to buy timbers and hewn stones to repair the house. ^7 But no accounting should be required of them for the money that they are given, because they are trustworthy.”

^8 Later Hil·kiʹah the high priest said to Shaʹphan the secretary: “I have found the book of the Law in the house of Jehovah.” So Hil·kiʹah gave the book to Shaʹphan, who began to read it. ^9 Then Shaʹphan the secretary went to the king and told him: “Your servants have poured out the money that was found in the house, and they have handed it over to those appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah.” ^10 Shaʹphan the secretary also told the king: “There is a book that Hil·kiʹah the priest has given me.” Then Shaʹphan began to read it before the king.

^11 As soon as the king heard the words of the book of the Law, he ripped his garments apart. ^12 Then the king gave this order to Hil·kiʹah the priest, A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan, Achʹbor the son of Mi·caiʹah, Shaʹphan the secretary, and A·saiʹah the king’s servant: ^13 “Go, inquire of Jehovah in my behalf, in behalf of the people, and in behalf of all Judah concerning the words of this book that has been found; for Jehovah’s rage that has been set ablaze against us is great, because our forefathers did not obey the words of this book by observing all that is written concerning us.”

^14 So Hil·kiʹah the priest, A·hiʹkam, Achʹbor, Shaʹphan, and A·saiʹah went to Hulʹdah the prophetess. She was the wife of Shalʹlum son of Tikʹvah son of Harʹhas, the caretaker of the wardrobe, and she was dwelling in the Second Quarter of Jerusalem; and they spoke to her there. ^15 She said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Tell the man who sent you to me: ^16 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘I will bring calamity on this place and its inhabitants, all the words of the book that the king of Judah has read. ^17 Because they have abandoned me and are making sacrifices smoke to other gods in order to offend me with all the work of their hands, my rage will be set ablaze against this place and it will not be extinguished.’” ^18 But to the king of Judah who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, this is what you should say to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Regarding the words that you have heard, ^19 because your heart was responsive[*] and you humbled yourself before Jehovah on hearing what I have spoken against this place and its inhabitants—that they would become an object of horror and a curse—and you ripped your garments apart and wept before me, I also have heard you, declares Jehovah. ^20 That is why I will gather you to your ancestors,[*] and you will be laid in your grave in peace, and your eyes will not see all the calamity that I will bring on this place.’”’” Then they brought the reply to the king.

^ 2 Ki. 22:5 Or “the cracks in.”

^ 2 Ki. 22:19 Lit., “soft.”

^ 2 Ki. 22:20 This is a poetic expression for death.

2 Kings  23 : 1 - 37

23 So the king sent word, and they summoned all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. ^2 After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah, all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, and the prophets—all the people, from small to great. He read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant that had been found in the house of Jehovah. ^3 The king stood by the pillar and made a covenant[*] before Jehovah, that he would follow Jehovah and keep his commandments, his reminders, and his statutes with all his heart and with all his soul[*] by carrying out the words of this covenant that were written in this book. And all the people agreed to the covenant.

^4 The king then ordered Hil·kiʹah the high priest, the priests of the second rank, and the doorkeepers to bring out from the temple of Jehovah all the utensils made for Baʹal, for the sacred pole,[*] and for all the army of the heavens. Then he burned them outside Jerusalem on the terraces of Kidʹron, and he took their ashes to Bethʹel. ^5 So he put out of business the foreign-god priests, whom the kings of Judah had appointed to make sacrificial smoke on the high places in the cities of Judah and the surroundings of Jerusalem, as well as those making sacrificial smoke to Baʹal, to the sun, to the moon, to the constellations of the zodiac, and to all the army of the heavens. ^6 He brought the sacred pole[*] out from the house of Jehovah to the outskirts of Jerusalem, to the Kidʹron Valley, and he burned it in the Kidʹron Valley and ground it to dust and scattered its dust on the graves of the common people. ^7 He also tore down the houses of the male temple prostitutes, which were in the house of Jehovah and where the women were weaving tent shrines for the sacred pole.[*]

^8 Then he brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and he made unfit for worship the high places where the priests had been making sacrificial smoke, from Geʹba to Beʹer-sheʹba. He also tore down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua the chief of the city, which were on the left as one entered the city gate. ^9 The priests of the high places did not serve at the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem, but they did eat unleavened bread along with their brothers. ^10 He also made unfit for worship Toʹpheth, which is in the Valley of the Sons of Hinʹnom,[*] so that no one could make his son or his daughter pass through the fire to Moʹlech. ^11 And he prohibited the horses that the kings of Judah had dedicated[*] to the sun from entering the house of Jehovah by the chamber[*] of Naʹthan-melʹech the court official, which was in the porticoes; and he burned the chariots of the sun in the fire. ^12 The king also tore down the altars that the kings of Judah had set up on the roof of Aʹhaz’s upper chamber, as well as the altars that Ma·nasʹseh had set up in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah. He crushed them and scattered their dust in the Kidʹron Valley. ^13 And the king made unfit for worship the high places in front of Jerusalem that were to the south[*] of the Mount of Ruination,[*] which Solʹo·mon the king of Israel had built to Ashʹto·reth the disgusting goddess of the Si·doʹni·ans; and to Cheʹmosh the disgusting god of Moʹab; and to Milʹcom the detestable god of the Amʹmon·ites. ^14 He broke the sacred pillars to pieces and cut down the sacred poles[*] and filled their places with human bones. ^15 He also tore down the altar in Bethʹel, the high place that Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat had made that caused Israel to sin. After tearing down that altar and the high place, he burned the high place, ground it to dust, and burned the sacred pole.[*]

^16 When Jo·siʹah turned and saw the graves on the mountain, he had the bones taken from the graves and burned them on the altar, making it unfit for worship, according to Jehovah’s word that had been proclaimed by the man of the true God who foretold that these things would happen. ^17 Then he said: “What is the gravestone over there that I am looking at?” At this the men of the city said to him: “It is the grave of the man of the true God from Judah who foretold these things that you have done against the altar of Bethʹel.” ^18 So he said: “Let him rest. Do not let anyone disturb his bones.” So they left his bones undisturbed, as well as the bones of the prophet who had come from Sa·marʹi·a.

^19 Jo·siʹah also removed all the houses of worship on the high places that were in the cities of Sa·marʹi·a, which the kings of Israel had built to offend God, and he did the same thing to them that he had done at Bethʹel. ^20 So he sacrificed on the altars all the priests of the high places who were there, and he burned human bones on them. After that he returned to Jerusalem.

^21 The king now commanded all the people: “Hold a Passover to Jehovah your God as is written in this book of the covenant.” ^22 No Passover like this had been held since the days when the judges had judged Israel or in all the days of the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah. ^23 But in the 18th year of King Jo·siʹah, this Passover to Jehovah was held in Jerusalem.

^24 Jo·siʹah also cleared out the spirit mediums, the fortune-tellers, the teraphim statues,[*] the disgusting idols,[*] and all the disgusting things that had appeared in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, in order to carry out the words of the Law that were written in the book that Hil·kiʹah the priest had found in the house of Jehovah. ^25 There was no king like him prior to him, who returned to Jehovah with all his heart and with all his soul[*] and with all his strength, according to all the Law of Moses; nor did anyone like him rise up after him.

^26 Nevertheless, Jehovah did not turn away from his burning anger that blazed against Judah because of all the offensive things that Ma·nasʹseh had done to offend Him. ^27 Jehovah said: “I will also remove Judah from my sight, just as I removed Israel; and I will reject this city that I chose, Jerusalem, and the house about which I said, ‘My name will continue there.’”

^28 As for the rest of the history of Jo·siʹah, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^29 In his days Pharʹaoh Neʹchoh the king of Egypt came to meet the king of As·syrʹi·a by the Eu·phraʹtes River, and King Jo·siʹah went out to confront him; but when Neʹchoh saw him, he put him to death at Me·gidʹdo. ^30 So his servants transported his dead body in a chariot from Me·gidʹdo and brought him to Jerusalem and buried him in his grave. Then the people of the land took Jo·siʹah’s son Je·hoʹa·haz and anointed him and made him king in place of his father.

^31 Je·hoʹa·haz was 23 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·muʹtal the daughter of Jeremiah from Libʹnah. ^32 He began to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his forefathers had done. ^33 Pharʹaoh Neʹchoh imprisoned him at Ribʹlah in the land of Haʹmath, to keep him from reigning in Jerusalem, and then imposed on the land a fine of 100 silver talents[*] and a gold talent. ^34 Furthermore, Pharʹaoh Neʹchoh made Jo·siʹah’s son E·liʹa·kim king in place of his father Jo·siʹah and changed his name to Je·hoiʹa·kim; but he took Je·hoʹa·haz and brought him to Egypt, where he eventually died. ^35 Je·hoiʹa·kim gave the silver and the gold to Pharʹaoh, but he had to tax the land to give the silver that Pharʹaoh demanded. He exacted an assessed amount of silver and gold from each of the people of the land to give to Pharʹaoh Neʹchoh.

^36 Je·hoiʹa·kim was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ze·biʹdah the daughter of Pe·daiʹah from Ruʹmah. ^37 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his forefathers had done.

^ 2 Ki. 23:3 Or “renewed the covenant.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:4 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:6 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:10 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:11 Lit., “given.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:11 Or “dining room.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:13 Lit., “right.” That is, south, when one faces east.

^ 2 Ki. 23:13 That is, the Mount of Olives, particularly the southern extremity also known as the Mount of Offense.

^ 2 Ki. 23:14 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:15 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:24 Or “household gods; idols.”

^ 2 Ki. 23:24 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ 2 Ki. 23:25 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 23:33 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

2 Kings  24 : 1 - 20

24 In Je·hoiʹa·kim’s days King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon came against him, and Je·hoiʹa·kim became his servant for three years. However, he turned against him and rebelled. ^2 Then Jehovah began to send against him marauder bands of Chal·deʹans, Syrians, Moʹab·ites, and Amʹmon·ites. He kept sending them against Judah to destroy it, according to Jehovah’s word that he had spoken through his servants the prophets. ^3 Surely it was by the order of Jehovah that this happened to Judah, to remove them from his sight because of all the sins that Ma·nasʹseh had committed, ^4 and also the innocent blood that he had shed, for he had filled Jerusalem with innocent blood and Jehovah was not willing to forgive.

^5 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoiʹa·kim, all that he did, is it not written in the book of the history of the times of the kings of Judah? ^6 Then Je·hoiʹa·kim was laid to rest with his forefathers; and his son Je·hoiʹa·chin became king in his place.

^7 Never again did the king of Egypt venture out of his land, for the king of Babylon had taken all that belonged to the king of Egypt, from the Wadi[*] of Egypt up to the Eu·phraʹtes River.

^8 Je·hoiʹa·chin was 18 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ne·hushʹta the daughter of El·naʹthan of Jerusalem. ^9 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that his father had done. ^10 During that time the servants of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon came up against Jerusalem, and the city came under siege. ^11 King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon came to the city while his servants were laying siege to it.

^12 King Je·hoiʹa·chin of Judah went out to the king of Babylon, along with his mother, his servants, his princes, and his court officials; and the king of Babylon took him captive in the eighth year of his reign. ^13 Then he took out from there all the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.[*] He cut into pieces all the gold utensils that Solʹo·mon the king of Israel had made in the temple of Jehovah. This happened just as Jehovah had foretold. ^14 He took into exile all Jerusalem, all the princes, all the mighty warriors, and every craftsman and metalworker[*]—he took 10,000 into exile. No one was left behind except the poorest people of the land. ^15 Thus he took Je·hoiʹa·chin into exile to Babylon; he also led away the king’s mother, the king’s wives, his court officials, and the foremost men of the land, taking them into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon. ^16 The king of Babylon also took into exile to Babylon all the warriors, 7,000, as well as 1,000 craftsmen and metalworkers,[*] all of them mighty men and trained for war. ^17 The king of Babylon made Mat·ta·niʹah, Je·hoiʹa·chin’s uncle, king in his place and changed his name to Zed·e·kiʹah.

^18 Zed·e·kiʹah was 21 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·muʹtal the daughter of Jeremiah from Libʹnah. ^19 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Je·hoiʹa·kim had done. ^20 It was because of Jehovah’s anger that these things took place in Jerusalem and in Judah, until he cast them out of his sight. And Zed·e·kiʹah rebelled against the king of Babylon.

^ 2 Ki. 24:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Ki. 24:13 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 24:14 Or possibly, “builder of bulwarks.”

^ 2 Ki. 24:16 Or possibly, “builders of bulwarks.”

2 Kings  25 : 1 - 30

25 In the ninth year of Zed·e·kiʹah’s reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon came with all his army against Jerusalem. He camped against it and built a siege wall all around it, ^2 and the city was under siege until the 11th year of King Zed·e·kiʹah. ^3 On the ninth day of the fourth month the famine was severe in the city, and there was no food for the people of the land. ^4 The city wall was broken through, and all the soldiers fled by night through the gate between the double wall near the king’s garden, while the Chal·deʹans were surrounding the city; and the king went by the way of the Arʹa·bah. ^5 But the Chal·deʹan army pursued the king, and they overtook him in the desert plains of Jerʹi·cho, and all his troops were scattered from his side. ^6 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Ribʹlah, and they passed sentence on him. ^7 They slaughtered Zed·e·kiʹah’s sons before his eyes; then Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar blinded Zed·e·kiʹah’s eyes, bound him with copper fetters, and brought him to Babylon.

^8 In the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, that is, in the 19th year of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar the king of Babylon, Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard, the servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. ^9 He burned down the house of Jehovah, the king’s house,[*] and all the houses of Jerusalem; he also burned down the house of every prominent man. ^10 And the walls surrounding Jerusalem were pulled down by the entire Chal·deʹan army that was with the chief of the guard. ^11 Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard took into exile the rest of the people who were left in the city, the deserters who had gone over to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the population. ^12 But the chief of the guard left some of the poorest people of the land to serve as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers. ^13 And the Chal·deʹans broke into pieces the copper pillars of the house of Jehovah and the carriages and the copper Sea that were in the house of Jehovah, and they carried the copper away to Babylon. ^14 They also took the cans, the shovels, the extinguishers, the cups, and all the copper utensils used in the temple service. ^15 The chief of the guard took the fire holders and the bowls that were of genuine gold and silver. ^16 As for the two pillars, the Sea, and the carriages that Solʹo·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, the copper of all these articles was beyond weighing. ^17 Each pillar was 18 cubits[*] high, and the capital on it was of copper; and the height of the capital was three cubits, and the network and pomegranates all around on the capital were all made of copper. The second pillar with its network was like it.

^18 The chief of the guard also took Se·raiʹah the chief priest, Zeph·a·niʹah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. ^19 And he took from the city one court official who was the commissioner over the soldiers, five close associates of the king who were found in the city, as well as the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and 60 men of the common people of the land who were yet found in the city. ^20 Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Ribʹlah. ^21 The king of Babylon struck them down and put them to death at Ribʹlah in the land of Haʹmath. Thus Judah went into exile from its land.

^22 King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon appointed Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan over the people whom he had left behind in the land of Judah. ^23 When all the army chiefs and their men heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Ged·a·liʹah, they immediately came to Ged·a·liʹah at Mizʹpah. They were Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah, Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah, Se·raiʹah the son of Tan·huʹmeth the Ne·tophʹa·thite, and Ja·az·a·niʹah the son of the Ma·acʹa·thite, together with their men. ^24 Ged·a·liʹah swore an oath to them and their men and said to them: “Do not be afraid of being servants to the Chal·deʹans. Live in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with you.”

^25 And in the seventh month, Ishʹma·el son of Neth·a·niʹah son of E·lishʹa·ma, who was of the royal line,[*] came with ten other men, and they struck down Ged·a·liʹah and he died, along with the Jews and the Chal·deʹans who were with him in Mizʹpah. ^26 After that all the people, from small to great, including the army chiefs, rose up and went to Egypt, for they were afraid of the Chal·deʹans.

^27 And in the 37th year of the exile of King Je·hoiʹa·chin of Judah, in the 12th month, on the 27th day of the month, King Eʹvil-merʹo·dach of Babylon, in the year he became king, released[*] King Je·hoiʹa·chin of Judah from prison. ^28 He spoke kindly with him and put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. ^29 So Je·hoiʹa·chin took off his prison garments, and he regularly ate before him all the days of his life. ^30 A regular allowance of food was given him from the king, day after day, all the days of his life.

^ 2 Ki. 25:9 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Ki. 25:17 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ 2 Ki. 25:25 Lit., “the seed of the kingdom.”

^ 2 Ki. 25:27 Lit., “raised up the head of.”

1 Chronicles  2 : 1 - 55

2 These were the sons of Israel: Reuʹben, Simʹe·on, Leʹvi, Judah, Isʹsa·char, Zebʹu·lun, ^2 Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naphʹta·li, Gad, and Ashʹer.

^3 The sons of Judah were Er, Oʹnan, and Sheʹlah. These three were born to him from Shuʹa’s daughter, the Caʹnaan·it·ess. But Er, Judah’s firstborn, was displeasing to Jehovah, so He put him to death. ^4 Taʹmar, Judah’s daughter-in-law, bore to him Peʹrez and Zeʹrah. Judah had five sons in all.

^5 The sons of Peʹrez were Hezʹron and Haʹmul.

^6 The sons of Zeʹrah were Zimʹri, Eʹthan, Heʹman, Calʹcol, and Daʹra. There were five of them in all.

^7 The son[*] of Carʹmi was Aʹchar,[*] who brought disaster[*] on Israel, who was unfaithful with regard to what had been devoted to destruction.

^8 The son[*] of Eʹthan was Az·a·riʹah.

^9 The sons of Hezʹron who were born to him were Je·rahʹme·el, Ram, and Che·luʹbai.[*]

^10 Ram became father to Am·minʹa·dab. Am·minʹa·dab became father to Nahʹshon the chieftain of the descendants of Judah. ^11 Nahʹshon became father to Salʹma. Salʹma became father to Boʹaz. ^12 Boʹaz became father to Oʹbed. Oʹbed became father to Jesʹse. ^13 Jesʹse became father to his firstborn E·liʹab, A·binʹa·dab the second, Shimʹe·a the third, ^14 Ne·thanʹel the fourth, Radʹdai the fifth, ^15 Oʹzem the sixth, and David the seventh. ^16 Their sisters were Ze·ruʹiah and Abʹi·gail. The sons of Ze·ruʹiah were A·bishʹai, Joʹab, and Asʹa·hel, three. ^17 Abʹi·gail gave birth to A·maʹsa, and the father of A·maʹsa was Jeʹther the Ishʹma·el·ite.

^18 Caʹleb[*] the son of Hezʹron became father to sons by his wife A·zuʹbah and by Jerʹi·oth; and these were her sons: Jeʹsher, Shoʹbab, and Arʹdon. ^19 When A·zuʹbah died, Caʹleb married Ephʹrath, and she bore Hur to him. ^20 Hur became father to Uʹri. Uʹri became father to Bezʹal·el.

^21 Afterward Hezʹron had relations with the daughter of Maʹchir the father of Gilʹe·ad. He married her when he was 60 years old, and she bore Seʹgub to him. ^22 Seʹgub became father to Jaʹir, who had 23 cities in the land of Gilʹe·ad. ^23 Later Geshʹur and Syria took Havʹvoth-jaʹir from them, along with Keʹnath and its dependent[*] towns, 60 cities. All of these were the descendants of Maʹchir the father of Gilʹe·ad.

^24 After the death of Hezʹron in Caʹleb-ephʹra·thah, A·biʹjah the wife of Hezʹron bore him Ashʹhur the father of Te·koʹa.

^25 The sons of Je·rahʹme·el the firstborn of Hezʹron were Ram the firstborn, Buʹnah, Oʹren, Oʹzem, and A·hiʹjah. ^26 Je·rahʹme·el had another wife, whose name was Atʹa·rah. She was the mother of Oʹnam. ^27 The sons of Ram the firstborn of Je·rahʹme·el were Maʹaz, Jaʹmin, and Eʹker. ^28 The sons of Oʹnam were Shamʹmai and Jaʹda. The sons of Shamʹmai were Naʹdab and A·biʹshur. ^29 The name of A·biʹshur’s wife was Abʹi·ha·il, who bore him Ahʹban and Moʹlid. ^30 The sons of Naʹdab were Seʹled and Apʹpa·im. But Seʹled died without sons. ^31 The son[*] of Apʹpa·im was Ishʹi. And the son[*] of Ishʹi was Sheʹshan, and the son[*] of Sheʹshan, Ahʹlai. ^32 The sons of Jaʹda the brother of Shamʹmai were Jeʹther and Jonʹa·than. But Jeʹther died without sons. ^33 The sons of Jonʹa·than were Peʹleth and Zaʹza. These were the descendants of Je·rahʹme·el.

^34 Sheʹshan had no sons, only daughters. Now Sheʹshan had an Egyptian servant whose name was Jarʹha. ^35 Sheʹshan gave his daughter to be the wife of his servant Jarʹha, and she bore him Atʹtai. ^36 Atʹtai became father to Nathan. Nathan became father to Zaʹbad. ^37 Zaʹbad became father to Ephʹlal. Ephʹlal became father to Oʹbed. ^38 Oʹbed became father to Jeʹhu. Jeʹhu became father to Az·a·riʹah. ^39 Az·a·riʹah became father to Heʹlez. Heʹlez became father to El·e·aʹsah. ^40 El·e·aʹsah became father to Sisʹmai. Sisʹmai became father to Shalʹlum. ^41 Shalʹlum became father to Jek·a·miʹah. Jek·a·miʹah became father to E·lishʹa·ma.

^42 The sons of Caʹleb[*] the brother of Je·rahʹme·el were Meʹsha his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph, and the sons of Ma·reʹshah the father of Hebʹron. ^43 The sons of Hebʹron were Korʹah, Tapʹpu·ah, Reʹkem, and Sheʹma. ^44 Sheʹma became father to Raʹham the father of Jorʹke·am. Reʹkem became father to Shamʹmai. ^45 The son of Shamʹmai was Maʹon. Maʹon was the father of Beth-zur. ^46 Caʹleb’s concubine Eʹphah gave birth to Haʹran, Moʹza, and Gaʹzez. Haʹran became father to Gaʹzez. ^47 The sons of Jahʹdai were Reʹgem, Joʹtham, Geʹshan, Pelʹet, Eʹphah, and Shaʹaph. ^48 Caʹleb’s concubine Maʹa·cah gave birth to Sheʹber and Tirʹha·nah. ^49 In time she bore Shaʹaph the father of Mad·manʹnah and Sheʹva the father of Mach·beʹnah and Gibʹe·a. Caʹleb’s daughter was Achʹsah. ^50 These were the descendants of Caʹleb.

The sons of Hur the firstborn of Ephʹra·thah were Shoʹbal the father of Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim, ^51 Salʹma the father of Bethʹle·hem, and Haʹreph the father of Beth-gaʹder. ^52 Shoʹbal the father of Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim had sons: Ha·roʹeh and half of the Me·nuʹhoth. ^53 The families of Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim were the Ithʹrites, the Puʹthites, the Shuʹmath·ites, and the Mishʹra·ites. It was from these that the Zoʹrath·ites and the Eshʹta·ol·ites came. ^54 The sons of Salʹma were Bethʹle·hem, the Ne·tophʹa·thites, Atʹroth-beth-joʹab, half of the Man·a·haʹthites, and the Zorʹites. ^55 The families of the scribes dwelling at Jaʹbez were the Tiʹrath·ites, the Shimʹe·ath·ites, and the Suʹcath·ites. These were the Kenʹites who came from Hamʹmath the father of the house of Reʹchab.

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Meaning “Bringer of Disaster; Bringer of Ostracism.” In Jos 7:1, also called Achan.

^ 1 Chron. 2:7 Or “trouble; ostracism.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:8 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:9 Also called Caleb in vss. 18, 19, 42.

^ 1 Chron. 2:18 Also called Chelubai in vs. 9.

^ 1 Chron. 2:23 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:31 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 2:42 Also called Chelubai in vs. 9.

1 Chronicles  4 : 1 - 43

4 The sons of Judah were Peʹrez, Hezʹron, Carʹmi, Hur, and Shoʹbal. ^2 Re·aʹiah the son of Shoʹbal became father to Jaʹhath; Jaʹhath became father to A·huʹmai and Laʹhad. These were the families of the Zoʹrath·ites. ^3 These were the sons of the father of Eʹtam: Jezʹre·el, Ishʹma, and Idʹbash (and the name of their sister was Haz·ze·lel·poʹni), ^4 and Pe·nuʹel was the father of Geʹdor, and Eʹzer was the father of Huʹshah. These were the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephʹra·thah and the father of Bethʹle·hem. ^5 Ashʹhur the father of Te·koʹa had two wives, Heʹlah and Naʹa·rah. ^6 Naʹa·rah bore to him A·huzʹzam, Heʹpher, Teʹme·ni, and Ha·a·hashʹta·ri. These were the sons of Naʹa·rah. ^7 And the sons of Heʹlah were Zeʹreth, Izʹhar, and Ethʹnan. ^8 Koz became father to Aʹnub, Zo·beʹbah, and the families of A·harʹhel the son of Haʹrum.

^9 Jaʹbez was more honorable than his brothers; and his mother named him Jaʹbez,[*] saying: “I gave birth to him in pain.” ^10 Jaʹbez called on the God of Israel, saying: “O that you would bless me and enlarge my territory and let your hand be with me and preserve me from calamity, so that it may bring no harm to me!” So God brought about what he had asked for.

^11 Cheʹlub the brother of Shuʹhah became father to Meʹhir, who was the father of Eshʹton. ^12 Eshʹton became father to Beth-raʹpha, Pa·seʹah, and Te·hinʹnah, the father of Ir-naʹhash. These were the men of Reʹcah. ^13 And the sons of Keʹnaz were Othʹni·el and Se·raiʹah, and the son[*] of Othʹni·el was Haʹthath. ^14 Me·oʹno·thai became father to Ophʹrah. Se·raiʹah became father to Joʹab the father of Ge-harʹa·shim,[*] so called because they were craftsmen.

^15 The sons of Caʹleb the son of Je·phunʹneh were Iʹru, Eʹlah, and Naʹam; and the son[*] of Eʹlah was Keʹnaz. ^16 The sons of Je·halʹle·lel were Ziph, Ziʹphah, Tirʹi·a, and Asʹa·rel. ^17 The sons of Ezʹrah were Jeʹther, Meʹred, Eʹpher, and Jaʹlon; she[*] conceived and bore Mirʹi·am, Shamʹmai, and Ishʹbah the father of Esh·te·moʹa. ^18 (And his Jewish wife gave birth to Jeʹred the father of Geʹdor, Heʹber the father of Soʹco, and Je·kuʹthi·el the father of Za·noʹah.) These were the sons of Bi·thiʹah, the daughter of Pharʹaoh, whom Meʹred married.

^19 The sons of Ho·diʹah’s wife, the sister of Naʹham, were the fathers of Keiʹlah the Garʹmite and Esh·te·moʹa the Ma·acʹa·thite. ^20 And the sons of Shiʹmon were Amʹnon, Rinʹnah, Ben-haʹnan, and Tiʹlon. And the sons of Ishʹi were Zoʹheth and Ben-zoʹheth.

^21 The sons of Sheʹlah the son of Judah were Er the father of Leʹcah, Laʹa·dah the father of Ma·reʹshah, and the families of the workers of fine fabric of the house of Ash·beʹa, ^22 and Joʹkim, the men of Co·zeʹba, Joʹash, and Saʹraph, who became husbands of Moʹab·ite women, and Jashʹu·bi-leʹhem. These records are ancient.[*] ^23 They were potters who lived in Ne·taʹim and Ge·deʹrah. They lived there and worked for the king.

^24 The sons of Simʹe·on were Nemʹu·el, Jaʹmin, Jaʹrib, Zeʹrah, and Shaʹul. ^25 Shalʹlum was his son, Mibʹsam his son, and Mishʹma his son. ^26 And the sons of Mishʹma were Hamʹmu·el his son, Zacʹcur his son, Shimʹe·i his son. ^27 And Shimʹe·i had 16 sons and 6 daughters; but his brothers did not have many sons, and none of their families had as many as the men of Judah had. ^28 They lived in Beʹer-sheʹba, Mo·laʹdah, Haʹzar-shuʹal, ^29 Bilʹhah, Eʹzem, Toʹlad, ^30 Be·thuʹel, Horʹmah, Zikʹlag, ^31 Beth-marʹca·both, Haʹzar-suʹsim, Beth-birʹi, and Shaʹa·raʹim. These were their cities until the reign of David.

^32 Their settlements were Eʹtam, Aʹin, Rimʹmon, Toʹchen, and Aʹshan, five cities, ^33 along with their settlements that were all around these cities as far as Baʹal. These were their genealogical enrollments and the places where they lived. ^34 And Me·shoʹbab, Jamʹlech, Joʹshah the son of Am·a·ziʹah, ^35 Joel, Jeʹhu son of Josh·i·biʹah son of Se·raiʹah son of Asʹi·el, ^36 and Eli·o·eʹnai, Ja·a·koʹbah, Jesh·o·haiʹah, A·saiʹah, Adʹi·el, Je·simʹi·el, Be·naiʹah, ^37 and Ziʹza son of Shiʹphi son of Alʹlon son of Je·daʹiah son of Shimʹri son of She·maiʹah; ^38 these mentioned by name were the chieftains among their families, and the household of their forefathers increased in number. ^39 And they went to the entrance of Geʹdor, to the east side of the valley, to look for pastures for their flocks. ^40 They eventually found rich and good pastures, and the land was spacious, quiet, and undisturbed. Those who previously lived there were Hamʹites. ^41 These whose names are listed came during the days of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah and struck down the tents of the Hamʹites and the Me·uʹnim who were there. They devoted them to destruction down to this day; and they settled in their place because there were pastures for their flocks there.

^42 Some of the Simʹe·on·ites, 500 men, went to Mount Seʹir with Pel·a·tiʹah, Ne·a·riʹah, Re·phaʹiah, and Uzʹzi·el, the sons of Ishʹi who led them. ^43 And they struck down the rest of the A·malʹek·ites who had escaped, and they have lived there down to this day.

^ 1 Chron. 4:9 The name Jabez may be related to a Hebrew word meaning “pain.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:13 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:14 Meaning “Valley of Craftsmen.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:15 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 4:17 Possibly referring to Bithiah in vs. 18.

^ 1 Chron. 4:22 Or “The sayings are of old tradition.”

1 Chronicles  5 : 1 - 26

5 These are the sons of Reuʹben, Israel’s firstborn. He was the firstborn, but because he defiled[*] the bed of his father, his right as firstborn was given to the sons of Joseph the son of Israel, so he was not enrolled genealogically for the right of the firstborn. ^2 Though Judah was superior to his brothers and from him came the one to be the leader, the right as firstborn belonged to Joseph. ^3 The sons of Reuʹben the firstborn of Israel were Haʹnoch, Palʹlu, Hezʹron, and Carʹmi. ^4 The sons of Joel were She·maiʹah his son, Gog his son, Shimʹe·i his son, ^5 Miʹcah his son, Re·aʹiah his son, Baʹal his son, ^6 and Be·erʹah his son, whom King Tilʹgath-pil·neʹser of As·syrʹi·a took into exile; he was a chieftain of the Reuʹben·ites. ^7 His brothers by their families in the genealogical enrollment by their descendants were, as the head, Je·iʹel, Zech·a·riʹah, ^8 and Beʹla son of Aʹzaz son of Sheʹma son of Joel, who lived in A·roʹer and as far as Neʹbo and Baʹal-meʹon. ^9 To the east he settled as far as the beginning of the wilderness at the Eu·phraʹtes River, for their livestock had become numerous in the land of Gilʹe·ad. ^10 In the days of Saul, they waged war against the Hagʹrites, who were defeated before them, so they dwelled in their tents throughout all the territory east of Gilʹe·ad.

^11 Now the descendants of Gad lived next to them in the land of Baʹshan as far as Salʹe·cah. ^12 Joel was the head, Shaʹpham the second, and Jaʹnai and Shaʹphat in Baʹshan. ^13 And their brothers belonging to their paternal houses were Miʹcha·el, Me·shulʹlam, Sheʹba, Joʹrai, Jaʹcan, Ziʹa, and Eʹber, seven in all. ^14 These were the sons of Abʹi·ha·il son of Huʹri son of Ja·roʹah son of Gilʹe·ad son of Miʹcha·el son of Je·shishʹai son of Jahʹdo son of Buz. ^15 Aʹhi son of Abʹdi·el son of Guʹni was head of their paternal house. ^16 They lived in Gilʹe·ad, in Baʹshan and its dependent[*] towns, and in all the pastures of Sharʹon as far as they extended. ^17 They were all enrolled genealogically in the days of King Joʹtham of Judah and in the days of King Jer·o·boʹam[*] of Israel.

^18 The Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh had 44,760 mighty warriors in their army who carried shields and swords and were armed with bows,[*] and they were trained in war. ^19 They waged war against the Hagʹrites, Jeʹtur, Naʹphish, and Noʹdab. ^20 And they were helped in fighting them, so that the Hagʹrites and all who were with them were given into their hand, for they called to God for help in the war, and he responded to their entreaty because they trusted in him. ^21 They captured their livestock—50,000 camels, 250,000 sheep, and 2,000 donkeys—as well as 100,000 people.[*] ^22 Many had fallen slain, because the war was waged by the true God. And they lived in their place until the time of the exile.

^23 The descendants of the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh lived in the land from Baʹshan to Baʹal-herʹmon and Seʹnir and Mount Herʹmon. They were numerous. ^24 These were the heads of their paternal houses: Eʹpher, Ishʹi, Eʹli·el, Azʹri·el, Jeremiah, Hod·a·viʹah, and Jahʹdi·el; they were mighty warriors, men of fame, and heads of their paternal houses. ^25 But they acted unfaithfully toward the God of their forefathers and prostituted themselves to the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God had annihilated from before them. ^26 So the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of King Pul of As·syrʹi·a (that is, King Tilʹgath-pil·neʹser of As·syrʹi·a) so that he took into exile those of the Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh and brought them to Haʹlah, Haʹbor, Haʹra, and the river Goʹzan, where they are until this day.

^ 1 Chron. 5:1 Or “profaned.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:16 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:17 That is, Jeroboam II.

^ 1 Chron. 5:18 Lit., “and tread the bow.”

^ 1 Chron. 5:21 Or “human souls.”

1 Chronicles  6 : 1 - 81

6 The sons of Leʹvi were Gerʹshon, Koʹhath, and Me·rarʹi. ^2 The sons of Koʹhath were Amʹram, Izʹhar, Hebʹron, and Uzʹzi·el. ^3 The children[*] of Amʹram were Aaron, Moses, and also Mirʹi·am. And the sons of Aaron were Naʹdab, A·biʹhu, El·e·aʹzar, and Ithʹa·mar. ^4 El·e·aʹzar became father to Phinʹe·has; Phinʹe·has became father to Ab·i·shuʹa. ^5 Ab·i·shuʹa became father to Bukʹki; Bukʹki became father to Uzʹzi. ^6 Uzʹzi became father to Zer·a·hiʹah; Zer·a·hiʹah became father to Me·raʹioth. ^7 Me·raʹioth became father to Am·a·riʹah; Am·a·riʹah became father to A·hiʹtub. ^8 A·hiʹtub became father to Zaʹdok; Zaʹdok became father to A·himʹa·az. ^9 A·himʹa·az became father to Az·a·riʹah; Az·a·riʹah became father to Jo·haʹnan. ^10 Jo·haʹnan became father to Az·a·riʹah. He served as priest in the house that Solʹo·mon built in Jerusalem.

^11 Az·a·riʹah became father to Am·a·riʹah; Am·a·riʹah became father to A·hiʹtub. ^12 A·hiʹtub became father to Zaʹdok; Zaʹdok became father to Shalʹlum. ^13 Shalʹlum became father to Hil·kiʹah; Hil·kiʹah became father to Az·a·riʹah. ^14 Az·a·riʹah became father to Se·raiʹah; Se·raiʹah became father to Je·hozʹa·dak. ^15 And Je·hozʹa·dak went into exile when Jehovah took Judah and Jerusalem into exile by the hand of Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar.

^16 The sons of Leʹvi were Gerʹshom,[*] Koʹhath, and Me·rarʹi. ^17 These are the names of the sons of Gerʹshom: Libʹni and Shimʹe·i. ^18 The sons of Koʹhath were Amʹram, Izʹhar, Hebʹron, and Uzʹzi·el. ^19 The sons of Me·rarʹi were Mahʹli and Muʹshi.

These were the families of the Levites by their forefathers: ^20 Of Gerʹshom, Libʹni his son, Jaʹhath his son, Zimʹmah his son, ^21 Joʹah his son, Idʹdo his son, Zeʹrah his son, Je·athʹe·rai his son. ^22 The sons[*] of Koʹhath were Am·minʹa·dab his son, Korʹah his son, Asʹsir his son, ^23 El·kaʹnah his son, E·biʹa·saph his son, Asʹsir his son, ^24 Taʹhath his son, U·riʹel his son, Uz·ziʹah his son, and Shaʹul his son. ^25 The sons of El·kaʹnah were A·maʹsai and A·hiʹmoth. ^26 As for El·kaʹnah, the sons of El·kaʹnah were Zoʹphai his son, Naʹhath his son, ^27 E·liʹab his son, Je·roʹham his son, El·kaʹnah his son. ^28 The sons of Samuel were Joel the firstborn and A·biʹjah the second. ^29 The sons[*] of Me·rarʹi were Mahʹli, Libʹni his son, Shimʹe·i his son, Uzʹzah his son, ^30 Shimʹe·a his son, Hag·giʹah his son, and A·saiʹah his son.

^31 These were the ones whom David appointed to direct the singing at the house of Jehovah after the Ark came to rest there. ^32 They were responsible for the singing at the tabernacle of the tent of meeting until Solʹo·mon built the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem, and they carried out their service as prescribed for them. ^33 These are the men who served with their sons: Of the Koʹhath·ites, Heʹman the singer, son of Joel son of Samuel ^34 son of El·kaʹnah son of Je·roʹham son of Eʹli·el son of Toʹah ^35 son of Zuph son of El·kaʹnah son of Maʹhath son of A·maʹsai ^36 son of El·kaʹnah son of Joel son of Az·a·riʹah son of Zeph·a·niʹah ^37 son of Taʹhath son of Asʹsir son of E·biʹa·saph son of Korʹah ^38 son of Izʹhar son of Koʹhath son of Leʹvi son of Israel.

^39 His brother Aʹsaph stood at his right hand; Aʹsaph was son of Ber·e·chiʹah son of Shimʹe·a ^40 son of Miʹcha·el son of Ba·a·seʹiah son of Mal·chiʹjah ^41 son of Ethʹni son of Zeʹrah son of A·daiʹah ^42 son of Eʹthan son of Zimʹmah son of Shimʹe·i ^43 son of Jaʹhath son of Gerʹshom son of Leʹvi.

^44 The descendants of Me·rarʹi their brothers were at the left hand; there was Eʹthan son of Kishʹi son of Abʹdi son of Malʹluch ^45 son of Hash·a·biʹah son of Am·a·ziʹah son of Hil·kiʹah ^46 son of Amʹzi son of Baʹni son of Sheʹmer ^47 son of Mahʹli son of Muʹshi son of Me·rarʹi son of Leʹvi.

^48 Their brothers the Levites were appointed[*] for all the service of the tabernacle, the house of the true God. ^49 Aaron and his sons made the sacrifices smoke on the altar of burnt offering and on the altar of incense, performing the duties connected with the most holy things, to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of the true God had commanded. ^50 These were the descendants of Aaron: El·e·aʹzar his son, Phinʹe·has his son, Ab·i·shuʹa his son, ^51 Bukʹki his son, Uzʹzi his son, Zer·a·hiʹah his son, ^52 Me·raʹioth his son, Am·a·riʹah his son, A·hiʹtub his son, ^53 Zaʹdok his son, and A·himʹa·az his son.

^54 These were their settlements by their encampments[*] in their territory: for the descendants of Aaron belonging to the family of the Koʹhath·ites, as the first lot fell to them, ^55 they gave them Hebʹron in the land of Judah, with its surrounding pastures. ^56 But the field of the city and its settlements they gave to Caʹleb the son of Je·phunʹneh. ^57 And to the descendants of Aaron they gave the cities[*] of refuge, Hebʹron, also Libʹnah with its pastures, Jatʹtir, Esh·te·moʹa with its pastures, ^58 Hiʹlen with its pastures, Deʹbir with its pastures, ^59 Aʹshan with its pastures, and Beth-sheʹmesh with its pastures; ^60 and from the tribe of Benjamin, Geʹba with its pastures, Alʹe·meth with its pastures, and Anʹa·thoth with its pastures. All their cities for their families were 13 cities.

^61 To the rest of the Koʹhath·ites, there were allotted[*] ten cities, from the family of the tribe, from the half tribe, the half of Ma·nasʹseh.

^62 To the Gerʹshom·ites by their families they assigned 13 cities from the tribe of Isʹsa·char, the tribe of Ashʹer, the tribe of Naphʹta·li, and the tribe of Ma·nasʹseh in Baʹshan.

^63 To the Me·rarʹites by their families they assigned by lot 12 cities from the tribe of Reuʹben, the tribe of Gad, and the tribe of Zebʹu·lun.

^64 Thus the Israelites gave the Levites these cities with their pastures. ^65 Furthermore, they assigned by lot these cities from the tribe of Judah, the tribe of Simʹe·on, and the tribe of Benjamin, which are mentioned by their names.

^66 Some of the Koʹhath·ite families had cities from the tribe of Eʹphra·im as their territory. ^67 They gave them the cities[*] of refuge, Sheʹchem with its pastures in the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im, Geʹzer with its pastures, ^68 Jokʹme·am with its pastures, Beth-hoʹron with its pastures, ^69 Aiʹja·lon with its pastures, and Gath-rimʹmon with its pastures; ^70 and from half of the tribe of Ma·nasʹseh, Aʹner with its pastures and Bilʹe·am with its pastures, to the rest of the families of the Koʹhath·ites.

^71 To the Gerʹshom·ites they assigned from the family of the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh, Goʹlan in Baʹshan with its pastures and Ashʹta·roth with its pastures; ^72 and from the tribe of Isʹsa·char, Keʹdesh with its pastures, Dabʹe·rath with its pastures, ^73 Raʹmoth with its pastures, and Aʹnem with its pastures; ^74 and from the tribe of Ashʹer, Maʹshal with its pastures, Abʹdon with its pastures, ^75 Huʹkok with its pastures, and Reʹhob with its pastures; ^76 and from the tribe of Naphʹta·li, Keʹdesh in Galʹi·lee with its pastures, Hamʹmon with its pastures, and Kir·i·a·thaʹim with its pastures.

^77 To the rest of the Me·rarʹites they assigned from the tribe of Zebʹu·lun, Rimʹmo·no with its pastures, Taʹbor with its pastures; ^78 and in the region of the Jordan at Jerʹi·cho, to the east of the Jordan, from the tribe of Reuʹben, they were given Beʹzer in the wilderness with its pastures, Jaʹhaz with its pastures, ^79 Kedʹe·moth with its pastures, and Mephʹa·ath with its pastures; ^80 and from the tribe of Gad, Raʹmoth in Gilʹe·ad with its pastures, Ma·ha·naʹim with its pastures, ^81 Heshʹbon with its pastures, and Jaʹzer with its pastures.

^ 1 Chron. 6:3 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:16 Also called Gershon in vs. 1.

^ 1 Chron. 6:22 Or “descendants.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:29 Or “descendants.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:48 Lit., “were the ones given.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:54 Or “walled camps.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:57 Or possibly, “city,” in agreement with Jos 21:13.

^ 1 Chron. 6:61 Or “given by lot.”

^ 1 Chron. 6:67 Or possibly, “city,” in agreement with Jos 21:21.

1 Chronicles  7 : 1 - 40

7 Now the sons of Isʹsa·char were Toʹla, Puʹah, Jaʹshub, and Shimʹron—four. ^2 And the sons of Toʹla were Uzʹzi, Re·phaʹiah, Jeʹri·el, Jahʹmai, Ibʹsam, and She·muʹel, the heads of their paternal houses. Descended from Toʹla were mighty warriors, whose number in the days of David was 22,600. ^3 And the descendants[*] of Uzʹzi were Iz·ra·hiʹah and the sons of Iz·ra·hiʹah: Miʹcha·el, O·ba·diʹah, Joel, and Is·shiʹah—all five of them were chiefs.[*] ^4 And with them by their descendants, according to their paternal houses, there were 36,000 soldiers in their army available for war, for they had many wives and sons. ^5 And their brothers of all the families of Isʹsa·char were mighty warriors, 87,000 as listed in the genealogical enrollment.

^6 The sons of Benjamin were Beʹla, Beʹcher, and Je·diʹa·el—three. ^7 And the sons of Beʹla were Ezʹbon, Uzʹzi, Uzʹzi·el, Jerʹi·moth, and Iʹri—five—heads of their paternal houses, mighty warriors, and 22,034 were in their genealogical enrollment. ^8 And the sons of Beʹcher were Ze·miʹrah, Joʹash, E·li·eʹzer, Eli·o·eʹnai, Omʹri, Jerʹe·moth, A·biʹjah, Anʹa·thoth, and Alʹe·meth—all of these were the sons of Beʹcher. ^9 Their genealogical enrollment by their descendants as respects the heads of their paternal houses was 20,200 mighty warriors. ^10 And the sons of Je·diʹa·el were Bilʹhan and the sons of Bilʹhan: Jeʹush, Benjamin, Eʹhud, Che·naʹa·nah, Zeʹthan, Tarʹshish, and A·hishʹa·har. ^11 All of these were the sons of Je·diʹa·el, according to the heads of their forefathers, 17,200 mighty warriors ready to go out to the army for war.

^12 The Shupʹpim and the Hupʹpim were the sons of Ir; the Huʹshim were the sons of Aʹher.

^13 The sons of Naphʹta·li were Jahʹzi·el, Guʹni, Jeʹzer, and Shalʹlum—descendants[*] of Bilʹhah.

^14 The sons of Ma·nasʹseh: Asʹri·el, whom his Syrian concubine bore. (She bore Maʹchir the father of Gilʹe·ad. ^15 Maʹchir took a wife for Hupʹpim and for Shupʹpim, and the name of his sister was Maʹa·cah.) The name of the second was Ze·loʹphe·had, but Ze·loʹphe·had had daughters. ^16 Maʹa·cah, Maʹchir’s wife, bore a son and named him Peʹresh; and the name of his brother was Sheʹresh; and his sons were Uʹlam and Reʹkem. ^17 And the son[*] of Uʹlam was Beʹdan. These were the sons of Gilʹe·ad son of Maʹchir son of Ma·nasʹseh. ^18 And his sister was Ham·moʹle·cheth. She gave birth to Ishʹhod, Abi-eʹzer, and Mahʹlah. ^19 And the sons of She·miʹda were A·hiʹan, Sheʹchem, Likʹhi, and A·niʹam.

^20 The sons of Eʹphra·im were Shuʹthe·lah, Beʹred his son, Taʹhath his son, E·le·aʹdah his son, Taʹhath his son, ^21 Zaʹbad his son, Shuʹthe·lah his son, Eʹzer, and Eʹle·ad. The men of Gath who were born in the land killed them because they went down to take their livestock. ^22 Eʹphra·im their father carried on mourning for many days, and his brothers kept coming in to comfort him. ^23 Afterward he had relations with his wife, and she became pregnant and gave birth to a son. But he named him Be·riʹah[*] because it was with calamity that she was in his house. ^24 And his daughter was Sheʹe·rah, who built Lower and Upper Beth-hoʹron and Uzʹzen-sheʹe·rah. ^25 And there was Reʹphah his son, Reʹsheph, Teʹlah his son, Taʹhan his son, ^26 Laʹdan his son, Am·miʹhud his son, E·lishʹa·ma his son, ^27 Nun his son, and Joshua[*] his son.

^28 Their possession and their settlements were Bethʹel and its dependent[*] towns, and to the east Naʹa·ran, and to the west Geʹzer and its dependent towns, and Sheʹchem and its dependent towns, as far as Ayʹyah[*] and its dependent towns; ^29 and next to the descendants of Ma·nasʹseh, Beth-sheʹan and its dependent towns, Taʹa·nach and its dependent towns, Me·gidʹdo and its dependent towns, and Dor and its dependent towns. In these the descendants of Joseph the son of Israel lived.

^30 The sons of Ashʹer were Imʹnah, Ishʹvah, Ishʹvi, and Be·riʹah, and their sister was Seʹrah. ^31 The sons of Be·riʹah were Heʹber and Malʹchi·el, who was the father of Birʹza·ith. ^32 Heʹber became father to Japhʹlet, Shoʹmer, and Hoʹtham, and to Shuʹa their sister. ^33 The sons of Japhʹlet were Paʹsach, Bimʹhal, and Ashʹvath. These were the sons of Japhʹlet. ^34 The sons of Sheʹmer[*] were Aʹhi, Rohʹgah, Je·hubʹbah, and Aʹram. ^35 The sons of Heʹlem[*] his brother were Zoʹphah, Imʹna, Sheʹlesh, and Aʹmal. ^36 The sons of Zoʹphah were Suʹah, Harʹne·pher, Shuʹal, Beʹri, Imʹrah, ^37 Beʹzer, Hod, Shamʹma, Shilʹshah, Ithʹran, and Be·eʹra. ^38 The sons of Jeʹther were Je·phunʹneh, Pisʹpah, and Aʹra. ^39 The sons of Ulʹla were Aʹrah, Hanʹni·el, and Ri·ziʹa. ^40 All of these were the sons of Ashʹer, heads of their paternal houses, select, mighty warriors, heads of the chieftains; and their number listed in the genealogical enrollment was 26,000 men in the army available for war.

^ 1 Chron. 7:3 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:3 Lit., “heads.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:13 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:17 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:23 Meaning “With Calamity.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:27 Or “Jehoshua,” meaning “Jehovah Is Salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:28 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 7:28 Or possibly, “Gaza,” though not the Gaza in Philistia.

^ 1 Chron. 7:34 Also called Shomer in vs. 32.

^ 1 Chron. 7:35 Likely the same as “Hotham” in vs. 32.

1 Chronicles  9 : 1 - 44

9 All the Israelites were enrolled genealogically, and they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel. And Judah was taken into exile to Babylon for its unfaithfulness. ^2 The first inhabitants to return to their possession in their cities were some Israelites, the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants.[*] ^3 And some of the descendants of Judah, of Benjamin, of Eʹphra·im, and of Ma·nasʹseh settled in Jerusalem: ^4 Uʹthai son of Am·miʹhud son of Omʹri son of Imʹri son of Baʹni, of the descendants of Peʹrez son of Judah. ^5 And of the Shiʹlo·nites, A·saiʹah the firstborn and his sons. ^6 And of the sons of Zeʹrah, Je·uʹel and 690 of their brothers.

^7 And of the descendants of Benjamin, Salʹlu son of Me·shulʹlam son of Hod·a·viʹah son of Has·se·nuʹah, ^8 Ib·neʹiah son of Je·roʹham, Eʹlah son of Uzʹzi son of Michʹri, and Me·shulʹlam son of Sheph·a·tiʹah son of Reuʹel son of Ib·niʹjah. ^9 And their brothers by line of descent were 956. All these men were heads of their paternal houses.[*]

^10 And of the priests, there were Je·daʹiah, Je·hoiʹa·rib, Jaʹchin, ^11 Az·a·riʹah son of Hil·kiʹah son of Me·shulʹlam son of Zaʹdok son of Me·raʹioth son of A·hiʹtub, a leader of the house[*] of the true God, ^12 A·daiʹah son of Je·roʹham son of Pashʹhur son of Mal·chiʹjah, Maʹa·sai son of Adʹi·el son of Jahʹze·rah son of Me·shulʹlam son of Me·shilʹle·mith son of Imʹmer, ^13 and their brothers, heads of the paternal houses, 1,760 mighty, capable men available for the service of the house of the true God.

^14 And of the Levites, there were She·maiʹah son of Hasʹshub son of Az·riʹkam son of Hash·a·biʹah from the descendants of Me·rarʹi; ^15 and Bak·bakʹkar, Heʹresh, Gaʹlal, Mat·ta·niʹah son of Miʹca son of Zichʹri son of Aʹsaph, ^16 O·ba·diʹah son of She·maiʹah son of Gaʹlal son of Je·duʹthun, and Ber·e·chiʹah son of Aʹsa son of El·kaʹnah, who was dwelling in the settlements of the Ne·tophʹa·thites.

^17 The gatekeepers were Shalʹlum, Akʹkub, Talʹmon, A·hiʹman, and their brother Shalʹlum the head, ^18 and until then he was at the king’s gate to the east. These were the gatekeepers of the camps of the Levites. ^19 And Shalʹlum son of Koʹre son of E·biʹa·saph son of Korʹah, and his brothers of his paternal house, the Korʹah·ites, were over the duties of the service, the doorkeepers of the tent, and their fathers had been over the camp of Jehovah as the keepers of the entryway. ^20 It was Phinʹe·has the son of El·e·aʹzar who had been their leader in the past; Jehovah was with him. ^21 Zech·a·riʹah the son of Me·shel·e·miʹah was the gatekeeper of the entrance of the tent of meeting.

^22 All those selected as gatekeepers at the thresholds numbered 212. They were in their settlements by their genealogical enrollment. David and Samuel the seer appointed these to their office of trust. ^23 They and their sons were over the guard service for the gates of the house of Jehovah, the house of the tent. ^24 The gatekeepers were on the four sides—east, west, north, and south. ^25 From time to time, their brothers were to come in from their settlements for seven days to serve along with them. ^26 There were four chief[*] gatekeepers in the office of trust. They were Levites, and they were in charge of the chambers[*] and of the treasuries of the house of the true God. ^27 They would spend the night in their stations all around the house of the true God, for they cared for the guard service and were in charge of the key and would open up the house from morning to morning.

^28 Some of them were in charge of the utensils of the service; they would count them when they brought them in and count them when they took them out. ^29 Some of them were appointed over the utensils, over all the holy utensils, and over the fine flour, the wine, the oil, the frankincense, and the balsam oil. ^30 Some of the sons of the priests mixed the ointment of balsam oil. ^31 And Mat·ti·thiʹah of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shalʹlum the Korʹah·ite, was in the office of trust over the things baked in pans. ^32 Some of their brothers of the Koʹhath·ites were in charge of the layer bread,[*] to prepare it every sabbath.

^33 These were the singers, the heads of the paternal houses of the Levites in the chambers,[*] those set free from other duties; for by day and by night it was their responsibility to be on duty. ^34 These were the heads of the paternal houses of the Levites by their line of descent, headmen. These lived in Jerusalem.

^35 The father of Gibʹe·on, Je·iʹel, lived in Gibʹe·on. His wife’s name was Maʹa·cah. ^36 And his firstborn son was Abʹdon, followed by Zur, Kish, Baʹal, Ner, Naʹdab, ^37 Geʹdor, A·hiʹo, Zech·a·riʹah, and Mikʹloth. ^38 Mikʹloth became father to Shimʹe·am. And they all lived near their brothers in Jerusalem, along with their other brothers. ^39 Ner became father to Kish; Kish became father to Saul; Saul became father to Jonʹa·than, Malʹchi-shuʹa, A·binʹa·dab, and Esh·baʹal. ^40 And Jonʹa·than’s son was Merʹib-baʹal. Merʹib-baʹal became father to Miʹcah. ^41 And the sons of Miʹcah were Piʹthon, Melʹech, Tahrʹe·a, and Aʹhaz. ^42 Aʹhaz became father to Jaʹrah; Jaʹrah became father to Alʹe·meth, Azʹma·veth, and Zimʹri. Zimʹri became father to Moʹza. ^43 Moʹza became father to Binʹe·a and Re·phaʹiah his son, El·e·aʹsah his son, Aʹzel his son. ^44 Aʹzel had six sons, and their names were Az·riʹkam, Boʹche·ru, Ishʹma·el, She·a·riʹah, O·ba·diʹah, and Haʹnan. These were the sons of Aʹzel.

^ 1 Chron. 9:2 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:9 Lit., “heads of fathers for the house of their fathers.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:11 Or “temple.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:26 Lit., “mighty.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:26 Or “dining rooms.”

^ 1 Chron. 9:32 That is, the showbread.

^ 1 Chron. 9:33 Or “dining rooms.”

1 Chronicles  10 : 1 - 14

10 Now the Phi·lisʹtines were fighting against Israel. And the men of Israel fled from before the Phi·lisʹtines, and many fell slain on Mount Gil·boʹa. ^2 The Phi·lisʹtines kept in close range of Saul and his sons, and the Phi·lisʹtines struck down Jonʹa·than, A·binʹa·dab, and Malʹchi-shuʹa, Saul’s sons. ^3 The fighting grew fierce against Saul, and the archers found him, and he was wounded by the archers. ^4 Then Saul said to his armor-bearer: “Draw your sword and run me through with it, so that these uncircumcised men may not come and deal ruthlessly[*] with me.” But his armor-bearer was unwilling, because he was very much afraid. So Saul took the sword and fell on it. ^5 When his armor-bearer saw that Saul was dead, he too fell on his own sword and died. ^6 Thus Saul and his three sons died, and all those of his house died together. ^7 When all the people of Israel in the valley[*] saw that everyone had fled and that Saul and his sons had died, they began to abandon their cities and flee; the Phi·lisʹtines then came and occupied them.

^8 The next day, when the Phi·lisʹtines came to strip the slain, they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gil·boʹa. ^9 So they stripped him and took off his head and his armor, and they sent word throughout the land of the Phi·lisʹtines to spread the news to their idols and the people. ^10 Then they put his armor in the house[*] of their god and fastened his skull to the house of Daʹgon.

^11 When all those of Jaʹbesh in Gilʹe·ad heard about all that the Phi·lisʹtines had done to Saul, ^12 all the warriors rose up and carried off the corpse of Saul and the corpses of his sons. They brought them to Jaʹbesh and buried their bones under the big tree in Jaʹbesh, and they fasted for seven days.

^13 Thus Saul died for the unfaithfulness he had shown against Jehovah because he had not obeyed the word of Jehovah, also for consulting a spirit medium ^14 instead of inquiring of Jehovah. So He put him to death and turned the kingship over to David the son of Jesʹse.

^ 1 Chron. 10:4 Or “abusively.”

^ 1 Chron. 10:7 Or “low plain.”

^ 1 Chron. 10:10 Or “temple.”

1 Chronicles  11 : 1 - 47

11 In time all the Israelites gathered to David at Hebʹron and said: “Look! We are your own bone and flesh.[*] ^2 In times past while Saul was king, you were the one who was leading Israel on its campaigns.[*] And Jehovah your God said to you: ‘You will shepherd my people Israel, and you will become leader over my people Israel.’” ^3 So all the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebʹron, and David made a covenant with them in Hebʹron before Jehovah. Then they anointed David as king over Israel, according to Jehovah’s word through Samuel.

^4 Later David and all Israel set out for Jerusalem, that is, Jeʹbus, where the Jebʹu·sites were inhabiting the land. ^5 The inhabitants of Jeʹbus taunted David: “You will never come in here!” However, David captured the stronghold of Zion, which is now the City of David. ^6 So David said: “Whoever is the first to strike the Jebʹu·sites will become chief[*] and prince.” And Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah went up first, and he became the chief. ^7 Then David took up residence in the stronghold. That is why they called it the City of David. ^8 He began to build up the city all around, from the Mound[*] to the areas around it, and Joʹab restored the rest of the city. ^9 Thus David became greater and greater, and Jehovah of armies was with him.

^10 Now these are the heads of David’s mighty warriors, who gave him strong support in his kingship, together with all Israel, to make him king according to Jehovah’s word concerning Israel. ^11 This is the list of David’s mighty warriors: Ja·shoʹbe·am the son of a Hachʹmon·ite, the head of the three. He brandished his spear over 300 slain at one time. ^12 Next to him was El·e·aʹzar the son of Doʹdo the A·hoʹhite. He was among the three mighty warriors. ^13 He was with David at Pas-damʹmim, where the Phi·lisʹtines had gathered together for war. Now there was a plot of land full of barley, and the people had fled because of the Phi·lisʹtines. ^14 But he took his stand in the middle of the field and defended it and kept striking down the Phi·lisʹtines, so that Jehovah brought about a great victory.[*]

^15 Three of the 30 headmen went down to the rock, to David at the cave of A·dulʹlam, while a Phi·lisʹtine army was camped in the Valley[*] of Rephʹa·im. ^16 David was then in the stronghold, and a garrison of the Phi·lisʹtines was in Bethʹle·hem. ^17 Then David expressed his longing: “If only I could have a drink of the water from the cistern by the gate of Bethʹle·hem!” ^18 At that the three forced their way into the camp of the Phi·lisʹtines and drew water from the cistern by the gate of Bethʹle·hem and brought it to David; but David refused to drink it and poured it out to Jehovah. ^19 He said: “It is unthinkable on my part from the standpoint of my God to do this! Should I drink the blood of these men who risked their lives?[*] For it was at the risk of their lives[*] that they brought it.” So he refused to drink it. These are the things that his three mighty warriors did.

^20 A·bishʹai the brother of Joʹab became head of another three; he brandished his spear over 300 slain, and he had a reputation like the three. ^21 Of the other three, he was more distinguished than two of them, and he was their chief; yet he did not attain to the rank of the first three.

^22 Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was a courageous man[*] who performed many exploits in Kabʹze·el. He struck down the two sons of Arʹi·el of Moʹab, and he descended into a waterpit on a snowy day and killed a lion. ^23 He also struck down an Egyptian man of extraordinary size—five cubits[*] tall. Though the Egyptian had a spear in his hand like the beam of loom workers, he went against him with a rod and snatched the spear away from the Egyptian’s hand and killed him with his own spear. ^24 These things Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da did, and he had a reputation like that of the three mighty warriors. ^25 Although he was distinguished even more than the thirty, he did not attain to the rank of the three. However, David appointed him over his own bodyguard.

^26 The mighty warriors of the military forces were Asʹa·hel the brother of Joʹab, El·haʹnan the son of Doʹdo of Bethʹle·hem, ^27 Shamʹmoth the Haʹro·rite, Heʹlez the Pelʹo·nite, ^28 Iʹra the son of Ikʹkesh the Te·koʹite, Abi-eʹzer the Anʹa·thoth·ite, ^29 Sibʹbe·cai the Huʹshath·ite, Iʹlai the A·hoʹhite, ^30 Maʹha·rai the Ne·tophʹa·thite, Heʹled the son of Baʹa·nah the Ne·tophʹa·thite, ^31 Iʹthai the son of Riʹbai of Gibʹe·ah of the Benʹja·min·ites, Be·naiʹah the Pirʹa·thon·ite, ^32 Huʹrai of the wadis[*] of Gaʹash, A·biʹel the Arʹbath·ite, ^33 Azʹma·veth the Ba·haʹrum·ite, E·liʹah·ba the Sha·alʹbo·nite, ^34 the sons of Haʹshem the Giʹzo·nite, Jonʹa·than the son of Shaʹgee the Harʹa·rite, ^35 A·hiʹam the son of Saʹcar the Harʹa·rite, E·liʹphal the son of Ur, ^36 Heʹpher the Me·cheʹrath·ite, A·hiʹjah the Pelʹo·nite, ^37 Hezʹro the Carʹmel·ite, Naʹa·rai the son of Ezʹbai, ^38 Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibʹhar the son of Hagʹri, ^39 Zeʹlek the Amʹmon·ite, Naʹha·rai the Be·rothʹite, the armor-bearer of Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah; ^40 Iʹra the Ithʹrite, Gaʹreb the Ithʹrite, ^41 U·riʹah the Hitʹtite, Zaʹbad the son of Ahʹlai, ^42 Adʹi·na the son of Shiʹza the Reuʹben·ite, a head of the Reuʹben·ites, and 30 with him; ^43 Haʹnan the son of Maʹa·cah, Joshʹa·phat the Mithʹnite, ^44 Uz·ziʹa the Ashʹte·rath·ite, Shaʹma and Je·iʹel, the sons of Hoʹtham the A·roʹer·ite; ^45 Je·diʹa·el the son of Shimʹri, and Joʹha his brother the Tiʹzite; ^46 Eʹli·el the Maʹha·vite, Jerʹi·bai and Josh·a·viʹah the sons of Elʹna·am, and Ithʹmah the Moʹab·ite; ^47 Eʹli·el, Oʹbed, and Ja·a·siʹel the Me·zoʹba·ite.

^ 1 Chron. 11:1 Or “your blood relatives.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:2 Lit., “the one bringing out and the one bringing in Israel.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:6 Lit., “head.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:8 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:14 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:15 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:19 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:19 Or “souls.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:22 Lit., “the son of a man of valor.”

^ 1 Chron. 11:23 His height was about 2.23 m (7.3 ft). See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 11:32 See Glossary.

1 Chronicles  12 : 1 - 40

12 These were the men who came to David at Zikʹlag while he was unable to move about freely because of Saul the son of Kish, and they were among the mighty warriors who supported him in battle. ^2 They were armed with the bow, and they could use both the right hand and the left hand to sling stones or to shoot arrows with the bow. They were of the brothers of Saul, from Benjamin. ^3 The head was A·hi·eʹzer, along with Joʹash, both sons of She·maʹah the Gibʹe·ath·ite; Jeʹzi·el and Pelʹet the sons of Azʹma·veth, Berʹa·cah, Jeʹhu the Anʹa·thoth·ite, ^4 Ish·maʹiah the Gibʹe·on·ite, a mighty warrior among the thirty and over the thirty; also Jeremiah, Ja·ha·ziʹel, Jo·haʹnan, Joʹza·bad the Ge·deʹrath·ite, ^5 E·luʹzai, Jerʹi·moth, Be·a·liʹah, Shem·a·riʹah, Sheph·a·tiʹah the Harʹi·phite, ^6 El·kaʹnah, Is·shiʹah, Azʹar·el, Jo·eʹzer, and Ja·shoʹbe·am, the Korʹah·ites; ^7 and Jo·eʹlah and Zeb·a·diʹah the sons of Je·roʹham of Geʹdor.

^8 Some of the Gadʹites went over to David’s side at the stronghold in the wilderness; they were mighty warriors, soldiers trained for war, standing ready with the large shield and the lance, whose faces were like those of lions and who were as swift as the gazelles on the mountains. ^9 Eʹzer was the head, O·ba·diʹah the second, E·liʹab the third, ^10 Mish·manʹnah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, ^11 Atʹtai the sixth, Eʹli·el the seventh, ^12 Jo·haʹnan the eighth, El·zaʹbad the ninth, ^13 Jeremiah the tenth, Machʹban·nai the eleventh. ^14 These were of the Gadʹites, heads of the army. The least one was equal to 100, and the greatest to 1,000. ^15 These are the men who crossed the Jordan in the first month when it was overflowing its banks, and they chased away all those living in the lowlands, to the east and to the west.

^16 Some of the men of Benjamin and Judah also came to David at his stronghold. ^17 Then David went out before them and said to them: “If you have come to me in peace to help me, my heart will be united with you. But if it is to betray me to my adversaries when my hands have done no wrong, let the God of our forefathers see it and judge.” ^18 Then the spirit came upon[*] A·maʹsai, the head of the thirty:

“We are yours, O David, and we are with you, O son of Jesʹse.

Peace, peace be yours, and peace to the one helping you,

For your God is helping you.”

So David received them and appointed them among the heads of the troops.

^19 Some from Ma·nasʹseh also deserted to David when he came with the Phi·lisʹtines to battle against Saul; but he did not help the Phi·lisʹtines, for after consultation, the lords of the Phi·lisʹtines sent him away, saying: “He will desert to his lord Saul, and it will cost us our heads.” ^20 When he went to Zikʹlag, these deserted to him from Ma·nasʹseh: Adʹnah, Joʹza·bad, Je·diʹa·el, Miʹcha·el, Joʹza·bad, E·liʹhu, and Zilʹle·thai, heads of the thousands of Ma·nasʹseh. ^21 They helped David against the marauder band, because all of them were mighty, courageous men, and they became chiefs in the army. ^22 Day after day people kept coming to David to help him until it was a camp as great as the camp of God.

^23 This is the number of the heads of those armed for battle who came to David at Hebʹron to turn the kingship of Saul over to him according to Jehovah’s order. ^24 The men of Judah carrying the large shield and the lance were 6,800, armed for battle. ^25 Of the Simʹe·on·ites, the mighty, courageous men of the army were 7,100.

^26 Of the Levites, 4,600. ^27 Je·hoiʹa·da was the leader of the sons of Aaron, and with him were 3,700, ^28 as well as Zaʹdok, a mighty and courageous young man, along with 22 chiefs from his paternal house.

^29 Of the Benʹja·min·ites, the brothers of Saul, there were 3,000, of whom the greater number had previously been guarding the interests of the house of Saul. ^30 Of the Eʹphra·im·ites, there were 20,800 mighty, courageous men of fame among their paternal houses.

^31 Of the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh, there were 18,000 who had been designated by name to come to make David king. ^32 Of the tribe of Isʹsa·char, who understood the times and knew what Israel should do, there were 200 of their headmen, and all their brothers were under their command. ^33 Of Zebʹu·lun, there were 50,000 who could serve in the army, drawing up in battle formation with all the weapons of war, all joining David with undivided loyalty.[*] ^34 Of Naphʹta·li, there were 1,000 chiefs, and with them were 37,000 with the large shield and the spear. ^35 Of the Danʹites, those drawing up in battle formation were 28,600. ^36 And of Ashʹer, those who could serve in the army for drawing up in battle formation were 40,000.

^37 From across the Jordan, of the Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh, there were 120,000 soldiers with all kinds of weapons of war. ^38 All of these were men of war, joining together in battle line; they came with a complete heart to Hebʹron to make David king over all Israel, and also all the rest of Israel were united in wanting[*] to make David king. ^39 And they remained there with David for three days, eating and drinking, for their brothers had made preparation for them. ^40 Also those near them, and even those as far as Isʹsa·char, Zebʹu·lun, and Naphʹta·li, were bringing food on donkeys, camels, mules, and cattle—provisions of flour, cakes of pressed figs and raisins, wine, oil, and cattle and sheep in great quantity, for there was rejoicing in Israel.

^ 1 Chron. 12:18 Lit., “clothed.”

^ 1 Chron. 12:33 Or “all those joining David were not doublehearted.”

^ 1 Chron. 12:38 Lit., “were of one heart.”

1 Chronicles  13 : 1 - 14

13 David consulted with the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds and with every leader. ^2 Then David said to all the congregation of Israel: “If it seems good to you and it is acceptable to Jehovah our God, let us send word to our remaining brothers in all regions of Israel and also to the priests and the Levites in their cities with pastures to come and join us. ^3 And let us bring back the Ark of our God.” For they had not cared for it in the days of Saul. ^4 All the congregation agreed to do that, for it seemed right to all the people. ^5 So David congregated all Israel, from the river[*] of Egypt as far as Leʹbo-haʹmath,[*] to bring the Ark of the true God from Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim.

^6 David and all Israel went up to Baʹal·ah, to Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim, which belongs to Judah, to bring up from there the Ark of the true God, Jehovah, who sits enthroned above[*] the cherubs, where his name is called on. ^7 However, they placed the Ark of the true God on a new wagon and brought it from the house of A·binʹa·dab, and Uzʹzah and A·hiʹo were leading the wagon. ^8 David and all Israel were celebrating before the true God with all their might, accompanied by songs, harps, other stringed instruments, tambourines, cymbals, and trumpets. ^9 But when they came to the threshing floor of Chiʹdon, Uzʹzah thrust his hand out and grabbed hold of the Ark, for the cattle nearly upset it. ^10 At that Jehovah’s anger blazed against Uzʹzah, and He struck him down because he had thrust his hand out to the Ark, and he died there before God. ^11 But David became angry[*] because Jehovah’s wrath had broken through against Uzʹzah; and that place has been called Peʹrez-uzʹzah[*] down to this day.

^12 So David became fearful of the true God on that day and said: “How can I bring the Ark of the true God to me?” ^13 David did not bring the Ark to where he was in the City of David, but he had it taken to the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom the Gitʹtite. ^14 The Ark of the true God was with the household of Oʹbed-eʹdom, remaining at his house for three months, and Jehovah kept blessing the household of Oʹbed-eʹdom and all he had.

^ 1 Chron. 13:5 Or “from Shihor.”

^ 1 Chron. 13:5 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ 1 Chron. 13:6 Or possibly, “between.”

^ 1 Chron. 13:11 Or “upset.”

^ 1 Chron. 13:11 Meaning “Breach Against Uzzah.”

1 Chronicles  15 : 1 - 29

15 And he continued building houses for himself in the City of David, and he prepared a place for the Ark of the true God and pitched a tent for it. ^2 It was then that David said: “No one is to carry the Ark of the true God except the Levites, for Jehovah has chosen them to carry the Ark of Jehovah and to minister to him always.” ^3 Then David congregated all Israel at Jerusalem to bring the Ark of Jehovah up to the place that he had prepared for it.

^4 David gathered the descendants of Aaron and the Levites: ^5 from the Koʹhath·ites, U·riʹel the chief and 120 of his brothers; ^6 from the Me·rarʹites, A·saiʹah the chief and 220 of his brothers; ^7 from the Gerʹshom·ites, Joel the chief and 130 of his brothers; ^8 from the descendants of E·li·zaʹphan, She·maiʹah the chief and 200 of his brothers; ^9 from the descendants of Hebʹron, Eʹli·el the chief and 80 of his brothers; ^10 from the descendants of Uzʹzi·el, Am·minʹa·dab the chief and 112 of his brothers. ^11 Furthermore, David called the priests Zaʹdok and A·biʹa·thar and the Levites U·riʹel, A·saiʹah, Joel, She·maiʹah, Eʹli·el, and Am·minʹa·dab, ^12 and he said to them: “You are the heads of the paternal houses of the Levites. Sanctify yourselves, you and your brothers, and bring the Ark of Jehovah the God of Israel up to the place that I have prepared for it. ^13 Since you did not carry it the first time, the anger of Jehovah our God broke out against us, because we did not search out the proper procedure.” ^14 So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the Ark of Jehovah the God of Israel.

^15 Then the Levites carried the Ark of the true God on their shoulders with the poles, just as Moses had commanded by Jehovah’s word. ^16 David then told the chiefs of the Levites to appoint their brothers the singers to sing out joyfully, accompanied by musical instruments: stringed instruments, harps, and cymbals.

^17 So the Levites appointed Heʹman the son of Joel and, of his brothers, Aʹsaph the son of Ber·e·chiʹah and, of the Me·rarʹites their brothers, Eʹthan the son of Kush·aʹiah. ^18 Together with them were their brothers of the second division, Zech·a·riʹah, Ben, Ja·aʹzi·el, She·mirʹa·moth, Je·hiʹel, Unʹni, E·liʹab, Be·naiʹah, Ma·a·seiʹah, Mat·ti·thiʹah, E·liphʹe·le·hu, and Mik·neʹiah and Oʹbed-eʹdom and Je·iʹel the gatekeepers. ^19 The singers Heʹman, Aʹsaph, and Eʹthan were to play the copper cymbals; ^20 and Zech·a·riʹah, Aʹzi·el, She·mirʹa·moth, Je·hiʹel, Unʹni, E·liʹab, Ma·a·seiʹah, and Be·naiʹah played stringed instruments tuned to Alʹa·moth;[*] ^21 and Mat·ti·thiʹah, E·liphʹe·le·hu, Mik·neʹiah, Oʹbed-eʹdom, Je·iʹel, and Az·a·ziʹah played harps tuned to Shemʹi·nith,[*] to act as directors. ^22 Chen·a·niʹah the chief of the Levites supervised the transport, for he was an expert, ^23 and Ber·e·chiʹah and El·kaʹnah were gatekeepers for the Ark. ^24 The priests Sheb·a·niʹah, Joshʹa·phat, Ne·thanʹel, A·maʹsai, Zech·a·riʹah, Be·naiʹah, and E·li·eʹzer loudly sounded the trumpets before the Ark of the true God, and Oʹbed-eʹdom and Je·hiʹah also served as gatekeepers for the Ark.

^25 Then David and the elders of Israel and the chiefs of the thousands were walking along to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah up from the house of Oʹbed-eʹdom with rejoicing. ^26 When the true God helped the Levites who were carrying the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, they sacrificed seven young bulls and seven rams. ^27 David was dressed in a sleeveless coat of fine fabric, as were all the Levites carrying the Ark, the singers, and Chen·a·niʹah the chief of the transport and the singers; David was also wearing a linen ephʹod. ^28 All the Israelites were bringing up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah with joyful shouting, with the sound of the horn, with trumpets, with cymbals, playing loudly on stringed instruments and harps.

^29 But when the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came to the City of David, Saul’s daughter Miʹchal looked down through the window and saw King David skipping about and celebrating; and she began to despise him in her heart.

^ 1 Chron. 15:20 See Glossary.

^ 1 Chron. 15:21 See Glossary.

1 Chronicles  17 : 1 - 27

17 As soon as David was settled in his own house,[*] he said to Nathan the prophet: “Here I am living in a house of cedars while the ark of the covenant of Jehovah is under tent cloths.” ^2 Nathan replied to David: “Do whatever is in your heart, for the true God is with you.”

^3 On that very night, the word of God came to Nathan, saying: ^4 “Go and say to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “You are not the one who will build the house for me to dwell in. ^5 For I have not dwelled in a house from the day I brought Israel out to this day, but I continued going from tent to tent and from one tabernacle to another.[*] ^6 During all the time that I went with all Israel, did I ever say one word to any of the judges of Israel whom I appointed to shepherd my people, saying, ‘Why did you not build a house of cedars for me?’”’

^7 “Now say this to my servant David, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “I took you from the pastures, from following the flock, to become a leader over my people Israel. ^8 And I will be with you wherever you go, and I will do away with[*] all your enemies from before you; and I will make a name for you like the name of the great men of the earth. ^9 I will appoint a place for my people Israel and settle them, and they will live there and not be disturbed anymore; and wicked men will not oppress them[*] again as they did in the past, ^10 from the day that I appointed judges over my people Israel. And I will subdue all your enemies. Moreover, I tell you, ‘Jehovah will build a house[*] for you.’

^11 “‘“When your days come to an end and you go to be with your forefathers, I will raise up your offspring[*] after you, one of your sons, and I will firmly establish his kingship. ^12 He is the one who will build a house for me, and I will firmly establish his throne forever. ^13 I will become his father, and he will become my son. I will not remove my loyal love from him the way I removed it from the one who was prior to you. ^14 I will cause him to stand in my house and in my kingship forever, and his throne will last forever.”’”

^15 Nathan told David all these words and this entire vision.

^16 At that King David came in and sat down before Jehovah and said: “Who am I, O Jehovah God? And what is my house that you have brought me this far? ^17 As if this were not enough, O God, you also speak about the house of your servant down to a distant future time, and you have looked on me as if I were a man who should be further exalted,[*] O Jehovah God. ^18 What more can your servant David say to you about the honor given me when you know your servant so well? ^19 O Jehovah, for the sake of your servant and in agreement with your heart[*] you have done all these great things by revealing your greatness. ^20 O Jehovah, there is no one like you, and there is no God except you; everything we have heard with our ears confirms this. ^21 And what other nation on earth is like your people Israel? The true God went and redeemed them as his people. You made a name for yourself by your great and awe-inspiring deeds, driving out nations from before your people, whom you redeemed from Egypt. ^22 You made your people Israel your own people for all time; and you, O Jehovah, became their God. ^23 Now, O Jehovah, may the promise you have made concerning your servant and his house prove faithful for all time, and may you do just as you have promised. ^24 May your name endure[*] and be exalted forever, so that people may say, ‘Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, is God to Israel,’ and may the house of your servant David be firmly established before you. ^25 For you, my God, have revealed to your servant your purpose to build him a house.[*] That is why your servant has the confidence to offer this prayer to you. ^26 And now, O Jehovah, you are the true God, and you have promised these good things concerning your servant. ^27 So may it please you to bless the house of your servant, and may it continue forever before you, for you, O Jehovah, have blessed, and it is blessed forever.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:1 Or “palace.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:5 Possibly meaning “from one tent site to another and from one dwelling place to another.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:8 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:9 Lit., “wear them out.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:10 Or “dynasty.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:11 Lit., “seed.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:17 Or “a man of high station.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:19 Or “in harmony with your will.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:24 Or “prove faithful.”

^ 1 Chron. 17:25 Or “dynasty.”

1 Chronicles  18 : 1 - 17

18 Some time later, David defeated the Phi·lisʹtines and subdued them and took Gath and its dependent[*] towns out of the hands of the Phi·lisʹtines. ^2 Then he defeated Moʹab, and the Moʹab·ites became David’s servants and brought tribute.

^3 David defeated King Had·ad·eʹzer of Zoʹbah near Haʹmath as he was on his way to establish his authority at the Eu·phraʹtes River. ^4 David captured 1,000 chariots, 7,000 horsemen, and 20,000 foot soldiers from him. Then David hamstrung all but 100 of the chariot horses. ^5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help King Had·ad·eʹzer of Zoʹbah, David struck down 22,000 of the Syrians. ^6 David then established garrisons in Syria of Damascus, and the Syrians became David’s servants and brought tribute. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. ^7 Moreover, David took the circular shields of gold from the servants of Had·ad·eʹzer and brought them to Jerusalem. ^8 From Tibʹhath and Cun, cities of Had·ad·eʹzer, David took a great quantity of copper. With it Solʹo·mon made the copper Sea, the pillars, and the copper utensils.

^9 When King Toʹu of Haʹmath heard that David had defeated the entire army of King Had·ad·eʹzer of Zoʹbah, ^10 he immediately sent his son Ha·doʹram to King David to ask about his welfare and to congratulate him because he had fought and defeated Had·ad·eʹzer (for Had·ad·eʹzer had often fought against Toʹu), and he brought all sorts of articles of gold, silver, and copper. ^11 King David sanctified these to Jehovah, along with the silver and the gold that he had carried off from all the nations: from Eʹdom and Moʹab, from the Amʹmon·ites, the Phi·lisʹtines, and the A·malʹek·ites.

^12 A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah struck down 18,000 Eʹdom·ites in the Valley of Salt. ^13 He established garrisons in Eʹdom, and all the Eʹdom·ites became David’s servants. Jehovah gave David victory[*] wherever he went. ^14 David kept reigning over all Israel, and he was administering justice and righteousness for all his people. ^15 Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah was over the army, Je·hoshʹa·phat the son of A·hiʹlud was recorder, ^16 Zaʹdok the son of A·hiʹtub and A·himʹe·lech the son of A·biʹa·thar were priests, and Shavʹsha was secretary. ^17 Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da was over the Cherʹe·thites and the Pelʹe·thites. And David’s sons were first in position next to the king.

^ 1 Chron. 18:1 Or “surrounding.”

^ 1 Chron. 18:6 Or “salvation.”

^ 1 Chron. 18:13 Or “salvation.”

1 Chronicles  19 : 1 - 19

19 Later Naʹhash the king of the Amʹmon·ites died, and his son became king in his place. ^2 At that David said: “I will show loyal love toward Haʹnun the son of Naʹhash, because his father showed loyal love toward me.” So David sent messengers to offer him comfort over the loss of his father. But when David’s servants came into the land of the Amʹmon·ites to comfort Haʹnun, ^3 the princes of the Amʹmon·ites said to Haʹnun: “Do you think that David is honoring your father by sending comforters to you? Is it not to make a thorough search and to overthrow you and to spy out the land that his servants have come to you?” ^4 So Haʹnun took the servants of David and shaved them and cut their garments in half at their buttocks and sent them away. ^5 When David was told about the men, he at once sent others to meet them, because the men had been deeply humiliated; and the king told them: “Stay in Jerʹi·cho until your beards grow back, and then return.”

^6 In time the Amʹmon·ites saw that they had become a stench to David, so Haʹnun and the Amʹmon·ites sent 1,000 silver talents[*] to hire chariots and horsemen from Mes·o·po·taʹmi·a,[*] Aʹram-maʹa·cah, and Zoʹbah. ^7 Thus they hired 32,000 chariots, along with the king of Maʹa·cah and his people. Then they came and camped before Medʹe·ba. The Amʹmon·ites gathered together from their cities and came out for the battle.

^8 When David heard about it, he sent Joʹab and the entire army, including his mightiest warriors. ^9 And the Amʹmon·ites went out and drew up in battle formation at the entrance of the city while the kings who had come were by themselves in the open field.

^10 When Joʹab saw that the battle charges were coming against him from the front and the rear, he chose some of the best troops in Israel and drew them up in battle formation to meet the Syrians. ^11 He put the rest of the men under the command[*] of his brother A·bishʹai, in order to draw them up in battle formation to meet the Amʹmon·ites. ^12 Then he said: “If the Syrians become too strong for me, then you must come to my rescue; but if the Amʹmon·ites become too strong for you, I will rescue you. ^13 We must be strong and courageous for our people and for the cities of our God, and Jehovah will do what is good in his eyes.”

^14 Then Joʹab and his men advanced to meet the Syrians in battle, and they fled from before him. ^15 When the Amʹmon·ites saw that the Syrians had fled, they also fled from his brother A·bishʹai and went into the city. After that Joʹab came to Jerusalem.

^16 When the Syrians saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they sent messengers to summon the Syrians in the region of the River,[*] with Shoʹphach the chief of the army of Had·ad·eʹzer leading them.

^17 When the report was made to David, he immediately gathered all Israel and crossed the Jordan and came to them and drew up in battle formation against them. David drew up in battle formation to meet the Syrians, and they fought against him. ^18 But the Syrians fled from Israel; and David killed 7,000 charioteers and 40,000 foot soldiers of the Syrians, and he put Shoʹphach the chief of the army to death. ^19 When the servants of Had·ad·eʹzer saw that they had been defeated by Israel, they promptly made peace with David and became his subjects; and Syria did not want to help the Amʹmon·ites anymore.

^ 1 Chron. 19:6 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 19:6 Lit., “Aram-naharaim.”

^ 1 Chron. 19:11 Lit., “in the hand.”

^ 1 Chron. 19:16 That is, the Euphrates.

1 Chronicles  20 : 1 - 8

20 At the start of the year,[*] at the time when kings go on campaigns, Joʹab led a military expedition and devastated the land of the Amʹmon·ites; he came and besieged Rabʹbah, while David stayed in Jerusalem. Joʹab attacked Rabʹbah and tore it down. ^2 Then David took the crown of Malʹcam from its head, and found that it weighed a talent[*] of gold, and in it there were precious stones; and it was placed on David’s head. He also took a vast amount of spoil from the city. ^3 And he brought out the people who were in it and put them to work at sawing stones and at working with sharp iron instruments and with axes. That was what David did to all the cities of the Amʹmon·ites. Finally David and all the troops returned to Jerusalem.

^4 After this, war broke out at Geʹzer with the Phi·lisʹtines. At that time Sibʹbe·cai the Huʹshath·ite struck down Sipʹpai, who was a descendant of the Rephʹa·im, and they were subdued.

^5 And there was war again with the Phi·lisʹtines, and El·haʹnan the son of Jaʹir struck down Lahʹmi the brother of Go·liʹath the Gitʹtite, whose spear had a shaft like the beam of loom workers.

^6 War broke out yet again at Gath, where there was a man of extraordinary size, with 6 fingers on each hand and 6 toes on each foot, 24 in all; and he too was a descendant of the Rephʹa·im. ^7 He kept taunting Israel. So Jonʹa·than the son of Shimʹe·a, David’s brother, struck him down.

^8 These were descendants of the Rephʹa·im in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.

^ 1 Chron. 20:1 That is, in the spring.

^ 1 Chron. 20:2 About 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

1 Chronicles  21 : 1 - 30

21 Then Satan[*] stood up against Israel and incited David to number Israel. ^2 So David said to Joʹab and the chiefs of the people: “Go, count Israel from Beʹer-sheʹba to Dan; then report to me so that I may know their number.” ^3 But Joʹab said: “May Jehovah multiply his people 100 times! My lord the king, are not all of them already servants of my lord? Why does my lord want to do this? Why should he become a cause of guilt to Israel?”

^4 But the king’s word prevailed over Joʹab. So Joʹab went out and traveled throughout Israel, after which he came to Jerusalem. ^5 Joʹab now gave to David the number of the people who were registered. All Israel amounted to 1,100,000 men armed with swords, and Judah, 470,000 men armed with swords. ^6 But Leʹvi and Benjamin were not registered among them, because the king’s word was detestable to Joʹab.

^7 Now this was very displeasing to the true God, so he struck Israel. ^8 David then said to the true God: “I have sinned greatly by doing this. And now, please, forgive your servant’s error, for I have acted very foolishly.” ^9 Jehovah then spoke to Gad, David’s visionary, saying: ^10 “Go and say to David, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I am giving you three options. Choose the one that I should bring on you.”’” ^11 So Gad came in to David and said to him: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Take your pick ^12 whether there should be three years of famine, or three months of being swept away by your adversaries while the sword of your enemies overtakes you, or three days of the sword of Jehovah—pestilence in the land—with Jehovah’s angel bringing destruction in all the territory of Israel.’ Now consider what I should reply to the One who sent me.” ^13 So David said to Gad: “It is very distressing to me. Please, let me fall into the hand of Jehovah, for his mercy is very great; but do not let me fall into the hand of man.”

^14 Then Jehovah sent a pestilence on Israel, so that 70,000 people out of Israel fell. ^15 Moreover, the true God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy it; but as he was about to do so, Jehovah saw it and felt regret[*] over the calamity, and he said to the angel bringing destruction: “It is enough! Now let your hand drop.” Jehovah’s angel was standing close to the threshing floor of Orʹnan the Jebʹu·site.

^16 When David raised his eyes, he saw Jehovah’s angel standing between the earth and the heavens with a drawn sword in his hand extended toward Jerusalem. David and the elders, covered with sackcloth, at once threw themselves down with their faces to the ground. ^17 David said to the true God: “Was it not I who said to number the people? I am the one who sinned, and I am the one who did wrong; but these sheep—what have they done? O Jehovah my God, let your hand, please, come against me and my father’s house; but do not bring this scourge on your people.”

^18 Jehovah’s angel then told Gad to tell David to go up and erect an altar to Jehovah on the threshing floor of Orʹnan the Jebʹu·site. ^19 So David went up at the word of Gad, which he had spoken in the name of Jehovah. ^20 Meanwhile, Orʹnan turned around and saw the angel, and his four sons who were with him hid themselves. Now Orʹnan had been threshing wheat. ^21 When David came up to him, Orʹnan looked and saw David, and he immediately went out from the threshing floor and bowed down to David with his face to the ground. ^22 David said to Orʹnan: “Sell[*] me the site of the threshing floor, so that I may build an altar to Jehovah on it. Sell it to me for the full price, so that the scourge against the people may be halted.” ^23 But Orʹnan said to David: “Take it as your own, and let my lord the king do what seems good to him.[*] Here, I am providing the cattle for burnt offerings and the threshing sledge for the wood and the wheat as a grain offering. I give all of it.”

^24 However, King David said to Orʹnan: “No, I must buy it for the full price, because I will not take what is yours and give it to Jehovah or offer up burnt sacrifices that cost me nothing.” ^25 So David gave Orʹnan 600 gold shekels[*] by weight for the site. ^26 And David built an altar there to Jehovah and offered up burnt sacrifices and communion sacrifices, and he called on Jehovah, who now answered him with fire from the heavens on the altar of burnt offering. ^27 Then Jehovah ordered the angel to return his sword to its sheath. ^28 At that time, when David saw that Jehovah had answered him at the threshing floor of Orʹnan the Jebʹu·site, he continued to sacrifice there. ^29 However, the tabernacle of Jehovah that Moses had made in the wilderness and the altar of burnt offering were at that time on the high place at Gibʹe·on. ^30 But David had not been able to go before it to consult God, for he was terrified because of the sword of Jehovah’s angel.

^ 1 Chron. 21:1 Or possibly, “a resister.”

^ 1 Chron. 21:15 Or “grieved.”

^ 1 Chron. 21:22 Lit., “Give.”

^ 1 Chron. 21:23 Lit., “what is good in his eyes.”

^ 1 Chron. 21:25 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

1 Chronicles  22 : 1 - 19

22 David then said: “This is the house of Jehovah the true God, and this is an altar for burnt offering for Israel.”

^2 David then gave orders to bring together the foreign residents who were in the land of Israel, and he assigned them to be stonecutters to cut and shape stones for building the house of the true God. ^3 David also prepared iron in great quantity for nails for the doors of the gates and for clamps, and so much copper that it was beyond weighing, ^4 and also cedar timbers without number, for the Si·doʹni·ans and the Tyrʹi·ans brought great quantities of cedar timbers to David. ^5 And David said: “My son Solʹo·mon is young and inexperienced,[*] and the house to be built for Jehovah is to be exceedingly magnificent, so that its fame and beauty will be known in all lands. Therefore, I will make preparation for him.” So David prepared materials in great quantity before his death.

^6 Moreover, he summoned his son Solʹo·mon and instructed him to build a house for Jehovah the God of Israel. ^7 David told his son Solʹo·mon: “As for me, it was my heart’s desire to build a house for the name of Jehovah my God. ^8 But Jehovah’s word came to me, saying, ‘You have shed a great deal of blood, and you have fought great wars. You will not build a house for my name, for you have shed a great deal of blood on the earth before me. ^9 Look! You will have a son who will be a man of peace,[*] and I will give him rest from all his enemies who surround him, for Solʹo·mon[*] will be his name and I will grant Israel peace and quiet in his days. ^10 He is the one who will build a house for my name. He will become my son, and I will be his father. I will firmly establish the throne of his kingship over Israel forever.’

^11 “Now, my son, may Jehovah be with you, and may you be successful and build the house of Jehovah your God, just as he has spoken concerning you. ^12 Only may Jehovah give you discretion and understanding when he gives you authority over Israel, so that you may keep the law of Jehovah your God. ^13 Then you will be successful if you carefully observe the regulations and the judgments that Jehovah ordered Moses to give Israel. Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid or be terrified. ^14 Here I have taken great pains to prepare for Jehovah’s house 100,000 talents[*] of gold and 1,000,000 talents of silver and such great quantities of copper and iron that they cannot be weighed, and I have prepared timbers and stones, but you will add to them. ^15 A great number of workmen are with you—stonecutters, stonemasons, woodworkers, and all kinds of skilled workers. ^16 The gold, silver, copper, and iron are beyond measure. Get up and begin the work, and may Jehovah be with you.”

^17 David then ordered all the princes of Israel to help his son Solʹo·mon: ^18 “Is not Jehovah your God with you, and has he not given you rest on every side? For he handed over to me the inhabitants of the land, and the land has been subdued before Jehovah and before his people. ^19 Now determine with all your heart and soul[*] to seek Jehovah your God, and start building the sanctuary of Jehovah the true God, in order to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and the holy utensils of the true God to the house built for the name of Jehovah.”

^ 1 Chron. 22:5 Or “delicate.”

^ 1 Chron. 22:9 Lit., “rest.”

^ 1 Chron. 22:9 From a Hebrew word meaning “Peace.”

^ 1 Chron. 22:14 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 22:19 See Glossary.

1 Chronicles  23 : 1 - 32

23 When David had grown old and was near the end of his life,[*] he made his son Solʹo·mon king over Israel. ^2 He then gathered all the princes of Israel, the priests, and the Levites. ^3 The Levites who were 30 years old and up were numbered; their number, their head count man by man, was 38,000. ^4 Of these, 24,000 served as supervisors over the work of Jehovah’s house, and there were 6,000 officers and judges, ^5 and there were 4,000 gatekeepers, and 4,000 gave praise to Jehovah on the instruments about which David said, “I made them for giving praise.”

^6 Then David organized[*] them into divisions according to the sons of Leʹvi: Gerʹshon, Koʹhath, and Me·rarʹi. ^7 Of the Gerʹshon·ites were Laʹdan and Shimʹe·i. ^8 The sons of Laʹdan were Je·hiʹel the headman, Zeʹtham, and Joel, three. ^9 The sons of Shimʹe·i were She·loʹmoth, Haʹzi·el, and Haʹran, three. These were the heads of the paternal houses for Laʹdan. ^10 And the sons of Shimʹe·i were Jaʹhath, Ziʹna, Jeʹush, and Be·riʹah. These four were the sons of Shimʹe·i. ^11 Jaʹhath was the head and Ziʹzah, the second. But since Jeʹush and Be·riʹah did not have many sons, they were counted as one paternal house with one area of responsibility.

^12 The sons of Koʹhath were Amʹram, Izʹhar, Hebʹron, and Uzʹzi·el, four. ^13 The sons of Amʹram were Aaron and Moses. But Aaron was permanently set apart to sanctify the Most Holy, he and his sons, to offer sacrifices before Jehovah, to minister to him, and to pronounce blessings in his name always. ^14 As for Moses the man of the true God, his sons were named among the tribe of the Levites. ^15 The sons of Moses were Gerʹshom and E·li·eʹzer. ^16 Of the sons of Gerʹshom, Shebʹu·el was the head. ^17 Of the descendants[*] of E·li·eʹzer, Re·ha·biʹah was the head; E·li·eʹzer did not have other sons, but the sons of Re·ha·biʹah were very many. ^18 Of the sons of Izʹhar, She·loʹmith was the headman. ^19 The sons of Hebʹron were Je·riʹah the head, Am·a·riʹah the second, Ja·ha·ziʹel the third, and Jek·a·meʹam the fourth. ^20 The sons of Uzʹzi·el were Miʹcah the head and Is·shiʹah the second.

^21 The sons of Me·rarʹi were Mahʹli and Muʹshi. The sons of Mahʹli were El·e·aʹzar and Kish. ^22 El·e·aʹzar died, but he had no sons, only daughters. So the sons of Kish, their relatives,[*] took them as wives. ^23 The sons of Muʹshi were Mahʹli, Eʹder, and Jerʹe·moth, three.

^24 These were the sons of Leʹvi according to their paternal houses, the heads of the paternal houses, by those registered who were counted and listed by their names and who carried out the work for the service of the house of Jehovah, from 20 years old and up. ^25 For David had said: “Jehovah the God of Israel has given rest to his people, and he will reside in Jerusalem forever. ^26 Also the Levites will not have to carry the tabernacle or any of its equipment for its service.” ^27 For according to the last instructions of David, the Levites from 20 years old and up were numbered. ^28 Their function was to assist the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Jehovah, to be in charge of the courtyards, the dining rooms, the purification of every holy thing, and any work needed for the service of the house of the true God. ^29 They assisted with the layer bread,[*] the fine flour for the grain offering, the wafers of unleavened bread, the griddle cakes, the mixed dough, and all measures of quantity and size. ^30 They were to stand morning by morning to thank and praise Jehovah and likewise in the evening. ^31 They assisted whenever the burnt sacrifices were offered to Jehovah on the Sabbaths, the new moons, and during the festival seasons, according to the number required by the rules concerning them, doing so regularly before Jehovah. ^32 They also took care of their responsibilities toward the tent of meeting, toward the holy place, and toward their brothers the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Jehovah.

^ 1 Chron. 23:1 Lit., “old and full of days.”

^ 1 Chron. 23:6 Or “divided.”

^ 1 Chron. 23:17 Lit., “sons.”

^ 1 Chron. 23:22 Lit., “brothers.”

^ 1 Chron. 23:29 That is, the showbread.

1 Chronicles  24 : 1 - 31

24 Now the divisions of the descendants of Aaron were these: The sons of Aaron were Naʹdab, A·biʹhu, El·e·aʹzar, and Ithʹa·mar. ^2 However, Naʹdab and A·biʹhu died before their father, and they did not have any sons; but El·e·aʹzar and Ithʹa·mar continued to serve as priests. ^3 David, along with Zaʹdok from the sons of El·e·aʹzar and A·himʹe·lech from the sons of Ithʹa·mar, made divisions of them for the office of their service. ^4 Since the sons of El·e·aʹzar had more headmen than the sons of Ithʹa·mar had, they divided them accordingly: The sons of El·e·aʹzar had 16 as heads of their paternal houses, and the sons of Ithʹa·mar had 8 as heads of their paternal houses.

^5 Further, they divided them by lots, the one group along with the other, for there were chiefs of the holy place and chiefs of the true God from both the sons of El·e·aʹzar and the sons of Ithʹa·mar. ^6 Then She·maiʹah the son of Ne·thanʹel the secretary of the Levites recorded their names before the king, the princes, Zaʹdok the priest, A·himʹe·lech the son of A·biʹa·thar, and the heads of the paternal houses of the priests and of the Levites, one paternal house being selected for El·e·aʹzar and one being selected for Ithʹa·mar.

^7 The first lot came out to Je·hoiʹa·rib; the second to Je·daʹiah, ^8 the third to Haʹrim, the fourth to Se·oʹrim, ^9 the fifth to Mal·chiʹjah, the sixth to Mijʹa·min, ^10 the seventh to Hakʹkoz, the eighth to A·biʹjah, ^11 the ninth to Jeshʹu·a, the tenth to Shec·a·niʹah, ^12 the 11th to E·liʹa·shib, the 12th to Jaʹkim, ^13 the 13th to Hupʹpah, the 14th to Je·shebʹe·ab, ^14 the 15th to Bilʹgah, the 16th to Imʹmer, ^15 the 17th to Heʹzir, the 18th to Hapʹpiz·zez, ^16 the 19th to Peth·a·hiʹah, the 20th to Je·hezʹkel, ^17 the 21st to Jaʹchin, the 22nd to Gaʹmul, ^18 the 23rd to De·laʹiah, the 24th to Ma·a·ziʹah.

^19 These were their offices for their service when they would come into the house of Jehovah according to the procedure set by their forefather Aaron, just as Jehovah the God of Israel had commanded him.

^20 And of the rest of the Levites: of the sons of Amʹram, there was Shuʹba·el; of the sons of Shuʹba·el, Jeh·deʹiah; ^21 of Re·ha·biʹah: of the sons of Re·ha·biʹah, Is·shiʹah the head; ^22 of the Izʹhar·ites, She·loʹmoth; of the sons of She·loʹmoth, Jaʹhath; ^23 and of the sons of Hebʹron, Je·riʹah the head, Am·a·riʹah the second, Ja·ha·ziʹel the third, Jek·a·meʹam the fourth; ^24 of the sons of Uzʹzi·el, Miʹcah; of the sons of Miʹcah, Shaʹmir. ^25 The brother of Miʹcah was Is·shiʹah; of the sons of Is·shiʹah, Zech·a·riʹah.

^26 The sons of Me·rarʹi were Mahʹli and Muʹshi; of the sons of Ja·a·ziʹah, Beʹno. ^27 The sons of Me·rarʹi: of Ja·a·ziʹah, Beʹno, Shoʹham, Zacʹcur, and Ibʹri; ^28 of Mahʹli, El·e·aʹzar, who did not have any sons; ^29 of Kish: the sons of Kish, Je·rahʹme·el; ^30 and the sons of Muʹshi were Mahʹli, Eʹder, and Jerʹi·moth.

These were the sons of Leʹvi by their paternal houses. ^31 And they also cast lots just as their brothers the sons of Aaron did in the presence of King David, Zaʹdok, A·himʹe·lech, and the heads of the paternal houses of the priests and of the Levites. Regarding the paternal houses, the head one was just as his younger brother.

1 Chronicles  25 : 1 - 31

25 Further, David and the chiefs of the groups for the service separated some of the sons of Aʹsaph, Heʹman, and Je·duʹthun to serve by prophesying with the harps, the stringed instruments, and the cymbals. The list of the official men for this service was, ^2 of the sons of Aʹsaph: Zacʹcur, Joseph, Neth·a·niʹah, and Ash·a·reʹlah, the sons of Aʹsaph under the direction of Aʹsaph, who prophesied under the direction of the king. ^3 Of Je·duʹthun, the sons of Je·duʹthun: Ged·a·liʹah, Zeʹri, Je·shaʹiah, Shimʹe·i, Hash·a·biʹah, and Mat·ti·thiʹah, six, under the direction of their father Je·duʹthun, who prophesied with the harp, thanking and praising Jehovah. ^4 Of Heʹman, the sons of Heʹman: Buk·kiʹah, Mat·ta·niʹah, Uzʹzi·el, Shebʹu·el, Jerʹi·moth, Han·a·niʹah, Ha·naʹni, E·liʹa·thah, Gid·dalʹti, Ro·mamʹti-eʹzer, Josh·be·kashʹah, Mal·loʹthi, Hoʹthir, and Ma·haʹzi·oth. ^5 All of these were sons of Heʹman, a visionary of the king in matters pertaining to the true God to his glory;[*] thus the true God gave Heʹman 14 sons and 3 daughters. ^6 All of these were under the direction of their father for singing at the house of Jehovah, with cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps for the service of the house of the true God.

Under the king’s direction were Aʹsaph, Je·duʹthun, and Heʹman.

^7 The number of them and their brothers who were trained in song to Jehovah, all experts, was 288. ^8 So they cast lots for their duties, the small and the great alike, the expert along with the learner.

^9 The first lot to come out belonged to Aʹsaph for Joseph, the second for Ged·a·liʹah (he and his brothers and his sons were 12); ^10 the third for Zacʹcur, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^11 the fourth for Izʹri, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^12 the fifth for Neth·a·niʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^13 the sixth for Buk·kiʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^14 the seventh for Jesh·a·reʹlah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^15 the eighth for Je·shaʹiah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^16 the ninth for Mat·ta·niʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^17 the tenth for Shimʹe·i, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^18 the 11th for Azʹar·el, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^19 the 12th for Hash·a·biʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^20 for the 13th, Shuʹba·el, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^21 for the 14th, Mat·ti·thiʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^22 for the 15th, for Jerʹe·moth, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^23 for the 16th, for Han·a·niʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^24 for the 17th, for Josh·be·kashʹah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^25 for the 18th, for Ha·naʹni, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^26 for the 19th, for Mal·loʹthi, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^27 for the 20th, for E·liʹa·thah, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^28 for the 21st, for Hoʹthir, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^29 for the 22nd, for Gid·dalʹti, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^30 for the 23rd, for Ma·haʹzi·oth, his sons and his brothers, 12; ^31 for the 24th, for Ro·mamʹti-eʹzer, his sons and his brothers, 12.

^ 1 Chron. 25:5 Lit., “to raise up his horn.”

1 Chronicles  26 : 1 - 32

26 The divisions of gatekeepers were as follows: of the Korʹah·ites, Me·shel·e·miʹah the son of Koʹre of the sons of Aʹsaph. ^2 And Me·shel·e·miʹah had sons: Zech·a·riʹah the firstborn, Je·diʹa·el the second, Zeb·a·diʹah the third, Jathʹni·el the fourth, ^3 Eʹlam the fifth, Je·ho·haʹnan the sixth, Elʹie·ho-eʹnai the seventh. ^4 And Oʹbed-eʹdom had sons: She·maiʹah the firstborn, Je·hozʹa·bad the second, Joʹah the third, Saʹcar the fourth, Ne·thanʹel the fifth, ^5 Amʹmi·el the sixth, Isʹsa·char the seventh, and Pe·ulʹle·thai the eighth; for God had blessed him.

^6 And to his son She·maiʹah, there were sons born who were rulers of their paternal house, for they were mighty, capable men. ^7 The sons of She·maiʹah: Othʹni, Rephʹa·el, Oʹbed, and El·zaʹbad; and his brothers E·liʹhu and Sem·a·chiʹah were also capable men. ^8 All of these were of the sons of Oʹbed-eʹdom; they and their sons and their brothers were capable men and qualified for the service, 62 belonging to Oʹbed-eʹdom. ^9 And Me·shel·e·miʹah had sons and brothers, 18 capable men. ^10 And Hoʹsah of the sons of Me·rarʹi had sons. Shimʹri was the head, for although he was not the firstborn, his father appointed him as head, ^11 Hil·kiʹah the second, Teb·a·liʹah the third, Zech·a·riʹah the fourth. All the sons and brothers of Hoʹsah were 13.

^12 Of these divisions of the gatekeepers, the headmen had duties just as their brothers did, to minister at the house of Jehovah. ^13 So they cast lots, the small and the great alike by their paternal houses, for the different gates. ^14 Then the lot to the east fell to Shel·e·miʹah. For Zech·a·riʹah his son, a discreet adviser, they cast the lots, and his lot came out to the north. ^15 Oʹbed-eʹdom had his to the south, and his sons were assigned the storehouses. ^16 Shupʹpim and Hoʹsah had theirs to the west, near the Shalʹlech·eth Gate by the highway that goes up, guard group corresponding to guard group; ^17 there were six Levites to the east; to the north, four each day and to the south, four each day; and for the storehouses, two by two; ^18 for the portico to the west, there were four at the highway and two at the portico. ^19 These were the divisions of the gatekeepers from the sons of the Korʹah·ites and of the Me·rarʹites.

^20 As regards the Levites, A·hiʹjah was in charge of the treasuries of the house of the true God and the treasuries of the things made holy.[*] ^21 The sons of Laʹdan: the sons of the Gerʹshon·ite belonging to Laʹdan, the heads of the paternal houses belonging to Laʹdan the Gerʹshon·ite, Je·hiʹe·li ^22 and the sons of Je·hiʹe·li, Zeʹtham and his brother Joel. They were in charge of the treasuries of the house of Jehovah. ^23 From the Amʹram·ites, the Izʹhar·ites, the Hebʹron·ites, and the Uz·ziʹel·ites, ^24 Shebʹu·el son of Gerʹshom son of Moses was a leader in charge of the storehouses. ^25 As regards his brothers, of E·li·eʹzer, there was Re·ha·biʹah his son, Je·shaʹiah his son, Joʹram his son, Zichʹri his son, and She·loʹmoth his son. ^26 This She·loʹmoth and his brothers were in charge of all the treasuries of the things made holy, which King David, the heads of the paternal houses, the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, and the chiefs of the army had made holy. ^27 From the wars and from the spoil, they had made things holy to maintain the house of Jehovah; ^28 also, all that Samuel the seer, Saul the son of Kish, Abʹner the son of Ner, and Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah had made holy. Whatever anyone made holy was put in the care of She·loʹmith and his brothers.

^29 Of the Izʹhar·ites, Chen·a·niʹah and his sons were assigned outside administrative duties as officers and as judges over Israel.

^30 Of the Hebʹron·ites, Hash·a·biʹah and his brothers, 1,700 capable men, were over the administration of Israel in the region west of the Jordan for all the work of Jehovah and for the king’s service. ^31 Of the Hebʹron·ites, Je·riʹjah was the head of the Hebʹron·ites by line of descent of their paternal house. In the 40th year of David’s kingship, they were sought out, and mighty, capable men were found among them in Jaʹzer in Gilʹe·ad. ^32 And his brothers numbered 2,700 capable men, heads of the paternal houses. So King David assigned them over the Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of the Ma·nasʹsites, for every matter of the true God and matter of the king.

^ 1 Chron. 26:20 Or “the things dedicated.”

1 Chronicles  27 : 1 - 34

27 This is the number of Israelites, the heads of the paternal houses, the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, and their officers who ministered to the king in every matter of the divisions that would come in and go out month by month during all the months of the year; there were 24,000 in each division.

^2 Over the first division of the first month was Ja·shoʹbe·am the son of Zabʹdi·el, and 24,000 were in his division. ^3 Of the sons of Peʹrez, he was the head of all the chiefs of the groups assigned to serve during the first month. ^4 Over the division of the second month was Doʹdai the A·hoʹhite with his division, and Mikʹloth was the leader, and 24,000 were in his division. ^5 The chief of the third group assigned to serve during the third month was Be·naiʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da the chief priest, and 24,000 were in his division. ^6 This Be·naiʹah was a mighty warrior of the thirty and in charge of the thirty, and over his division was his son Am·mizʹa·bad. ^7 The fourth for the fourth month was Asʹa·hel, Joʹab’s brother, and his son Zeb·a·diʹah after him, and 24,000 were in his division. ^8 The fifth chief for the fifth month was Shamʹhuth the Izʹrah·ite, and 24,000 were in his division. ^9 The sixth for the sixth month was Iʹra the son of Ikʹkesh the Te·koʹite, and 24,000 were in his division. ^10 The seventh for the seventh month was Heʹlez the Pelʹo·nite of the Eʹphra·im·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. ^11 The eighth for the eighth month was Sibʹbe·cai the Huʹshath·ite of the Zeʹrah·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. ^12 The ninth for the ninth month was Abi-eʹzer the Anʹa·thoth·ite of the Benʹja·min·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. ^13 The tenth for the tenth month was Maʹha·rai the Ne·tophʹa·thite of the Zeʹrah·ites, and 24,000 were in his division. ^14 The 11th for the 11th month was Be·naiʹah the Pirʹa·thon·ite of the sons of Eʹphra·im, and 24,000 were in his division. ^15 The 12th for the 12th month was Helʹdai the Ne·tophʹa·thite, of Othʹni·el, and 24,000 were in his division.

^16 These were the leaders of the tribes of Israel: Of the Reuʹben·ites, E·li·eʹzer the son of Zichʹri was leader; of the Simʹe·on·ites, Sheph·a·tiʹah the son of Maʹa·cah; ^17 of Leʹvi, Hash·a·biʹah the son of Kem·uʹel; of Aaron, Zaʹdok; ^18 of Judah, E·liʹhu, one of David’s brothers; of Isʹsa·char, Omʹri the son of Miʹcha·el; ^19 of Zebʹu·lun, Ish·maʹiah the son of O·ba·diʹah; of Naphʹta·li, Jerʹi·moth the son of Azʹri·el; ^20 of the Eʹphra·im·ites, Ho·sheʹa the son of Az·a·ziʹah; of the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh, Joel the son of Pe·daiʹah; ^21 of the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh in Gilʹe·ad, Idʹdo the son of Zech·a·riʹah; of Benjamin, Ja·a·siʹel the son of Abʹner; ^22 of Dan, Azʹar·el the son of Je·roʹham. These were the princes of the tribes of Israel.

^23 David did not count those 20 years of age and under, because Jehovah had promised to make Israel as many as the stars of the heavens. ^24 Joʹab the son of Ze·ruʹiah had started to take the count, but he did not finish; and God’s anger came against Israel[*] because of this, and the number was not entered into the account of the history of the times of King David.

^25 Over the treasuries of the king was Azʹma·veth the son of Adʹi·el. Jonʹa·than the son of Uz·ziʹah was over the storehouses[*] in the fields, in the cities, in the villages, and in the towers. ^26 Over the field workers who cultivated the soil was Ezʹri the son of Cheʹlub. ^27 Shimʹe·i the Raʹmath·ite was over the vineyards; over the produce of the vineyards for the wine supplies was Zabʹdi the Shiphʹmite. ^28 Over the olive groves and the sycamore trees in the She·pheʹlah was Baʹal-haʹnan the Ge·deʹrite; over the oil supplies was Joʹash. ^29 Over the herds that grazed in Sharʹon was Shitʹrai the Sharʹon·ite, and Shaʹphat the son of Adʹlai was over the herds in the valley plains.[*] ^30 Over the camels was Oʹbil the Ishʹma·el·ite; over the donkeys[*] was Jeh·deʹiah the Me·ronʹo·thite. ^31 Over the flocks was Jaʹziz the Hagʹrite. All of these were the chiefs of King David’s property.

^32 Jonʹa·than, David’s nephew, was an adviser, a man of understanding and a secretary, and Je·hiʹel the son of Hachʹmo·ni looked after the king’s sons. ^33 A·hithʹo·phel was an adviser to the king, and Huʹshai the Arʹchite was the king’s friend.[*] ^34 After A·hithʹo·phel there were Je·hoiʹa·da the son of Be·naiʹah and A·biʹa·thar; and Joʹab was chief of the king’s army.

^ 1 Chron. 27:24 Lit., “and anger was on Israel.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:25 Or “treasuries.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:29 Or “low plains.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:30 Lit., “female donkeys.”

^ 1 Chron. 27:33 Or “confidant.”

1 Chronicles  28 : 1 - 21

28 David then congregated all the princes of Israel to Jerusalem: the princes of the tribes, the chiefs of the divisions ministering to the king, the chiefs of thousands and the chiefs of hundreds, the chiefs of all the property and livestock of the king and of his sons, together with the court officials and every mighty and capable man. ^2 Then King David rose to his feet and said:

“Hear me, my brothers and my people. It was my heart’s desire to build a house as the resting-place for the ark of the covenant of Jehovah and as the footstool of our God, and I made preparations to build. ^3 But the true God told me, ‘You will not build a house for my name, for you are a man of wars, and you have shed blood.’ ^4 However, Jehovah the God of Israel chose me out of all the house of my father to become king over Israel forever, for he chose Judah as leader and of the house of Judah, my father’s house, and of my father’s sons, I was the one whom he approved, to make me king over all Israel. ^5 And of all my sons—for Jehovah has given me many sons—he chose my son Solʹo·mon to sit on the throne of the kingship of Jehovah over Israel.

^6 “He said to me, ‘Your son Solʹo·mon is the one who will build my house and my courtyards, for I have chosen him as my son and I will become his father. ^7 I will firmly establish his kingship forever if he resolutely observes my commandments and my judicial decisions, as he is now doing.’ ^8 So I say before the eyes of all Israel, Jehovah’s congregation, and in the ears of our God: Carefully observe and search for all the commandments of Jehovah your God, so that you may possess the good land and pass it on as a permanent inheritance to your sons after you.

^9 “And you, Solʹo·mon my son, know the God of your father and serve him with a complete[*] heart and with a delightful[*] soul,[*] for Jehovah searches through all hearts, and he discerns every inclination of the thoughts. If you search for him, he will let himself be found by you, but if you leave him, he will reject you forever. ^10 See, now, for Jehovah has chosen you to build a house as a sanctuary. Be courageous and go to work.”

^11 David then gave to his son Solʹo·mon the architectural plan of the porch and of its houses, its storerooms, its roof chambers, its inner rooms, and the house of the propitiatory cover.[*] ^12 He gave him the architectural plan of everything that had been conveyed to him through inspiration[*] for the courtyards of Jehovah’s house, for all the dining rooms around it, for the treasuries of the house of the true God, and for the treasuries of the things made holy;[*] ^13 also for the divisions of the priests and of the Levites, for all the duties of the service of Jehovah’s house, and for all the utensils of the service of Jehovah’s house; ^14 also for the weight of the gold, the gold for all the utensils for the different services, the weight of all the utensils of silver, and for all the utensils for the different services; ^15 also the weight for the gold lampstands and their gold lamps, the weight of the different lampstands and their lamps, and the weight of the silver lampstands, for each lampstand and its lamps according to its use; ^16 also the weight of the gold for the tables of the layer bread,[*] for each table, as well as the silver for the tables of silver, ^17 for the forks, the bowls, the pitchers of pure gold, and the weight of the small gold bowls, for each small bowl, and the weight of the small silver bowls, for each small bowl. ^18 He also gave the weight for the refined gold for the incense altar and for the representation of the chariot, namely, the cherubs of gold that spread their wings out and overshadow the ark of the covenant of Jehovah. ^19 David said: “The hand of Jehovah was upon me, and he gave me insight to put all the details of the architectural plan in writing.”

^20 Then David said to his son Solʹo·mon: “Be courageous and strong and go to work. Do not be afraid or be terrified, for Jehovah God, my God, is with you. He will not desert you or abandon you, but he will be with you until all the work for the service of Jehovah’s house is finished. ^21 And here are the divisions of the priests and of the Levites for all the service of the house of the true God. You have willing, skilled workers to perform every kind of service, as well as the princes and all the people who will carry out all your instructions.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:9 Or “completely devoted.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:9 Or “willing.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:9 See Glossary.

^ 1 Chron. 28:11 Or “house of the atonement.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:12 Lit., “by the spirit.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:12 Or “things dedicated.”

^ 1 Chron. 28:16 That is, the showbread.

1 Chronicles  29 : 1 - 30

29 King David now said to all the congregation: “My son Solʹo·mon, the one whom God has chosen, is young and inexperienced,[*] and the work is great, for it is not a temple[*] for man but for Jehovah God. ^2 And I have spared no effort to prepare for the house of my God, providing the gold for the goldwork, the silver for the silverwork, the copper for the copperwork, the iron for the ironwork, the timbers for the timberwork, onyx stones, and stones to be set with mortar, mosaic pebbles, every kind of precious stone, and alabaster stones in great quantity. ^3 Moreover, because of my delight in the house of my God, there is also my private treasure of gold and silver that I am giving to the house of my God, in addition to all that I have prepared for the holy house, ^4 including 3,000 talents[*] of gold from Oʹphir and 7,000 talents of refined silver, for coating the walls of the houses, ^5 the gold for the goldwork and the silver for the silverwork, and for all the work to be done by the craftsmen. Now who volunteers to come forward today with a gift in hand for Jehovah?”

^6 So the princes of the paternal houses, the princes of the tribes of Israel, the chiefs of thousands and of hundreds, and the chiefs of the business of the king came forward voluntarily. ^7 And they gave to the service of the house of the true God: 5,000 talents of gold, 10,000 darics,[*] 10,000 talents of silver, 18,000 talents of copper, and 100,000 talents of iron. ^8 Whoever had precious stones gave them to the treasury of the house of Jehovah, under the care of Je·hiʹel the Gerʹshon·ite. ^9 The people rejoiced over making these voluntary offerings, for they made the voluntary offerings to Jehovah with a complete heart, and David the king also rejoiced greatly.

^10 Then David praised Jehovah before the eyes of all the congregation. David said: “May you be praised, O Jehovah the God of Israel our father, throughout all eternity.[*] ^11 Yours, O Jehovah, are the greatness and the mightiness and the beauty and the splendor and the majesty,[*] for everything in the heavens and on the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, O Jehovah. You are the One exalting yourself as head over all. ^12 The riches and the glory are from you, and you rule over everything, and in your hand there are power and mightiness, and your hand is able to make great and to give strength to all. ^13 And now, O our God, we thank you and praise your beautiful name.

^14 “And yet, who am I and who are my people that we should be in a position to make voluntary offerings like this? For everything is from you, and we have given to you what comes from your own hand. ^15 For we are foreign residents in your presence and settlers, just like all our forefathers. For our days on the earth are like a shadow—without hope. ^16 O Jehovah our God, all this wealth that we have prepared to build for you a house for your holy name is from your own hand, and it all belongs to you. ^17 I well know, O my God, that you examine the heart and that you take pleasure in integrity.[*] In the uprightness[*] of my heart, I have voluntarily offered all these things, and I am overjoyed to see your people who are present here make voluntary offerings to you. ^18 O Jehovah, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, our forefathers, keep these inclinations and thoughts in the hearts of your people forever, and direct their hearts to you. ^19 And give a complete[*] heart to my son Solʹo·mon, so that he may observe your commandments, your reminders, and your regulations and do all these things and build the temple[*] for which I have made preparation.”

^20 David then said to all the congregation: “Now praise Jehovah your God.” And all the congregation praised Jehovah the God of their forefathers and bowed low and prostrated themselves to Jehovah and to the king. ^21 And they continued to offer sacrifices to Jehovah and to offer up burnt offerings to Jehovah on the following day, 1,000 young bulls, 1,000 rams, 1,000 male lambs, and their drink offerings; they offered sacrifices in great number for all Israel. ^22 They continued eating and drinking before Jehovah on that day with great rejoicing, and for a second time they made Solʹo·mon the son of David king and anointed him before Jehovah as leader, and also Zaʹdok as priest. ^23 And Solʹo·mon sat on Jehovah’s throne as king in place of David his father, and he was successful, and all the Israelites were obedient to him. ^24 All the princes, the mighty warriors, and also all the sons of King David submitted themselves to Solʹo·mon the king. ^25 And Jehovah made Solʹo·mon exceedingly great before the eyes of all Israel and bestowed on him royal majesty such as no king over Israel ever had before.

^26 Thus David the son of Jesʹse reigned over all Israel, ^27 and the length[*] of his reign over Israel was 40 years. In Hebʹron he reigned for 7 years, and in Jerusalem he reigned for 33 years. ^28 And he died at a good old age, satisfied with long life,[*] wealth, and glory; and his son Solʹo·mon became king in his place. ^29 As for the history of King David, from beginning to end, it is written among the words of Samuel the seer, Nathan the prophet, and Gad the visionary, ^30 together with all his kingship, his mightiness, and the events of the times involving him and Israel and all the surrounding kingdoms.

^ 1 Chron. 29:1 Or “delicate.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:1 Or “citadel; palace.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:4 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 29:7 A daric was a Persian gold coin. See App. B14.

^ 1 Chron. 29:10 Or “from eternity to eternity.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:11 Or “dignity.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:17 Or “rectitude; uprightness.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:17 Or “sincerity.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:19 Or “completely devoted.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:19 Or “citadel; palace.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:27 Lit., “the days.”

^ 1 Chron. 29:28 Lit., “with days.”

2 Chronicles  1 : 1 - 17

THE SECOND OF CHRONICLES

1 Solʹo·mon the son of David grew ever stronger in his kingship, and Jehovah his God was with him and made him exceedingly great.

^2 Solʹo·mon sent for all Israel, the chiefs of the thousands and of the hundreds, the judges, and all the chieftains of all Israel, the heads of the paternal houses. ^3 Then Solʹo·mon and all the congregation went to the high place at Gibʹe·on, for that was where the tent of meeting of the true God was, which tent Moses the servant of Jehovah had made in the wilderness. ^4 However, David had brought the Ark of the true God up from Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim to the place that David had prepared for it; he had pitched a tent for it in Jerusalem. ^5 And the copper altar that Bezʹal·el the son of Uʹri the son of Hur had made had been put before the tabernacle of Jehovah; and Solʹo·mon and the congregation would pray before it.[*] ^6 Solʹo·mon now made offerings there before Jehovah, and he offered up 1,000 burnt offerings on the copper altar of the tent of meeting.

^7 That night God appeared to Solʹo·mon and said to him: “Ask what you would like me to give you.” ^8 At this Solʹo·mon said to God: “You have shown great loyal love toward my father David, and you have made me king in his place. ^9 Now, O Jehovah God, let your promise to David my father prove faithful, for you have made me king over a people as numerous as the dust particles of the earth. ^10 Give me now wisdom and knowledge to lead this people,[*] for who can possibly judge this great people of yours?”

^11 Then God said to Solʹo·mon: “Because this is your heart’s desire and you have not asked for wealth, riches, and honor or for the death[*] of those hating you, nor have you asked for a long life,[*] but you have asked for wisdom and knowledge to judge my people over whom I have made you king, ^12 wisdom and knowledge will be given you; but I will also give you wealth and riches and honor such as no kings before you have had and none after you will have.”

^13 So Solʹo·mon came from the high place at Gibʹe·on, from before the tent of meeting, to Jerusalem; and he reigned over Israel. ^14 Solʹo·mon kept accumulating chariots and horses;[*] he had 1,400 chariots and 12,000 horses,[*] and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem. ^15 The king made the silver and the gold in Jerusalem as plentiful as the stones, and cedarwood as plentiful as the sycamore trees in the She·pheʹlah. ^16 The horses of Solʹo·mon had been imported from Egypt, and the company of the king’s merchants would obtain the horses in droves[*] for one price. ^17 Each chariot imported from Egypt cost 600 silver pieces, and a horse cost 150; in turn, they would export them to all the kings of the Hitʹtites and the kings of Syria.

^ 2 Chron. 1:5 Or “would inquire of Him there.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:10 Lit., “to go out before this people and to come in.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:11 Or “soul.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:11 Lit., “many days.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:14 Or “horsemen.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:14 Or “horsemen.”

^ 2 Chron. 1:16 Or possibly, “from Egypt and from Kue; the king’s merchants would buy them from Kue,” perhaps referring to Cilicia.

2 Chronicles  2 : 1 - 18

2 Solʹo·mon now gave the order to build a house for Jehovah’s name and a house[*] for his kingdom. ^2 Solʹo·mon enlisted 70,000 men as common laborers,[*] 80,000 men as stonecutters in the mountains, and 3,600 as overseers over them. ^3 Further, Solʹo·mon sent word to Hiʹram the king of Tyre: “Do for me as you did for David my father when you sent him cedarwood to build a house[*] to live in. ^4 Now I am building a house for the name of Jehovah my God, to sanctify it to him, to burn perfumed incense before him, and also for the constant layer bread[*] and the burnt offerings, morning and evening, on the Sabbaths, on the new moons, and at the festival seasons of Jehovah our God. This is a lasting obligation for Israel. ^5 The house that I am building will be great, for our God is greater than all the other gods. ^6 And who is up to the task of building him a house? For the heavens and the heaven of the heavens cannot contain him, so who am I that I should build him a house except as a place for making sacrifices smoke before him? ^7 Now send me a craftsman who is skilled in working in gold, silver, copper, iron, purple wool, crimson, and blue thread and who knows how to cut engravings. He will work in Judah and in Jerusalem with my skilled craftsmen, whom David my father has provided. ^8 And send me timbers of cedar, juniper, and algum from Lebʹa·non, for I well know that your servants are experienced at cutting down the trees of Lebʹa·non. My servants will work along with your servants ^9 to prepare for me great quantities of timber, for the house that I am to build will be extraordinarily great. ^10 Now look! I will supply the food for your servants, the woodcutters who cut down the trees: 20,000 cors[*] of wheat, 20,000 cors of barley, 20,000 baths[*] of wine, and 20,000 baths of oil.”

^11 At that Hiʹram the king of Tyre sent this written message to Solʹo·mon: “Because Jehovah loves his people, he has made you their king.” ^12 Hiʹram then said: “May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, who made the heavens and the earth, because he has given to King David a wise son, endowed with discretion and understanding, who will build a house for Jehovah and a house for his kingdom. ^13 Now I am sending a skilled craftsman, endowed with understanding, Hiʹram-aʹbi, ^14 who is the son of a Danʹite woman but whose father was a man of Tyre; he has experience in working in gold, silver, copper, iron, stones, timbers, purple wool, blue thread, fine fabric, and crimson. He can do every sort of engraving and make any design he is given. He will work with your own skilled craftsmen and the skilled craftsmen of my lord David your father. ^15 Now let my lord send the wheat, barley, oil, and wine he has promised to his servants. ^16 And we will cut down trees from Lebʹa·non, as many as you need, and we will bring them to you as rafts by sea to Jopʹpa; and you will take them up to Jerusalem.”

^17 Solʹo·mon then took a count of all the men who were foreign residents in the land of Israel, after the census taken by David his father, and there were found 153,600. ^18 So he assigned 70,000 of them as common laborers,[*] 80,000 as stonecutters in the mountains, and 3,600 as overseers for putting the people to work.

^ 2 Chron. 2:1 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 2:2 Or “as burden bearers.”

^ 2 Chron. 2:3 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 2:4 That is, the showbread.

^ 2 Chron. 2:10 A cor equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 2:10 A bath equaled 22 L (5.81 gal). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 2:18 Or “as burden bearers.”

2 Chronicles  5 : 1 - 14

5 So Solʹo·mon completed all the work he had to do for the house of Jehovah. Solʹo·mon then brought in the things that David his father had made holy, and he put the silver, the gold, and all the articles into the treasuries of the house of the true God. ^2 At that time Solʹo·mon congregated the elders of Israel, all the heads of the tribes, the chieftains of the paternal houses of Israel. They came to Jerusalem to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah from the City of David, that is, Zion. ^3 All the men of Israel assembled before the king at the festival[*] that is held in the seventh month.

^4 So all the elders of Israel came, and the Levites lifted up the Ark. ^5 They brought up the Ark, the tent of meeting, and all the holy utensils that were in the tent. The priests and the Levites[*] brought them up. ^6 King Solʹo·mon and the entire assembly of Israel who had been summoned to meet with him were before the Ark. So many sheep and cattle were being sacrificed that they could not be counted or numbered. ^7 Then the priests brought the ark of the covenant of Jehovah to its place, into the innermost room of the house, the Most Holy, underneath the wings of the cherubs. ^8 Thus the wings of the cherubs were spread out over the place of the Ark, so that the cherubs covered over the Ark and its poles from above. ^9 The poles were so long that the tips of the poles were visible from the Holy in front of the innermost room, but they were not visible from outside. And they are there to this day. ^10 There was nothing in the Ark but the two tablets that Moses placed in it at Horʹeb, when Jehovah made a covenant with the people of Israel while they were coming out of Egypt.

^11 When the priests came out from the holy place (for all the priests who were present had sanctified themselves, regardless of their divisions), ^12 all the Levite singers who belonged to Aʹsaph, to Heʹman, to Je·duʹthun, and to their sons and their brothers were clothed in fine fabric, holding cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps; they were standing east of the altar, and along with them 120 priests were sounding the trumpets. ^13 At the moment when the trumpeters and the singers were praising and thanking Jehovah in unison, and as the sound ascended from the trumpets, the cymbals, and the other musical instruments as they were praising Jehovah, “for he is good; his loyal love endures forever,” then the house, the house of Jehovah, was filled with a cloud. ^14 The priests were not able to stand to minister because of the cloud, for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of the true God.

^ 2 Chron. 5:3 That is, the Festival of Booths.

^ 2 Chron. 5:5 Or “The Levitical priests.”

2 Chronicles  6 : 1 - 42

6 At that time Solʹo·mon said: “Jehovah said he would reside in the thick gloom. ^2 Now I have built a lofty house for you, an established place for you to dwell in forever.”

^3 Then the king turned around and began to bless all the congregation of Israel while all the congregation of Israel stood. ^4 He said: “May Jehovah the God of Israel be praised, the one who by his own mouth promised my father David and by his own hands has given fulfillment, saying, ^5 ‘From the day I brought my people out of the land of Egypt, I have not chosen a city out of all the tribes of Israel in which to build a house for my name to remain there, and I have not chosen a man to become leader over my people Israel. ^6 But I have chosen Jerusalem for my name to remain there, and I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.’ ^7 And it was the heart’s desire of my father David to build a house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel. ^8 But Jehovah said to my father David, ‘It was your heart’s desire to build a house for my name, and you did well to desire this in your heart. ^9 However, you will not build the house, but your own son who is to be born to you[*] is the one who will build the house for my name.’ ^10 Jehovah has carried out the promise that he made, for I have succeeded my father David and I sit on the throne of Israel, just as Jehovah promised. I have also built the house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel, ^11 and there I have placed the Ark containing the covenant that Jehovah made with the people of Israel.”

^12 Then he stood before the altar of Jehovah in front of all the congregation of Israel, and he spread out his hands. ^13 (For Solʹo·mon had made a platform of copper and put it in the middle of the court.[*] It was five cubits[*] long, five cubits wide, and three cubits high; and he stood on it.) And he knelt down in front of all the congregation of Israel and spread his hands out to the heavens, ^14 and he said: “O Jehovah the God of Israel, there is no God like you in the heavens or on the earth, keeping the covenant and showing loyal love to your servants who are walking before you with all their heart. ^15 You have kept the promise that you made to your servant David my father. You made the promise with your own mouth, and this day you have fulfilled it with your own hand. ^16 And now, O Jehovah the God of Israel, keep the promise you made to your servant David my father when you said: ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line before me to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your sons will pay attention to their way by walking in my law, just as you have walked before me.’ ^17 And now, O Jehovah the God of Israel, let the promise that you made to your servant David prove trustworthy.

^18 “But will God really dwell with mankind on the earth? Look! The heavens, yes, the heaven of the heavens, cannot contain you; how much less, then, this house that I have built! ^19 Now pay attention to the prayer of your servant and to his request for favor, O Jehovah my God, and listen to the cry for help and to the prayer that your servant is praying before you. ^20 May your eyes be open toward this house day and night, toward the place where you said that you would put your name, to listen to the prayer that your servant prays toward this place. ^21 And listen to your servant’s pleas for help and to the pleas of your people Israel when they pray toward this place, and may you hear from your dwelling place, from the heavens; yes, may you hear and forgive.

^22 “If a man sins against his fellow man and is made to take an oath[*] and is brought under liability to the oath,[*] and while under the oath[*] he comes before your altar in this house, ^23 may you then hear from the heavens and act and judge your servants by paying back the wicked one and bringing what he did on his own head and by pronouncing the righteous one innocent[*] and rewarding him according to his own righteousness.

^24 “And if your people Israel are defeated by an enemy because they kept sinning against you, and they return and glorify your name and pray and beg for favor before you in this house, ^25 may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your people Israel and bring them back to the land that you gave to them and their forefathers.

^26 “When the heavens are shut up and there is no rain because they kept sinning against you, and they pray toward this place and glorify your name and turn back from their sin because you humbled[*] them, ^27 may you then hear from the heavens and forgive the sin of your servants, of your people Israel, for you will instruct them about the good way in which they should walk; and bring rain on your land that you gave to your people as an inheritance.

^28 “If a famine occurs in the land, or a pestilence, a scorching blight, mildew, swarming locusts, or voracious locusts[*] or if their enemies besiege them in any of the cities of the land[*] or if any other sort of plague or disease occurs, ^29 whatever prayer, whatever request for favor may be made by any man or by all your people Israel (for each one knows his own plague and his own pain) when they spread out their hands toward this house, ^30 then may you hear from the heavens, your dwelling place, and may you forgive; and reward each one according to all his ways, for you know his heart (you alone truly know the human heart), ^31 so that they may fear you by walking in your ways all the days they live on the land that you gave to our forefathers.

^32 “Also concerning the foreigner who is not part of your people Israel and who comes from a distant land because of your great name[*] and your mighty hand and your outstretched arm, and he comes and prays toward this house, ^33 may you then listen from the heavens, your dwelling place, and do all that the foreigner asks of you, so that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you, as your people Israel do, and may know that your name has been called on this house that I have built.

^34 “If your people go to war against their enemies in the way that you send them and they pray to you in the direction of this city that you have chosen and toward the house that I have built for your name, ^35 then hear from the heavens their prayer and their request for favor and execute judgment for them.

^36 “If they sin against you (for there is no man who does not sin), and you are furious with them and you abandon them to an enemy, and their captors carry them off captive to a land, far or near, ^37 and they come to their senses in the land where they were carried off captive, and they return to you and beg you for favor in the land where they are captives, saying, ‘We have sinned and done wrong; we have acted wickedly,’ ^38 and they return to you with all their heart and all their soul[*] in the land of their captivity where they were carried off captive, and they pray in the direction of their land that you gave to their forefathers and the city that you have chosen and the house that I have built for your name, ^39 then hear from the heavens, your dwelling place, their prayer and their request for favor, and execute judgment for them and forgive your people who have sinned against you.

^40 “Now, O my God, please, may your eyes be opened and your ears attentive to the prayer offered in[*] this place. ^41 And now go up, O Jehovah God, to your resting-place, you and the Ark of your strength. Let your priests, O Jehovah God, be clothed with salvation, and let your loyal ones rejoice in your goodness. ^42 O Jehovah God, do not reject[*] your anointed one. May you remember your loyal love to David your servant.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:9 Lit., “your son, the one coming out of your loins.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:13 Or “enclosure.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:13 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 6:22 Or “and the latter lays a cursing on him.” That is, an oath that carried with it a curse as its penalty if sworn falsely or violated.

^ 2 Chron. 6:22 Lit., “curse.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:22 Lit., “curse.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:23 Lit., “righteous.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:26 Or “afflicted.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:28 Or “grasshoppers.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:28 Lit., “in the land of his gates.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:32 Or “reputation.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:38 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 6:40 Or “respecting.”

^ 2 Chron. 6:42 Lit., “turn away the face of.”

2 Chronicles  7 : 1 - 22

7 Now as soon as Solʹo·mon had finished praying, fire came down from the heavens and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices, and Jehovah’s glory filled the house. ^2 The priests were unable to enter the house of Jehovah because Jehovah’s glory had filled the house of Jehovah. ^3 And all the people of Israel were looking on when the fire came down and the glory of Jehovah was upon the house, and they bowed low with their faces to the ground on the pavement and prostrated themselves and thanked Jehovah, “for he is good; his loyal love endures forever.”

^4 Now the king and all the people offered sacrifices before Jehovah. ^5 King Solʹo·mon offered the sacrifice of 22,000 cattle and 120,000 sheep. Thus the king and all the people inaugurated the house of the true God. ^6 The priests were standing at their posts of duty, as were the Levites who had the instruments used to accompany the song to Jehovah. (King David had made these instruments for giving thanks to Jehovah—“for his loyal love endures forever”—when David would offer praise with them.[*]) And the priests were loudly sounding the trumpets in front of them, while all the Israelites were standing.

^7 Then Solʹo·mon sanctified the middle of the courtyard that was before the house of Jehovah, for there he had to offer up the burnt offerings and the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices, because the copper altar that Solʹo·mon had made could not contain the burnt sacrifices, the grain offerings, and the fat pieces. ^8 At that time Solʹo·mon held the festival for seven days together with all Israel, a very great congregation from Leʹbo-haʹmath[*] down to the Wadi[*] of Egypt. ^9 But on the eighth day[*] they held a solemn assembly, because they had held the inauguration of the altar for seven days and the festival for seven days. ^10 Then on the 23rd day of the seventh month, he sent the people away to their homes rejoicing and feeling glad of heart over the goodness that Jehovah had shown to David and Solʹo·mon and Israel his people.

^11 Thus Solʹo·mon finished the house of Jehovah and the house[*] of the king; and everything that came into Solʹo·mon’s heart to do regarding the house of Jehovah and his own house he accomplished successfully. ^12 Jehovah then appeared to Solʹo·mon during the night and said to him: “I have heard your prayer, and I have chosen this place for myself as a house of sacrifice. ^13 When I shut up the heavens and there is no rain and when I command the grasshoppers to devour the land and if I send a pestilence among my people, ^14 if my people on whom my name has been called humble themselves and pray and seek my face and turn away from their evil ways, then I will hear from the heavens and forgive their sin and heal their land. ^15 Now my eyes will be open and my ears attentive to prayer at this place. ^16 And now I have chosen and sanctified this house so that my name may be there permanently, and my eyes and my heart will always be there.

^17 “And you, if you walk before me as your father David walked by doing everything I have commanded you, and you obey my regulations and my judgments, ^18 then I will establish the throne of your kingship, just as I made a covenant with your father David, saying, ‘There will never fail to be a man of your line ruling over Israel.’ ^19 But if you turn away and forsake my statutes and my commandments that I have put before you and you go and serve other gods and bow down to them, ^20 I will uproot Israel from my land that I have given them, and this house that I have sanctified for my name I will cast out of my sight, and I will make it an object of scorn[*] and a cause for ridicule among all the peoples. ^21 And this house will become heaps of ruins. Everyone passing by it will stare in amazement and will say, ‘Why did Jehovah do that to this land and this house?’ ^22 Then they will say, ‘It was because they abandoned Jehovah the God of their forefathers, who had brought them out of the land of Egypt, and they embraced other gods and bowed down to them and served them. That is why he brought all this calamity on them.’”

^ 2 Chron. 7:6 Possibly referring to the Levites.

^ 2 Chron. 7:8 Or “the entrance of Hamath.”

^ 2 Chron. 7:8 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 7:9 The day after the festival, or the 15th day.

^ 2 Chron. 7:11 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 7:20 Lit., “a proverb.”

2 Chronicles  8 : 1 - 18

8 At the end of 20 years, during which Solʹo·mon built the house of Jehovah and his own house,[*] ^2 Solʹo·mon rebuilt the cities that Hiʹram had given Solʹo·mon and settled Israelites[*] there. ^3 Furthermore, Solʹo·mon went to Haʹmath-zoʹbah and captured it. ^4 Then he built up[*] Tadʹmor in the wilderness and all the storage cities that he had built in Haʹmath. ^5 He also built up Upper Beth-hoʹron and Lower Beth-hoʹron, fortified cities with walls, gates, and bars, ^6 and Baʹal·ath as well as all of Solʹo·mon’s storage cities, all the chariot cities, the cities for the horsemen, and whatever Solʹo·mon desired to build in Jerusalem, in Lebʹa·non, and in all the land of his dominion.

^7 As for all the people who were left from the Hitʹtites, the Amʹor·ites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Hiʹvites, and the Jebʹu·sites, who were not part of Israel, ^8 their descendants who were left in the land—those whom the Israelites had not exterminated—were conscripted by Solʹo·mon for forced labor until this day. ^9 But Solʹo·mon did not make any of the Israelites slaves for his work, for they were his warriors, the chiefs of his adjutants, and the chiefs of his charioteers and horsemen. ^10 There were 250 chiefs of the deputies of King Solʹo·mon, the foremen over the people.

^11 Solʹo·mon also brought Pharʹaoh’s daughter up from the City of David to the house that he had built for her, for he said: “Although she is my wife, she should not dwell in the house of King David of Israel, for the places to which the Ark of Jehovah has come are holy.”

^12 Then Solʹo·mon offered up burnt sacrifices to Jehovah on the altar of Jehovah that he had built in front of the porch. ^13 He followed the daily routine and made offerings according to the commandment of Moses for the Sabbaths, the new moons, and the appointed festivals three times in the year—the Festival of Unleavened Bread, the Festival of Weeks, and the Festival of Booths.[*] ^14 Further, he appointed the divisions of the priests for their services according to the rule of his father David, and the Levites for their posts of duty, to praise and to minister in the presence of the priests according to the daily routine, and the gatekeepers in their divisions for the different gates, for such was the commandment of David, the man of the true God. ^15 And they did not deviate from the king’s commandment to the priests and the Levites concerning any matter or concerning the storehouses. ^16 So Solʹo·mon’s work was all well-organized,[*] from the day the foundation of the house of Jehovah was laid until it was finished. So the house of Jehovah was completed.

^17 It was then that Solʹo·mon went to Eʹzi·on-geʹber and to Eʹloth on the seashore in the land of Eʹdom. ^18 Hiʹram sent him ships and experienced seamen by means of his own servants. They went with Solʹo·mon’s servants to Oʹphir and took from there 450 talents[*] of gold and brought it to King Solʹo·mon.

^ 2 Chron. 8:1 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 8:2 Lit., “sons of Israel.”

^ 2 Chron. 8:4 Or “rebuilt.”

^ 2 Chron. 8:13 Or “Temporary Shelters.”

^ 2 Chron. 8:16 Or “well-arranged; completed.”

^ 2 Chron. 8:18 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

2 Chronicles  9 : 1 - 31

9 Now the queen of Sheʹba heard the report about Solʹo·mon, so she came to Jerusalem to test Solʹo·mon with perplexing questions.[*] She was accompanied by a very impressive entourage,[*] with camels carrying balsam oil and great quantities of gold and precious stones. She went in to Solʹo·mon and spoke to him about everything that was close to her heart. ^2 Solʹo·mon then answered all her questions. There was nothing too difficult for[*] Solʹo·mon to explain to her.

^3 When the queen of Sheʹba had seen Solʹo·mon’s wisdom, the house that he built, ^4 the food of his table, the seating of his servants, the table service of his waiters and their attire, his cupbearers and their attire, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, she was left completely breathless.[*] ^5 So she said to the king: “The report that I heard in my own land about your achievements[*] and about your wisdom was true. ^6 But I did not put faith in the reports until I had come and had seen it with my own eyes. And look! I had not been told the half of your great wisdom. You have far surpassed the report that I heard. ^7 Happy are your men, and happy are your servants who stand before you constantly, listening to your wisdom! ^8 May Jehovah your God be praised, who has taken pleasure in you by putting you on his throne as king for Jehovah your God. Because your God loves Israel, in order to make it continue forever, he appointed you over it as king to administer justice and righteousness.”

^9 Then she gave the king 120 talents[*] of gold and a great quantity of balsam oil and precious stones. Never again was such balsam oil brought in as what the queen of Sheʹba gave to King Solʹo·mon.

^10 Moreover, the servants of Hiʹram and the servants of Solʹo·mon who brought gold from Oʹphir also brought algum timbers and precious stones. ^11 The king made from the algum timbers stairs for the house of Jehovah and for the king’s house,[*] as well as harps and stringed instruments for the singers. Nothing like them had ever been seen before in the land of Judah.

^12 King Solʹo·mon also gave the queen of Sheʹba whatever she desired and asked for, more than[*] what she had brought to the king. Then she left and returned to her own land, together with her servants.

^13 And the weight of the gold that came to Solʹo·mon in one year amounted to 666 talents of gold, ^14 besides that brought in by the merchants and the traders and all the kings of the Arabs and the governors of the land who were bringing gold and silver in to Solʹo·mon.

^15 King Solʹo·mon made 200 large shields of alloyed gold (600 shekels[*] of alloyed gold went on each shield) ^16 and 300 bucklers[*] of alloyed gold (three miʹnas[*] of gold went on each buckler). Then the king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebʹa·non.

^17 The king also made a great ivory throne and overlaid it with pure gold. ^18 There were six steps to the throne, and there was a gold footstool attached to the throne, and there were armrests on both sides of the seat, and two lions were standing beside the armrests. ^19 And there were 12 lions standing on the six steps, one at each end of the six steps. No other kingdom had made anything like it. ^20 All the drinking vessels of King Solʹo·mon were of gold, and all the utensils of the House of the Forest of Lebʹa·non were of pure gold. There was nothing made of silver, for silver was considered as nothing in the days of Solʹo·mon. ^21 For the king’s ships would go to Tarʹshish with the servants of Hiʹram. Once every three years, the ships of Tarʹshish would come loaded with gold and silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.

^22 So King Solʹo·mon was greater than all the other kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. ^23 And the kings of all the earth sought an audience with[*] Solʹo·mon to hear his wisdom that the true God had put in his heart. ^24 They would each bring a gift—articles of silver, articles of gold, garments, armor, balsam oil, horses, and mules—and this continued year after year. ^25 And Solʹo·mon had 4,000 stalls for his horses and chariots and 12,000 horses,[*] and he kept them stationed in the chariot cities and close by the king in Jerusalem. ^26 And he ruled over all the kings from the River[*] to the land of the Phi·lisʹtines and to the boundary of Egypt. ^27 The king made the silver in Jerusalem as plentiful as the stones, and cedarwood as plentiful as the sycamore trees in the She·pheʹlah. ^28 And they would bring horses to Solʹo·mon from Egypt and from all the other lands.

^29 As for the rest of the history of Solʹo·mon, from beginning to end, is it not written among the words of Nathan the prophet, in the prophecy of A·hiʹjah the Shiʹlo·nite, and in the record of visions of Idʹdo the visionary concerning Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat? ^30 Solʹo·mon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel for 40 years. ^31 Then Solʹo·mon was laid to rest with his forefathers. So they buried him in the City of David his father; and his son Re·ho·boʹam became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 9:1 Or “with riddles.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:1 Or “train.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:2 Lit., “nothing hidden from.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:4 Lit., “there was no more spirit in her.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:5 Or “words.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:9 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:11 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:12 Or possibly, “in addition to gifts corresponding to the value of.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:15 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:16 A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ 2 Chron. 9:16 A mina in the Hebrew Scriptures equaled 570 g (18.35 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 9:23 Lit., “sought the face of.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:25 Or “horsemen.”

^ 2 Chron. 9:26 That is, the Euphrates.

2 Chronicles  10 : 1 - 19

10 Re·ho·boʹam went to Sheʹchem, for all Israel had come to Sheʹchem to make him king. ^2 As soon as Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat heard of it (he was still in Egypt because he had fled on account of King Solʹo·mon), Jer·o·boʹam came back from Egypt. ^3 Then they sent for him, and Jer·o·boʹam and all Israel came to Re·ho·boʹam and said: ^4 “Your father made our yoke harsh. But if you make the harsh service of your father easier and you lighten the heavy[*] yoke he put on us, we will serve you.”

^5 At this he said to them: “Return to me after three days.” So the people went away. ^6 King Re·ho·boʹam then consulted with the older men[*] who had served his father Solʹo·mon while he was alive, saying: “What advice would you give on how to reply to this people?” ^7 They answered him: “If you are good to this people and please them and give them a favorable answer, they will always be your servants.”

^8 However, he rejected the advice that the older men[*] gave him, and he consulted with the young men who had grown up with him and who were now his attendants. ^9 He asked them: “What advice do you offer on how we should reply to this people who have said to me, ‘Make the yoke your father put on us lighter’?” ^10 The young men who had grown up with him said to him: “This is what you should say to the people who have said to you, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but you should make it lighter for us’; this is what you should tell them, ‘My little finger will be thicker than my father’s hips. ^11 My father imposed a heavy yoke on you, but I will add to your yoke. My father punished you with whips, but I will do so with scourges.’”

^12 Jer·o·boʹam and all the people came to Re·ho·boʹam on the third day, just as the king had said: “Return to me on the third day.” ^13 But the king answered them harshly. Thus King Re·ho·boʹam rejected the advice of the older men.[*] ^14 He spoke to them according to the advice of the young men, saying: “I will make your yoke heavier, and I will add to it. My father punished you with whips, but I will do so with scourges.” ^15 So the king did not listen to the people, for this turn of events was caused by the true God, in order to carry out the word that Jehovah had spoken through A·hiʹjah the Shiʹlo·nite to Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat.

^16 As for all Israel, because the king refused to listen to them, the people replied to the king: “What share do we have in David? We have no inheritance in the son of Jesʹse. Each one to your gods, O Israel! Now look after your own house, O David.” With that all Israel returned to their homes.[*]

^17 But Re·ho·boʹam continued to reign over the Israelites living in the cities of Judah.

^18 Then King Re·ho·boʹam sent Ha·doʹram, who was in charge of those conscripted for forced labor, but the Israelites stoned him to death. King Re·ho·boʹam managed to mount his chariot to flee to Jerusalem. ^19 And the Israelites have been in revolt against the house of David down to this day.

^ 2 Chron. 10:4 Or “oppressive.”

^ 2 Chron. 10:6 Or “the elders.”

^ 2 Chron. 10:8 Or “the elders.”

^ 2 Chron. 10:13 Or “the elders.”

^ 2 Chron. 10:16 Lit., “tents.”

2 Chronicles  11 : 1 - 23

11 When Re·ho·boʹam arrived in Jerusalem, he immediately congregated the house of Judah and Benjamin, 180,000 trained[*] warriors, to fight against Israel in order to restore the kingdom to Re·ho·boʹam. ^2 Then the word of Jehovah came to She·maiʹah the man of the true God, saying: ^3 “Say to Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon the king of Judah and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, ^4 ‘This is what Jehovah says: “You must not go up and fight against your brothers. Each of you return to his house, for I have caused this to happen.”’” So they obeyed the word of Jehovah and returned and did not go against Jer·o·boʹam.

^5 Re·ho·boʹam lived in Jerusalem and built fortified cities in Judah. ^6 Thus he built up[*] Bethʹle·hem, Eʹtam, Te·koʹa, ^7 Beth-zur, Soʹco, A·dulʹlam, ^8 Gath, Ma·reʹshah, Ziph, ^9 Ad·o·raʹim, Laʹchish, A·zeʹkah, ^10 Zoʹrah, Aiʹja·lon, and Hebʹron, fortified cities that were in Judah and Benjamin. ^11 Further, he reinforced the fortified places and put commanders in them and supplied them with food and oil and wine, ^12 and he supplied all the different cities with large shields and lances; he reinforced them to a very great degree. And Judah and Benjamin remained his.

^13 And the priests and the Levites who were in all Israel took their stand with him, coming out of all their territories. ^14 The Levites left their pastures and their possession and came to Judah and Jerusalem, because Jer·o·boʹam and his sons had dismissed them from serving as priests to Jehovah. ^15 Jer·o·boʹam then appointed his own priests for the high places and for the goatlike demons[*] and for the calves that he had made. ^16 And those from all the tribes of Israel who had their heart set on seeking Jehovah the God of Israel followed them to Jerusalem to sacrifice to Jehovah the God of their forefathers. ^17 For three years they strengthened the kingship of Judah and supported Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon, for they walked in the way of David and Solʹo·mon for three years.

^18 Then Re·ho·boʹam took as his wife Maʹha·lath the daughter of David’s son Jerʹi·moth and of Abʹi·ha·il the daughter of Jesʹse’s son E·liʹab. ^19 In time she bore him sons: Jeʹush, Shem·a·riʹah, and Zaʹham. ^20 After her, he married Maʹa·cah the granddaughter of Abʹsa·lom. In time she bore him A·biʹjah, Atʹtai, Ziʹza, and She·loʹmith. ^21 Re·ho·boʹam loved Maʹa·cah the granddaughter of Abʹsa·lom more than all his other wives and concubines, for he took 18 wives and 60 concubines, and he became father to 28 sons and 60 daughters. ^22 So Re·ho·boʹam appointed A·biʹjah the son of Maʹa·cah as head and leader among his brothers, for he intended to make him king. ^23 However, he acted with understanding and sent[*] some of his sons to all the regions of Judah and Benjamin, to all the fortified cities, and gave them abundant provisions and acquired many wives for them.

^ 2 Chron. 11:1 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 2 Chron. 11:6 Or “fortified.”

^ 2 Chron. 11:15 Lit., “the goats.”

^ 2 Chron. 11:23 Or “dispersed.”

2 Chronicles  12 : 1 - 16

12 Soon after the kingship of Re·ho·boʹam was firmly established and he had become strong, he abandoned the Law of Jehovah, and also all Israel with him. ^2 In the fifth year of King Re·ho·boʹam, King Shiʹshak of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, for they had behaved unfaithfully toward Jehovah. ^3 He had 1,200 chariots, 60,000 horsemen, and countless troops who came with him from Egypt—Libʹy·ans, Sukʹki·im, and E·thi·oʹpi·ans. ^4 He captured the fortified cities of Judah and finally reached Jerusalem.

^5 She·maiʹah the prophet came to Re·ho·boʹam and the princes of Judah who had gathered at Jerusalem because of Shiʹshak, and he said to them: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘You have abandoned me, so I have also abandoned you to the hand of Shiʹshak.’” ^6 At that the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves and said: “Jehovah is righteous.” ^7 When Jehovah saw that they had humbled themselves, the word of Jehovah came to She·maiʹah, saying: “They have humbled themselves. I will not destroy them, and in a little while I will rescue them. I will not pour out my wrath on Jerusalem through Shiʹshak. ^8 But they will become his servants, so that they will know the difference between serving me and serving the kings[*] of other lands.”

^9 So King Shiʹshak of Egypt came up against Jerusalem. He took the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king’s house.[*] He took everything, including the gold shields that Solʹo·mon had made. ^10 So King Re·ho·boʹam made copper shields to replace them, and he entrusted them to the chiefs of the guard,[*] who guarded the entrance of the king’s house. ^11 Whenever the king came to the house of Jehovah, the guards would come in and carry them, and then they would return them to the guard chamber. ^12 Because the king humbled himself, Jehovah’s anger turned away from him, and he did not destroy them completely. Moreover, there were some good things found in Judah.

^13 King Re·ho·boʹam strengthened his position in Jerusalem and continued to reign; Re·ho·boʹam was 41 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 17 years in Jerusalem, the city that Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel as the place to put his name. The name of the king’s mother was Naʹa·mah the Amʹmon·it·ess. ^14 But he did what was bad, for he had not resolved in his heart to search for Jehovah.

^15 As for Re·ho·boʹam’s history, from beginning to end, is it not written among the words of She·maiʹah the prophet and of Idʹdo the visionary in the genealogical record? And there were constant wars between Re·ho·boʹam and Jer·o·boʹam. ^16 Then Re·ho·boʹam was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried in the City of David; and his son A·biʹjah became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 12:8 Lit., “kingdoms.”

^ 2 Chron. 12:9 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 12:10 Lit., “runners.”

2 Chronicles  13 : 1 - 22

13 In the 18th year of King Jer·o·boʹam, A·biʹjah became king over Judah. ^2 He reigned for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Mi·caiʹah the daughter of U·riʹel of Gibʹe·ah. And there was war between A·biʹjah and Jer·o·boʹam.

^3 So A·biʹjah went to war with an army of 400,000 mighty, trained[*] warriors. And Jer·o·boʹam drew up in battle formation against him with 800,000 trained[*] men, mighty warriors. ^4 A·biʹjah now stood on Mount Zem·a·raʹim, which is in the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im, and said: “Hear me, O Jer·o·boʹam and all Israel. ^5 Do you not know that Jehovah the God of Israel gave to David a kingdom over Israel forever, to him and to his sons, by a covenant of salt?[*] ^6 But Jer·o·boʹam the son of Neʹbat, the servant of David’s son Solʹo·mon, rose up and rebelled against his lord. ^7 And idle, worthless men kept gathering to him. And they proved superior to Re·ho·boʹam the son of Solʹo·mon when Re·ho·boʹam was young and fainthearted, and he could not hold his own against them.

^8 “And now you think you can hold your own against the kingdom of Jehovah in the hand of the sons of David because you are a large crowd and you have the golden calves that Jer·o·boʹam made as gods for you. ^9 Have you not driven out Jehovah’s priests, the descendants of Aaron, and the Levites, and have you not appointed your own priests just like the peoples of the other lands? Anyone who came along with[*] a young bull and seven rams could become a priest of what are not gods. ^10 As for us, Jehovah is our God, and we have not abandoned him; our priests, the descendants of Aaron, are ministering to Jehovah, and the Levites assist in the work. ^11 They are making burnt offerings smoke to Jehovah each morning and each evening along with perfumed incense, and the layer bread[*] is on the table of pure gold, and they light up the golden lampstand and its lamps each evening, because we are caring for our responsibility to Jehovah our God; but you have abandoned him. ^12 Now look! the true God is with us, leading us, with his priests and the signal trumpets for sounding the battle alarm against you. O men of Israel, do not fight against Jehovah the God of your forefathers, for you will not be successful.”

^13 But Jer·o·boʹam dispatched an ambush to come from behind them, so that they were in front of Judah and the ambush was behind them. ^14 When the men of Judah turned around, they saw that they had to fight the battle both in front and from behind. So they began to cry out to Jehovah, while the priests were loudly sounding the trumpets. ^15 The men of Judah broke out in a war cry, and when the men of Judah shouted the war cry, the true God defeated Jer·o·boʹam and all Israel before A·biʹjah and Judah. ^16 The Israelites fled before Judah, and God gave them into their hand. ^17 A·biʹjah and his people inflicted a great slaughter on them, and the slain of Israel kept falling, 500,000 trained[*] men. ^18 Thus the men of Israel were humbled at that time, but the men of Judah proved superior because they relied[*] on Jehovah the God of their forefathers. ^19 A·biʹjah kept chasing after Jer·o·boʹam and captured cities from him, Bethʹel and its dependent[*] towns, Jeshʹa·nah and its dependent towns, and Eʹphra·in and its dependent towns. ^20 And Jer·o·boʹam never regained his power during the time of A·biʹjah; then Jehovah struck him down and he died.

^21 But A·biʹjah grew in strength. In time he took 14 wives, and he became father to 22 sons and 16 daughters. ^22 And the rest of A·biʹjah’s history, his deeds and his words, is recorded in the writings[*] of the prophet Idʹdo.

^ 2 Chron. 13:3 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:3 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:5 That is, a permanent and unchanging covenant.

^ 2 Chron. 13:9 Lit., “came to fill his hand with.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:11 That is, the showbread.

^ 2 Chron. 13:17 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:18 Lit., “leaned.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:19 Or “surrounding.”

^ 2 Chron. 13:22 Or “exposition; commentary.”

2 Chronicles  14 : 1 - 15

14 Then A·biʹjah was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the City of David; and his son Aʹsa became king in his place. In his days the land had rest for ten years.

^2 Aʹsa did what was good and right in the eyes of Jehovah his God. ^3 He removed the foreign altars and the high places, smashed the sacred pillars, and cut down the sacred poles.[*] ^4 Further, he told Judah to search for Jehovah the God of their forefathers and to observe the Law and the commandment. ^5 So he removed from all the cities of Judah the high places and the incense stands, and under him, the kingdom continued without disturbance. ^6 He built fortified cities in Judah, since the land had no disturbance and there was no war against him during these years, for Jehovah gave him rest. ^7 He said to Judah: “Let us build these cities and surround them with walls and towers, gates[*] and bars. For the land is still at our disposal, because we have searched for Jehovah our God. We have searched, and he has given us rest all around.” So their building was successful.

^8 Aʹsa had an army of 300,000 men from Judah, equipped with large shields and lances. And out of Benjamin were 280,000 mighty warriors who carried bucklers[*] and were armed with bows.[*]

^9 Later Zeʹrah the E·thi·oʹpi·an came against them with an army of 1,000,000 men and 300 chariots. When he reached Ma·reʹshah, ^10 Aʹsa went out against him and they drew up in battle formation in the Valley of Zephʹa·thah at Ma·reʹshah. ^11 Aʹsa then called to Jehovah his God and said: “O Jehovah, it does not matter to you whether those you help are many or have no power. Help us, O Jehovah our God, for we are relying[*] on you, and in your name we have come against this crowd. O Jehovah, you are our God. Do not let mortal man prevail against you.”

^12 So Jehovah defeated the E·thi·oʹpi·ans before Aʹsa and before Judah, and the E·thi·oʹpi·ans fled. ^13 Aʹsa and the people with him pursued them as far as Geʹrar, and the E·thi·oʹpi·ans continued falling until not one of them was alive, for they were crushed by Jehovah and by his army. Afterward they carried off a very great deal of spoil. ^14 Further, they struck all the cities around Geʹrar, for the dread of Jehovah had come upon them; and they plundered all the cities, for there was much to plunder in them. ^15 They also attacked the tents of those with livestock, and they captured a great number of flocks and camels, after which they returned to Jerusalem.

^ 2 Chron. 14:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 14:7 Lit., “double doors.”

^ 2 Chron. 14:8 A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ 2 Chron. 14:8 Lit., “and tread the bow.”

^ 2 Chron. 14:11 Lit., “we lean.”

2 Chronicles  15 : 1 - 19

15 Now the spirit of God came upon Az·a·riʹah the son of Oʹded. ^2 So he went out to meet Aʹsa and said to him: “Hear me, O Aʹsa and all Judah and Benjamin! Jehovah is with you as long as you remain with him; and if you search for him, he will let himself be found by you, but if you abandon him, he will abandon you. ^3 For a long time[*] Israel had been without the true God, without a priest teaching, and without law. ^4 But when in their distress they returned to Jehovah the God of Israel and searched for him, he let himself be found by them. ^5 In those times no one could travel safely,[*] for there was much unrest among all the inhabitants of the lands. ^6 Nation was being crushed by nation and one city by another city, because God kept them in disorder with every sort of distress. ^7 But you, be strong and do not become discouraged,[*] for your activity will be rewarded.”

^8 As soon as Aʹsa heard these words and the prophecy of Oʹded the prophet, he took courage and removed the disgusting idols from all the land of Judah and Benjamin and from the cities that he had captured from the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im, and he restored Jehovah’s altar that was before the porch of Jehovah. ^9 And he gathered together all Judah and Benjamin and the foreign residents with them from Eʹphra·im and Ma·nasʹseh and Simʹe·on, for they had deserted to him from Israel in great number when they saw that Jehovah his God was with him. ^10 So they were gathered together at Jerusalem in the third month of the 15th year of Aʹsa’s reign. ^11 On that day they sacrificed to Jehovah from the spoil they had brought, 700 cattle and 7,000 sheep. ^12 Furthermore, they entered into a covenant to search for Jehovah the God of their forefathers with all their heart and with all their soul.[*] ^13 Whoever would not search for Jehovah the God of Israel was to be put to death, whether small or great, man or woman. ^14 So they took an oath to Jehovah with a loud voice, with joyful shouting, and with the trumpets and horns. ^15 And all Judah rejoiced over the oath, for they had taken the oath with all their heart and they eagerly sought him and he let himself be found by them, and Jehovah continued to give them rest on every side.

^16 Aʹsa the king even removed Maʹa·cah his grandmother from her position as queen mother,[*] because she had made an obscene idol for the worship of the sacred pole.[*] Aʹsa cut down her obscene idol and pulverized it and burned it in the Kidʹron Valley. ^17 But the high places were not removed from Israel. Nevertheless, Aʹsa’s heart was complete[*] all his life.[*] ^18 And he brought the things that he and his father had made holy into the house of the true God—silver, gold, and various utensils. ^19 There was no war until the 35th year of Aʹsa’s reign.

^ 2 Chron. 15:3 Lit., “And many days.”

^ 2 Chron. 15:5 Lit., “there was no peace for the one going out or the one coming in.”

^ 2 Chron. 15:7 Lit., “do not let your hands drop.”

^ 2 Chron. 15:12 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 15:16 Or “as lady.”

^ 2 Chron. 15:16 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 15:17 Or “completely devoted.”

^ 2 Chron. 15:17 Lit., “days.”

2 Chronicles  17 : 1 - 19

17 And his son Je·hoshʹa·phat became king in his place, and he strengthened his position over Israel. ^2 He stationed military forces in all the fortified cities of Judah and put garrisons in the land of Judah and in the cities of Eʹphra·im that Aʹsa his father had captured. ^3 Jehovah continued with Je·hoshʹa·phat because he walked in the former ways of his forefather David and did not search for the Baʹals. ^4 For he searched for the God of his father and followed[*] his commandment and not the practices of Israel. ^5 Jehovah kept the kingdom firmly established in his hand; and all Judah continued to give gifts to Je·hoshʹa·phat, and he had riches and glory in abundance. ^6 His heart became bold in the ways of Jehovah, and he even removed the high places and the sacred poles[*] from Judah.

^7 In the third year of his reign he sent for his princes, Ben-haʹil, O·ba·diʹah, Zech·a·riʹah, Ne·thanʹel, and Mi·caiʹah, to teach in the cities of Judah. ^8 There were Levites with them: She·maiʹah, Neth·a·niʹah, Zeb·a·diʹah, Asʹa·hel, She·mirʹa·moth, Je·honʹa·than, Ad·o·niʹjah, To·biʹjah, and Tob-ad·o·niʹjah, and along with them E·lishʹa·ma and Je·hoʹram the priests. ^9 They began teaching in Judah, taking with them the book of Jehovah’s Law, and they went around through all the cities of Judah teaching among the people.

^10 And the dread of Jehovah came upon all the kingdoms of the lands surrounding Judah, and they did not fight against Je·hoshʹa·phat. ^11 And the Phi·lisʹtines brought to Je·hoshʹa·phat gifts and money as tribute. The Arabs brought him 7,700 rams and 7,700 male goats from their flocks.

^12 Je·hoshʹa·phat grew greater and greater, and he continued building fortified places and storage cities in Judah. ^13 He carried out extensive projects in the cities of Judah, and he had soldiers, mighty warriors, in Jerusalem. ^14 These were grouped by their paternal houses: of Judah the chiefs of thousands, Adʹnah the chief, and with him were 300,000 mighty warriors. ^15 And under his command was Je·ho·haʹnan the chief, and with him were 280,000. ^16 And also under his command was Am·a·siʹah the son of Zichʹri, who volunteered for Jehovah’s service, and with him were 200,000 mighty warriors. ^17 And out of Benjamin was E·liʹa·da, a mighty warrior, and with him were 200,000 men equipped with the bow and shield. ^18 And under his command was Je·hozʹa·bad, and with him were 180,000 men equipped for the army. ^19 These were ministering to the king in addition to those whom the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.

^ 2 Chron. 17:4 Lit., “walked in.”

^ 2 Chron. 17:6 See Glossary.

2 Chronicles  18 : 1 - 34

18 Je·hoshʹa·phat had riches and glory in abundance, but he made a marriage alliance with Aʹhab. ^2 So years later he went down to Aʹhab at Sa·marʹi·a, and Aʹhab sacrificed sheep and cattle in abundance for him and for the people with him. And he urged[*] him to go up against Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad. ^3 Then King Aʹhab of Israel said to King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah: “Will you go with me to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad?” He replied to him: “I am the same as you, and my people are the same as your people and will support you in the war.”

^4 But Je·hoshʹa·phat said to the king of Israel: “First inquire, please, for the word of Jehovah.” ^5 So the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, 400 men, and said to them: “Should we go to war against Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, or should I refrain?” They said: “Go up, and the true God will give it into the king’s hand.”

^6 Je·hoshʹa·phat then said: “Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah? Let us also inquire through him.” ^7 At that the king of Israel said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “There is still one more man through whom we can inquire of Jehovah; but I hate him, for he never prophesies good things concerning me, but always bad. He is Mi·caiʹah the son of Imʹlah.” However, Je·hoshʹa·phat said: “The king should not say such a thing.”

^8 So the king of Israel called a court official and said: “Bring Mi·caiʹah the son of Imʹlah quickly.” ^9 Now the king of Israel and Je·hoshʹa·phat the king of Judah were each sitting on his throne, dressed in royal attire; they were sitting at the threshing floor at the entrance of the gate of Sa·marʹi·a, and all the prophets were prophesying before them. ^10 Then Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Che·naʹa·nah made for himself iron horns and said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘With these you will gore[*] the Syrians until you exterminate them.’” ^11 All the other prophets were prophesying the same way, saying: “Go up to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad and you will be successful; Jehovah will give it into the king’s hand.”

^12 So the messenger who went to call Mi·caiʹah said to him: “Look! The words of the prophets are unanimously favorable to the king. Let your word, please, become like theirs, and speak favorably.” ^13 But Mi·caiʹah said: “As surely as Jehovah is living, whatever my God says is what I will speak.” ^14 Then he came in to the king, and the king asked him: “Mi·caiʹah, should we go to war against Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, or should I refrain?” At once he replied: “Go up and you will be successful; they will be given into your hand.” ^15 At that the king said to him: “How many times must I put you under oath not to speak to me anything but the truth in the name of Jehovah?” ^16 So he said: “I see all the Israelites scattered on the mountains, like sheep that have no shepherd. Jehovah said: ‘These have no master. Let each one go back to his house in peace.’”

^17 Then the king of Israel said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “Did I not tell you, ‘He will not prophesy good things concerning me, only bad’?”

^18 Mi·caiʹah then said: “Therefore, hear the word of Jehovah: I saw Jehovah sitting on his throne and all the army of the heavens standing at his right and at his left. ^19 Jehovah then said, ‘Who will fool King Aʹhab of Israel, so that he will go up and fall at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad?’ And one was saying one thing while another said something else. ^20 Then a spirit[*] came forward and stood before Jehovah and said, ‘I will fool him.’ Jehovah asked him, ‘How will you do it?’ ^21 He replied, ‘I will go out and become a deceptive spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’ So he said, ‘You will fool him, and what is more, you will be successful. Go out and do that.’ ^22 And now Jehovah has put a deceptive spirit in the mouth of these prophets of yours, but Jehovah has declared calamity for you.”

^23 Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Che·naʹa·nah now approached and struck Mi·caiʹah on the cheek and said: “Which way did the spirit of Jehovah pass from me to speak with you?” ^24 Mi·caiʹah replied: “Look! You will see which way on the day when you will enter the innermost room to hide.” ^25 Then the king of Israel said: “Take Mi·caiʹah and turn him over to Aʹmon the chief of the city and to Joʹash the king’s son. ^26 Tell them, ‘This is what the king says: “Put this fellow in the prison and feed him with a reduced allowance of bread and water until I return in peace.”’” ^27 But Mi·caiʹah said: “If you do return in peace, Jehovah has not spoken with me.” Then he added: “Take note, all you peoples.”

^28 So the king of Israel and Je·hoshʹa·phat the king of Judah went up to Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad. ^29 The king of Israel now said to Je·hoshʹa·phat: “I will disguise myself and will go into the battle, but you should put on your royal attire.” So the king of Israel disguised himself, and they entered the battle. ^30 Now the king of Syria had ordered his chariot commanders: “Do not fight with anyone, small or great, except the king of Israel.” ^31 And as soon as the chariot commanders saw Je·hoshʹa·phat, they said to themselves: “It is the king of Israel.” So they turned to fight against him; and Je·hoshʹa·phat began to cry for help, and Jehovah helped him, and God at once diverted them from him. ^32 When the chariot commanders saw that it was not the king of Israel, they immediately turned back from following him.

^33 But one man shot his bow at random,[*] and he struck the king of Israel between the joints of his coat of mail. So the king said to his charioteer: “Turn around and take me out of the battle,[*] for I have been badly wounded.” ^34 The fighting raged throughout that day, and the king of Israel had to be propped up in the chariot, facing the Syrians until the evening; and he died at sunset.

^ 2 Chron. 18:2 Or “persuaded.”

^ 2 Chron. 18:10 Or “push.”

^ 2 Chron. 18:20 Or “an angel.”

^ 2 Chron. 18:33 Or “in his innocence.”

^ 2 Chron. 18:33 Lit., “camp.”

2 Chronicles  19 : 1 - 11

19 Then King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah returned safely[*] to his own house[*] in Jerusalem. ^2 Jeʹhu the son of Ha·naʹni the visionary went out to meet him and said to King Je·hoshʹa·phat: “Is it the wicked you should be helping, and is it those who hate Jehovah you should love? Because of this the indignation of Jehovah is against you. ^3 Nevertheless, there are good things that have been found in you, because you cleared out the sacred poles[*] from the land and you have prepared your heart[*] to search for the true God.”

^4 Je·hoshʹa·phat continued living in Jerusalem, and he went out again among the people from Beʹer-sheʹba to the mountainous region of Eʹphra·im, to bring them back to Jehovah the God of their forefathers. ^5 He also appointed judges throughout the land in all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city. ^6 And he said to the judges: “Pay attention to what you are doing, for you do not judge for man but for Jehovah, and he is with you when you pass judgment. ^7 Now let the fear of Jehovah be upon you. Be careful about what you do, for with Jehovah our God there is no injustice, no partiality, no bribe-taking.”

^8 In Jerusalem also, Je·hoshʹa·phat appointed some of the Levites and the priests and some of the heads of the paternal houses of Israel to serve as judges for Jehovah and to settle legal cases for the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^9 And he commanded them: “This is what you should do in the fear of Jehovah, with faithfulness and a complete[*] heart: ^10 Whenever your brothers living in their cities bring a legal case that involves the shedding of blood or a question about a law, a commandment, regulations, or judgments, you should warn them so that they may not become guilty before Jehovah; otherwise his indignation will come against you and your brothers. This is what you should do, so that you may not incur guilt. ^11 Here is Am·a·riʹah the chief priest who is over you for every matter of Jehovah. Zeb·a·diʹah the son of Ishʹma·el is the leader of the house of Judah for every matter pertaining to the king. And the Levites will serve as officers for you. Be strong and act, and let Jehovah be with those who do what is good.”[*]

^ 2 Chron. 19:1 Or “in peace.”

^ 2 Chron. 19:1 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 19:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 19:3 Or “your heart is resolved.”

^ 2 Chron. 19:9 Or “completely devoted.”

^ 2 Chron. 19:11 Or “with what is good.”

2 Chronicles  20 : 1 - 37

20 Afterward the Moʹab·ites and the Amʹmon·ites, together with some of the Amʹmon·im,[*] came to wage war against Je·hoshʹa·phat. ^2 So Je·hoshʹa·phat was told: “A large crowd has come against you from the region of the sea,[*] from Eʹdom, and there they are in Hazʹa·zon-taʹmar, that is, En-gedʹi.” ^3 At that Je·hoshʹa·phat became afraid, and he resolved[*] to search for Jehovah. So he proclaimed a fast for all Judah. ^4 The people of Judah then gathered together to inquire of Jehovah; they came from all the cities of Judah to consult Jehovah.

^5 Then Je·hoshʹa·phat stood up in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem in the house of Jehovah before the new courtyard, ^6 and he said:

“O Jehovah the God of our forefathers, are you not God in the heavens; do you not have dominion over all the kingdoms of the nations? In your hand are power and might, and no one can stand against you. ^7 O our God, did you not drive away the inhabitants of this land from before your people Israel and then give it as a lasting possession to the offspring[*] of your friend Abraham? ^8 And they settled in it, and they built for you there a sanctuary for your name, saying, ^9 ‘If disaster should come on us, whether by sword, adverse judgment, pestilence, or famine, let us stand before this house and before you (for your name is in this house) and call to you for help out of our distress, and may you hear and save us.’ ^10 Now here are the men of Amʹmon, Moʹab, and the mountainous region of Seʹir, whom you did not allow Israel to invade when they came out of the land of Egypt. They turned away from them and did not annihilate them. ^11 Now they are repaying us by coming in to drive us out from your possession that you gave us as an inheritance. ^12 O our God, will you not execute judgment on them? For we are powerless before this large crowd that is coming against us; and we do not know what we should do, but our eyes are toward you.”

^13 Meanwhile, all those of Judah were standing before Jehovah, along with their little ones, their wives, and their children.[*]

^14 Then in the middle of the congregation, the spirit of Jehovah came upon Ja·ha·ziʹel son of Zech·a·riʹah son of Be·naiʹah son of Je·iʹel son of Mat·ta·niʹah the Levite of the sons of Aʹsaph. ^15 He said: “Pay attention, all Judah and you inhabitants of Jerusalem and King Je·hoshʹa·phat! Here is what Jehovah says to you, ‘Do not be afraid or be terrified because of this large crowd, for the battle is not yours but God’s. ^16 Tomorrow go down against them. They will be coming up by the pass of Ziz, and you will find them at the end of the valley[*] before the wilderness of Je·ruʹel. ^17 You will not need to fight this battle. Take your position, stand still, and see the salvation of Jehovah in your behalf.[*] O Judah and Jerusalem, do not be afraid or be terrified. Tomorrow go out against them, and Jehovah will be with you.’”

^18 At once Je·hoshʹa·phat bowed low with his face to the ground, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell down before Jehovah to worship Jehovah. ^19 Then the Levites who were descendants of the Koʹhath·ites and the Korʹah·ites rose up to praise Jehovah the God of Israel with a very loud voice.

^20 They rose up early the next morning and went out to the wilderness of Te·koʹa. As they went out, Je·hoshʹa·phat stood up and said: “Listen to me, O Judah and you inhabitants of Jerusalem! Put faith in Jehovah your God so that you may be able to stand firm.[*] Put faith in his prophets, and you will be successful.”

^21 After he consulted with the people, he appointed men to sing to Jehovah and to offer praise in holy adornment as they went out ahead of the armed men, saying: “Give thanks to Jehovah, for his loyal love endures forever.”

^22 When they began joyfully singing praises, Jehovah set an ambush against the men of Amʹmon, Moʹab, and the mountainous region of Seʹir who were invading Judah, and they struck each other down. ^23 And the Amʹmon·ites and the Moʹab·ites turned against the inhabitants of the mountainous region of Seʹir to destroy and annihilate them; and when they finished with the inhabitants of Seʹir, they helped to destroy one another.

^24 But when Judah came to the watchtower of the wilderness and looked toward the crowd, there they saw their carcasses fallen to the ground; there were no survivors. ^25 So Je·hoshʹa·phat and his people came to carry off the spoil from them, and they found among them an abundance of goods, clothing, and desirable articles, which they stripped off for themselves until they could carry no more. It took three days to carry off the spoil, for it was abundant. ^26 On the fourth day they congregated together at the Valley[*] of Berʹa·cah, for there they praised[*] Jehovah. That is why they named that place Valley of Berʹa·cah[*]—until today.

^27 Then all the men of Judah and Jerusalem, with Je·hoshʹa·phat at their head, returned to Jerusalem with rejoicing, for Jehovah had made them rejoice over their enemies. ^28 So they came into Jerusalem with stringed instruments, harps, and trumpets and went to the house of Jehovah. ^29 And the dread of God came upon all the kingdoms of the lands when they heard that Jehovah had fought against the enemies of Israel. ^30 Thus the kingdom of Je·hoshʹa·phat had no disturbance, and his God continued to give him rest on every side.

^31 And Je·hoshʹa·phat continued reigning over Judah. He was 35 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 25 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A·zuʹbah the daughter of Shilʹhi. ^32 He kept walking in the way of his father Aʹsa. He did not deviate from it, and he did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes. ^33 However, the high places were not removed, and the people had not yet prepared their heart for the God of their forefathers.

^34 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoshʹa·phat, from beginning to end, there it is written among the words of Jeʹhu the son of Ha·naʹni, which were included in the Book of the Kings of Israel. ^35 After this King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Judah made an alliance with King A·ha·ziʹah of Israel, who acted wickedly. ^36 So he made him his partner in making ships to go to Tarʹshish, and they built the ships in Eʹzi·on-geʹber. ^37 However, E·li·eʹzer the son of Dod·avʹa·hu of Ma·reʹsha spoke prophetically against Je·hoshʹa·phat, saying: “Because you have made an alliance with A·ha·ziʹah, Jehovah will destroy your works.” So the ships were wrecked, and they were unable to go to Tarʹshish.

^ 2 Chron. 20:1 Or possibly, “the Meunites.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:2 Evidently, the Dead Sea.

^ 2 Chron. 20:3 Lit., “set his face.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:7 Lit., “seed.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:13 Lit., “sons.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:16 Or “wadi.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:17 Or “see how Jehovah rescues you.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:20 Or “to endure.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:26 Or “Low Plain.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:26 Lit., “blessed.”

^ 2 Chron. 20:26 Meaning “Blessing.”

2 Chronicles  21 : 1 - 20

21 Then Je·hoshʹa·phat was laid to rest with his forefathers and was buried with his forefathers in the City of David; and his son Je·hoʹram became king in his place. ^2 His brothers, Je·hoshʹa·phat’s sons, were Az·a·riʹah, Je·hiʹel, Zech·a·riʹah, Az·a·riʹah, Miʹcha·el, and Sheph·a·tiʹah; all of these were the sons of King Je·hoshʹa·phat of Israel. ^3 And their father had given them many gifts in silver and gold, and valuable things, along with fortified cities in Judah; but he gave the kingdom to Je·hoʹram, for he was the firstborn.

^4 When Je·hoʹram had taken control of the kingdom of his father, he strengthened his position by killing all his brothers with the sword, as well as some of the princes of Israel. ^5 Je·hoʹram was 32 years old when he became king, and he reigned for eight years in Jerusalem. ^6 He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, just as those of the house of Aʹhab had done, for Aʹhab’s daughter had become his wife; and he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. ^7 But Jehovah did not want to bring the house of David to ruin for the sake of the covenant that he had made with David, since he had promised to give a lamp to him and to his sons always.

^8 In his days Eʹdom revolted against Judah and then set up its own king. ^9 So Je·hoʹram and his commanders crossed over with all his chariots, and he rose up by night and defeated the Eʹdom·ites who were surrounding him and the chariot commanders. ^10 But Eʹdom has kept up its revolt against Judah to this day. Libʹnah also revolted against him at that time, because he had abandoned Jehovah the God of his forefathers. ^11 He had also made high places on the mountains of Judah to cause the inhabitants of Jerusalem to commit spiritual prostitution, and he led Judah astray.

^12 Eventually a written message came to him from E·liʹjah the prophet, saying: “This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather says, ‘You have not walked in the ways of your father Je·hoshʹa·phat or in the ways of King Aʹsa of Judah. ^13 But you walk in the way of the kings of Israel and cause Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to commit spiritual prostitution like the prostitution of the house of Aʹhab, and you even killed your own brothers, the household of your father, who were better than you. ^14 Therefore, Jehovah is dealing a great blow to your people, to your sons, to your wives, and to all your possessions. ^15 And you will suffer with many sicknesses, including a disease of your intestines, until your intestines come out because of the disease, day after day.’”

^16 Then Jehovah stirred up against Je·hoʹram the Phi·lisʹtines[*] and the Arabs who were near the E·thi·oʹpi·ans. ^17 So they invaded Judah, forcing their way in, and carried off all the possessions that were found in the king’s house,[*] as well as his sons and his wives; and the only son left to him was Je·hoʹa·haz,[*] his youngest son. ^18 And after all of this, Jehovah afflicted him with an incurable disease in his intestines. ^19 Some time later, when two full years had passed, his intestines came out because of his disease, and he died while suffering severely from his disease; and his people did not make a burning for him like the burning that was made for his forefathers. ^20 He was 32 years old when he became king, and he reigned for eight years in Jerusalem. No one regretted it when he died. So they buried him in the City of David, but not in the burial places of the kings.

^ 2 Chron. 21:16 Lit., “the spirit of the Philistines.”

^ 2 Chron. 21:17 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 21:17 Also called Ahaziah.

2 Chronicles  22 : 1 - 12

22 Then the inhabitants of Jerusalem made his youngest son A·ha·ziʹah king in his place, for the marauder band that came with the Arabs to the camp had killed all the older ones. So A·ha·ziʹah the son of Je·hoʹram began to reign as king of Judah. ^2 A·ha·ziʹah was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ath·a·liʹah the granddaughter[*] of Omʹri.

^3 He too walked in the ways of the house of Aʹhab, for his mother became his adviser in acting wickedly. ^4 And he kept doing what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, like the house of Aʹhab, for they became his advisers after the death of his father, to his destruction. ^5 He followed their advice and went with Je·hoʹram the son of King Aʹhab of Israel to wage war against King Hazʹa·el of Syria at Raʹmoth-gilʹe·ad, where the archers wounded Je·hoʹram. ^6 He returned to Jezʹre·el to recover from the wounds that they had inflicted on him at Raʹmah when he fought against King Hazʹa·el of Syria.

A·ha·ziʹah[*] the son of Je·hoʹram the king of Judah went down to Jezʹre·el to see Je·hoʹram the son of Aʹhab, because he had been wounded.[*] ^7 But God brought about the downfall of A·ha·ziʹah by his coming to Je·hoʹram; and when he came, he went out with Je·hoʹram to meet Jeʹhu the grandson[*] of Nimʹshi, whom Jehovah had anointed to do away with[*] the house of Aʹhab. ^8 When Jeʹhu began to execute judgment on the house of Aʹhab, he found the princes of Judah and the sons of A·ha·ziʹah’s brothers, ministers of A·ha·ziʹah, and he killed them. ^9 Then he looked for A·ha·ziʹah; they captured him where he was hiding in Sa·marʹi·a, and they brought him to Jeʹhu. Then they put him to death and buried him, for they said: “He is the grandson of Je·hoshʹa·phat, who searched for Jehovah with all his heart.” There was no one of the house of A·ha·ziʹah who had the power to rule the kingdom.

^10 When Ath·a·liʹah, A·ha·ziʹah’s mother, saw that her son had died, she rose up and destroyed the entire royal line[*] of the house of Judah. ^11 However, Je·ho·shabʹe·ath the daughter of the king took Je·hoʹash the son of A·ha·ziʹah and stole him away from among the sons of the king who were to be put to death, and she put him and his nurse in an inner bedroom. Je·ho·shabʹe·ath the daughter of King Je·hoʹram (she was the wife of Je·hoiʹa·da the priest and a sister of A·ha·ziʹah) managed to keep him concealed from Ath·a·liʹah, so that she did not put him to death. ^12 He remained with them for six years, hidden at the house of the true God, while Ath·a·liʹah was ruling over the land.

^ 2 Chron. 22:2 Lit., “daughter.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:6 In some Hebrew manuscripts, “Azariah.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:6 Or “he was sick.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:7 Lit., “son.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:7 Lit., “cut off.”

^ 2 Chron. 22:10 Lit., “all seed of the kingdom.”

2 Chronicles  23 : 1 - 21

23 In the seventh year, Je·hoiʹa·da acted courageously and made a pact[*] with the chiefs of hundreds, namely, Az·a·riʹah the son of Je·roʹham, Ishʹma·el the son of Je·ho·haʹnan, Az·a·riʹah the son of Oʹbed, Ma·a·seiʹah the son of A·daiʹah, and E·li·shaʹphat the son of Zichʹri. ^2 Then they went throughout Judah and gathered together the Levites from all the cities of Judah and the heads of the paternal houses of Israel. When they came to Jerusalem, ^3 the entire congregation made a covenant with the king in the house of the true God, after which he said to them:

“Look! The king’s son will reign, just as Jehovah promised concerning the sons of David. ^4 This is what you are to do: One third of the priests and of the Levites who will be on duty on the Sabbath will be doorkeepers; ^5 another third will be at the house[*] of the king, and the other third will be at the Gate of the Foundation, and all the people will be in the courtyards of the house of Jehovah. ^6 Do not let anyone enter the house of Jehovah except the priests and the Levites who are ministering. These may enter because they are a holy group, and all the people will keep the obligation to Jehovah. ^7 The Levites must surround the king on every side, each with his weapons in hand. Anyone entering the house will be put to death. Stay with the king wherever he goes.”[*]

^8 The Levites and all Judah did exactly what Je·hoiʹa·da the priest had commanded. So each one took his men who were on duty on the Sabbath, together with those who were off duty on the Sabbath, for Je·hoiʹa·da the priest had not dismissed the divisions from their duty. ^9 Je·hoiʹa·da the priest then gave the chiefs of hundreds the spears and the bucklers[*] and the circular shields that had belonged to King David, which were in the house of the true God. ^10 He then stationed all the people, each with his weapon[*] in hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, by the altar and by the house, all around the king. ^11 Then they brought the king’s son out and put on him the crown[*] and the Testimony[*] and made him king, and Je·hoiʹa·da and his sons anointed him. Then they said: “Long live the king!”

^12 When Ath·a·liʹah heard the sound of the people running and praising the king, she immediately came to the people at the house of Jehovah. ^13 Then she saw the king standing there by his pillar at the entrance. The princes and the trumpeters were with the king, and all the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing the trumpets, and the singers with musical instruments were leading[*] the praises. At this Ath·a·liʹah ripped her garments apart and cried out: “Conspiracy! Conspiracy!” ^14 But Je·hoiʹa·da the priest brought out the chiefs of hundreds, those appointed over the army, and said to them: “Take her out from among the ranks, and if anyone follows her, put him to death with the sword!” For the priest had said: “Do not put her to death in the house of Jehovah.” ^15 So they seized her, and when she reached the entrance of the Horse Gate of the king’s house,[*] they immediately put her to death there.

^16 Then Je·hoiʹa·da made a covenant between himself and all the people and the king, that they would continue as the people of Jehovah. ^17 After that all the people came to the house[*] of Baʹal and tore it down, and they smashed his altars and his images, and they killed Matʹtan the priest of Baʹal in front of the altars. ^18 Then Je·hoiʹa·da put the oversight of the house of Jehovah in the hands of the priests and the Levites, whom David had assigned in divisions over the house of Jehovah to offer up the burnt sacrifices of Jehovah according to what is written in the Law of Moses, with rejoicing and with song, as directed by[*] David. ^19 He also stationed the gatekeepers by the gates of the house of Jehovah, so that no one unclean in any respect could enter. ^20 He now took the chiefs of hundreds, the nobles, the rulers of the people, and all the people of the land and escorted the king down from the house of Jehovah. Then they came through the upper gate to the king’s house[*] and seated the king on the throne of the kingdom. ^21 So all the people of the land rejoiced and the city was quiet, for they had put Ath·a·liʹah to death with the sword.

^ 2 Chron. 23:1 Or “covenant.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:5 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:7 Lit., “when he goes out and when he comes in.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:9 A small shield, often carried by archers.

^ 2 Chron. 23:10 Or “missile.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:11 Or “diadem.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:11 Possibly a scroll containing the Law of God.

^ 2 Chron. 23:13 Or “giving the signal for.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:15 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:17 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:18 Lit., “by the hands of.”

^ 2 Chron. 23:20 Or “palace.”

2 Chronicles  24 : 1 - 27

24 Je·hoʹash was seven years old when he became king, and he reigned for 40 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zibʹi·ah from Beʹer-sheʹba. ^2 Je·hoʹash continued doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes all the days of Je·hoiʹa·da the priest. ^3 Je·hoiʹa·da chose two wives for him, and he became father to sons and daughters.

^4 Afterward it was the heart’s desire of Je·hoʹash to renovate the house of Jehovah. ^5 So he gathered the priests and the Levites together and said to them: “Go out to the cities of Judah and collect money from all Israel to repair the house of your God from year to year; and you should act quickly in the matter.” But the Levites did not act quickly. ^6 So the king called Je·hoiʹa·da the chief and said to him: “Why have you not required the Levites to bring in from Judah and Jerusalem the sacred tax ordered by Moses the servant of Jehovah, the sacred tax of the congregation of Israel, for the tent of the Testimony? ^7 For the sons of Ath·a·liʹah, that wicked woman, had broken into the house of the true God, and they had used all the holy things of the house of Jehovah for the Baʹals.” ^8 Then, at the king’s order, a chest was made and placed outside at the gate of the house of Jehovah. ^9 After that a proclamation was issued throughout Judah and Jerusalem to bring to Jehovah the sacred tax that Moses the servant of the true God had imposed on Israel in the wilderness. ^10 All the princes and all the people rejoiced, and they kept bringing contributions and dropping them into the chest until it was full.[*]

^11 Whenever the Levites brought the chest in to be turned over to the king and they saw that there was a great deal of money in it, the secretary of the king and the commissioner of the chief priest would come and empty the chest, and then they would take it back to its place. That was what they did from day to day, and they gathered money in abundance. ^12 Then the king and Je·hoiʹa·da would give it to those supervising the work of the service of Jehovah’s house, and they would hire the stonecutters and the craftsmen for renovating Jehovah’s house, and also workers in iron and copper to repair Jehovah’s house. ^13 And those supervising the work got it started, and the repair work progressed under their supervision, and they restored the house of the true God to its proper condition and reinforced it. ^14 And as soon as they finished, they brought the money that was left over to the king and Je·hoiʹa·da, and they used it to make utensils for the house of Jehovah, utensils for the ministry and for making offerings and cups and utensils of gold and of silver. And they would offer up burnt sacrifices at the house of Jehovah regularly all the days of Je·hoiʹa·da.

^15 When Je·hoiʹa·da was old and satisfied with years, he died; he was 130 years old at his death. ^16 So they buried him in the City of David along with the kings, because he had done good in Israel with respect to the true God and His house.

^17 After Je·hoiʹa·da’s death the princes of Judah came and bowed down to the king, and the king listened to them. ^18 They abandoned the house of Jehovah the God of their forefathers and began serving the sacred poles[*] and the idols, so that God’s anger came[*] against Judah and Jerusalem because of their guilt. ^19 He kept sending prophets among them to bring them back to Jehovah, and they kept warning[*] them, but they refused to listen.

^20 God’s spirit came upon[*] Zech·a·riʹah the son of Je·hoiʹa·da the priest, and he stood above the people and said to them: “This is what the true God says, ‘Why are you violating the commandments of Jehovah? You will not be successful! Because you have abandoned Jehovah, he will, in turn, abandon you.’” ^21 But they conspired against him and stoned him at the king’s order in the courtyard of Jehovah’s house. ^22 Thus King Je·hoʹash did not remember the loyal love that his father[*] Je·hoiʹa·da had shown toward him, and he killed his son, who said as he was dying: “May Jehovah see to it and call you to account.”

^23 At the beginning of the year[*] the Syrian army came up against Je·hoʹash, and they invaded Judah and Jerusalem. Then they did away with all the princes of the people, and they sent all their spoil to the king of Damascus. ^24 For although the invading Syrian army had a small number of men, Jehovah handed over to them a very large army, because they had abandoned Jehovah the God of their forefathers; so they[*] executed judgment on Je·hoʹash. ^25 And when they withdrew from him (for they left him severely wounded[*]), his own servants conspired against him because he had shed the blood of the sons[*] of Je·hoiʹa·da the priest. They killed him on his own bed. So he died and they buried him in the City of David, but they did not bury him in the burial places of the kings.

^26 These were the conspirators against him: Zaʹbad the son of Shimʹe·ath the Amʹmon·it·ess and Je·hozʹa·bad the son of Shimʹrith the Moʹab·i·tess. ^27 Regarding his sons and the many pronouncements against him and the renovation[*] of the house of the true God, all these things are recorded in the writings[*] of the Book of the Kings. And his son Am·a·ziʹah became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 24:10 Or possibly, “until they all had given.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:18 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 24:18 Lit., “there was anger.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:19 Or “bearing witness against.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:20 Lit., “clothed.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:22 That is, Zechariah’s father.

^ 2 Chron. 24:23 Lit., “the turn of the year.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:24 That is, the Syrians.

^ 2 Chron. 24:25 Or “with many diseases.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:25 Or “son.” Possibly the plural form denotes excellence.

^ 2 Chron. 24:27 Lit., “founding.”

^ 2 Chron. 24:27 Or “exposition; commentary.”

2 Chronicles  25 : 1 - 28

25 Am·a·ziʹah was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·ho·adʹdan of Jerusalem. ^2 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, but not with a complete heart. ^3 As soon as he had the kingdom firmly in his control, he killed his servants who had killed his father the king. ^4 But he did not put their sons to death, for he acted in harmony with what is written in the Law, in the book of Moses, where Jehovah commanded: “Fathers should not die for their sons, and sons should not die for their fathers; but each one should die for his own sin.”

^5 And Am·a·ziʹah gathered Judah together and had them stand according to the paternal houses, by the chiefs of thousands and by the chiefs of hundreds for all Judah and Benjamin. He registered them from 20 years old and up, and he found them to be 300,000 trained[*] warriors to serve in the army, able to handle the lance and the large shield. ^6 Further, he hired from Israel 100,000 mighty warriors for 100 silver talents.[*] ^7 But a man of the true God came to him, saying: “O king, do not let the army of Israel go with you, for Jehovah is not with Israel, not with any of the Eʹphra·im·ites. ^8 But go by yourself, act, and be courageous in battle. Otherwise, the true God could cause you to stumble before an enemy, for God has the power to help and to cause stumbling.” ^9 At this Am·a·ziʹah said to the man of the true God: “But what about the 100 talents that I have given to the troops of Israel?” The man of the true God replied: “Jehovah has the means to give you much more than that.” ^10 So Am·a·ziʹah dismissed the troops that had come to him from Eʹphra·im, sending them to their own place. However, they were very angry with Judah, so they returned to their own place in the heat of anger.

^11 Then Am·a·ziʹah took courage and led his own troops to the Valley of Salt, and he struck down 10,000 men of Seʹir. ^12 And the men of Judah captured 10,000 alive. So they brought them to the top of the crag and threw them down from the top of the crag, and they were all dashed to pieces. ^13 But the members of the troop whom Am·a·ziʹah had sent back from accompanying him to the war were making raids on the cities of Judah, from Sa·marʹi·a clear to Beth-hoʹron; they struck down 3,000 of them and took much spoil.

^14 But after Am·a·ziʹah returned from striking down the Eʹdom·ites, he brought the gods of the men of Seʹir and set them up for himself as gods, and he began to bow down before them and to make sacrificial smoke to them. ^15 So Jehovah grew very angry with Am·a·ziʹah, and he sent a prophet who said to him: “Why are you following the people’s gods that did not rescue their own people out of your hand?” ^16 As he spoke to him, the king said: “Did we appoint you as an adviser to the king? Stop! Why should they strike you down?” Then the prophet quit, but he added: “I know that God has decided to bring you to ruin, because you have done this and you have not listened to my advice.”

^17 After consulting with his advisers, King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah sent a message to Je·hoʹash son of Je·hoʹa·haz son of Jeʹhu the king of Israel, saying: “Come, let us confront each other in battle.”[*] ^18 King Je·hoʹash of Israel sent this message to King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah: “The thorny weed in Lebʹa·non sent a message to the cedar in Lebʹa·non, ‘Give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ However, a wild beast of Lebʹa·non passed by and trampled down the thorny weed. ^19 You have said, ‘Look! I[*] have struck down Eʹdom.’ So your heart has become arrogant, wanting to be glorified. But now stay in your own house.[*] Why should you provoke disaster and fall, bringing Judah down with you?”

^20 But Am·a·ziʹah did not listen, for this was from the true God to give them into the hand of the enemy, because they had followed the gods of Eʹdom. ^21 So King Je·hoʹash of Israel went up, and he and King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah confronted each other in battle at Beth-sheʹmesh, which belongs to Judah. ^22 Judah was defeated by Israel, so each one fled to his home.[*] ^23 King Je·hoʹash of Israel captured King Am·a·ziʹah of Judah, son of Je·hoʹash son of Je·hoʹa·haz,[*] at Beth-sheʹmesh. Then he brought him to Jerusalem and made a breach in the wall of Jerusalem from the Gate of Eʹphra·im to the Corner Gate, 400 cubits.[*] ^24 He took all the gold and the silver and all the articles that were found in the house of the true God with[*] Oʹbed-eʹdom and in the treasuries of the king’s house,[*] as well as hostages. Then he returned to Sa·marʹi·a.

^25 Am·a·ziʹah the son of Je·hoʹash the king of Judah lived for 15 years after the death of Je·hoʹash the son of Je·hoʹa·haz the king of Israel. ^26 As for the rest of the history of Am·a·ziʹah, from beginning to end, look! is it not written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and of Israel? ^27 From the time that Am·a·ziʹah turned away from following Jehovah, they formed a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Laʹchish, but they sent men after him to Laʹchish and put him to death there. ^28 So they carried him back on horses and buried him with his forefathers in the city of Judah.

^ 2 Chron. 25:5 Lit., “chosen.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:6 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 25:17 Or “meet face-to-face.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:19 Lit., “You.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:19 Or “palace.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:22 Lit., “tents.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:23 Also called Ahaziah.

^ 2 Chron. 25:23 About 178 m (584 ft). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 25:24 Or “under the care of.”

^ 2 Chron. 25:24 Or “palace.”

2 Chronicles  26 : 1 - 23

26 Then all the people of Judah took Uz·ziʹah, who was 16 years old, and made him king in place of his father Am·a·ziʹah. ^2 He rebuilt Eʹloth and restored it to Judah after the king[*] was laid to rest with his forefathers. ^3 Uz·ziʹah was 16 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 52 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Je·co·liʹah of Jerusalem. ^4 He continued to do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Am·a·ziʹah had done. ^5 And he kept searching for God in the days of Zech·a·riʹah, who taught him to fear the true God. During the time he was searching for Jehovah, the true God made him prosper.

^6 He went out and fought against the Phi·lisʹtines and broke through the wall of Gath, the wall of Jabʹneh, and the wall of Ashʹdod. Then he built cities in the territory of Ashʹdod and among the Phi·lisʹtines. ^7 The true God continued to help him against the Phi·lisʹtines, against the Arabians who were dwelling in Gur·baʹal, and against the Me·uʹnim. ^8 The Amʹmon·ites began to give tribute to Uz·ziʹah. His fame eventually spread as far as Egypt, for he became extremely powerful. ^9 Moreover, Uz·ziʹah built towers in Jerusalem by the Corner Gate, the Valley Gate, and the Buttress, and he fortified them. ^10 Further, he built towers in the wilderness and dug[*] many cisterns (for he had a great deal of livestock); he also did so in the She·pheʹlah and on the plain.[*] He had farmers and vinedressers in the mountains and in Carʹmel, for he loved agriculture.

^11 Moreover, Uz·ziʹah came to have an army equipped for war. They would go out on military campaigns, organized in divisions. They were numbered and registered by Je·iʹel the secretary and Ma·a·seiʹah the officer, under the command of Han·a·niʹah, one of the king’s princes. ^12 The entire number of the heads of the paternal houses who were over these mighty warriors was 2,600. ^13 The armed forces under their command numbered 307,500 men ready for war, a powerful military force to support the king against the enemy. ^14 Uz·ziʹah equipped the entire army with shields, lances, helmets, coats of mail, bows, and slingstones. ^15 Further, in Jerusalem he made engines of war designed by engineers; they were set on the towers and on the corners of the walls and could shoot arrows and large stones. So his fame spread far and wide, for he received tremendous help and he became strong.

^16 However, as soon as he was strong, his heart became haughty to his own ruin, and he acted unfaithfully against Jehovah his God by entering the temple of Jehovah to burn incense on the altar of incense. ^17 Immediately Az·a·riʹah the priest and 80 other courageous priests of Jehovah went in after him. ^18 They confronted King Uz·ziʹah and said to him: “It is not proper for you, Uz·ziʹah, to burn incense to Jehovah! It is only the priests who should burn incense, for they are the descendants of Aaron, those who have been sanctified. Go out from the sanctuary, for you have acted unfaithfully and you will receive no glory from Jehovah God for this.”

^19 But Uz·ziʹah, who had a censer in his hand to burn incense, became enraged; and during his rage against the priests, leprosy broke out on his forehead in the presence of the priests in the house of Jehovah next to the altar of incense. ^20 When Az·a·riʹah the chief priest and all the priests turned toward him, they saw that he had been stricken with leprosy in his forehead! So they rushed him out of there, and he himself hurried out, because Jehovah had struck him.

^21 King Uz·ziʹah remained a leper until the day of his death, and he kept staying in a separate house as a leper, for he had been excluded from the house of Jehovah. His son Joʹtham was in charge of the king’s house,[*] judging the people of the land.

^22 And the rest of the history of Uz·ziʹah, from beginning to end, was recorded by the prophet Isaiah the son of Aʹmoz. ^23 Then Uz·ziʹah was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him with his forefathers, but in the burial field that belonged to the kings, for they said: “He is a leper.” And his son Joʹtham became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 26:2 That is, his father Amaziah.

^ 2 Chron. 26:10 Or “hewed out,” likely from rock.

^ 2 Chron. 26:10 Or “tableland.”

^ 2 Chron. 26:21 Or “palace.”

2 Chronicles  28 : 1 - 27

28 Aʹhaz was 20 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 16 years in Jerusalem. He did not do what was right in Jehovah’s eyes as David his forefather had done. ^2 Instead, he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and he even made metal statues[*] of the Baʹals. ^3 Moreover, he made sacrificial smoke in the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom[*] and burned up his sons in the fire, following the detestable practices of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the Israelites. ^4 He also kept sacrificing and making sacrificial smoke on the high places, on the hills, and under every luxuriant tree.

^5 So Jehovah his God gave him into the hand of the king of Syria, so that they defeated him and carried off a great number of captives and brought them to Damascus. He was also given into the hand of the king of Israel, who inflicted on him a great slaughter. ^6 For Peʹkah the son of Rem·a·liʹah killed in Judah 120,000 in one day, all brave men, because they had abandoned Jehovah the God of their forefathers. ^7 And Zichʹri, an Eʹphra·im·ite warrior, killed the king’s son Ma·a·seiʹah and Az·riʹkam, who was in charge of the palace,[*] and El·kaʹnah, who was second to the king. ^8 Moreover, the Israelites took 200,000 of their brothers captive—women, sons, and daughters; they also seized a great deal of spoil, and they took the spoil to Sa·marʹi·a.

^9 But a prophet of Jehovah named Oʹded was there. He went out before the army that was coming to Sa·marʹi·a and said to them: “Look! It was because Jehovah the God of your forefathers was angry with Judah that he gave them into your hand, and you slaughtered them with a fury that has reached clear to the heavens. ^10 And now you intend to make the people of Judah and Jerusalem your male and female servants. Nevertheless, are you not also guilty before Jehovah your God? ^11 Now listen to me and return the captives whom you took from your brothers, for Jehovah’s burning anger is against you.”

^12 At that some of the chiefs of the Eʹphra·im·ites, Az·a·riʹah the son of Je·ho·haʹnan, Ber·e·chiʹah the son of Me·shilʹle·moth, Je·hiz·kiʹah the son of Shalʹlum, and A·maʹsa the son of Hadʹlai, confronted those coming in from the military campaign, ^13 and they said to them: “Do not bring the captives in here, for it will make us guilty before Jehovah. What you intend to do will add to our sins and to our guilt, for our guilt is already great and there is burning anger against Israel.” ^14 So the armed soldiers handed over the captives and the plunder to the princes and the entire congregation. ^15 Then the men who had been designated by name rose up and took hold of the captives, and they provided clothes from the spoil for all those among them who were naked. So they clothed them and gave them sandals, food and drink, and oil for their skin. Furthermore, they transported the feeble on donkeys and brought them to their brothers in Jerʹi·cho, the city of palm trees. After that they returned to Sa·marʹi·a.

^16 At that time King Aʹhaz asked the kings of As·syrʹi·a for help. ^17 And once again the Eʹdom·ites invaded and attacked Judah and carried off captives. ^18 The Phi·lisʹtines also made a raid on the cities of the She·pheʹlah and the Negʹeb of Judah and captured Beth-sheʹmesh, Aiʹja·lon, Ge·deʹroth, Soʹco and its dependent[*] towns, Timʹnah and its dependent towns, and Gimʹzo and its dependent towns; and they settled there. ^19 Jehovah humbled Judah because of King Aʹhaz of Israel, for he had let Judah go unrestrained, resulting in great unfaithfulness toward Jehovah.

^20 King Tilʹgath-pil·neʹser of As·syrʹi·a eventually came against him and caused him distress rather than strengthening him. ^21 For Aʹhaz had stripped the house of Jehovah and the house[*] of the king and the houses of the princes and made a gift to the king of As·syrʹi·a; but it was of no help to him. ^22 And during his time of distress, King Aʹhaz acted even more unfaithfully toward Jehovah. ^23 He began to sacrifice to the gods of Damascus that had defeated him, and he went on to say: “Because the gods of the kings of Syria are helping them, I will sacrifice to them so that they may help me.” But they caused him and all Israel to stumble. ^24 Furthermore, Aʹhaz collected the utensils of the house of the true God; he then cut to pieces the utensils of the house of the true God, closed the doors of the house of Jehovah, and made altars for himself in every corner of Jerusalem. ^25 And in all the cities of Judah, he made high places for making sacrificial smoke to other gods, and he offended Jehovah the God of his forefathers.

^26 As for the rest of his history, all his dealings from beginning to end, there it is written in the Book of the Kings of Judah and of Israel. ^27 Then Aʹhaz was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the city, in Jerusalem, for they did not bring him into the burial places of the kings of Israel. And his son Hez·e·kiʹah became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 28:2 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Chron. 28:3 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

^ 2 Chron. 28:7 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Chron. 28:18 Or “surrounding.”

^ 2 Chron. 28:21 Or “palace.”

2 Chronicles  29 : 1 - 36

29 Hez·e·kiʹah became king at the age of 25, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A·biʹjah the daughter of Zech·a·riʹah. ^2 He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as David his forefather had done. ^3 In the first year of his reign, in the first month, he opened the doors of the house of Jehovah and repaired them. ^4 Then he brought the priests and the Levites and assembled them in the square to the east. ^5 He said to them: “Listen to me, you Levites. Now sanctify yourselves and sanctify the house of Jehovah the God of your forefathers, and remove what is impure from the holy place. ^6 For our fathers have been unfaithful and have done what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah our God. They abandoned him and turned their faces away from the tabernacle of Jehovah and turned their back on him. ^7 They also closed the doors of the porch and extinguished the lamps. They stopped burning incense and offering up burnt sacrifices in the holy place to the God of Israel. ^8 Therefore, Jehovah’s indignation came against Judah and Jerusalem, so that he made them an object of horror and astonishment and a cause for whistling,[*] as you can see with your own eyes. ^9 Here our forefathers fell by the sword, and our sons, our daughters, and our wives went into captivity for this. ^10 Now it is my heart’s desire to make a covenant with Jehovah the God of Israel, so that his burning anger may turn away from us. ^11 My sons, now is not the time to be negligent,[*] for Jehovah has chosen you to stand before him, to serve as his ministers, and to make his sacrifices smoke.”

^12 At that the Levites rose up: Maʹhath the son of A·maʹsai and Joel the son of Az·a·riʹah of the Koʹhath·ites; from the Me·rarʹites, Kish the son of Abʹdi and Az·a·riʹah the son of Je·halʹle·lel; from the Gerʹshon·ites, Joʹah the son of Zimʹmah and Eʹden the son of Joʹah; ^13 from the sons of E·li·zaʹphan, Shimʹri and Je·uʹel; from the sons of Aʹsaph, Zech·a·riʹah and Mat·ta·niʹah; ^14 from the sons of Heʹman, Je·hiʹel and Shimʹe·i; from the sons of Je·duʹthun, She·maiʹah and Uzʹzi·el. ^15 Then they gathered their brothers together and sanctified themselves and came, as the king had commanded by the words of Jehovah, to cleanse the house of Jehovah. ^16 The priests then went inside the house of Jehovah to do the cleansing and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of Jehovah and took it to the courtyard of the house of Jehovah. In turn the Levites took it and carried it outside to the Kidʹron Valley. ^17 Thus they began the sanctification on the first day of the first month, and on the eighth day of the month they reached the porch of Jehovah. They sanctified the house of Jehovah for eight days, and on the 16th day of the first month they finished.

^18 After that they went in to King Hez·e·kiʹah and said: “We have cleansed the whole house of Jehovah, the altar of burnt offering and all its utensils, and the table of the layer bread[*] and all its utensils. ^19 And all the utensils that King Aʹhaz cast aside during his reign when he acted unfaithfully we have made ready and sanctified, and they are before the altar of Jehovah.”

^20 And King Hez·e·kiʹah got up early and gathered the princes of the city together, and they went up to the house of Jehovah. ^21 They brought seven bulls, seven rams, seven male lambs, and seven male goats as a sin offering for the kingdom, for the sanctuary, and for Judah. So he told the priests, the descendants of Aaron, to offer them up on the altar of Jehovah. ^22 Then they slaughtered the cattle, and the priests took the blood and sprinkled it on the altar; next they slaughtered the rams and sprinkled the blood on the altar, and they slaughtered the male lambs and sprinkled the blood on the altar. ^23 Then they brought the male goats of the sin offering before the king and the congregation and laid their hands on them. ^24 The priests slaughtered them and made a sin offering with their blood on the altar, to make atonement for all Israel, because the king said that the burnt offering and the sin offering should be for all Israel.

^25 Meanwhile, he had the Levites stationed at the house of Jehovah with cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps, by the commandment of David and of Gad the king’s visionary and of Nathan the prophet, for the commandment was from Jehovah through his prophets. ^26 So the Levites were standing with the instruments of David, and the priests with the trumpets.

^27 Then Hez·e·kiʹah ordered that the burnt sacrifice be offered on the altar. When the burnt offering started, the song of Jehovah started and also the trumpets, following the direction of the instruments of King David of Israel. ^28 And the whole congregation bowed down while the song was sung and the trumpets were sounding—all this continued until the burnt offering was finished. ^29 And as soon as they finished making the offering, the king and all those with him bowed low and prostrated themselves. ^30 King Hez·e·kiʹah and the princes now told the Levites to praise Jehovah with the words of David and of Aʹsaph the visionary. So they offered praise with great rejoicing, and they bowed down and prostrated themselves.

^31 Then Hez·e·kiʹah said: “Now that you have been set apart[*] for Jehovah, come and bring sacrifices and thanksgiving offerings to the house of Jehovah.” So the congregation began to bring sacrifices and thanksgiving offerings, and everyone with a willing heart brought burnt offerings. ^32 The number of burnt offerings that the congregation brought was 70 cattle, 100 rams, 200 male lambs—all of these as a burnt offering to Jehovah— ^33 and the holy offerings were 600 cattle and 3,000 of the flock. ^34 But there were not enough priests to skin all the burnt offerings, so their brothers the Levites helped them out until the work was finished and until the priests could sanctify themselves, for the Levites were more conscientious[*] about sanctifying themselves than the priests were. ^35 Also, there were many burnt offerings, as well as the fat pieces of the communion sacrifices and the drink offerings for the burnt offerings. Thus the service of the house of Jehovah was restored.[*] ^36 So Hez·e·kiʹah and all the people rejoiced over what the true God had established for the people, for this had all happened so suddenly.

^ 2 Chron. 29:8 Or “mocking.”

^ 2 Chron. 29:11 Or “to rest.”

^ 2 Chron. 29:18 That is, the showbread.

^ 2 Chron. 29:31 Lit., “Now you have filled your hand.”

^ 2 Chron. 29:34 Lit., “upright of heart.”

^ 2 Chron. 29:35 Or “prepared.”

2 Chronicles  30 : 1 - 27

30 Hez·e·kiʹah sent word to all Israel and Judah, and even wrote letters to Eʹphra·im and Ma·nasʹseh, to come to the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem to observe the Passover to Jehovah the God of Israel. ^2 However, the king, his princes, and the whole congregation in Jerusalem decided to observe the Passover in the second month, ^3 for they had not been able to observe it at the regular time, because not enough priests had sanctified themselves nor had the people gathered in Jerusalem. ^4 This arrangement seemed right in the eyes of the king and the entire congregation. ^5 So they decided to make an announcement throughout Israel, from Beʹer-sheʹba to Dan, that the people should come and observe the Passover to Jehovah the God of Israel at Jerusalem, for as a group they had not observed it according to what is written.

^6 Then the couriers[*] went throughout all Israel and Judah with the letters from the king and his princes, as the king had commanded, saying: “People of Israel, return to Jehovah the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, so that he may return to the remnant who escaped out of the hand of the kings of As·syrʹi·a. ^7 Do not be like your forefathers and your brothers who acted unfaithfully toward Jehovah the God of their forefathers, so that he made them an object of horror, just as you are seeing. ^8 Now do not be obstinate like your forefathers. Submit to Jehovah and come to his sanctuary that he has sanctified forever and serve Jehovah your God, so that his burning anger may turn away from you. ^9 For when you return to Jehovah, your brothers and your sons will be shown mercy by their captors and will be allowed to return to this land, for Jehovah your God is compassionate[*] and merciful, and he will not turn his face away from you if you return to him.”

^10 So the couriers[*] went from city to city throughout the land of Eʹphra·im and Ma·nasʹseh, even to Zebʹu·lun, but the people were making fun of them and mocking them. ^11 However, some individuals from Ashʹer, Ma·nasʹseh, and Zebʹu·lun humbled themselves and came to Jerusalem. ^12 The hand of the true God was also in Judah to unite them[*] to carry out what the king and the princes had commanded by the word of Jehovah.

^13 A multitude of people gathered together at Jerusalem to observe the Festival of Unleavened Bread in the second month; it was a very large congregation. ^14 They rose up and removed the altars that were in Jerusalem, and they removed all the incense altars and threw them into the Kidʹron Valley. ^15 Then they slaughtered the Passover sacrifice on the 14th day of the second month. The priests and the Levites felt ashamed, so they sanctified themselves and brought burnt offerings to the house of Jehovah. ^16 They took their customary places, according to the Law of Moses the man of the true God; then the priests sprinkled the blood received from the hand of the Levites. ^17 There were many in the congregation who had not sanctified themselves, and the Levites were in charge of slaughtering the Passover sacrifices for all who were not clean, to sanctify them to Jehovah. ^18 For a great number of the people, especially those from Eʹphra·im, Ma·nasʹseh, Isʹsa·char, and Zebʹu·lun, had not cleansed themselves, but they still ate the Passover, contrary to what is written. But Hez·e·kiʹah prayed for them, saying: “May Jehovah, who is good, make allowance for ^19 everyone who has prepared his heart to search for the true God, Jehovah, the God of his forefathers, although he has not been purified according to the standard of holiness.” ^20 And Jehovah listened to Hez·e·kiʹah and pardoned[*] the people.

^21 So the Israelites who were in Jerusalem observed the Festival of Unleavened Bread for seven days with great rejoicing, and the Levites and the priests were praising Jehovah day by day, loudly playing their instruments to Jehovah. ^22 Moreover, Hez·e·kiʹah spoke to and encouraged[*] all the Levites who served Jehovah with discretion. And they ate throughout the festival for seven days, sacrificing communion sacrifices and giving thanks to Jehovah the God of their forefathers.

^23 Then all the congregation decided to observe it for seven more days, so they observed it for seven more days with rejoicing. ^24 And King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah contributed for the congregation 1,000 bulls and 7,000 sheep, and the princes contributed for the congregation 1,000 bulls and 10,000 sheep; and priests were sanctifying themselves in great number. ^25 And all the congregation of Judah, the priests, the Levites, all the congregation that came from Israel, and the foreign residents who came from the land of Israel and those living in Judah continued rejoicing. ^26 And there was great rejoicing in Jerusalem, for from the days of Solʹo·mon the son of David the king of Israel, nothing like this had happened in Jerusalem. ^27 Finally the Levite priests stood up and blessed the people; and God heard their voice, and their prayer reached his holy dwelling, the heavens.

^ 2 Chron. 30:6 Lit., “runners.”

^ 2 Chron. 30:9 Or “gracious.”

^ 2 Chron. 30:10 Lit., “runners.”

^ 2 Chron. 30:12 Lit., “to give them one heart.”

^ 2 Chron. 30:20 Lit., “healed.”

^ 2 Chron. 30:22 Lit., “spoke to the heart of.”

2 Chronicles  31 : 1 - 21

31 As soon as they had finished all of this, all the Israelites who were present went out to the cities of Judah, and they smashed the sacred pillars, cut down the sacred poles,[*] and tore down the high places and the altars throughout Judah and Benjamin, as well as in Eʹphra·im and Ma·nasʹseh, until they had destroyed them completely, after which all the Israelites returned to their cities, each one to his own possession.

^2 Then Hez·e·kiʹah appointed the priests in their divisions and the Levites in their divisions, each of the priests and Levites for their service, for the burnt offerings and the communion sacrifices, to minister and to give thanks and praise in the gates of the courtyards[*] of Jehovah. ^3 A portion of the king’s own goods was given for the burnt offerings, including the morning and evening offerings, as well as the burnt offerings for the Sabbaths, the new moons, and the festivals, according to what is written in the Law of Jehovah.

^4 Furthermore, he commanded the people living in Jerusalem to give the portion due the priests and the Levites, so that they might adhere strictly[*] to the law of Jehovah. ^5 As soon as the order was issued, the Israelites gave in great quantities the firstfruits of the grain, new wine, oil, and honey, and of all the produce of the field; they brought in abundantly the tenth of everything. ^6 And the people of Israel and of Judah living in the cities of Judah also brought in the tenth of cattle and sheep and the tenth of the holy things that were sanctified to Jehovah their God. They brought it in and put it in many heaps. ^7 In the third month they began laying their contributions in heaps; and in the seventh month they finished. ^8 When Hez·e·kiʹah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they praised Jehovah and blessed his people Israel.

^9 Hez·e·kiʹah asked the priests and the Levites about the heaps, ^10 and Az·a·riʹah the chief priest of the house of Zaʹdok said to him: “From the time they started bringing the contributions into the house of Jehovah, the people have been eating to satisfaction and there is still an abundant surplus, for Jehovah has blessed his people, and this great plenty is left over.”

^11 At this Hez·e·kiʹah told them to prepare storerooms[*] in the house of Jehovah, so they prepared them. ^12 They kept faithfully bringing in the contributions, the tenth parts,[*] and the holy things; Con·a·niʹah the Levite was put in charge of all of this as supervisor, and his brother Shimʹe·i was second. ^13 Je·hiʹel, Az·a·ziʹah, Naʹhath, Asʹa·hel, Jerʹi·moth, Joʹza·bad, Eʹli·el, Is·ma·chiʹah, Maʹhath, and Be·naiʹah were commissioners assisting Con·a·niʹah and his brother Shimʹe·i, by the order of King Hez·e·kiʹah, and Az·a·riʹah was supervisor of the house of the true God. ^14 And Koʹre the son of Imʹnah, the Levite gatekeeper on the east side, was in charge of the voluntary offerings of the true God, and he distributed the contribution made to Jehovah and the most holy things. ^15 And under his direction were Eʹden, Mi·niʹa·min, Jeshʹu·a, She·maiʹah, Am·a·riʹah, and Shec·a·niʹah, in the cities of the priests, in their office of trust, to distribute equally to their brothers in the divisions, to great and small alike. ^16 This was in addition to the distribution made to the males from three years old and up who were listed in the genealogical enrollment, who came daily to serve in the house of Jehovah and to carry out the duties of their divisions.

^17 The genealogical enrollment of the priests was by their paternal house, as was that of the Levites who were 20 years old and up, by the duties of their divisions. ^18 The genealogical enrollment included all their children, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, their entire congregation—for they kept themselves sanctified for what was holy because of their office of trust— ^19 as well as the descendants of Aaron, the priests who were living in the fields of the pastures surrounding their cities. In all the cities, men had been designated by name to give portions to every male among the priests and to everyone included in the genealogical enrollment of the Levites.

^20 Hez·e·kiʹah did this throughout Judah, and he continued to do what was good and right and faithful before Jehovah his God. ^21 And every work that he undertook to search for his God, whether in connection with the service of the house of the true God or in the Law and the commandment, he did wholeheartedly, and he was successful.

^ 2 Chron. 31:1 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 31:2 Lit., “camps.”

^ 2 Chron. 31:4 Or “devote themselves fully.”

^ 2 Chron. 31:11 Or “dining rooms.”

^ 2 Chron. 31:12 Or “tithes.”

2 Chronicles  32 : 1 - 33

32 After these things and these acts of faithfulness, King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a came and invaded Judah. He besieged the fortified cities, intent on breaking through and capturing them.

^2 When Hez·e·kiʹah saw that Sen·nachʹer·ib had come and intended to wage war against Jerusalem, ^3 he decided, after consulting with his princes and his warriors, to stop up the waters of the springs outside the city, and they gave him their support. ^4 Many people were gathered together, and they stopped up all the springs and the stream that flowed through the land, saying: “Why should the kings of As·syrʹi·a come and find plenty of water?”

^5 Furthermore, with determination he rebuilt the entire broken-down wall and raised towers on it, and outside he made another wall. He also repaired the Mound[*] of the City of David, and he made a large number of weapons[*] and shields. ^6 He then appointed military chiefs over the people and assembled them at the public square of the city gate and encouraged them,[*] saying: ^7 “Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid or be terrified because of the king of As·syrʹi·a and all the multitude with him, for there are more with us than there are with him. ^8 With him is an arm of flesh,[*] but with us is Jehovah our God to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people were strengthened by the words of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah.

^9 After this, while King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a was at Laʹchish with all his imperial might,[*] he sent his servants to Jerusalem, to King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah and to all the Ju·deʹans in Jerusalem, saying:

^10 “This is what King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a says, ‘In what are you trusting that you remain in Jerusalem while it is besieged? ^11 Is not Hez·e·kiʹah misleading you and handing you over to die by famine and thirst, saying: “Jehovah our God will rescue us from the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a”? ^12 Is this not the same Hez·e·kiʹah who removed your God’s[*] high places and His altars and then said to Judah and Jerusalem: “You should bow down before one altar and on it you should make your sacrifices smoke”? ^13 Do you not know what I and my forefathers did to all the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of the lands able to rescue their land from my hand? ^14 Who among all the gods of these nations that my forefathers devoted to destruction was able to rescue his people from my hand, so that your God should be able to rescue you from my hand? ^15 Now do not let Hez·e·kiʹah deceive you or mislead you like this! Do not put faith in him, for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to rescue his people from my hand and from the hand of my forefathers. How much less, then, will your own God rescue you from my hand!’”

^16 His servants said even more against Jehovah the true God and against Hez·e·kiʹah his servant. ^17 He also wrote letters to insult Jehovah the God of Israel and to speak against him, saying: “Like the gods of the nations of the lands who could not rescue their people from my hand, so the God of Hez·e·kiʹah will not rescue his people from my hand.” ^18 They kept calling loudly in the language of the Jews to the people of Jerusalem who were on the wall, to make them afraid and to terrify them, in order to capture the city. ^19 They spoke against the God of Jerusalem the same way as against the gods of the peoples of the earth, which are the work of man’s hands. ^20 But King Hez·e·kiʹah and the prophet Isaiah the son of Aʹmoz kept praying about this and crying out to the heavens for help.

^21 Then Jehovah sent an angel and wiped out every mighty warrior, leader, and chief in the camp of the king of As·syrʹi·a, so that he went back to his own land in disgrace. He later entered the house[*] of his god, and there some of his own sons struck him down with the sword. ^22 So Jehovah saved Hez·e·kiʹah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a and from the hand of all others and gave them rest on every side. ^23 And many brought gifts to Jehovah at Jerusalem and choice things to King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah, and he was greatly respected by all the nations after that.

^24 In those days Hez·e·kiʹah became sick and was at the point of death, and he prayed to Jehovah, who answered him and gave him a sign.[*] ^25 But Hez·e·kiʹah did not respond appreciatively to the good done to him, for his heart became haughty, bringing indignation against him and against Judah and Jerusalem. ^26 However, Hez·e·kiʹah humbled himself for the haughtiness of his heart, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and Jehovah’s indignation did not come upon them in the days of Hez·e·kiʹah.

^27 And Hez·e·kiʹah came to have vast riches and glory; and he made storehouses for himself for silver, gold, precious stones, balsam oil, shields, and for all the desirable articles. ^28 He also made storage places for the produce of grain and new wine and oil, as well as stalls for all the different kinds of livestock and stalls for the flocks. ^29 He also acquired cities for himself, and an abundance of livestock, flocks, and herds, for God gave him very many possessions. ^30 It was Hez·e·kiʹah who stopped up the upper source of the waters of Giʹhon and directed them straight down to the west to the City of David, and Hez·e·kiʹah was successful in every work of his. ^31 However, when the spokesmen of the princes of Babylon were sent to ask him about the sign[*] that had occurred in the land, the true God left him alone to put him to the test, to get to know all that was in his heart.

^32 As for the rest of the history of Hez·e·kiʹah and his acts of loyal love, they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet, the son of Aʹmoz, in the Book of the Kings of Judah and of Israel. ^33 Then Hez·e·kiʹah was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him in the ascent to the burial places of the sons of David; and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem honored him at his death. And his son Ma·nasʹseh became king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 32:5 Or “Millo.” A Hebrew term meaning “fill.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:5 Or “missiles.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:6 Lit., “spoke to their heart.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:8 Or “is human strength.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:9 Or “all his military might and splendor.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:12 Lit., “his.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:21 Or “temple.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:24 Or “portent.”

^ 2 Chron. 32:31 Or “portent.”

2 Chronicles  33 : 1 - 25

33 Ma·nasʹseh was 12 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 55 years in Jerusalem.

^2 He did what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, following the detestable practices of the nations that Jehovah had driven out from before the people of Israel. ^3 He rebuilt the high places that his father Hez·e·kiʹah had torn down, he set up altars to the Baʹals and made sacred poles,[*] and he bowed down to all the army of the heavens and served them. ^4 He also built altars in the house of Jehovah, about which Jehovah had said: “In Jerusalem my name will be forever.” ^5 And he built altars to all the army of the heavens in two courtyards of the house of Jehovah. ^6 And he made his own sons pass through the fire in the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom; he practiced magic, used divination, practiced sorcery, and appointed spirit mediums and fortune-tellers. He did on a grand scale what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, to offend him.

^7 He put the carved image that he made into the house of the true God about which God had said to David and to his son Solʹo·mon: “In this house and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, I will permanently put my name. ^8 And I will never again remove the feet of Israel from the land that I assigned to their forefathers, provided they carefully observe all that I have commanded them, the entire Law, the regulations and the judicial decisions given through Moses.” ^9 Ma·nasʹseh kept leading Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem astray, causing them to do worse than the nations that Jehovah had annihilated from before the Israelites.

^10 Jehovah kept speaking to Ma·nasʹseh and his people, but they paid no attention. ^11 So Jehovah brought against them the army chiefs of the king of As·syrʹi·a, and they captured Ma·nasʹseh with hooks[*] and bound him with two copper fetters and took him to Babylon. ^12 In his distress, he begged Jehovah his God for favor[*] and kept humbling himself greatly before the God of his forefathers. ^13 He kept praying to Him, and He was moved by his entreaty and heard his request for favor, and He restored him to Jerusalem to his kingship. Then Ma·nasʹseh came to know that Jehovah is the true God.

^14 After this he built an outer wall for the City of David west of Giʹhon in the valley[*] and as far as the Fish Gate, and he continued it around to Oʹphel, and he made it very high. Further, he appointed army chiefs in all the fortified cities in Judah. ^15 He then removed the foreign gods and the idol image from the house of Jehovah and all the altars that he had built in the mountain of the house of Jehovah and in Jerusalem, and he had them thrown outside the city. ^16 He also prepared the altar of Jehovah and began to offer up communion sacrifices and thanksgiving sacrifices on it, and he told Judah to serve Jehovah the God of Israel. ^17 Nevertheless, the people were still sacrificing on the high places, although only to Jehovah their God.

^18 As for the rest of the history of Ma·nasʹseh, his prayer to his God, and the words of the visionaries who spoke to him in the name of Jehovah the God of Israel, they are recorded in the history of the kings of Israel. ^19 Also his prayer and how his entreaty was granted him, all his sins and his unfaithfulness, the locations where he built high places and set up the sacred poles[*] and the graven images before he humbled himself, they are written among the words of his visionaries. ^20 Then Ma·nasʹseh was laid to rest with his forefathers, and they buried him at his house; and his son Aʹmon became king in his place.

^21 Aʹmon was 22 years old when he became king, and he reigned for two years in Jerusalem. ^22 And he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, just as his father Ma·nasʹseh had done; and Aʹmon sacrificed to all the graven images that his father Ma·nasʹseh had made, and he kept serving them. ^23 But he did not humble himself before Jehovah as Ma·nasʹseh his father had humbled himself; instead, Aʹmon greatly increased his guilt. ^24 Eventually his servants conspired against him and put him to death in his own house. ^25 But the people of the land struck down all those who conspired against King Aʹmon, and they made his son Jo·siʹah king in his place.

^ 2 Chron. 33:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 33:11 Or possibly, “in the hollows.”

^ 2 Chron. 33:12 Or “softened the face of Jehovah his God.”

^ 2 Chron. 33:14 Or “wadi.”

^ 2 Chron. 33:19 See Glossary.

2 Chronicles  34 : 1 - 33

34 Jo·siʹah was eight years old when he became king, and he reigned for 31 years in Jerusalem. ^2 He did what was right in Jehovah’s eyes and walked in the ways of David his forefather, and he did not deviate to the right or to the left.

^3 In the 8th year of his reign, while he was still a boy, he started to search for the God of David his forefather; and in the 12th year, he started to cleanse Judah and Jerusalem of the high places and the sacred poles,[*] the graven images, and the metal statues.[*] ^4 Further, they tore down the altars of the Baʹals in his presence, and he cut down the incense stands that were up above them. He also broke into pieces the sacred poles,[*] the graven images, and the metal statues[*] and reduced them to powder and sprinkled it over the graves of those who used to sacrifice to them. ^5 And he burned the bones of priests on their altars. Thus he cleansed Judah and Jerusalem.

^6 And in the cities of Ma·nasʹseh, Eʹphra·im, Simʹe·on, and clear to Naphʹta·li, in their surrounding ruins, ^7 he tore down the altars and he crushed the sacred poles[*] and the graven images, reducing them to powder; and he cut down all the incense stands in all the land of Israel, after which he returned to Jerusalem.

^8 In the 18th year of his reign, when he had cleansed the land and the temple,[*] he sent Shaʹphan the son of Az·a·liʹah, Ma·a·seiʹah the chief of the city, and Joʹah the son of Joʹa·haz the recorder to repair the house of Jehovah his God. ^9 They came to Hil·kiʹah the high priest and gave him the money that had been brought to the house of God, which the Levites serving as doorkeepers had collected from Ma·nasʹseh, Eʹphra·im, and all the rest of Israel, as well as from Judah, Benjamin, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^10 Then they gave it to those who were appointed over the work in the house of Jehovah. In turn the workers in the house of Jehovah used it to mend and repair the house. ^11 They gave it to the craftsmen and the builders to buy hewn stones and timbers for braces and to build with beams the houses that the kings of Judah had allowed to fall into ruin.

^12 And the men did the work faithfully. Over them were appointed the Levites Jaʹhath and O·ba·diʹah of the Me·rarʹites, and Zech·a·riʹah and Me·shulʹlam of the Koʹhath·ites, to serve as overseers. And the Levites, all of whom were skilled musicians, ^13 were in charge of the common laborers[*] and were overseers of all those who were doing the work in every kind of service; and some of the Levites were secretaries, officers, and gatekeepers.

^14 While they were taking out the money that had been brought to the house of Jehovah, Hil·kiʹah the priest found the book of Jehovah’s Law given through[*] Moses. ^15 So Hil·kiʹah said to Shaʹphan the secretary: “I have found the book of the Law in the house of Jehovah.” With that Hil·kiʹah gave the book to Shaʹphan. ^16 Then Shaʹphan brought the book to the king and told him: “Your servants are doing everything that was assigned to them. ^17 They have poured out the money that was found in the house of Jehovah, and they have handed it over to the appointed men and to those doing the work.” ^18 Shaʹphan the secretary also told the king: “There is a book that Hil·kiʹah the priest has given me.” Then Shaʹphan began to read from it before the king.

^19 As soon as the king heard the words of the Law, he ripped his garments apart. ^20 Then the king gave this order to Hil·kiʹah, A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan, Abʹdon the son of Miʹcah, Shaʹphan the secretary, and A·saiʹah the king’s servant: ^21 “Go, inquire of Jehovah in my behalf and in behalf of those who remain in Israel and in Judah concerning the words of the book that has been found; for Jehovah’s rage that will be poured out against us is great because our forefathers did not carry out the word of Jehovah by observing all that is written in this book.”

^22 So Hil·kiʹah, along with those sent by the king, went to Hulʹdah the prophetess. She was the wife of Shalʹlum son of Tikʹvah son of Harʹhas, the caretaker of the wardrobe, and she was dwelling in the Second Quarter of Jerusalem; and they spoke to her there. ^23 She said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Tell the man who sent you to me: ^24 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘I will bring calamity on this place and its inhabitants, all the curses that are written in the book that they read before the king of Judah. ^25 Because they have abandoned me and are making sacrifices smoke to other gods in order to offend me with all the works of their hands, my rage will pour out on this place and it will not be extinguished.’” ^26 But to the king of Judah who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, this is what you should say to him, “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘Regarding the words that you have heard, ^27 because your heart was responsive[*] and you humbled yourself before God on hearing his words concerning this place and its inhabitants and you humbled yourself before me and ripped your garments apart and wept before me, I also have heard you, declares Jehovah. ^28 That is why I will gather you to your ancestors,[*] and you will be laid in your grave in peace, and your eyes will not see all the calamity that I will bring on this place and its inhabitants.’”’”

Then they brought the reply to the king. ^29 So the king sent word and summoned all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. ^30 After that the king went up to the house of Jehovah with all the men of Judah, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, the Levites—all the people, the great as well as the small. He read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant that had been found in the house of Jehovah. ^31 The king stood in his place and made a covenant[*] before Jehovah that he would follow Jehovah and keep his commandments, his reminders, and his regulations with all his heart and with all his soul[*] by carrying out the words of the covenant that were written in this book. ^32 Furthermore, he had all those who were in Jerusalem and Benjamin to agree to it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem acted according to the covenant of God, the God of their forefathers. ^33 Jo·siʹah then removed all the detestable things[*] out of all the lands that belonged to the Israelites, and he made everyone in Israel serve Jehovah their God. Throughout his lifetime[*] they did not deviate from following Jehovah the God of their forefathers.

^ 2 Chron. 34:3 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:3 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:4 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:4 Or “molten statues.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:7 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:8 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:13 Or “the burden bearers.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:14 Lit., “by the hand of.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:27 Lit., “soft.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:28 This is a poetic expression for death.

^ 2 Chron. 34:31 Or “renewed the covenant.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:31 See Glossary.

^ 2 Chron. 34:33 Or “idols.”

^ 2 Chron. 34:33 Lit., “All his days.”

2 Chronicles  35 : 1 - 27

35 Jo·siʹah held a Passover to Jehovah in Jerusalem, and they slaughtered the Passover sacrifice on the 14th day of the first month. ^2 He assigned the priests to their duties and encouraged them to carry out their service of the house of Jehovah. ^3 Then he said to the Levites, the instructors of all Israel, those who were holy to Jehovah: “Put the holy Ark in the house that Solʹo·mon the son of David the king of Israel built; you are no longer to carry it on your shoulders. Now serve Jehovah your God and his people Israel. ^4 And prepare yourselves by your paternal houses according to your divisions, following what was written by King David of Israel and by his son Solʹo·mon. ^5 Stand in the holy place grouped by the paternal houses of your brothers, the rest of the people,[*] with a corresponding group of the paternal house of the Levites. ^6 Slaughter the Passover sacrifice and sanctify yourselves and make preparation for your brothers to carry out the word of Jehovah through Moses.”

^7 Jo·siʹah contributed flocks to the people, male lambs and young male goats, for the Passover sacrifices for all who were present, a total of 30,000, as well as 3,000 cattle. These were from the king’s own property. ^8 His princes also made a contribution as a voluntary offering for the people, the priests, and the Levites. Hil·kiʹah, Zech·a·riʹah, and Je·hiʹel, the leaders of the house of the true God, gave to the priests 2,600 Passover sacrifices and 300 cattle. ^9 Con·a·niʹah and his brothers She·maiʹah and Ne·thanʹel, along with Hash·a·biʹah, Je·iʹel, and Joʹza·bad, the chiefs of the Levites, contributed to the Levites 5,000 Passover sacrifices and 500 cattle.

^10 The service was prepared, and the priests stood at their places and the Levites by their divisions, as the king had commanded. ^11 They slaughtered the Passover sacrifices, and the priests sprinkled the blood they received from them, while the Levites were skinning the animals. ^12 Next they prepared the burnt offerings so as to distribute them to the rest of the people, who were grouped by paternal house, so that they could be presented to Jehovah as it is written in the book of Moses; and they did the same with the cattle. ^13 They cooked[*] the Passover offering over the fire according to the custom; and they cooked the holy offerings in pots, cauldrons, and pans, after which they brought it quickly to all the rest of the people. ^14 Then they made preparations for themselves and for the priests, because the priests, the descendants of Aaron, were offering up the burnt sacrifices and the fat pieces until nightfall, so the Levites made preparations for themselves and for the priests, the descendants of Aaron.

^15 And the singers, the sons of Aʹsaph, were at their positions by the commandment of David, Aʹsaph, Heʹman, and Je·duʹthun the visionary of the king; and the gatekeepers were at the different gates. There was no need for them to leave their service, because their brothers the Levites made preparations for them. ^16 So all the service of Jehovah was prepared on that day to hold the Passover and to offer up the burnt offerings on the altar of Jehovah, according to the order of King Jo·siʹah.

^17 The Israelites who were present held the Passover at that time and the Festival of Unleavened Bread for seven days. ^18 There had never been held a Passover like it in Israel since the days of Samuel the prophet; nor had any of the other kings of Israel held a Passover like that held by Jo·siʹah, the priests, the Levites, all Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^19 This Passover was held in the 18th year of Jo·siʹah’s reign.

^20 After all of this, when Jo·siʹah had prepared the temple,[*] King Neʹcho of Egypt came up to fight at Carʹche·mish by the Eu·phraʹtes. Then Jo·siʹah went out against him. ^21 So he sent messengers to him, saying: “What does this have to do with you, O king of Judah? I am not coming against you today, but my fight is against another house, and God says that I should hurry. For your own sake, refrain from opposing God, who is with me, or he will bring you to ruin.” ^22 However, Jo·siʹah would not turn away from him, but he disguised himself to fight against him and would not listen to the words of Neʹcho, which were from the mouth of God. So he came to fight in the Plain of Me·gidʹdo.

^23 And the archers shot King Jo·siʹah, and the king said to his servants: “Get me out of here, for I am severely wounded.” ^24 So his servants took him out of the chariot and had him ride in his second war chariot and brought him to Jerusalem. Thus he died and was buried in the tomb of his forefathers, and all Judah and Jerusalem mourned Jo·siʹah. ^25 And Jeremiah chanted over Jo·siʹah, and all the male and female singers keep singing about Jo·siʹah in their dirges[*] down to this day; and a decision was made that they should be sung in Israel, and they are written among the dirges.

^26 As for the rest of the history of Jo·siʹah and his deeds of loyal love, in keeping with what is written in the Law of Jehovah, ^27 and what he did, from beginning to end, they are written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and of Judah.

^ 2 Chron. 35:5 Lit., “the sons of the people.”

^ 2 Chron. 35:13 Or possibly, “roasted.”

^ 2 Chron. 35:20 Lit., “house.”

^ 2 Chron. 35:25 Or “songs of mourning.”

2 Chronicles  36 : 1 - 23

36 Then the people of the land took Jo·siʹah’s son Je·hoʹa·haz and made him king in Jerusalem in place of his father. ^2 Je·hoʹa·haz was 23 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months in Jerusalem. ^3 However, the king of Egypt deposed him in Jerusalem and fined the land 100 silver talents[*] and a gold talent. ^4 Furthermore, the king of Egypt made Je·hoʹa·haz’ brother E·liʹa·kim king over Judah and Jerusalem and changed his name to Je·hoiʹa·kim; but Neʹcho took his brother Je·hoʹa·haz and brought him to Egypt.

^5 Je·hoiʹa·kim was 25 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. He continued to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah his God. ^6 King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon came up against him in order to bind him with two copper fetters to take him off to Babylon. ^7 And Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar took some of the utensils of the house of Jehovah to Babylon and put them in his palace in Babylon. ^8 As for the rest of the history of Je·hoiʹa·kim, the detestable things that he did and what was found against him, it is written in the Book of the Kings of Israel and of Judah; and his son Je·hoiʹa·chin became king in his place.

^9 Je·hoiʹa·chin was 18 years old when he became king, and he reigned for three months and ten days in Jerusalem; and he continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes. ^10 At the start of the year,[*] King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar sent to have him brought to Babylon, along with valuable articles of the house of Jehovah. And he made his father’s brother Zed·e·kiʹah king over Judah and Jerusalem.

^11 Zed·e·kiʹah was 21 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. ^12 He continued to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah his God. He did not humble himself before the prophet Jeremiah, who spoke at the order of Jehovah. ^13 He also rebelled against King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar, who had made him take an oath by God, and he remained stubborn[*] and hardhearted and refused to turn to Jehovah the God of Israel. ^14 All the chiefs of the priests as well as the people were exceedingly unfaithful, practicing all the detestable things of the nations, and they defiled the house of Jehovah that he had sanctified in Jerusalem.

^15 Jehovah the God of their forefathers kept warning them by means of his messengers, warning them again and again, because he felt compassion for his people and for his dwelling place. ^16 But they kept ridiculing the messengers of the true God, and they despised his words and mocked his prophets, until the rage of Jehovah came up against his people, until they were beyond healing.

^17 So he brought against them the king of the Chal·deʹans, who killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary; he felt no compassion for young man or virgin, old or infirm. God gave everything into his hand. ^18 All the utensils of the house of the true God, great and small, as well as the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king and his princes, everything he brought to Babylon. ^19 He burned down the house of the true God, tore down the wall of Jerusalem, burned all its fortified towers with fire, and destroyed everything of value. ^20 He carried off captive to Babylon those who escaped the sword, and they became servants to him and his sons until the kingdom[*] of Persia began to reign, ^21 to fulfill Jehovah’s word spoken by Jeremiah, until the land had paid off its sabbaths. All the days it lay desolate it kept sabbath, to fulfill 70 years.

^22 In the first year of King Cyrus of Persia, in order that Jehovah’s word spoken by Jeremiah would be fulfilled, Jehovah stirred the spirit of King Cyrus of Persia to make a proclamation throughout his kingdom, which he also put in writing, saying: ^23 “This is what King Cyrus of Persia says, ‘Jehovah the God of the heavens has given me all the kingdoms of the earth, and he has commissioned me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whoever there is among you of all his people, may Jehovah his God be with him, and let him go up.’”

^ 2 Chron. 36:3 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ 2 Chron. 36:10 Possibly, in the spring.

^ 2 Chron. 36:13 Lit., “he hardened his neck.”

^ 2 Chron. 36:20 Or “royalty.”

Ezra  1 : 1 - 11

EZRA

1 In the first year of King Cyrus of Persia, in order that Jehovah’s word spoken by Jeremiah would be fulfilled, Jehovah stirred the spirit of King Cyrus of Persia to make a proclamation throughout his kingdom, which he also put in writing, saying:

^2 “This is what King Cyrus of Persia says, ‘Jehovah the God of the heavens has given me all the kingdoms of the earth, and he has commissioned me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. ^3 Whoever there is among you of all his people, may his God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and rebuild the house of Jehovah the God of Israel—he is the true God—whose house was in Jerusalem.[*] ^4 Anyone who is residing as a foreigner, wherever he may be, let him be helped by his neighbors[*] by their giving him silver and gold, goods and livestock, along with the voluntary offering for the house of the true God, which was in Jerusalem.’”

^5 Then the heads of the paternal houses of Judah and of Benjamin and the priests and the Levites—everyone whose spirit the true God had stirred—prepared to go up and rebuild the house of Jehovah, which was in Jerusalem. ^6 All those around them supported them by giving them[*] utensils of silver and of gold, goods, livestock, and valuable things, besides all the voluntary offerings.

^7 King Cyrus also brought out the utensils of the house of Jehovah that Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar had taken from Jerusalem and had put in the house of his god. ^8 King Cyrus of Persia brought them out under the supervision of Mithʹre·dath the treasurer, who made an inventory of them for Shesh·bazʹzar[*] the chieftain of Judah.

^9 Now this was the inventory: 30 basket-shaped vessels of gold, 1,000 basket-shaped vessels of silver, 29 replacement vessels, ^10 30 small gold bowls, 410 small silver bowls, 1,000 other utensils. ^11 All the utensils of gold and of silver were 5,400. Shesh·bazʹzar brought all of these up when the exiles were brought out of Babylon to Jerusalem.

^ Ezra 1:3 Or possibly, “who is in Jerusalem.”

^ Ezra 1:4 Lit., “the men of his place.”

^ Ezra 1:6 Lit., “strengthened their hands with.”

^ Ezra 1:8 Possibly Zerubbabel at Ezr 2:2; 3:8.

Ezra  3 : 1 - 13

3 When the seventh month arrived and the Israelites[*] were in their cities, they gathered together with one accord in Jerusalem. ^2 Jeshʹu·a the son of Je·hozʹa·dak and his fellow priests and Ze·rubʹba·bel the son of She·alʹti·el and his brothers rose up and built the altar of the God of Israel, so that they could offer up burnt sacrifices on it, as it is written in the Law of Moses the man of the true God.

^3 So they set the altar up on its former site, despite their fear of the peoples of the surrounding lands, and they began offering up burnt sacrifices to Jehovah on it, the morning and the evening burnt sacrifices. ^4 Then they held the Festival of Booths[*] according to what is written, and day by day they offered up the specified number of burnt sacrifices that were required each day. ^5 Afterward they offered up the regular burnt offering and the offerings for the new moons and those for all the sanctified festival seasons of Jehovah, as well as those from everyone who willingly offered a voluntary offering to Jehovah. ^6 From the first day of the seventh month they started to offer up burnt sacrifices to Jehovah, though the foundation of Jehovah’s temple had not yet been laid.

^7 They gave money to the stonecutters and the craftsmen, and food and drink and oil to the Si·doʹni·ans and the Tyrʹi·ans for bringing cedar timbers by sea from Lebʹa·non to Jopʹpa, according to the authorization granted them by King Cyrus of Persia.

^8 In the second year after they came to the house of the true God at Jerusalem, in the second month, Ze·rubʹba·bel the son of She·alʹti·el, Jeshʹu·a the son of Je·hozʹa·dak and the rest of their brothers, the priests and the Levites, and all those who had come to Jerusalem out of the captivity started the work; they appointed the Levites from 20 years old and up to serve as supervisors over the work of the house of Jehovah. ^9 So Jeshʹu·a, his sons and his brothers, and Kadʹmi·el and his sons, the sons of Judah, joined together to supervise those doing the work in the house of the true God, along with the sons of Henʹa·dad, their sons and their brothers, the Levites.

^10 When the builders laid the foundation of the temple of Jehovah, then the priests in official clothing, with the trumpets, and the Levites, the sons of Aʹsaph, with the cymbals, stood up to praise Jehovah according to the direction of King David of Israel. ^11 And they began to sing in response by praising and giving thanks to Jehovah, “for he is good; his loyal love toward Israel endures forever.” Then all the people shouted with a loud shout of praise to Jehovah because the foundation of the house of Jehovah had been laid. ^12 Many of the priests, the Levites, and the heads of the paternal houses—the old men who had seen the former house—wept with a loud voice when they saw the foundation of this house being laid, while many others shouted joyfully at the top of their voice. ^13 So the people could not distinguish the sound of the joyful shouts from the sound of the weeping, for the people were shouting so loudly that the sound was heard from a great distance.

^ Ezra 3:1 Lit., “sons of Israel.”

^ Ezra 3:4 Or “Temporary Shelters.”

Ezra  4 : 1 - 24

4 When the enemies of Judah and Benjamin heard that the returned exiles were building a temple to Jehovah the God of Israel, ^2 they immediately approached Ze·rubʹba·bel and the heads of the paternal houses and said to them: “Let us build along with you; for like you, we worship[*] your God and we have been sacrificing to him since the days of King Eʹsar-hadʹdon of As·syrʹi·a, who brought us here.” ^3 However, Ze·rubʹba·bel and Jeshʹu·a and the rest of the heads of the paternal houses of Israel said to them: “You have no share with us in building a house to our God, for we alone will build it to Jehovah the God of Israel, just as King Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us.”

^4 Then the people of the land were continually discouraging[*] the people of Judah and disheartening them from building. ^5 They hired advisers against them to frustrate their plans all the days of King Cyrus of Persia until the reign of King Da·riʹus of Persia. ^6 At the beginning of the reign of A·has·u·eʹrus, they wrote an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem. ^7 And in the days of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes of Persia, Bishʹlam, Mithʹre·dath, Tabʹe·el, and the rest of his colleagues wrote to Ar·ta·xerxʹes the king; they translated the letter into Ar·a·maʹic, writing it with Ar·a·maʹic characters.[*]

^8 [*] Reʹhum the chief government official and Shimʹshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to King Ar·ta·xerxʹes, as follows: ^9 (It was from Reʹhum the chief government official and Shimʹshai the scribe and the rest of their colleagues, the judges and the lesser governors, the secretaries, the people of Eʹrech, the Babylonians, the inhabitants of Suʹsa, that is, the Eʹlam·ites, ^10 and the rest of the nations that the great and honorable Asʹe·nap·par took into exile and settled in the cities of Sa·marʹi·a, and the rest in the region Beyond the River,[*] and now ^11 this is a copy of the letter that they sent him.)

“To King Ar·ta·xerxʹes from your servants, the men of the region Beyond the River: And now ^12 let it be known to the king that the Jews who came up here from you to us have arrived at Jerusalem. They are rebuilding the rebellious and wicked city, and they are finishing the walls and repairing the foundations. ^13 Now let it be known to the king that if this city should be rebuilt and its walls finished, they will not give tax, tribute, or toll, and it will result in a loss to the treasuries of the kings. ^14 Since we eat the salt of the palace[*] and it is not proper for us to see the king’s interests harmed, we have therefore sent to make this known to the king, ^15 so that there may be an investigation of the book of records of your ancestors. You will find in the book of records and learn that this city is a rebellious city, injurious to kings and provinces,[*] and within it have been those stirring up sedition from ancient times. That is why this city was destroyed. ^16 We are making known to the king that if this city is rebuilt and its walls are finished, you will have no control[*] of the region Beyond the River.”

^17 The king sent word to Reʹhum the chief government official and Shimʹshai the scribe and the rest of their colleagues who were dwelling in Sa·marʹi·a and the rest of the region Beyond the River:

“Greetings! And now ^18 the official document that you sent us has been clearly read[*] before me. ^19 By my order an investigation was made, and it was found that from long ago the city has had uprisings against kings, and rebellions and revolts have taken place there. ^20 There were powerful kings over Jerusalem who ruled the whole region Beyond the River, and tax, tribute, and toll were paid to them. ^21 Now issue an order for these men to stop work, so that the city may not be rebuilt until I issue an order. ^22 Be careful not to neglect acting in this regard, so that the king’s interests are not harmed any further.”

^23 Now after the copy of the official document of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes had been read before Reʹhum and Shimʹshai the scribe and their colleagues, they quickly went to Jerusalem to the Jews and used force to stop them. ^24 It was then that the work on the house of God, which was in Jerusalem, came to a halt; and it remained at a standstill until the second year of the reign of King Da·riʹus of Persia.

^ Ezra 4:2 Lit., “search for.”

^ Ezra 4:4 Lit., “weakening the hands of.”

^ Ezra 4:7 Or possibly, “it was written in Aramaic and then translated.”

^ Ezra 4:8 Ezr 4:8 through 6:18 was originally written in Aramaic.

^ Ezra 4:10 Or “in Trans-Euphrates.”

^ Ezra 4:14 Or “we receive our salary from the palace.”

^ Ezra 4:15 Or “jurisdictional districts.”

^ Ezra 4:16 Lit., “share.”

^ Ezra 4:18 Or possibly, “has been translated and read.”

Ezra  5 : 1 - 17

5 Then the prophets Hagʹgai and Zech·a·riʹah the grandson of Idʹdo prophesied to the Jews who were in Judah and in Jerusalem, in the name of the God of Israel who was over them. ^2 It was then that Ze·rubʹba·bel the son of She·alʹti·el and Jeshʹu·a the son of Je·hozʹa·dak started to rebuild the house of God, which was in Jerusalem; and the prophets of God were with them and supported them. ^3 At that time Tatʹte·nai the governor of the region Beyond the River[*] and Sheʹthar-bozʹe·nai and their colleagues came to them and asked them: “Who issued an order to you to build this house and to finish this structure?”[*] ^4 Then they asked them: “What are the names of the men who are working on this building?” ^5 But God was watching over[*] the elders of the Jews, and they did not stop them until the report could be sent to Da·riʹus and an official document could be sent back concerning this.

^6 Here is a copy of the letter that Tatʹte·nai the governor of the region Beyond the River and Sheʹthar-bozʹe·nai and his colleagues, the lesser governors of the region Beyond the River, sent to King Da·riʹus; ^7 they sent the report to him, and this is what they wrote:

“To King Da·riʹus:

“All peace! ^8 Let it be known to the king that we went to the province[*] of Judah to the house of the great God, and it is being built with large stones rolled into place, and timbers are being laid in the walls. The work is being eagerly done by the people and is making progress through their efforts. ^9 Then we questioned their elders, asking them: ‘Who issued an order to you to build this house and to finish this structure?’[*] ^10 We also asked them their names to inform you, so that we could write the names of the men who are taking the lead.

^11 “This is the response they gave us: ‘We are the servants of the God of the heavens and the earth, and we are rebuilding the house that was built many years ago, which a great king of Israel built and finished. ^12 However, because our fathers angered the God of the heavens, he gave them into the hand of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon, the Chal·deʹan, who demolished this house and took the people into exile to Babylon. ^13 Nevertheless, in the first year of King Cyrus of Babylon, King Cyrus issued an order to rebuild this house of God. ^14 Moreover, King Cyrus took out of the temple of Babylon the gold and silver vessels of the house of God that Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar had taken from the temple in Jerusalem and had brought to the temple of Babylon. They were given to a man named Shesh·bazʹzar,[*] whom Cyrus made governor. ^15 Cyrus said to him: “Take these vessels. Go, deposit them in the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let the house of God be rebuilt in its former place.” ^16 Then this Shesh·bazʹzar came, and he laid the foundations of the house of God, which is in Jerusalem; and it has been under construction from then until now, but it has not been completed.’

^17 “Now if it seems good to the king, let an investigation be made in the royal treasury there in Babylon, to determine whether King Cyrus issued an order to rebuild that house of God in Jerusalem; and let the decision of the king concerning this be sent to us.”

^ Ezra 5:3 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

^ Ezra 5:3 Or “these beams.”

^ Ezra 5:5 Lit., “the eye of their God was on.”

^ Ezra 5:8 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Ezra 5:9 Or “these beams.”

^ Ezra 5:14 Possibly Zerubbabel at Ezr 2:2; 3:8.

Ezra  6 : 1 - 22

6 It was then that King Da·riʹus issued an order, and they made an investigation in the archives[*] where the treasures were deposited in Babylon. ^2 And a scroll was found in the citadel at Ec·batʹa·na, in the province[*] of Meʹdi·a, and the following memorandum was written on it:

^3 “In the first year of King Cyrus, King Cyrus issued an order concerning the house of God in Jerusalem: ‘Let the house be rebuilt as the place where they are to offer sacrifices, and its foundations are to be set in place; its height is to be 60 cubits,[*] its width 60 cubits, ^4 with three layers of large stones rolled into place and one layer of timbers; and let the expense be paid from the king’s house. ^5 Also, let the gold and silver vessels of the house of God that Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem and brought to Babylon be returned, so that they may be put in their place in the temple in Jerusalem and be deposited in the house of God.’

^6 “So now Tatʹte·nai the governor of the region Beyond the River,[*] Sheʹthar-bozʹe·nai, and your colleagues, the lesser governors of the region Beyond the River—stay away from there. ^7 Do not interfere with the work on that house of God. The governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews will rebuild that house of God in its former place. ^8 Furthermore, I am issuing an order as to what you are to do for these elders of the Jews for rebuilding that house of God: From the royal treasury, from the tax collected in the region Beyond the River, the expenses are to be promptly given to these men to continue without interruption. ^9 And whatever is needed—young bulls as well as rams and lambs for the burnt offerings to the God of heaven, wheat, salt, wine, and oil, just as the priests who are in Jerusalem say—is to be given them continually day by day without fail, ^10 so that they may continually present offerings that please the God of the heavens and pray for the life of the king and his sons. ^11 I have also issued an order that if anyone violates this decree, a timber will be pulled out of his house and he will be lifted up and fastened to it,[*] and his house will be turned into a public latrine[*] for this offense. ^12 And may the God who has caused his name to reside there overthrow any king and people who lift a hand to violate this order and destroy that house of God, which is in Jerusalem. I, Da·riʹus, issue this order. Let it be done promptly.”

^13 Then Tatʹte·nai the governor of the region Beyond the River, Sheʹthar-bozʹe·nai, and their colleagues promptly carried out everything that King Da·riʹus had ordered. ^14 And the elders of the Jews continued building and making progress, urged on by the prophesying of Hagʹgai the prophet and Zech·a·riʹah the grandson of Idʹdo; they finished building it by the order of the God of Israel and by the order of Cyrus and Da·riʹus and King Ar·ta·xerxʹes of Persia. ^15 They completed the house by the third day of the month of Aʹdar,[*] in the sixth year of the reign of King Da·riʹus.

^16 Then the Israelites, the priests, the Levites, and the rest of the former exiles held the inauguration[*] of this house of God with joy. ^17 And they presented for the inauguration of this house of God 100 bulls, 200 rams, 400 lambs, and as a sin offering for all Israel 12 male goats, corresponding to the number of the tribes of Israel. ^18 And they appointed the priests in their groups and the Levites in their divisions for the service of God in Jerusalem, according to what is written in the book of Moses.

^19 And the former exiles held the Passover on the 14th day of the first month. ^20 The priests and the Levites, without exception, had cleansed themselves, so they were all clean; they slaughtered the Passover sacrifice for all the former exiles, for their fellow priests, and for themselves. ^21 Then the Israelites who had returned from the exile ate of it, along with everyone who had joined them and had separated himself from the uncleanness of the nations of the land to worship[*] Jehovah the God of Israel. ^22 They also joyfully held the Festival of Unleavened Bread for seven days, for Jehovah caused them to rejoice and he had made the heart of the king of As·syrʹi·a favorable toward them, so that he supported them[*] in the work of the house of the true God, the God of Israel.

^ Ezra 6:1 Lit., “the house of the records.”

^ Ezra 6:2 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Ezra 6:3 About 26.7 m (87.6 ft). See App. B14.

^ Ezra 6:6 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

^ Ezra 6:11 Or “and he will be impaled on it.”

^ Ezra 6:11 Or possibly, “a garbage dump; a dunghill.”

^ Ezra 6:15 See App. B15.

^ Ezra 6:16 Or “dedication.”

^ Ezra 6:21 Lit., “search for.”

^ Ezra 6:22 Lit., “strengthened their hands.”

Ezra  8 : 1 - 36

8 Now these were the heads of their paternal houses and the genealogical enrollment of those who went up with me out of Babylon during the reign of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes: ^2 of the sons of Phinʹe·has, Gerʹshom; of the sons of Ithʹa·mar, Daniel; of the sons of David, Hatʹtush; ^3 of the sons of Shec·a·niʹah, of the sons of Paʹrosh, Zech·a·riʹah, and with him there was an enrollment of 150 males; ^4 of the sons of Paʹhath-moʹab, Elʹie·ho-eʹnai the son of Zer·a·hiʹah, and with him 200 males; ^5 of the sons of Zatʹtu, Shec·a·niʹah the son of Ja·ha·ziʹel, and with him 300 males; ^6 of the sons of Aʹdin, Eʹbed the son of Jonʹa·than, and with him 50 males; ^7 of the sons of Eʹlam, Je·shaʹiah the son of Ath·a·liʹah, and with him 70 males; ^8 of the sons of Sheph·a·tiʹah, Zeb·a·diʹah the son of Miʹcha·el, and with him 80 males; ^9 of the sons of Joʹab, O·ba·diʹah the son of Je·hiʹel, and with him 218 males; ^10 of the sons of Baʹni, She·loʹmith the son of Jo·si·phiʹah, and with him 160 males; ^11 of the sons of Beʹbai, Zech·a·riʹah the son of Beʹbai, and with him 28 males; ^12 of the sons of Azʹgad, Jo·haʹnan the son of Hakʹka·tan, and with him 110 males; ^13 of the sons of Ad·o·niʹkam, those who were the last, and these were their names: E·liphʹe·let, Je·iʹel, and She·maiʹah, and with them 60 males; ^14 and of the sons of Bigʹvai, Uʹthai and Zabʹbud, and with them 70 males.

^15 I assembled them at the river that comes to A·haʹva, and we camped there for three days. But when I examined the people and the priests, I did not find any of the Levites there. ^16 So I sent for E·li·eʹzer, Arʹi·el, She·maiʹah, El·naʹthan, Jaʹrib, El·naʹthan, Nathan, Zech·a·riʹah, and Me·shulʹlam, who were leading men, and for Joiʹa·rib and El·naʹthan, who were instructors. ^17 Then I gave them a command concerning Idʹdo the leader in the place called Ca·si·phiʹa. I told them to tell Idʹdo and his brothers, the temple servants[*] who were in Ca·si·phiʹa, to bring to us ministers for the house of our God. ^18 Since the good hand of our God was upon us, they brought a discreet man from the sons of Mahʹli the grandson of Leʹvi the son of Israel, namely, She·re·biʹah, and his sons and his brothers, 18 men; ^19 and Hash·a·biʹah, and with him Je·shaʹiah from the Me·rarʹites, his brothers and their sons, 20 men. ^20 And there were 220 of the temple servants,[*] whom David and the princes gave to the service of the Levites, all of whom had been designated by name.

^21 Then I proclaimed a fast there at the river A·haʹva, to humble ourselves before our God, to seek guidance from him for our journey, for us and for our children and for all our goods. ^22 I was ashamed to ask the king for soldiers and horsemen to protect us against the enemies along the way, because we had said to the king: “The good hand of our God is over all those seeking him, but his strength and his anger are against all those abandoning him.” ^23 So we fasted and made request of our God concerning this, and he listened to our entreaty.

^24 I now set apart 12 of the chiefs of the priests, namely, She·re·biʹah and Hash·a·biʹah, along with ten of their brothers. ^25 Then I weighed out to them the silver and the gold and the utensils, the contribution that the king and his advisers and his princes and all the Israelites who were present there had made to the house of our God. ^26 Thus I weighed out into their hand 650 talents[*] of silver, 100 silver utensils worth 2 talents, 100 talents of gold, ^27 20 small gold bowls worth 1,000 darics,[*] and 2 utensils of fine copper, gleaming red, as desirable as gold.

^28 Then I said to them: “You are holy to Jehovah, and the utensils are holy, and the silver and the gold are a voluntary offering to Jehovah the God of your forefathers. ^29 Guard them carefully until you weigh them out before the chiefs of the priests and the Levites and the princes of the paternal houses of Israel in Jerusalem, in the chambers[*] of the house of Jehovah.” ^30 And the priests and the Levites took the silver and the gold and the utensils that had been weighed out to them, in order to bring them to Jerusalem to the house of our God.

^31 Finally we pulled away from the river A·haʹva on the 12th day of the first month to go to Jerusalem, and the hand of our God was over us, and he rescued us from the hand of the enemy and from ambush along the way. ^32 So we came to Jerusalem and stayed there for three days. ^33 And on the fourth day, we weighed out the silver and the gold and the utensils in the house of our God and handed them over to Merʹe·moth son of U·riʹjah the priest, and with him was El·e·aʹzar son of Phinʹe·has, and with them were the Levites Joʹza·bad son of Jeshʹu·a and No·a·diʹah son of Binʹnu·i. ^34 Everything was numbered and weighed, and all the weight was recorded. ^35 Those coming out of the captivity, the former exiles, presented burnt sacrifices to the God of Israel, 12 bulls for all Israel, 96 rams, 77 male lambs, and 12 male goats as a sin offering; all of this was a burnt offering to Jehovah.

^36 Then we gave the decrees of the king to the satraps[*] of the king and the governors of the region Beyond the River,[*] and they supported the people and the house of the true God.

^ Ezra 8:17 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Ezra 8:20 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Ezra 8:26 A talent equaled 34.2 kg (1,101 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Ezra 8:27 A daric was a Persian gold coin. See App. B14.

^ Ezra 8:29 Or “dining halls.”

^ Ezra 8:36 Title meaning “protectors of the realm,” here applied to governors of provinces in the Persian Empire.

^ Ezra 8:36 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

Ezra  9 : 1 - 15

9 And as soon as these things had been done, the princes approached me and said: “The people of Israel and the priests and the Levites have not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands and their detestable practices, those of the Caʹnaan·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Jebʹu·sites, the Amʹmon·ites, the Moʹab·ites, the Egyptians, and the Amʹor·ites. ^2 They have taken some of their daughters as wives for themselves and for their sons. Now they, the holy offspring,[*] have become mingled with the peoples of the lands. The princes and the deputy rulers have been the foremost offenders in this unfaithfulness.”

^3 Now as soon as I heard of this, I ripped apart my garment and my sleeveless coat and pulled out some of the hair of my head and my beard, and I sat down in shock. ^4 Then everyone who had reverence for[*] the words of the God of Israel gathered around me because of the unfaithfulness of the exiled people, while I was sitting in shock until the evening grain offering.

^5 And at the time of the evening grain offering, I stood up from my humiliation, with my garment and my sleeveless coat torn apart, and I got down on my knees and spread out my hands to Jehovah my God. ^6 And I said: “O my God, I feel ashamed and embarrassed to raise my face to you, O my God, for our errors have multiplied over our heads and our guilt has mounted up to the heavens. ^7 From the days of our forefathers until this day our guilt has been great; and because of our errors, we, our kings, and our priests have been given into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, to plunder, and to disgrace, as is the case today. ^8 But now for a brief moment, favor has come from Jehovah our God by letting a remnant escape and by giving us a secure position[*] in his holy place, to make our eyes shine, O our God, and to revive us a little in our slavery. ^9 For although we are slaves, our God has not abandoned us in our slavery; but he has extended his loyal love toward us before the kings of Persia, to revive us so as to raise up the house of our God and to restore its ruins and to give us a stone wall[*] in Judah and in Jerusalem.

^10 “But now what can we say, O our God, after this? For we have left your commandments, ^11 which you gave us through your servants the prophets, saying: ‘The land that you are going in to take possession of is an impure land because of the impurity of the peoples of the lands, because of their detestable practices with which they have filled it from end to end with their uncleanness. ^12 Therefore, do not give your daughters to their sons, neither accept their daughters for your sons; and you must never seek their peace and their prosperity, so that you may grow strong and eat the good of the land and take possession of it for your sons forever.’ ^13 And after all that has come upon us for our bad deeds and our great guilt—for you, O our God, have not dealt with us according to our error, and you have allowed those of us here to escape— ^14 are we to break your commandments again and form marriage alliances[*] with the peoples who practice these detestable things? Would you not become so angry with us that you would completely destroy us, leaving no remnant or survivor? ^15 O Jehovah the God of Israel, you are righteous, for we have survived as a remnant to this day. Here we are before you in our guilt, for it is impossible to stand before you because of this.”

^ Ezra 9:2 Lit., “seed.”

^ Ezra 9:4 Lit., “who trembled at.”

^ Ezra 9:8 Lit., “a peg.”

^ Ezra 9:9 Or “a wall of protection.”

^ Ezra 9:14 Or “and intermarry.”

Ezra  10 : 1 - 44

10 While Ezʹra was praying and making confession, weeping and lying prostrate before the house of the true God, a large crowd of men, women, and children of Israel gathered around him, for the people were weeping profusely. ^2 Then Shec·a·niʹah the son of Je·hiʹel of the sons of Eʹlam said to Ezʹra: “We have acted unfaithfully against our God by marrying[*] foreign women from the peoples of the land. Despite this, there is still hope for Israel. ^3 Now let us make a covenant with our God to send away all the wives and those born from them, in harmony with the direction of Jehovah and of those who have reverence for[*] the commandment of our God. Let us act according to the Law. ^4 Get up, for this matter is your responsibility, and we are with you. Be strong and take action.”

^5 At that Ezʹra rose and had the chiefs of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel take an oath to do what had been said. So they took an oath. ^6 Ezʹra now got up from before the house of the true God and went to the chamber[*] of Je·ho·haʹnan the son of E·liʹa·shib. Although he went there, he ate no food and drank no water, for he was in mourning because of the unfaithfulness of the exiled people.

^7 Then they made a proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem that all the former exiles gather together at Jerusalem; ^8 and according to the decision of the princes and the elders, anyone who did not come within three days’ time would have all his goods confiscated,[*] and he would be banished from the congregation of the exiled people. ^9 So all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered together at Jerusalem within three days, that is, in the ninth month, on the 20th day of the month. All the people were sitting in a courtyard of the house of the true God, shivering because of the matter at hand and because of the heavy rain.

^10 Then Ezʹra the priest rose and said to them: “You have acted unfaithfully by marrying foreign women, and so you have added to the guilt of Israel. ^11 Now make confession to Jehovah the God of your forefathers and do his will. Separate yourselves from the peoples of the land and from these foreign wives.” ^12 To this the whole congregation answered with a loud voice: “It is our duty to do exactly as you say. ^13 However, there are many people, and it is the rainy season. It is not possible to stand outside, and the matter will not take just one or two days, for we have rebelled extensively in this matter. ^14 So, please, let our princes represent the entire congregation; and let all those in our cities who have married foreign women come at an appointed time, along with the elders and judges of each city, until we turn back the burning anger of our God from us concerning this matter.”

^15 However, Jonʹa·than the son of Asʹa·hel and Jah·zeiʹah the son of Tikʹvah objected to this, and the Levites Me·shulʹlam and Shabʹbe·thai supported them. ^16 But the former exiles did what was agreed on; and Ezʹra the priest and the family heads of their paternal houses, all designated by name, convened separately on the first day of the tenth month to look into the matter; ^17 and by the first day of the first month they finished dealing with all the men who had married foreign women. ^18 And it was discovered that some of the sons of the priests had married foreign women: of the sons of Jeshʹu·a the son of Je·hozʹa·dak and his brothers, Ma·a·seiʹah, E·li·eʹzer, Jaʹrib, and Ged·a·liʹah. ^19 But they promised[*] to send their wives away, and since they were guilty, they would offer a ram of the flock for their guilt.

^20 Of the sons of Imʹmer, there were Ha·naʹni and Zeb·a·diʹah; ^21 and of the sons of Haʹrim, Ma·a·seiʹah, E·liʹjah, She·maiʹah, Je·hiʹel, and Uz·ziʹah; ^22 and of the sons of Pashʹhur, Eli·o·eʹnai, Ma·a·seiʹah, Ishʹma·el, Ne·thanʹel, Joʹza·bad and El·e·aʹsah. ^23 And of the Levites, there were Joʹza·bad, Shimʹe·i, Ke·laiʹah (that is, Ke·liʹta), Peth·a·hiʹah, Judah, and E·li·eʹzer; ^24 and of the singers, E·liʹa·shib; and of the gatekeepers, Shalʹlum, Teʹlem, and Uʹri.

^25 And of Israel, of the sons of Paʹrosh, there were Ra·miʹah, Iz·ziʹah, Mal·chiʹjah, Mijʹa·min, El·e·aʹzar, Mal·chiʹjah, and Be·naiʹah; ^26 and of the sons of Eʹlam, Mat·ta·niʹah, Zech·a·riʹah, Je·hiʹel, Abʹdi, Jerʹe·moth, and E·liʹjah; ^27 and of the sons of Zatʹtu, Eli·o·eʹnai, E·liʹa·shib, Mat·ta·niʹah, Jerʹe·moth, Zaʹbad, and A·ziʹza; ^28 and of the sons of Beʹbai, Je·ho·haʹnan, Han·a·niʹah, Zabʹbai, and Athʹlai; ^29 and of the sons of Baʹni, Me·shulʹlam, Malʹluch, A·daiʹah, Jaʹshub, Sheʹal, and Jerʹe·moth; ^30 and of the sons of Paʹhath-moʹab, Adʹna, Cheʹlal, Be·naiʹah, Ma·a·seiʹah, Mat·ta·niʹah, Bezʹal·el, Binʹnu·i, and Ma·nasʹseh; ^31 and of the sons of Haʹrim, E·li·eʹzer, Is·shiʹjah, Mal·chiʹjah, She·maiʹah, Shimʹe·on, ^32 Benjamin, Malʹluch, and Shem·a·riʹah; ^33 of the sons of Haʹshum, Mat·teʹnai, Matʹtat·tah, Zaʹbad, E·liphʹe·let, Jerʹe·mai, Ma·nasʹseh, and Shimʹe·i; ^34 of the sons of Baʹni, Ma·a·daʹi, Amʹram, Uʹel, ^35 Be·naiʹah, Be·deiʹah, Chelʹu·hi, ^36 Va·niʹah, Merʹe·moth, E·liʹa·shib, ^37 Mat·ta·niʹah, Mat·teʹnai, and Jaʹa·su; ^38 and of the sons of Binʹnu·i, Shimʹe·i, ^39 Shel·e·miʹah, Nathan, A·daiʹah, ^40 Mach·nadʹe·bai, Shaʹshai, Shaʹrai, ^41 Azʹar·el, Shel·e·miʹah, Shem·a·riʹah, ^42 Shalʹlum, Am·a·riʹah, and Joseph; ^43 and of the sons of Neʹbo, Je·iʹel, Mat·ti·thiʹah, Zaʹbad, Ze·biʹna, Jadʹdai, Joel, and Be·naiʹah. ^44 All of these had taken foreign wives, and they sent their wives away, along with their sons.

^ Ezra 10:2 Or “by taking into our houses.”

^ Ezra 10:3 Lit., “who tremble at.”

^ Ezra 10:6 Or “dining hall.”

^ Ezra 10:8 Or “put under ban.”

^ Ezra 10:19 Lit., “they gave their hands.”

Nehemiah  1 : 1 - 11

NEHEMIAH

1 The words of Ne·he·miʹah[*] the son of Hac·a·liʹah: Now in the month of Chisʹlev,[*] in the 20th year, I was in Shuʹshan[*] the citadel.[*] ^2 At that time Ha·naʹni, one of my brothers, arrived with other men from Judah, and I asked them about the remaining Jews who had escaped the captivity, and also about Jerusalem. ^3 They replied: “Those remaining there in the province[*] who have survived the captivity are in a terrible situation and in disgrace. The walls of Jerusalem are broken down, and its gates have been burned with fire.”

^4 As soon as I heard these words, I sat down and began to weep and mourn for days, and I kept fasting and praying before the God of the heavens. ^5 I said: “O Jehovah, the God of the heavens, the great and awe-inspiring God who keeps his covenant and shows loyal love to those who love him and keep his commandments, ^6 please, let your ear be attentive and your eyes open to listen to the prayer of your servant that I am praying to you today, day and night, concerning your servants the Israelites, all the while confessing the sins that the people of Israel have committed against you. We have sinned, both I and the house of my father. ^7 We have certainly acted corruptly against you by not keeping the commandments, regulations, and judicial decisions that you gave to your servant Moses.

^8 “Remember, please, the word that you commanded[*] your servant Moses: ‘If you act unfaithfully, I will scatter you among the peoples. ^9 But if you return to me and observe my commandments and obey them, though your dispersed people should be at the end of the heavens, I will gather them from there and bring them to the place that I have chosen to have my name reside.’ ^10 They are your servants and your people, whom you redeemed by your great power and by your mighty hand. ^11 O Jehovah, please, let your ear be attentive to the prayer of your servant and to the prayer of your servants who take delight in fearing your name, and please, grant success to your servant today, and may this man show me compassion.”

Now I was cupbearer to the king.

^ Neh. 1:1 Meaning “Jah Comforts.”

^ Neh. 1:1 See App. B15.

^ Neh. 1:1 Or “Susa.”

^ Neh. 1:1 Or “palace; fortress.”

^ Neh. 1:3 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Neh. 1:8 Or “the warning you gave to.”

Nehemiah  2 : 1 - 20

2 In the month of Niʹsan,[*] in the 20th year of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes, wine was set before him, and as usual I took up the wine and gave it to the king. But I had never been gloomy in his presence. ^2 So the king said to me: “Why do you look so gloomy when you are not sick? This can be nothing but gloominess of heart.” At this I became very frightened.

^3 Then I said to the king: “Long live the king! Why should I not look gloomy when the city, the place where my forefathers are buried, lies in ruins, and its gates have been consumed by fire?” ^4 The king then said to me: “What is it that you are seeking?” At once I prayed to the God of the heavens. ^5 I then said to the king: “If it pleases the king and if your servant has found favor with you, send me to Judah, to the city where my forefathers are buried, so that I may rebuild it.” ^6 Then the king, with his royal consort[*] sitting beside him, said to me: “How long will your journey be, and when will you return?” So it pleased the king to send me, and I gave him a set time.

^7 Then I said to the king: “If it pleases the king, let letters be given me for the governors of the region Beyond the River,[*] granting me safe passage until I reach Judah, ^8 as well as a letter to Aʹsaph the keeper of the Royal Park,[*] so that he may give me timber for beams for the gates of the Fortress of the House[*] and for the walls of the city and for the house where I will go.” So the king gave them to me, for the good hand of my God was upon me.

^9 Eventually I came to the governors of the region Beyond the River and gave them the king’s letters. The king also sent with me army chiefs and horsemen. ^10 When San·balʹlat the Horʹo·nite and To·biʹah the Amʹmon·ite official[*] heard about it, they were very displeased that someone had come to do something good for the people of Israel.

^11 At length I came to Jerusalem, and I stayed there for three days. ^12 I rose up by night, I and a few men with me, and I did not tell anyone what my God had put into my heart to do for Jerusalem, and there was no animal with me except the one I was riding. ^13 And I went out at night through the Valley Gate, passing in front of the Fountain of the Big Snake to the Gate of the Ash Heaps, and I inspected the walls of Jerusalem that were broken down and its gates that had been consumed by fire. ^14 And I passed along to the Fountain Gate and to the King’s Pool, and there was not enough space for the animal I was riding to pass. ^15 But I continued up the valley[*] by night, and I kept inspecting the wall, after which I came back and entered through the Valley Gate, and then I returned.

^16 The deputy rulers did not know where I had gone and what I was doing, for I had not yet said anything to the Jews, the priests, the nobles, the deputy rulers, and the rest of the workers. ^17 Finally I said to them: “You can see what a terrible situation we are in, how Jerusalem lies in ruins and its gates have been burned with fire. Come, let us rebuild the walls of Jerusalem, so that this disgrace will not continue.” ^18 Then I told them of how the good hand of my God was upon me and also of the words that the king had spoken to me. At this they said: “Let us get up and build.” So they strengthened themselves[*] for the good work.

^19 Now when San·balʹlat the Horʹo·nite, To·biʹah the Amʹmon·ite official,[*] and Geʹshem the Arabian heard of it, they began to mock us and show us their contempt and say: “What are you doing? Are you rebelling against the king?” ^20 However, I replied: “The God of the heavens is the One who will grant us success, and we his servants will get up and build; but you have neither share nor claim nor memorial[*] in Jerusalem.”

^ Neh. 2:1 See App. B15.

^ Neh. 2:6 Or “his queen.”

^ Neh. 2:7 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

^ Neh. 2:8 Or “the king’s forest.”

^ Neh. 2:8 Or “Temple.”

^ Neh. 2:10 Lit., “servant.”

^ Neh. 2:15 Or “wadi.”

^ Neh. 2:18 Lit., “their hands.”

^ Neh. 2:19 Lit., “servant.”

^ Neh. 2:20 Or “entitlement.”

Nehemiah  3 : 1 - 32

3 E·liʹa·shib the high priest and his brothers the priests got up to build the Sheep Gate. They sanctified[*] it and set up its doors; they sanctified it as far as the Tower of Meʹah, as far as the Tower of Ha·nanʹel. ^2 And next to them the men of Jerʹi·cho were building; and next to them Zacʹcur the son of Imʹri was building.

^3 The sons of Has·se·naʹah built the Fish Gate; they timbered it and then set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars. ^4 And next to them Merʹe·moth the son of U·riʹjah the son of Hakʹkoz did repair work, and next to them Me·shulʹlam the son of Ber·e·chiʹah the son of Me·shezʹa·bel did repair work, and next to them Zaʹdok the son of Baʹa·na did repair work. ^5 And next to them the Te·koʹites did repair work, but their prominent men would not lower themselves to share in[*] the service of their masters.

^6 Joiʹa·da the son of Pa·seʹah and Me·shulʹlam the son of Bes·o·deiʹah repaired the Gate of the Old City; they timbered it and then set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars. ^7 Next to them Mel·a·tiʹah the Gibʹe·on·ite and Jaʹdon the Me·ronʹo·thite did repair work, men of Gibʹe·on and Mizʹpah who were under the authority of[*] the governor of the region Beyond the River.[*] ^8 Next to them Uzʹzi·el the son of Har·haiʹah, one of the goldsmiths, did repair work, and next to him Han·a·niʹah, one of the ointment mixers,[*] did repair work; and they paved[*] Jerusalem as far as the Broad Wall. ^9 And next to them Re·phaʹiah the son of Hur, a prince of half the district of Jerusalem, did repair work. ^10 And next to them Je·daʹiah the son of Ha·ruʹmaph did repair work in front of his own house, and next to him Hatʹtush the son of Hash·ab·neiʹah did repair work.

^11 Mal·chiʹjah the son of Haʹrim and Hasʹshub the son of Paʹhath-moʹab repaired another section,[*] as well as the Tower of the Ovens. ^12 And next to them Shalʹlum the son of Hal·loʹhesh, a prince of half the district of Jerusalem, did repair work, along with his daughters.

^13 Haʹnun and the inhabitants of Za·noʹah repaired the Valley Gate; they built it and then set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, and they repaired 1,000 cubits[*] of the wall as far as the Gate of the Ash Heaps. ^14 Mal·chiʹjah the son of Reʹchab, a prince of the district of Beth-hac·cheʹrem, repaired the Gate of the Ash Heaps; he built it and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars.

^15 Shalʹlun the son of Col·hoʹzeh, a prince of the district of Mizʹpah, repaired the Fountain Gate; he built it and its roof, set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, and also repaired the wall of the Pool of the Canal to the King’s Garden and as far as the Stairway that goes down from the City of David.

^16 After him Ne·he·miʹah the son of Azʹbuk, a prince of half the district of Beth-zur, did repair work from in front of the Burial Places of David as far as the pool that had been built and as far as the House of the Mighty Ones.

^17 After him the Levites did repair work: Reʹhum the son of Baʹni; and next to him Hash·a·biʹah, a prince of half the district of Keiʹlah, did repair work for his district. ^18 After him their brothers did repair work: Bavʹvai the son of Henʹa·dad, a prince of half the district of Keiʹlah.

^19 And next to him Eʹzer the son of Jeshʹu·a, a prince of Mizʹpah, was repairing another section in front of the ascent to the Armory at the Buttress.

^20 After him Barʹuch the son of Zabʹbai worked with fervor and repaired another section, from the Buttress as far as the entrance of the house of E·liʹa·shib the high priest.

^21 After him Merʹe·moth the son of U·riʹjah the son of Hakʹkoz repaired another section, from the entrance of the house of E·liʹa·shib as far as the end of E·liʹa·shib’s house.

^22 And after him the priests, men of the district of the Jordan,[*] did repair work. ^23 After them Benjamin and Hasʹshub did repair work in front of their own house. After them Az·a·riʹah the son of Ma·a·seiʹah the son of A·na·niʹah did repair work near his own house. ^24 After him Binʹnu·i the son of Henʹa·dad repaired another section, from the house of Az·a·riʹah as far as the Buttress and as far as the corner.

^25 After him Paʹlal the son of Uʹzai did repair work in front of the Buttress and the tower that goes out from the King’s House,[*] the upper one that belongs to the Courtyard of the Guard. After him there was Pe·daiʹah the son of Paʹrosh.

^26 And the temple servants[*] who lived in Oʹphel did repair work as far as in front of the Water Gate on the east and the protruding tower.

^27 After them the Te·koʹites repaired another section, from in front of the great protruding tower as far as the wall of Oʹphel.

^28 The priests did repair work above the Horse Gate, each in front of his own house.

^29 After them Zaʹdok the son of Imʹmer did repair work in front of his own house.

And after him She·maiʹah the son of Shec·a·niʹah, the keeper of the East Gate, did repair work.

^30 After him Han·a·niʹah the son of Shel·e·miʹah and Haʹnun the sixth son of Zaʹlaph repaired another section.

After him Me·shulʹlam the son of Ber·e·chiʹah did repair work in front of his own hall.

^31 After him Mal·chiʹjah, a member of the goldsmith guild, did repair work as far as the house of the temple servants[*] and the traders, in front of the Inspection Gate and as far as the roof chamber of the corner.

^32 And between the roof chamber of the corner and the Sheep Gate, the goldsmiths and the traders did repair work.

^ Neh. 3:1 Or “dedicated.”

^ Neh. 3:5 Lit., “not bring their neck into.”

^ Neh. 3:7 Lit., “belonging to the throne of.”

^ Neh. 3:7 Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

^ Neh. 3:8 Or “the perfume makers.”

^ Neh. 3:8 Or “paved with flagstone.”

^ Neh. 3:11 Or “measured section.”

^ Neh. 3:13 About 445 m (1,460 ft). See App. B14.

^ Neh. 3:22 Or possibly, “the nearby district.”

^ Neh. 3:25 Or “Palace.”

^ Neh. 3:26 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

^ Neh. 3:31 Or “the Nethinim.” Lit., “the given ones.”

Nehemiah  4 : 1 - 23

4 Now as soon as San·balʹlat heard that we were rebuilding the wall, he became angry and very upset,[*] and he kept mocking the Jews. ^2 And in the presence of his brothers and the army of Sa·marʹi·a, he said: “What are the feeble Jews doing? Will they do this by themselves? Will they offer sacrifices? Will they finish up in a day? Will they bring the charred stones to life out of the heaps of dusty rubble?”

^3 Now To·biʹah the Amʹmon·ite, who was standing beside him, said: “If even a fox would climb up on what they are building, it would knock down their stone wall.”

^4 Hear, O our God, for we are being treated with contempt, and make their reproach return on their own heads, and give them over as plunder in a land of captivity. ^5 And do not cover over their guilt or let their sin be erased from before you, for they have insulted the builders.

^6 So we kept building the wall, and the entire wall was joined together and rebuilt up to half its height, and the people continued to put their heart into the work.

^7 Now as soon as San·balʹlat, To·biʹah, the Arabians, the Amʹmon·ites, and the Ashʹdod·ites heard that the repairing of the walls of Jerusalem was progressing and that the gaps were being filled in, they became very angry. ^8 They conspired together to come and fight against Jerusalem and to create a disturbance in it. ^9 But we prayed to our God and kept a guard posted against them day and night.

^10 However, people of Judah were saying: “The strength of the laborers[*] has failed, and there is so much rubble; we will never be able to build the wall.”

^11 And our enemies kept saying: “Before they know it or see us, we will come right in among them and kill them and stop the work.”

^12 Whenever the Jews living near them came in, they told us again and again:[*] “They will come at us from all directions.”

^13 So I kept men posted at the lowest parts of the space behind the wall at the exposed places, and I posted them by families with their swords, their lances, and their bows. ^14 When I saw their fear, I immediately rose and said to the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the people: “Do not be afraid of them. Remember Jehovah, who is great and awe-inspiring; and fight for your brothers, your sons and daughters, your wives and homes.”

^15 Now after our enemies heard that what they were doing had become known to us and that the true God had frustrated their plan, we all went back to work on the wall. ^16 From that day forward, half of my men would do the work and half of them would hold the lances, the shields, the bows, and the coats of mail. And the princes stood behind the whole house of Judah ^17 who were building the wall. Those who were carrying the loads did the work with one hand while holding a weapon[*] in the other hand. ^18 And each of the builders had a sword strapped to his hip while building, and the one to blow the horn stood beside me.

^19 I then said to the nobles and the deputy rulers and the rest of the people: “The work is large and extensive, and we are spread out on the wall far apart from one another. ^20 When you hear the sound of the horn, gather together to where we are. Our God will fight for us.”

^21 So we kept working while the other half were holding the lances, from the break of dawn until the stars came out. ^22 At that time I said to the people: “Let the men, each along with his attendant, spend the night inside Jerusalem, and they will guard us by night and work during the day.” ^23 So neither I nor my brothers, my attendants, and the guards who followed me ever took off our garments, and each of us kept his weapon in his right hand.

^ Neh. 4:1 Or “offended.”

^ Neh. 4:10 Or “burden bearers.”

^ Neh. 4:12 Lit., “ten times.”

^ Neh. 4:17 Or “missile.”

Nehemiah  5 : 1 - 19

5 However, there was a great outcry from the people and their wives against their Jewish brothers. ^2 Some were saying: “We are many with our sons and our daughters. We must get grain in order to eat and stay alive.” ^3 Others were saying: “We are giving our fields and our vineyards and our houses as security to get grain during the food shortage.” ^4 Still others were saying: “We have borrowed money on our fields and our vineyards for the king’s tribute. ^5 Now we are of the same flesh and blood as our brothers,[*] and our children are just like their children; yet we have to subject our sons and daughters to slavery, and some of our daughters are already in slavery. But we are powerless to stop this, because our fields and our vineyards belong to others.”

^6 I became very angry when I heard their outcry and these words. ^7 So I considered these things in my heart, and I took issue with the nobles and the deputy rulers and said to them: “Each one of you is demanding interest[*] from your own brother.”

Further, I arranged for a great assembly because of them. ^8 And I said to them: “To the extent possible, we have bought back our own Jewish brothers who were sold to the nations; but will you now sell your own brothers, and are they to be sold back to us?” At this they became speechless, and they could find nothing to say. ^9 Then I said: “What you are doing is not good. Should you not walk in the fear of our God so that the nations, our enemies, cannot reproach us? ^10 Moreover, I, my brothers, and my attendants are lending them money and grain. Let us, please, stop this lending on interest. ^11 Please, restore to them on this very day their fields, their vineyards, their olive groves, and their houses, as well as the hundredth[*] of the money, the grain, the new wine, and the oil that you are demanding as interest from them.”

^12 To this they said: “We will restore these things to them and ask nothing back. We will do precisely as you say.” So I called the priests and made those men swear to keep this promise. ^13 Also, I shook out the folds of my garment[*] and said: “In this manner may the true God shake out from his house and from his possessions every man who does not carry out this promise, and in this manner may he be shaken out and emptied.” To this all the congregation said: “Amen!”[*] And they praised Jehovah, and the people did as they promised.

^14 Moreover, from the day that he commissioned me to become their governor in the land of Judah, from the 20th year to the 32nd year of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes, 12 years, neither I nor my brothers ate the food allowance due the governor. ^15 But the former governors who were before me had burdened the people and had been taking from them 40 silver shekels[*] for bread and wine each day. Also, their attendants had oppressed the people. But I did not do that because of the fear of God.

^16 Furthermore, I took a hand in the work on this wall, and not a field did we acquire; all my attendants were gathered there for the work. ^17 There were 150 Jews and deputy rulers dining at my table, as well as those who came to us from the nations. ^18 Every day one bull, six choice sheep, and birds were prepared for me,[*] and once every ten days we had all sorts of wine in abundance. Despite all this I did not demand the food allowance due the governor, because the people were already bearing their burden of service. ^19 Do remember me favorably,[*] O my God, for all that I have done in behalf of this people.

^ Neh. 5:5 Lit., “like the flesh of our brothers is our flesh.”

^ Neh. 5:7 Or “usury.”

^ Neh. 5:11 Or “1 percent,” that is, monthly.

^ Neh. 5:13 Lit., “shook out my bosom.”

^ Neh. 5:13 Or “So be it!”

^ Neh. 5:15 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Neh. 5:18 Or “at my expense.”

^ Neh. 5:19 Or “for good.”

Nehemiah  6 : 1 - 19

6 Now as soon as San·balʹlat, To·biʹah, Geʹshem the Arabian, and the rest of our enemies were told that I had rebuilt the wall and that there were no gaps left in it (although up to that time I had not set up the doors in the gates), ^2 San·balʹlat and Geʹshem immediately sent this message to me: “Come, and let us set a time to meet together in the villages of the Valley Plain of Oʹno.” But they were scheming to harm me. ^3 So I sent messengers to them, saying: “I am engaged in a great work, and I am not able to go down. Why should the work stop while I leave it to come to you?” ^4 They sent me the same message four times, and I gave them the same reply each time.

^5 Then San·balʹlat sent his attendant to me with the same message a fifth time, with an open letter in his hand. ^6 There it was written: “Among the nations it has been heard, and Geʹshem is also saying it, that you and the Jews are scheming to rebel. That is why you are building the wall; and according to these reports you are to become their king. ^7 Also, you have appointed prophets to proclaim about you throughout Jerusalem, ‘There is a king in Judah!’ And now these things will be told to the king. So come, and let us discuss this together.”

^8 However, I sent him this reply: “None of the things you are saying have taken place; you are making them up out of your own imagination.”[*] ^9 For they were all trying to frighten us, saying: “Their hands will slacken in the work, and it will not be done.” Now, I pray, strengthen my hands.

^10 Then I went to the house of She·maiʹah the son of De·laʹiah the son of Me·hetʹa·bel while he was confined there. He said: “Let us set a time to meet at the house of the true God, within the temple, and let us close the doors of the temple, for they are coming to kill you. They are coming to kill you by night.” ^11 But I said: “Should a man like me run away? Can a man like me go into the temple and live? I will not go in!” ^12 Then I realized that God had not sent him, but that To·biʹah and San·balʹlat had hired him to speak this prophecy against me. ^13 He had been hired to frighten me and to cause me to sin, so that they would have grounds to damage my reputation in order to reproach me.

^14 Do remember, O my God, To·biʹah and San·balʹlat and these deeds, and also No·a·diʹah the prophetess and the rest of the prophets who were constantly trying to frighten me.

^15 So the wall was completed on the 25th day of Eʹlul,[*] in 52 days.

^16 As soon as all our enemies heard of it and all the surrounding nations saw it, they became greatly ashamed,[*] and they realized that it was with our God’s help that this work had been done. ^17 In those days the nobles of Judah were sending many letters to To·biʹah, and To·biʹah would reply to them. ^18 Many in Judah swore allegiance to him, for he was a son-in-law of Shec·a·niʹah the son of Aʹrah, and his son Je·ho·haʹnan had married the daughter of Me·shulʹlam the son of Ber·e·chiʹah. ^19 Also, they would constantly tell me good things about him and then report to him what I said. Then To·biʹah would send letters to frighten me.

^ Neh. 6:8 Lit., “from your heart.”

^ Neh. 6:15 See App. B15.

^ Neh. 6:16 Lit., “they fell greatly in their own eyes.”

Nehemiah  8 : 1 - 18

8 All the people then gathered with one accord at the public square in front of the Water Gate, and they told Ezʹra the copyist[*] to bring the book of the Law of Moses, which Jehovah had commanded Israel. ^2 So Ezʹra the priest brought the Law before the congregation of men, women, and all who could listen with understanding, on the first day of the seventh month. ^3 And he read aloud from it before the public square in front of the Water Gate, from daybreak until midday, to the men, the women, and all who could understand; and the people listened attentively to the book of the Law. ^4 And Ezʹra the copyist[*] was standing on a wooden podium made for the occasion; and standing alongside him on his right were Mat·ti·thiʹah, Sheʹma, A·naiʹah, U·riʹah, Hil·kiʹah, and Ma·a·seiʹah; and on his left were Pe·daiʹah, Mishʹa·el, Mal·chiʹjah, Haʹshum, Hash-badʹda·nah, Zech·a·riʹah, and Me·shulʹlam.

^5 Ezʹra opened the book in the sight of all the people, for he was above all the people. As he opened it, all the people stood up. ^6 Then Ezʹra praised Jehovah the true God, the great One, at which all the people answered, “Amen![*] Amen!” and lifted up their hands. They then bowed low and prostrated themselves to Jehovah with their faces to the ground. ^7 And Jeshʹu·a, Baʹni, She·re·biʹah, Jaʹmin, Akʹkub, Shabʹbe·thai, Ho·diʹah, Ma·a·seiʹah, Ke·liʹta, Az·a·riʹah, Joʹza·bad, Haʹnan, and Pe·laʹiah, who were Levites, were explaining the Law to the people, while the people remained standing. ^8 And they continued reading aloud from the book, from the Law of the true God, clearly explaining it and putting meaning into it; so they helped the people to understand what was being read.[*]

^9 And Ne·he·miʹah, who was then the governor,[*] Ezʹra the priest and copyist,[*] and the Levites who were instructing the people said to all the people: “This day is holy to Jehovah your God. Do not mourn or weep.” For all the people were weeping as they heard the words of the Law. ^10 He said to them: “Go, eat the choice things[*] and drink what is sweet, and send portions of food to those who have nothing prepared; for this day is holy to our Lord, and do not feel sad, for the joy of Jehovah is your stronghold.”[*] ^11 And the Levites were calming all the people, saying: “Be quiet! for this day is holy, and do not feel sad.” ^12 So all the people went away to eat and to drink and to send out portions of food and to carry on a great rejoicing, for they understood the words that had been made known to them.

^13 And on the second day, the heads of the paternal houses of all the people, the priests, and the Levites gathered around Ezʹra the copyist[*] to gain further insight into the words of the Law. ^14 Then they found written in the Law that Jehovah had commanded through Moses that the Israelites should dwell in booths[*] during the festival in the seventh month, ^15 and that they should make proclamation and announce throughout all their cities and throughout Jerusalem, saying: “Go out to the mountainous region and bring in leafy branches from olive trees, pine trees, myrtle and palm trees, and the leafy branches of other trees to make booths, according to what is written.”

^16 So the people went out and brought them in to make booths for themselves, each one on his roof, as well as in their courtyards, in the courtyards of the house of the true God, in the public square of the Water Gate, and in the public square of the Gate of Eʹphra·im. ^17 Thus all those of the congregation who had come back from the captivity made booths and were dwelling in the booths, for the Israelites had not done it this way from the days of Joshua the son of Nun until that day, so that there was very great rejoicing. ^18 And day by day there was a reading from the book of the Law of the true God, from the first day until the last day. And they held the festival for seven days, and there was a solemn assembly on the eighth day, as was required.

^ Neh. 8:1 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 8:4 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 8:6 Or “So be it!”

^ Neh. 8:8 Or “they gave understanding in the reading.”

^ Neh. 8:9 Or “the Tirshatha,” a Persian title for a governor of a province.

^ Neh. 8:9 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 8:10 Lit., “fatty things.”

^ Neh. 8:10 Or “strength.”

^ Neh. 8:13 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 8:14 Or “temporary shelters.”

Nehemiah  9 : 1 - 38

9 On the 24th day of this month the Israelites assembled; they were fasting with sackcloth and dust on themselves. ^2 Those of Israelite descent then separated themselves from all the foreigners, and they stood and confessed their own sins and the errors of their fathers. ^3 Then they stood up at their place and read aloud from the book of the Law of Jehovah their God for a fourth of the day;[*] and for another fourth of it they were confessing and bowing down to Jehovah their God.

^4 Jeshʹu·a, Baʹni, Kadʹmi·el, Sheb·a·niʹah, Bunʹni, She·re·biʹah, Baʹni, and Che·naʹni stood on the raised platform of the Levites, and they cried out with a loud voice to Jehovah their God. ^5 And the Levites Jeshʹu·a, Kadʹmi·el, Baʹni, Hash·ab·neiʹah, She·re·biʹah, Ho·diʹah, Sheb·a·niʹah, and Peth·a·hiʹah said: “Stand up and praise Jehovah your God throughout all eternity.[*] And let them praise your glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise.

^6 “You alone are Jehovah; you made the heavens, yes, the heaven of the heavens and all their army, the earth and all that is on it, the seas and all that is in them. And you preserve all of them alive, and the army of the heavens are bowing down to you. ^7 You are Jehovah the true God, who chose Aʹbram and brought him out of Ur of the Chal·deʹans and gave him the name Abraham. ^8 You found his heart faithful before you, so you made a covenant with him to give him the land of the Caʹnaan·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Amʹor·ites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Jebʹu·sites, and the Girʹga·shites, to give it to his offspring;[*] and you kept your promises, because you are righteous.

^9 “So you saw the affliction of our forefathers in Egypt, and you heard their outcry at the Red Sea. ^10 Then you performed signs and miracles against Pharʹaoh and all his servants and all the people of his land, for you knew that they acted presumptuously against them. You made a name for yourself that remains to this day. ^11 And you split the sea before them, so that they crossed through the sea on the dry land, and you hurled their pursuers into the depths like a stone thrown into the turbulent waters. ^12 You led them by day with a pillar of cloud, and by night with a pillar of fire, to light up for them the way they should go. ^13 And you came down on Mount Siʹnai and spoke with them from heaven and gave them righteous judgments, laws of truth,[*] good regulations and commandments. ^14 You made known to them your holy Sabbath, and you gave them commandments, regulations, and a law through your servant Moses. ^15 You gave them bread from heaven when they were hungry, and you brought water out of the crag when they were thirsty, and you told them to enter and take possession of the land that you had sworn[*] to give to them.

^16 “But they, our forefathers, acted presumptuously and became stubborn,[*] and they would not listen to your commandments. ^17 They refused to listen, and they did not remember your extraordinary acts that you performed among them, but they became stubborn[*] and appointed a head to return to their slavery in Egypt. But you are a God ready to forgive,[*] compassionate[*] and merciful, slow to anger and abundant in loyal love,[*] and you did not abandon them. ^18 Even when they made for themselves a metal statue[*] of a calf and were saying, ‘This is your God who led you up out of Egypt,’ and they committed great acts of disrespect, ^19 even then you, in your great mercy, did not abandon them in the wilderness. The pillar of cloud did not depart from over them by day to lead them in the way, nor the pillar of fire by night to light up for them the way they should go. ^20 And you gave your good spirit to give them insight, and you did not hold back your manna from their mouth, and you gave them water when they were thirsty. ^21 For 40 years you provided them with food in the wilderness. They lacked nothing. Their garments did not wear out, and their feet did not become swollen.

^22 “You gave them kingdoms and peoples, apportioning them piece by piece, so that they took possession of the land of Siʹhon, that is, the land of the king of Heshʹbon, as well as the land of Og the king of Baʹshan. ^23 And you made their sons as numerous as the stars of the heavens. Then you brought them into the land that you had promised their forefathers that they should enter and possess. ^24 So their sons went in and took possession of the land, and you subdued before them the Caʹnaan·ites, who were the inhabitants of the land, and you gave them into their hand, both their kings and the peoples of the land, to do with them as they pleased. ^25 And they captured fortified cities and a fertile[*] land, and they took possession of houses full of all sorts of good things, cisterns already dug, vineyards, olive groves, and fruit trees in abundance. So they ate and grew satisfied and fat, and they basked in your great goodness.

^26 “However, they became disobedient and rebelled against you and turned their back on your Law.[*] They killed your prophets who warned them so as to bring them back to you, and they committed acts of great disrespect. ^27 For this you gave them into the hand of their adversaries, who kept causing them distress. But they would cry out to you in the time of their distress, and you would hear from the heavens; and because of your great mercy, you would give them saviors to rescue them out of the hand of their adversaries.

^28 “But as soon as they had relief, they would again do what is bad before you, and you would abandon them to the hand of their enemies, who would dominate them.[*] Then they would return and call to you for help, and you would hear from the heavens and rescue them time and again because of your great mercy. ^29 Although you would warn them so as to bring them back to your Law, they behaved presumptuously and refused to listen to your commandments; and they sinned against your regulations, by which a man will live if he observes them. But they stubbornly turned their back and stiffened their neck, and they refused to listen. ^30 You extended patience to them for many years and kept warning them by your spirit through your prophets, but they refused to listen. Finally you gave them into the hand of the peoples of the lands. ^31 And in your great mercy, you did not exterminate them or abandon them, for you are a compassionate[*] and merciful God.

^32 “And now, O our God, the God great, mighty, and awe-inspiring, who has kept his covenant and shown loyal love, do not treat lightly all the hardship that has found us, our kings, our princes, our priests, our prophets, our forefathers, and all your people from the days of the kings of As·syrʹi·a down to this day. ^33 You have been righteous in all that has come upon us, for you have acted faithfully; but we are the ones who have acted wickedly. ^34 As for our kings, our princes, our priests, and our forefathers, they have not observed your Law nor paid attention to your commandments or to your reminders[*] by which you warned them. ^35 Even when they were in their kingdom and enjoying the abundant goodness that you gave them and they were in the broad and fertile[*] land that you bestowed on them, they did not serve you and did not turn away from their bad practices. ^36 So here we are today, slaves—yes, slaves in the land that you gave to our forefathers to eat its fruitage and its good things. ^37 Its abundant produce is for the kings whom you have put over us because of our sins. They rule over our bodies and over our livestock as they see fit, and we are in great distress.

^38 “So in view of all this, we are making a binding agreement in writing, and it is attested by the seal of our princes, our Levites, and our priests.”

^ Neh. 9:3 Or “for three hours.”

^ Neh. 9:5 Or “from eternity to eternity.”

^ Neh. 9:8 Lit., “seed.”

^ Neh. 9:13 Or “reliable laws.”

^ Neh. 9:15 Lit., “lifted your hand.”

^ Neh. 9:16 Lit., “hardened their neck.”

^ Neh. 9:17 Lit., “hardened their neck.”

^ Neh. 9:17 Or “a God of acts of forgiveness.”

^ Neh. 9:17 Or “gracious.”

^ Neh. 9:17 Or “loving-kindness.”

^ Neh. 9:18 Or “molten statue.”

^ Neh. 9:25 Or “rich.”

^ Neh. 9:26 Lit., “and cast your Law behind their back.”

^ Neh. 9:28 Or “crush them.”

^ Neh. 9:31 Or “gracious.”

^ Neh. 9:34 Or “warnings.”

^ Neh. 9:35 Or “rich.”

Nehemiah  12 : 1 - 47

12 These were the priests and the Levites who went up with Ze·rubʹba·bel the son of She·alʹti·el, and Jeshʹu·a: Se·raiʹah, Jeremiah, Ezʹra, ^2 Am·a·riʹah, Malʹluch, Hatʹtush, ^3 Shec·a·niʹah, Reʹhum, Merʹe·moth, ^4 Idʹdo, Ginʹne·thoi, A·biʹjah, ^5 Mijʹa·min, Ma·a·diʹah, Bilʹgah, ^6 She·maiʹah, Joiʹa·rib, Je·daʹiah, ^7 Salʹlu, Aʹmok, Hil·kiʹah, and Je·daʹiah. These were the heads of the priests and their brothers in the days of Jeshʹu·a.

^8 The Levites were Jeshʹu·a, Binʹnu·i, Kadʹmi·el, She·re·biʹah, Judah, and Mat·ta·niʹah, who led the songs of thanksgiving along with his brothers. ^9 And Bak·bu·kiʹah and Unʹni their brothers stood opposite them for guard duties.[*] ^10 Jeshʹu·a became father to Joiʹa·kim, and Joiʹa·kim became father to E·liʹa·shib, and E·liʹa·shib to Joiʹa·da. ^11 And Joiʹa·da became father to Jonʹa·than, and Jonʹa·than became father to Jadʹdu·a.

^12 In the days of Joiʹa·kim, these were the priests, the heads of the paternal houses: for Se·raiʹah, Me·raiʹah; for Jeremiah, Han·a·niʹah; ^13 for Ezʹra, Me·shulʹlam; for Am·a·riʹah, Je·ho·haʹnan; ^14 for Malʹlu·chi, Jonʹa·than; for Sheb·a·niʹah, Joseph; ^15 for Haʹrim, Adʹna; for Me·raʹioth, Helʹkai; ^16 for Idʹdo, Zech·a·riʹah; for Ginʹne·thon, Me·shulʹlam; ^17 for A·biʹjah, Zichʹri; for Mi·niʹa·min, . . .  ;[*] for Mo·a·diʹah, Pilʹtai; ^18 for Bilʹgah, Sham·muʹa; for She·maiʹah, Je·honʹa·than; ^19 for Joiʹa·rib, Mat·teʹnai; for Je·daʹiah, Uzʹzi; ^20 for Sal·laʹi, Kalʹlai; for Aʹmok, Eʹber; ^21 for Hil·kiʹah, Hash·a·biʹah; for Je·daʹiah, Ne·thanʹel.

^22 The heads of the paternal houses of the Levites in the days of E·liʹa·shib, Joiʹa·da, Jo·haʹnan, and Jadʹdu·a were recorded, as were the priests, down to the kingship of Da·riʹus the Persian.

^23 The Levites who were heads of the paternal houses were recorded in the book of the history of the times, down to the days of Jo·haʹnan the son of E·liʹa·shib. ^24 The heads of the Levites were Hash·a·biʹah, She·re·biʹah, and Jeshʹu·a the son of Kadʹmi·el, and their brothers stood opposite them to offer praise and give thanks according to the instructions of David the man of the true God, guard group corresponding to guard group. ^25 Mat·ta·niʹah, Bak·bu·kiʹah, O·ba·diʹah, Me·shulʹlam, Talʹmon, and Akʹkub were standing guard as gatekeepers, guarding the storerooms by the gates. ^26 These served in the days of Joiʹa·kim the son of Jeshʹu·a the son of Joʹza·dak and in the days of Ne·he·miʹah the governor and Ezʹra the priest and copyist.[*]

^27 At the inauguration of the walls of Jerusalem, they sought the Levites and brought them to Jerusalem from all the places they lived to celebrate the inauguration with rejoicing, with songs of thanksgiving, and with cymbals, stringed instruments, and harps. ^28 And the sons of the singers[*] gathered together from the district,[*] from all around Jerusalem, from the settlements of the Ne·tophʹa·thites, ^29 from Beth-gilʹgal, and from the fields of Geʹba and Azʹma·veth, for the singers had built settlements for themselves all around Jerusalem. ^30 And the priests and the Levites purified themselves, and they purified the people, the gates, and the wall.

^31 Then I brought the princes of Judah up on top of the wall. Further, I appointed two large thanksgiving choirs and processions, and the one walked to the right on the wall toward the Gate of the Ash Heaps. ^32 Ho·shaiʹah and half of the princes of Judah walked behind them, ^33 along with Az·a·riʹah, Ezʹra, Me·shulʹlam, ^34 Judah, Benjamin, She·maiʹah, and Jeremiah. ^35 With them were some of the sons of the priests with the trumpets: Zech·a·riʹah son of Jonʹa·than son of She·maiʹah son of Mat·ta·niʹah son of Mi·caiʹah son of Zacʹcur son of Aʹsaph, ^36 and his brothers She·maiʹah, Azʹar·el, Milʹa·lai, Gilʹa·lai, Maʹai, Ne·thanʹel, Judah, and Ha·naʹni, with the musical instruments of David the man of the true God; and Ezʹra the copyist[*] went before them. ^37 At the Fountain Gate they went straight ahead up the Stairway of the City of David by the ascent of the wall above the House of David and on to the Water Gate to the east.

^38 The other thanksgiving choir walked in the opposite direction,[*] and I followed it with half of the people, on the wall up over the Tower of the Ovens and on to the Broad Wall ^39 and up over the Gate of Eʹphra·im and on to the Gate of the Old City and on to the Fish Gate, the Tower of Ha·nanʹel, the Tower of Meʹah, and on to the Sheep Gate; and they came to a halt at the Gate of the Guard.

^40 At length the two thanksgiving choirs stood before the house of the true God; so did I and half of the deputy rulers with me, ^41 and the priests E·liʹa·kim, Ma·a·seiʹah, Mi·niʹa·min, Mi·caiʹah, Eli·o·eʹnai, Zech·a·riʹah, and Han·a·niʹah, with the trumpets, ^42 and Ma·a·seiʹah, She·maiʹah, El·e·aʹzar, Uzʹzi, Je·ho·haʹnan, Mal·chiʹjah, Eʹlam, and Eʹzer. And the singers sang loudly under the oversight of Iz·ra·hiʹah.

^43 On that day they offered great sacrifices and rejoiced, for the true God made them rejoice with great joy. The women and the children also rejoiced, so that the rejoicing of Jerusalem could be heard far away.

^44 On that day men were appointed over the storehouses for the contributions, the firstfruits, and the tenths.[*] Into them they were to gather from the fields of the cities the portions required by the Law for the priests and the Levites, for there was rejoicing in Judah because of the priests and the Levites who were ministering. ^45 And they began taking care of the duties of their God and the obligation of the purification, as did the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the instructions of David and his son Solʹo·mon. ^46 For long ago in the days of David and Aʹsaph, there were directors[*] for the singers and for the songs of praise and thanksgiving to God. ^47 And during the days of Ze·rubʹba·bel and during the days of Ne·he·miʹah, all Israel gave portions to the singers and the gatekeepers, according to the daily need. They also set aside the portion for the Levites, and the Levites set aside the portion for the descendants of Aaron.

^ Neh. 12:9 Or possibly, “during the service.”

^ Neh. 12:17 The Hebrew text evidently omits a name here.

^ Neh. 12:26 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 12:28 Or “And the trained singers.”

^ Neh. 12:28 That is, the district around the Jordan.

^ Neh. 12:36 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 12:38 Or “in front.”

^ Neh. 12:44 Or “tithes.”

^ Neh. 12:46 Lit., “heads.”

Nehemiah  13 : 1 - 31

13 On that day the book of Moses was read in the hearing of the people, and it was found written that no Amʹmon·ite or Moʹab·ite should ever enter the congregation of the true God, ^2 for they had not met the Israelites with bread and water, but instead they had hired Baʹlaam against them to curse them. However, our God had changed the curse into a blessing. ^3 As soon as they heard the Law, they began to separate from Israel all those of foreign descent.[*]

^4 Now before this, the priest in charge of the storerooms[*] of the house[*] of our God was E·liʹa·shib, a relative of To·biʹah. ^5 He had made available for him a large storeroom,[*] where previously they used to put the grain offering, the frankincense, and the utensils and the tenth[*] of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, to which the Levites, the singers, and the gatekeepers are entitled, along with the contribution for the priests.

^6 And during all this time I was not in Jerusalem, for I went to the king in the 32nd year of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes of Babylon; and sometime later I asked the king for a leave of absence. ^7 Then I came to Jerusalem and noticed the terrible thing that E·liʹa·shib had done in behalf of To·biʹah, making a storeroom available for him in the courtyard of the house of the true God. ^8 This was very displeasing to me, so I threw all of To·biʹah’s household furniture out of the storeroom.[*] ^9 After that I gave orders, and they cleansed the storerooms;[*] and I put back there the utensils of the house of the true God, with the grain offering and the frankincense.

^10 I also found out that the portions of the Levites had not been given them, so that the Levites and the singers who did the work had gone off, each to his own field. ^11 So I reprimanded the deputy rulers and said: “Why has the house of the true God been neglected?” Then I gathered them together and assigned them back to their posts. ^12 And all Judah brought in the tenth of the grain, the new wine, and the oil to the storerooms. ^13 Then I put Shel·e·miʹah the priest, Zaʹdok the copyist,[*] and Pe·daiʹah of the Levites in charge of the storerooms, and Haʹnan the son of Zacʹcur the son of Mat·ta·niʹah was their assistant, for these men were considered reliable. It was their responsibility to make the distribution to their brothers.

^14 Do remember me, O my God, concerning this, and do not wipe out my acts of loyal love that I have done for the house of my God and its services.[*]

^15 In those days I saw people in Judah treading winepresses on the Sabbath, bringing in heaps of grain and loading them on donkeys, and bringing wine, grapes, figs, and every sort of load into Jerusalem on the Sabbath day. So I warned them against selling provisions on that day.[*] ^16 And the Tyrʹi·ans who lived in the city were bringing in fish and all kinds of merchandise, selling them to the people of Judah and in Jerusalem on the Sabbath. ^17 So I reprimanded the nobles of Judah and said to them: “What is this evil thing that you are doing, even profaning the Sabbath day? ^18 Was not this what your forefathers did, so that our God brought all this disaster on us and also on this city? Now you are adding to the burning anger against Israel by profaning the Sabbath.”

^19 So as soon as the shadows began to fall on the gates of Jerusalem before the Sabbath, I ordered that the doors be closed. I also said that they should not open them until after the Sabbath, and I stationed some of my own attendants at the gates so that no loads would be brought in on the Sabbath day. ^20 So the traders and the sellers of all kinds of merchandise spent the night outside Jerusalem once or twice. ^21 Then I warned them and said to them: “Why are you spending the night in front of the wall? If you do it again, I will use force against you.” From that time on they did not come on the Sabbath.

^22 And I told the Levites that they should regularly purify themselves and come and guard the gates to keep the Sabbath day holy. This, also, do remember to my credit, O my God, and show me pity according to your abundant loyal love.

^23 In those days I also saw Jews who had married[*] Ashʹdod·ite, Amʹmon·ite, and Moʹab·ite women. ^24 Half of their sons were speaking Ashʹdod·ite and half spoke the language of the different peoples, but none of them knew how to speak the language of the Jews. ^25 So I reprimanded them and called down a curse on them and struck some of the men and pulled out their hair and made them swear by God: “You should not give your daughters to their sons, and you should not accept any of their daughters for your sons or yourselves. ^26 Was it not because of these that King Solʹo·mon of Israel sinned? Among the many nations there was no king like him; and he was loved by his God, so that God made him king over all Israel. But the foreign wives caused even him to sin. ^27 Is it not something unheard of for you to commit this great evil in acting unfaithfully against our God by marrying foreign women?”

^28 One of the sons of Joiʹa·da the son of E·liʹa·shib the high priest had become a son-in-law of San·balʹlat the Horʹo·nite. So I drove him away from me.

^29 Do remember them, O my God, because they have defiled the priesthood and the covenant of the priesthood and the Levites.

^30 And I purified them from every foreign defilement, and I assigned duties to the priests and to the Levites, each to his own service, ^31 and arranged for the supply of the wood at appointed times and for the first ripe fruits.

Do remember me favorably,[*] O my God.

^ Neh. 13:3 Or “mixed descent.”

^ Neh. 13:4 Or “dining halls.”

^ Neh. 13:4 Or “temple.”

^ Neh. 13:5 Or “dining hall.”

^ Neh. 13:5 Or “tithe.”

^ Neh. 13:8 Or “dining hall.”

^ Neh. 13:9 Or “dining halls.”

^ Neh. 13:13 Or “scribe.”

^ Neh. 13:14 Or “guardianship.”

^ Neh. 13:15 Or possibly, “warned them on that day not to sell provisions.”

^ Neh. 13:23 Or “had taken into their houses.”

^ Neh. 13:31 Or “for good.”

Esther  4 : 1 - 17

4 When Morʹde·cai learned of everything that had been done, he ripped his garments apart and put on sackcloth and ashes. Then he went out into the middle of the city, crying out loudly and bitterly. ^2 He went only as far as the king’s gate, for no one was to enter the king’s gate wearing sackcloth. ^3 And in every province[*] where the king’s word and his decree reached, there was great mourning among the Jews, along with fasting and weeping and wailing. Many were lying down in sackcloth and ashes. ^4 When Esther’s female attendants and her eunuchs came in and told her, the queen was deeply distressed. Then she sent garments for Morʹde·cai to wear instead of his sackcloth, but he refused them. ^5 At this Esther summoned Haʹthach, one of the king’s eunuchs, whom he had appointed to serve her, and she ordered him to find out from Morʹde·cai what this meant and what was happening.

^6 So Haʹthach went out to Morʹde·cai in the public square of the city in front of the king’s gate. ^7 Morʹde·cai told him about everything that had happened to him and the exact amount of money that Haʹman had promised to pay to the king’s treasury for the Jews to be destroyed. ^8 He also gave him a copy of the written decree that had been issued in Shuʹshan[*] for their annihilation. He was to show it to Esther and explain it to her and instruct her to go in to the king to beg for his favor and to plead directly with him in behalf of her people.

^9 Haʹthach came back and told Esther what Morʹde·cai had said. ^10 Esther replied to Haʹthach with instructions to tell Morʹde·cai: ^11 “All the king’s servants and the people of the king’s provinces[*] are aware that if any man or woman goes into the king’s inner courtyard without being summoned, there is only one law that applies: He is to be put to death; he may live only if the king holds out to him the golden scepter. And I have not been summoned to the king now for 30 days.”

^12 When Morʹde·cai was told what Esther had said, ^13 he replied to Esther: “Do not imagine that because you are in the king’s household you are any more likely to escape than all the other Jews. ^14 For if you remain silent at this time, relief and deliverance will come to the Jews from another source, but you and your father’s house will perish. And who knows whether it is for a time like this that you have attained to your royal status?”

^15 Then Esther replied to Morʹde·cai: ^16 “Go, gather all the Jews who are found in Shuʹshan[*] and fast in my behalf. Do not eat or drink for three days, night and day. I along with my female attendants will also fast. I will go in to the king, which is against the law, and if I am to perish, I will perish.” ^17 So Morʹde·cai went his way and did all that Esther had instructed him to do.

^ Esther 4:3 Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ Esther 4:8 Or “Susa.”

^ Esther 4:11 Or “jurisdictional districts.”

^ Esther 4:16 Or “Susa.”

Esther  5 : 1 - 14

5 On the third day Esther put on her royal robes and stood in the inner courtyard of the king’s house,[*] opposite the king’s house, while the king was sitting on his royal throne in the royal house opposite the entrance. ^2 As soon as the king saw Queen Esther standing in the courtyard, she gained his favor, and the king held out to Esther the golden scepter that was in his hand. Esther then approached and touched the top of the scepter.

^3 The king asked her: “What is the matter, Queen Esther? What is your request? Even to[*] the half of my kingdom, it will be granted you!” ^4 Esther replied: “If it pleases the king, let the king along with Haʹman come today to the banquet that I have prepared for him.” ^5 So the king said to his men: “Tell Haʹman to come quickly, as Esther requests.” So the king and Haʹman went to the banquet that Esther had prepared.

^6 During the banquet of wine, the king said to Esther: “What is your petition? It will be granted you! And what is your request? Even to[*] the half of my kingdom, it will be done!” ^7 Esther answered: “My petition and my request is, ^8 If I have found favor with the king and if it pleases the king to grant my petition and to act on my request, let the king and Haʹman come to the banquet that I will hold for them tomorrow; and tomorrow I will do as the king says.”

^9 On that day Haʹman went out joyful and with a cheerful heart. But when Haʹman saw Morʹde·cai in the king’s gate and noticed that he did not rise and tremble in his presence, Haʹman was filled with rage against Morʹde·cai. ^10 However, Haʹman restrained himself and went to his house. Then he sent for his friends and Zeʹresh his wife. ^11 Haʹman boasted about his glorious wealth, his many sons, and how the king had promoted him and had exalted him over the princes and the servants of the king.

^12 Haʹman added: “What is more, Queen Esther invited no one else but me to accompany the king to the banquet she prepared. I am also invited tomorrow to be with her and the king. ^13 But all of this fails to satisfy me as long as I see Morʹde·cai the Jew sitting in the king’s gate.” ^14 So Zeʹresh his wife and all his friends said to him: “Have a stake put up, 50 cubits[*] high. And in the morning tell the king that Morʹde·cai should be hanged on it. Then go with the king to enjoy yourself at the banquet.” This suggestion seemed good to Haʹman, so he had the stake put up.

^ Esther 5:1 Or “palace.”

^ Esther 5:3 Or “for.”

^ Esther 5:6 Or “for.”

^ Esther 5:14 About 22.3 m (73 ft). See App. B14.

Esther  6 : 1 - 14

6 That night the king could not sleep.[*] So he said to bring the book of the historical records of the times, and it was read to the king. ^2 There it was found written what Morʹde·cai had reported concerning Big·thaʹna and Teʹresh, two court officials of the king, doorkeepers, who had plotted to do away with[*] King A·has·u·eʹrus. ^3 The king asked: “What honor and recognition has been given to Morʹde·cai for this?” To this the king’s personal attendants said: “Nothing has been done for him.”

^4 Later the king said: “Who is in the courtyard?” Now Haʹman had come into the outer courtyard of the king’s house[*] to speak to the king about having Morʹde·cai hanged on the stake that he had prepared for him. ^5 The king’s attendants said to him: “It is Haʹman standing in the courtyard.” So the king said: “Have him come in.”

^6 When Haʹman came in, the king said to him: “What should be done for the man whom the king wishes to honor?” Haʹman said in his heart: “Whom would the king wish to honor more than me?” ^7 So Haʹman said to the king: “For the man whom the king wishes to honor, ^8 let them bring royal attire that the king wears and a horse on which the king rides, with the royal headdress on its head. ^9 Then let the attire and the horse be put into the charge of one of the king’s noble princes, and they should clothe the man whom the king wishes to honor and have him ride on the horse in the public square of the city. They should call out before him: ‘This is what is done for the man whom the king wishes to honor!’” ^10 At once the king said to Haʹman: “Quick! Take the attire and the horse, and do what you just said for Morʹde·cai the Jew who is sitting in the king’s gate. Do not leave out anything that you have said.”

^11 So Haʹman took the attire and the horse, and he clothed Morʹde·cai and made him ride in the public square of the city and called out before him: “This is what is done for the man whom the king wishes to honor!” ^12 Afterward Morʹde·cai returned to the king’s gate, but Haʹman hurried to his house, mourning with his head covered. ^13 When Haʹman related to his wife Zeʹresh and to all his friends everything that had happened to him, his wise men and his wife Zeʹresh said to him: “If Morʹde·cai, before whom you have started to fall, is of Jewish descent,[*] you will not prevail against him; you will surely fall before him.”

^14 While they were still speaking with him, the king’s court officials arrived and quickly took Haʹman to the banquet that Esther had made.

^ Esther 6:1 Lit., “the king’s sleep fled.”

^ Esther 6:2 Lit., “to lay hand on.”

^ Esther 6:4 Or “palace.”

^ Esther 6:13 Lit., “from the seed of the Jews.”

Esther  7 : 1 - 10

7 So the king and Haʹman came in to Queen Esther’s banquet. ^2 The king said to Esther again on the second day during the banquet of wine: “What is your petition, Queen Esther? It will be granted you. And what is your request? Even to[*] the half of my kingdom, it will be done!” ^3 Queen Esther answered: “If I have found favor with you, O king, and if it pleases the king, let my life[*] be granted as my petition, and my people as my request. ^4 For we have been sold, I and my people, to be annihilated, killed, and destroyed. If we had simply been sold as male and female slaves, I would have kept silent. But the distress is not proper, for it will be damaging to the king.”

^5 King A·has·u·eʹrus then said to Queen Esther: “Who is this, and where is the man who has dared to do such a thing?” ^6 Esther said: “The adversary and enemy is this evil Haʹman.”

Haʹman became terrified because of the king and the queen. ^7 The king rose up in a rage from the banquet of wine and went into the palace garden, but Haʹman stood up to plead with Queen Esther for his life,[*] for he realized that the king was determined to punish him. ^8 The king returned from the palace garden to the house of the wine banquet and saw that Haʹman had thrown himself on the couch where Esther was. The king exclaimed: “Is he also going to rape the queen in my own house?” As soon as these words left the king’s mouth, they covered Haʹman’s face. ^9 Har·boʹna, one of the king’s court officials, now said: “Haʹman also prepared a stake for Morʹde·cai, whose report saved the king. It is standing at Haʹman’s house, 50 cubits[*] high.” At that the king said: “Hang him on it.” ^10 So they hanged Haʹman on the stake that he had prepared for Morʹde·cai, and the king’s rage subsided.

^ Esther 7:2 Or “for.”

^ Esther 7:3 Or “soul.”

^ Esther 7:7 Or “soul.”

^ Esther 7:9 About 22.3 m (73 ft). See App. B14.

Isaiah  19 : 1 - 25

19 A pronouncement against Egypt:

Look! Jehovah is riding on a swift cloud and is coming into Egypt.

The worthless gods of Egypt will tremble before him,

And the heart of Egypt will melt within it.

 ^2 “I will incite Egyptians against Egyptians,

And they will fight one another,

Each against his brother and his neighbor,

City against city, kingdom against kingdom.

 ^3 And the spirit of Egypt will become bewildered within it,

And I will confuse its plans.

They will resort to the worthless gods,

To the charmers and to the spirit mediums and to the fortune-tellers.

 ^4 I will hand Egypt over to a hard master,

And a harsh king will rule over them,” declares the true Lord, Jehovah of armies.

 ^5 The water of the sea will be dried up,

And the river will become parched and run dry.

 ^6 And the rivers will stink;

The Nile canals of Egypt will become low and parched.

The reeds and the rushes will decay.

 ^7 The plants along the Nile River, at the mouth of the Nile,

And all the land sown with seed along the Nile will dry up.

It will be blown away, and it will be no more.

 ^8 And the fishermen will mourn,

Those casting fishhooks into the Nile will lament,

And those who spread their nets on the water will dwindle.

 ^9 Those who work in combed flax

And those making white fabric on the loom will be put to shame.

^10 Her weavers will be crushed;

All the hired workers will grieve.[*]

^11 The princes of Zoʹan are foolish.

The wisest advisers of Pharʹaoh give unreasonable advice.

How can you say to Pharʹaoh:

“I am a descendant of wise ones,

A descendant of ancient kings”?

^12 Where, then, are your wise men?

Let them tell you if they know what Jehovah of armies has decided concerning Egypt.

^13 The princes of Zoʹan have acted foolishly;

The princes of Noph[*] have been deceived;

The chiefs of her tribes have led Egypt astray.

^14 Jehovah has poured out on her a spirit of confusion;

And they have led Egypt astray in whatever she does,

Like a drunk staggering in his vomit.

^15 And Egypt will not have any work to do,

Whether for the head or the tail, the shoot or the rush.[*]

^16 In that day Egypt will become like women, trembling and terrified because of the threatening hand that Jehovah of armies raises against it. ^17 And the land of Judah will become a cause for terror to Egypt. They will feel dread at the mention of it because of the decision that Jehovah of armies has made against them.

^18 In that day there will be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the language of Caʹnaan and swearing loyalty to Jehovah of armies. One city will be called The City of Tearing Down.

^19 In that day there will be an altar to Jehovah in the middle of the land of Egypt and a pillar to Jehovah at its boundary. ^20 It will be for a sign and for a witness to Jehovah of armies in the land of Egypt; for they will cry out to Jehovah because of the oppressors, and he will send them a savior, a grand one, who will save them. ^21 And Jehovah will become known to the Egyptians, and the Egyptians will know Jehovah in that day, and they will offer sacrifices and gifts and make a vow to Jehovah and pay it. ^22 Jehovah will strike Egypt, striking and healing it; and they will return to Jehovah, and he will respond to their entreaties and heal them.

^23 In that day there will be a highway out of Egypt to As·syrʹi·a. Then As·syrʹi·a will come into Egypt, and Egypt into As·syrʹi·a, and Egypt will serve God together with As·syrʹi·a. ^24 In that day Israel will be the third along with Egypt and with As·syrʹi·a, a blessing in the midst of the earth, ^25 for Jehovah of armies will have blessed it, saying: “Blessed be my people, Egypt, and the work of my hands, As·syrʹi·a, and my inheritance, Israel.”

^ Isa. 19:10 Or “be grieved in soul.”

^ Isa. 19:13 Or “Memphis.”

^ Isa. 19:15 Or possibly, “the palm branch or the reed.”

Isaiah  36 : 1 - 22

36 In the 14th year of King Hez·e·kiʹah, Sen·nachʹer·ib the king of As·syrʹi·a came up against all the fortified cities of Judah and captured them. ^2 The king of As·syrʹi·a then sent the Rabʹsha·keh[*] with a vast army from Laʹchish to King Hez·e·kiʹah in Jerusalem. They took up a position by the conduit of the upper pool, which is at the highway of the laundryman’s field. ^3 Then E·liʹa·kim son of Hil·kiʹah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹna the secretary, and Joʹah son of Aʹsaph the recorder came out to him.

^4 So the Rabʹsha·keh said to them: “Please, say to Hez·e·kiʹah, ‘This is what the great king, the king of As·syrʹi·a, says: “What is the basis for your confidence? ^5 You are saying, ‘I have a strategy and the power to wage war,’ but these are empty words. In whom have you put trust, so that you dare to rebel against me? ^6 Look! You trust in the support of this crushed reed, Egypt, which if a man should lean on it would enter into his palm and pierce it. That is the way Pharʹaoh king of Egypt is to all those who trust in him. ^7 And if you should say to me, ‘We trust in Jehovah our God,’ is he not the one whose high places and altars Hez·e·kiʹah has removed, while he says to Judah and Jerusalem, ‘You should bow down before this altar’?”’ ^8 So now make this wager, please, with my lord the king of As·syrʹi·a: I will give you 2,000 horses if you are able to find enough riders for them. ^9 How, then, could you drive back even one governor who is the least of my lord’s servants, while you put your trust in Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? ^10 Now is it without authorization from Jehovah that I have come up against this land to destroy it? Jehovah himself said to me, ‘Go up against this land and destroy it.’”

^11 At this E·liʹa·kim and Shebʹna and Joʹah said to the Rabʹsha·keh: “Speak to your servants, please, in the Ar·a·maʹic[*] language, for we can understand it; do not speak to us in the language of the Jews in the hearing of the people on the wall.” ^12 But the Rabʹsha·keh said: “Is it just to your lord and to you that my lord sent me to speak these words? Is it not also to the men who sit on the wall, those who will eat their own excrement and drink their own urine along with you?”

^13 Then the Rabʹsha·keh stood and called out loudly in the language of the Jews, saying: “Hear the word of the great king, the king of As·syrʹi·a. ^14 This is what the king says, ‘Do not let Hez·e·kiʹah deceive you, for he is not able to rescue you. ^15 And do not let Hez·e·kiʹah cause you to trust in Jehovah by saying: “Jehovah will surely rescue us, and this city will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a.” ^16 Do not listen to Hez·e·kiʹah, for this is what the king of As·syrʹi·a says: “Make peace with me and surrender,[*] and each of you will eat from his own vine and from his own fig tree and will drink the water of his own cistern, ^17 until I come and take you to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards. ^18 Do not let Hez·e·kiʹah mislead you by saying, ‘Jehovah will rescue us.’ Have any of the gods of the nations rescued their land out of the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a? ^19 Where are the gods of Haʹmath and Arʹpad? Where are the gods of Seph·ar·vaʹim? And have they rescued Sa·marʹi·a out of my hand? ^20 Who among all the gods of these lands have rescued their land out of my hand, so that Jehovah should rescue Jerusalem out of my hand?”’”

^21 But they kept silent and did not say a word to him in reply, for the order of the king was, “You must not answer him.” ^22 But E·liʹa·kim son of Hil·kiʹah, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹna the secretary, and Joʹah son of Aʹsaph the recorder came to Hez·e·kiʹah with their garments ripped apart and told him the words of the Rabʹsha·keh.

^ Isa. 36:2 Or “the chief cupbearer.”

^ Isa. 36:3 Or “palace.”

^ Isa. 36:11 Or “Syrian.”

^ Isa. 36:16 Lit., “Make with me a blessing and come out to me.”

^ Isa. 36:22 Or “palace.”

Isaiah  37 : 1 - 38

37 As soon as King Hez·e·kiʹah heard this, he ripped his garments apart and covered himself with sackcloth and went into the house of Jehovah. ^2 Then he sent E·liʹa·kim, who was in charge of the household,[*] Shebʹna the secretary, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to the prophet Isaiah, the son of Aʹmoz. ^3 They said to him: “This is what Hez·e·kiʹah says, ‘This day is a day of distress, of rebuke,[*] and of disgrace; for the children are ready to be born,[*] but there is no strength to give birth. ^4 Perhaps Jehovah your God will hear the words of the Rabʹsha·keh, whom the king of As·syrʹi·a his lord sent to taunt the living God, and he will call him to account for the words that Jehovah your God has heard. So offer up a prayer in behalf of the remnant who have survived.’”

^5 So the servants of King Hez·e·kiʹah went in to Isaiah, ^6 and Isaiah said to them: “This is what you should say to your lord, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Do not be afraid because of the words that you heard, the words with which the attendants of the king of As·syrʹi·a blasphemed me. ^7 Here I am putting a thought in his mind,[*] and he will hear a report and return to his own land; and I will make him fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

^8 After the Rabʹsha·keh heard that the king of As·syrʹi·a had pulled away from Laʹchish, he returned to him and found him fighting against Libʹnah. ^9 Now the king heard it said about King Tir·haʹkah of E·thi·oʹpi·a: “He has come out to fight against you.” When he heard this, he sent messengers again to Hez·e·kiʹah, saying: ^10 “This is what you should say to King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah, ‘Do not let your God in whom you trust deceive you by saying: “Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a.” ^11 Look! You have heard what the kings of As·syrʹi·a did to all the lands by devoting them to destruction. Will you alone be rescued? ^12 Did the gods of the nations that my forefathers destroyed rescue them? Where are Goʹzan, Haʹran, Reʹzeph, and the people of Eʹden who were in Tel-asʹsar? ^13 Where is the king of Haʹmath, the king of Arʹpad, and the king of the cities of Seph·ar·vaʹim, and of Heʹna, and of Ivʹvah?’”

^14 Hez·e·kiʹah took the letters out of the hand of the messengers and read them. Hez·e·kiʹah then went up to the house of Jehovah and spread them[*] out before Jehovah. ^15 And Hez·e·kiʹah began to pray to Jehovah and say: ^16 “O Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, sitting enthroned above[*] the cherubs, you alone are the true God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You made the heavens and the earth. ^17 Incline your ear, O Jehovah, and hear! Open your eyes, O Jehovah, and see! Hear all the words that Sen·nachʹer·ib has sent to taunt the living God. ^18 It is a fact, O Jehovah, that the kings of As·syrʹi·a have devastated all the lands, as well as their own land. ^19 And they have thrown their gods into the fire, because they were not gods but the work of human hands, wood and stone. That is why they could destroy them. ^20 But now, O Jehovah our God, save us out of his hand, so that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you alone are God, O Jehovah.”

^21 Isaiah son of Aʹmoz then sent this message to Hez·e·kiʹah: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Because you prayed to me concerning King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a, ^22 this is the word that Jehovah has spoken against him:

“The virgin daughter of Zion despises you, she scoffs at you.

The daughter of Jerusalem shakes her head at you.

^23 Whom have you taunted and blasphemed?

Against whom have you raised your voice

And lifted your arrogant eyes?

It is against the Holy One of Israel!

^24 Through your servants you have taunted Jehovah and said,

‘With the multitude of my war chariots

I will ascend the heights of mountains,

The remotest parts of Lebʹa·non.

I will cut down its lofty cedars, its choice juniper trees.

I will enter its highest retreats, its densest forests.

^25 I will dig wells and drink waters;

I will dry up the streams[*] of Egypt with the soles of my feet.’

^26 Have you not heard? From long ago it was determined.[*]

From days gone by I have prepared[*] it.

Now I will bring it about.

You will turn fortified cities into desolate piles of ruins.

^27 Their inhabitants will be helpless;

They will be terrified and put to shame.

They will become as vegetation of the field and green grass,

As grass of the roofs that is scorched by the east wind.

^28 But I well know when you sit, when you go out, when you come in,

And when you are enraged against me,

^29 Because your rage against me and your roaring have reached my ears.

So I will put my hook in your nose and my bridle between your lips,

And I will lead you back the way you came.”

^30 “‘And this will be the sign for you:[*] This year you will eat what grows on its own;[*] and in the second year, you will eat grain that sprouts from that; but in the third year you will sow seed and reap, and you will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. ^31 Those of the house of Judah who escape, those who are left, will take root downward and produce fruit upward. ^32 For a remnant will go out of Jerusalem and survivors from Mount Zion. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

^33 “‘Therefore this is what Jehovah says about the king of As·syrʹi·a:

“He will not come into this city

Or shoot an arrow there

Or confront it with a shield

Or cast up a siege rampart against it.”’

^34 ‘By the way he came he will return;

He will not come into this city,’ declares Jehovah.

^35 ‘I will defend this city and save it for my own sake

And for the sake of my servant David.’”

^36 And the angel of Jehovah went out and struck down 185,000 men in the camp of the As·syrʹi·ans. When people rose up early in the morning, they saw all the dead bodies. ^37 So King Sen·nachʹer·ib of As·syrʹi·a departed and returned to Ninʹe·veh and stayed there. ^38 And as he was bowing down at the house[*] of his god Nisʹroch, his own sons A·dramʹme·lech and Shar·eʹzer struck him down with the sword and then escaped to the land of Arʹa·rat. And his son Eʹsar-hadʹdon became king in his place.

^ Isa. 37:2 Or “palace.”

^ Isa. 37:3 Or “insult.”

^ Isa. 37:3 Lit., “have come to the opening of the womb.”

^ Isa. 37:7 Lit., “a spirit in him.”

^ Isa. 37:14 Lit., “it.”

^ Isa. 37:16 Or possibly, “between.”

^ Isa. 37:25 Or “the Nile canals.”

^ Isa. 37:26 Lit., “done.”

^ Isa. 37:26 Or “formed.”

^ Isa. 37:30 That is, Hezekiah.

^ Isa. 37:30 Or “the growth from spilled kernels of grain.”

^ Isa. 37:38 Or “temple.”

Jeremiah  7 : 1 - 34

7 This is the word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: ^2 “Stand in the gate of the house of Jehovah and proclaim there this message, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, all you people of Judah who enter these gates to bow down to Jehovah. ^3 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “Reform your ways and your actions, and I will allow you to keep residing in this place. ^4 Do not put your trust in deceptive words and say, ‘This is[*] the temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah!’ ^5 For if you truly reform your ways and actions; if you truly uphold justice between a man and his neighbor; ^6 if you do not oppress foreign residents, orphans,[*] and widows; if you do not shed innocent blood in this place; and if you do not follow other gods to your own harm; ^7 then I will allow you to keep residing in this place, in the land I gave to your forefathers for all time.”’”[*]

^8 “But you are putting your trust in deceptive words—it will bring absolutely no benefit. ^9 Can you steal, murder, commit adultery, swear falsely, make sacrifices[*] to Baʹal, and follow after gods you had not known, ^10 and then come and stand before me in this house that bears my name and say, ‘We will be saved,’ despite your doing all these detestable things? ^11 Has this house that bears my name become a cave of robbers in your eyes? Here I have seen it for myself,” declares Jehovah.

^12 “‘However, go now to my place in Shiʹloh, where I first caused my name to reside, and see what I did to it because of the badness of my people Israel. ^13 But you kept doing all these things,’ declares Jehovah, ‘and even though I spoke to you again and again,[*] you did not listen. I kept calling you, but you would not answer. ^14 So I will do to the house that bears my name, in which you are trusting, and to this place that I gave to you and your forefathers, just as I did to Shiʹloh. ^15 I will throw you out of my sight, just as I threw out all your brothers, all the descendants of Eʹphra·im.’

^16 “As for you, do not pray in behalf of this people. Do not cry out or offer a prayer or plead with me in their behalf, for I will not listen to you. ^17 Do you not see what they are doing in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem? ^18 The sons are gathering wood, the fathers are lighting the fire, and the wives are kneading dough in order to make sacrificial cakes to the Queen of Heaven,[*] and they are pouring out drink offerings to other gods to offend me. ^19 ‘But am I the one they are hurting?’[*] declares Jehovah. ‘Is it not they themselves, to their own shame?’ ^20 Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says, ‘Look! My anger and my wrath will be poured out on this place, on man and beast, on the trees of the field and the fruitage of the ground; it will burn and will not be extinguished.’

^21 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Go ahead, add your whole burnt offerings to your other sacrifices, and eat the flesh yourselves. ^22 For on the day I brought your forefathers out of the land of Egypt, I did not speak with them or command them concerning whole burnt offerings and sacrifices. ^23 But I did give them this command: “Obey my voice, and I will become your God, and you will become my people. You must walk in all the way that I command, so that it may go well with you.”’ ^24 But they did not listen or incline their ear; instead, they walked in their own schemes,[*] stubbornly following their wicked heart, and they went backward, not forward, ^25 from the day your forefathers came out of the land of Egypt until this day. So I kept sending all my servants the prophets to you, sending them each day, again and again.[*] ^26 But they refused to listen to me, and they did not incline their ear. Instead, they were stubborn,[*] and they acted worse than their forefathers!

^27 “You will speak all these words to them, but they will not listen to you; you will call to them, but they will not answer you. ^28 And you will say to them, ‘This is the nation that did not obey the voice of Jehovah their God and refused to accept discipline. Faithfulness has perished and is not even mentioned among them.’[*]

^29 “Shear off your uncut[*] hair and throw it away, and on the bare hills raise a dirge,[*] for Jehovah has rejected and will abandon this generation that has infuriated him. ^30 ‘For the people of Judah have done what is bad in my eyes,’ declares Jehovah. ‘They have set up their disgusting idols in the house that bears my name, in order to defile it. ^31 They have built the high places of Toʹpheth, which is in the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom,[*] in order to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire, something that I had not commanded and that had never even come into my heart.’[*]

^32 “‘Therefore look! the days are coming,’ declares Jehovah, ‘when it will no longer be called Toʹpheth or the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom[*] but the Valley of the Slaughter. They will bury in Toʹpheth until there is no place left. ^33 And the dead bodies of this people will become food for the birds of the heavens and for the beasts of the earth, with no one to frighten them away. ^34 I will put an end to the sound of exultation and the sound of rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem, for the land will be reduced to ruins.’”

^ Jer. 7:4 Lit., “They are,” referring to all the buildings of the temple complex.

^ Jer. 7:6 Or “fatherless children.”

^ Jer. 7:7 Or “from eternity to eternity.”

^ Jer. 7:9 Or “sacrificial smoke.”

^ Jer. 7:13 Lit., “rising up early and speaking.”

^ Jer. 7:18 The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites; possibly a fertility goddess.

^ Jer. 7:19 Or “offending; provoking.”

^ Jer. 7:24 Or “advice.”

^ Jer. 7:25 Lit., “daily rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 7:26 Lit., “they hardened their neck.”

^ Jer. 7:28 Lit., “is cut off from their mouth.”

^ Jer. 7:29 Or “dedicated.”

^ Jer. 7:29 Or “song of mourning.”

^ Jer. 7:31 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

^ Jer. 7:31 Or “had never entered my thoughts.”

^ Jer. 7:32 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

Jeremiah  11 : 1 - 23

11 This is the word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: ^2 “Hear the words of this covenant, you people!

“Speak[*] them to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem ^3 and say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “Cursed is the man who does not obey the words of this covenant, ^4 which I commanded your forefathers on the day I brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of the iron-smelting furnace, saying, ‘Obey my voice, and do all the things that I command you; and you will become my people and I will be your God, ^5 so that I may fulfill the oath that I swore to your forefathers, to give them the land flowing with milk and honey, as it is this day.’”’”

And I answered: “Amen,[*] O Jehovah.”

^6 Jehovah then said to me: “Proclaim all these words in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem: ‘Hear the words of this covenant, and carry them out. ^7 For I solemnly admonished your forefathers in the day I brought them out of the land of Egypt and to this day, admonishing them again and again:[*] “Obey my voice.” ^8 But they did not listen or incline their ear; instead, each kept stubbornly following his own wicked heart. So I brought on them all the words of this covenant that I commanded them to do and that they refused to carry out.’”

^9 Jehovah then said to me: “There is a conspiracy among the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^10 They have returned to the errors of their forefathers of old, who refused to obey my words. They too have followed other gods and have served them. The house of Israel and the house of Judah have broken my covenant that I made with their forefathers. ^11 Therefore this is what Jehovah says, ‘Here I am bringing on them a calamity that they will not be able to escape. When they call to me for help, I will not listen to them. ^12 Then the cities of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem will go to the gods to which they are making sacrifices[*] and call for help, but these will by no means save them in the time of their calamity. ^13 For your gods have become as many as your cities, O Judah, and you have set up as many altars to the shameful thing[*] as there are streets in Jerusalem, altars to make sacrifices to Baʹal.’

^14 “As for you,[*] do not pray in behalf of this people. Do not cry out in their behalf or offer a prayer for them, for I will not be listening when they call out to me because of their calamity.

^15 What right does my beloved one have to be in my house

When so many have carried out evil schemes?

With holy flesh[*] will they avert the calamity when it comes upon you?

Will you exult at that time?

^16 Jehovah once called you a thriving olive tree,

Beautiful with fine fruit.

With a great roaring sound, he has set her on fire,

And they have broken its branches.

^17 “Jehovah of armies, your Planter, has declared that a calamity will come upon you because of the evil committed by the house of Israel and the house of Judah, who have offended me by making sacrifices to Baʹal.”

^18 Jehovah informed me so that I would know;

At that time you caused me to see what they were doing.

^19 I was like a docile lamb being brought to the slaughter.

I did not know that they were scheming against me:

“Let us destroy the tree with its fruit,

And let us cut him off from the land of the living,

So that his name may be remembered no more.”

^20 But Jehovah of armies judges with righteousness;

He examines the innermost thoughts[*] and the heart.

Let me see your vengeance on them,

For to you I have committed my legal case.

^21 Therefore this is what Jehovah says against the men of Anʹa·thoth who are seeking to take your life[*] and who say: “You must not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, or you will die by our hand”; ^22 therefore this is what Jehovah of armies says: “Here I am going to call them to account. The young men will die by the sword, and their sons and their daughters will die by famine. ^23 Not even a remnant will be left of them, because I will bring calamity on the men of Anʹa·thoth in the year of their being called to account.”

^ Jer. 11:2 Apparently addressed to Jeremiah.

^ Jer. 11:5 Or “So be it.”

^ Jer. 11:7 Lit., “rising up early and admonishing.”

^ Jer. 11:12 Or “sacrificial smoke.”

^ Jer. 11:13 Or “the shameful god.”

^ Jer. 11:14 That is, Jeremiah.

^ Jer. 11:15 That is, sacrifices made in the temple.

^ Jer. 11:20 Or “deepest emotions.” Lit., “kidneys.”

^ Jer. 11:21 Or “seeking your soul.”

Jeremiah  13 : 1 - 27

13 This is what Jehovah told me: “Go and buy a linen belt for yourself and put it around your waist, but do not dip it in water.” ^2 So I bought the belt according to the word of Jehovah and put it around my waist. ^3 And the word of Jehovah came to me a second time: ^4 “Take the belt that you bought and are wearing and get up, go to the Eu·phraʹtes, and hide it there in a cleft of the crag.” ^5 So I went and hid it by the Eu·phraʹtes, just as Jehovah had commanded me.

^6 But many days later Jehovah said to me: “Get up, go to the Eu·phraʹtes, and take from there the belt that I commanded you to hide there.” ^7 So I went to the Eu·phraʹtes and dug up the belt and took it from the place where I had hidden it, and I saw that the belt had been ruined; it was completely useless.

^8 Then the word of Jehovah came to me: ^9 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘In the same way I will destroy the pride of Judah and the immense pride of Jerusalem. ^10 These evil people who refuse to obey my words, who stubbornly follow their own heart, and who are following other gods, serving and bowing down to them, will become just like this belt that is completely useless.’ ^11 ‘For just as a belt clings to the waist of a man, so I made the whole house of Israel and the whole house of Judah cling to me,’ declares Jehovah, ‘to become to me a people, a name, a praise, and something beautiful. But they did not obey.’

^12 “And you must also give this message to them, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: “Every large jar should be filled with wine.”’ And they will reply to you, ‘Do we not already know that every large jar should be filled with wine?’ ^13 Then say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “Here I am filling with drunkenness all the inhabitants of this land, the kings sitting on the throne of David, the priests and the prophets, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^14 And I will smash them against each other, fathers and sons alike,” declares Jehovah. “I will not show compassion or feel any sorrow or have any mercy on them; nothing will stop me from bringing them to ruin.”’

^15 Hear and pay attention.

Do not be haughty, for Jehovah has spoken.

^16 Give glory to Jehovah your God

Before he brings darkness

And before your feet stumble on the mountains at dusk.

You will hope for the light,

But he will bring deep shadow;

He will turn it into thick gloom.

^17 And if you refuse to listen,

I[*] will weep in secret because of your pride.

I will shed many tears, and my eyes will stream with tears,

Because the flock of Jehovah has been carried away captive.

^18 Tell the king and the queen mother,[*] ‘Sit in a lower place,

For your beautiful crown will fall from your head.’

^19 The cities of the south are shut,[*] with no one to open them.

All of Judah has been taken into exile, taken completely into exile.

^20 Raise your eyes and see those coming from the north.

Where is the flock you were given, your beautiful sheep?

^21 What will you say when your punishment comes

From your close friends whom you cultivated from the start?

Will not birth pains seize you, like those of a woman giving birth?

^22 And when you say in your heart, ‘Why have these things befallen me?’

It is because of your great error that your skirts have been stripped off

And your heels have been treated violently.

^23 Can a Cushʹite[*] change his skin, or a leopard its spots?

If so, then you can do good,

You who are trained to do bad.

^24 So I will scatter them like straw blown by the desert wind.

^25 This is your lot, the portion that I have measured out to you,” declares Jehovah,

“Because you have forgotten me and you trust in lies.

^26 Therefore, I will lift up your skirts over your face,

And your shame will be seen,

^27 Your acts of adultery and your lustful neighing,

Your obscene[*] prostitution.

On the hills, in the field,

I have seen your disgusting behavior.

Woe to you, O Jerusalem!

How much longer will you remain unclean?”

^ Jer. 13:17 Or “My soul.”

^ Jer. 13:18 Or “the lady.”

^ Jer. 13:19 Or “besieged.”

^ Jer. 13:23 Or “an Ethiopian.”

^ Jer. 13:27 Or “shameful.”

Jeremiah  14 : 1 - 22

14 This is the word of Jehovah that came to Jeremiah concerning the droughts:

 ^2 Judah mourns, and its gates have faded away.

They sink to the ground dejected,

And a cry goes up from Jerusalem.

 ^3 And their masters send their servants[*] for water.

They go to the water holes[*] and find no water.

They return with their vessels empty.

They are ashamed and disappointed,

And they cover their heads.

 ^4 Because the ground is cracked,

For there is no rain on the land,

The farmers are dismayed and cover their heads.

 ^5 Even the doe in the field forsakes her newborn

Because there is no grass.

 ^6 The wild donkeys stand on the bare hills.

They pant for air like jackals;

Their eyes fail because there is no vegetation.

 ^7 Although our own errors testify against us,

O Jehovah, act for the sake of your name.

For our acts of unfaithfulness are many,

And it is against you that we have sinned.

 ^8 O hope of Israel, his Savior in times of distress,

Why are you like a stranger in the land,

Like a traveler who stops only to spend the night?

 ^9 Why are you like a man who is stunned,

Like a mighty man who cannot save?

For you are among us, O Jehovah,

And your name has been called on us.

Do not abandon us.

^10 This is what Jehovah says concerning this people: “They love to wander about; they have not restrained their feet. So Jehovah finds no pleasure in them. Now he will remember their error and call them to account for their sins.”

^11 Then Jehovah said to me: “Do not pray for good to come to this people. ^12 When they fast, I do not listen to their entreaties, and when they offer whole burnt offerings and grain offerings, I take no pleasure in them, for by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence,[*] I will do away with them.”

^13 At this I said: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Here the prophets are saying to them, ‘You will not see the sword, and famine will not come upon you, but I will give you true peace in this place.’”

^14 Jehovah then said to me: “The prophets are prophesying lies in my name. I have not sent them or commanded them or spoken to them. A lying vision and a worthless divination and the deceit of their own heart is what they are prophesying to you. ^15 Therefore this is what Jehovah says concerning the prophets who are prophesying in my name, though I did not send them, and who say that no sword or famine will occur in this land: ‘By sword and by famine those prophets will perish. ^16 And the people to whom they are prophesying will be cast out into the streets of Jerusalem because of the famine and the sword, with no one to bury them—them, their wives, their sons, or their daughters—for I will pour out on them the calamity they deserve.’

^17 “You must speak this word to them,

‘Let my eyes stream with tears night and day, let them not cease,

For the virgin daughter of my people has been completely crushed and broken,

With an extremely severe wound.

^18 If I go out into the field and look,

I see those slain by the sword!

And if I come into the city,

I see the diseases from the famine!

For both the prophet and the priest have gone around in a land that they do not know.’”

^19 Have you completely rejected Judah, or have you[*] abhorred Zion?

Why have you struck us, so that there is no healing for us?

There was a hope for peace, but nothing good came,

For a time of healing, but there is terror!

^20 We acknowledge our wickedness, O Jehovah,

And the error of our forefathers,

For we have sinned against you.

^21 For the sake of your name, do not reject us;

Do not despise your glorious throne.

Remember, and do not break your covenant with us.

^22 Can any of the worthless idols of the nations give rain,

Or can even the heavens send showers of rain on their own?

Are you not the only One, O Jehovah our God?

And we hope in you,

For you alone have done all these things.

^ Jer. 14:3 Or “their small ones.”

^ Jer. 14:3 Or “the ditches; the cisterns.”

^ Jer. 14:12 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 14:19 Or “has your soul.”

Jeremiah  16 : 1 - 21

16 The word of Jehovah again came to me, saying: ^2 “You must not take a wife for yourself, and you must not have sons and daughters in this place. ^3 For this is what Jehovah says concerning the sons and daughters who are born here and concerning their mothers who give birth to them and concerning their fathers who cause their birth in this land: ^4 ‘They will die of deadly diseases, but no one will mourn them or bury them; they will become like manure on the surface of the ground. They will perish by the sword and by famine, and their dead bodies will be food for the birds of the heavens and for the beasts of the earth.’

 ^5 For this is what Jehovah says,

‘Do not enter a house where a mourners’ feast is held,

And do not go to wail or offer sympathy.’

‘For I have taken away my peace from this people,’ declares Jehovah,

‘As well as my loyal love and mercy.

 ^6 Both the great and the small will die in this land.

They will not be buried,

No one will mourn them,

Nor will anyone cut himself or make himself bald for them.[*]

 ^7 And no one will provide food for those in mourning,

To comfort them over their dead;

Nor will anyone give them the cup of consolation

To drink over the loss of their father or mother.

 ^8 And do not enter a house of feasting

To sit down with them to eat and drink.’

^9 “For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Here in this place, in your days and before your very eyes, I will put an end to the sounds of exultation and rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride.’

^10 “When you tell this people all these words, they will ask you, ‘Why has Jehovah spoken of all this great calamity against us? What error and what sin have we committed against Jehovah our God?’ ^11 You must reply to them, ‘“Because your forefathers abandoned me,” declares Jehovah, “and they kept following other gods and serving them and bowing down to them. But me they abandoned, and my law they did not keep. ^12 And you have behaved far worse than your forefathers, and each one of you follows the stubbornness of his wicked heart instead of obeying me. ^13 So I will hurl you out of this land into a land that neither you nor your forefathers have known, and there you will have to serve other gods day and night, because I will show you no favor.”’

^14 “‘However, the days are coming,’ declares Jehovah, ‘when they will no longer say: “As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought the people of Israel out of the land of Egypt!” ^15 but rather: “As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought the people of Israel from the land of the north and from all the lands to which he had dispersed them!” and I will bring them back to their land, which I gave to their forefathers.’

^16 ‘Here I am sending for many fishermen,’ declares Jehovah,

‘And they will fish for them.

After that I will send for many hunters,

And they will hunt them down on every mountain and every hill

And out of the clefts of the crags.

^17 For my eyes are on everything they do.[*]

They have not been hidden from before me,

Nor has their error been hidden from my eyes.

^18 First, I will repay the full amount due for their error and their sin,

For they have profaned my land with the lifeless figures[*] of their disgusting idols

And have filled my inheritance with their detestable things.’”

^19 O Jehovah, my strength and my stronghold,

My place to flee in the day of distress,

To you the nations will come from the ends of the earth,

And they will say: “Our forefathers inherited utter falsehood,

Futility and useless things of no benefit.”

^20 Can a man make gods for himself

When they are not really gods?

^21 “So I will make them know,

At this time I will make them know my power and my might,

And they will have to know that my name is Jehovah.”

^ Jer. 16:6 Pagan mourning customs apparently practiced in apostate Israel.

^ Jer. 16:17 Lit., “on all their ways.”

^ Jer. 16:18 Lit., “the corpses.”

Jeremiah  19 : 1 - 15

19 This is what Jehovah said: “Go and buy an earthenware flask from a potter. Take some of the elders of the people and some of the elders of the priests, ^2 and go out to the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom, at the entrance of the Gate of the Potsherds. And there proclaim the words that I speak to you. ^3 You will say, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, you kings of Judah and inhabitants of Jerusalem. This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says:

“‘“I am about to bring a calamity on this place, and the ears of anyone who hears about it will tingle. ^4 It is because they abandoned me and made this place unrecognizable. In it they are sacrificing to other gods, whom they and their forefathers and the kings of Judah had not known, and they have filled this place with the blood of the innocent ones. ^5 They built the high places of Baʹal in order to burn their sons in the fire as whole burnt offerings to Baʹal, something that I had not commanded or spoken of and that had never even come into my heart.”’[*]

^6 “‘“Therefore look! the days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when this place will no longer be called Toʹpheth or the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom but the Valley of the Slaughter. ^7 I will thwart the plans of Judah and Jerusalem in this place, and I will make them fall by the sword before their enemies and by the hand of those seeking to take their life.[*] And I will give their dead bodies as food to the birds of the heavens and to the beasts of the earth. ^8 And I will make this city an object of horror and something to whistle at. Every last one passing by it will stare in horror and whistle over all its plagues. ^9 And I will make them eat the flesh of their sons and daughters, and they will each eat the flesh of his fellow man, because of the siege and their desperation when they are hemmed in by their enemies and those seeking to take their life.”’[*]

^10 “Then break the flask before the eyes of the men who go with you, ^11 and say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “This is how I will break this people and this city, like someone who breaks a potter’s vessel so that it can never be repaired; and they will bury the dead in Toʹpheth until there is no more room to bury them.”’

^12 “‘That is what I will do to this place,’ declares Jehovah, ‘and to its inhabitants, to make this city like Toʹpheth. ^13 And the houses of Jerusalem and the houses of the kings of Judah will become unclean like this place, Toʹpheth, yes, all the houses on whose roofs they offered sacrifices to all the army of the heavens and where they poured out drink offerings to other gods.’”

^14 When Jeremiah returned from Toʹpheth where Jehovah sent him to prophesy, he stood in the courtyard of the house of Jehovah and said to all the people: ^15 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Here I am bringing on this city and on all its towns all the calamity that I have spoken against it, because they stubbornly refused[*] to obey my words.’”

^ Jer. 19:5 Or “had never entered my thoughts.”

^ Jer. 19:7 Or “seeking their soul.”

^ Jer. 19:9 Or “seeking their soul.”

^ Jer. 19:15 Lit., “hardened their neck so as not.”

Jeremiah  20 : 1 - 18

20 Now Pashʹhur the son of Imʹmer, the priest, who was also the leading commissioner in the house of Jehovah, was listening when Jeremiah prophesied these things. ^2 Then Pashʹhur struck Jeremiah the prophet and put him in the stocks that were at the Upper Gate of Benjamin, which was in the house of Jehovah. ^3 But on the following day when Pashʹhur released Jeremiah from the stocks, Jeremiah said to him:

“Jehovah has named you, not Pashʹhur, but Terror All Around. ^4 For this is what Jehovah says, ‘I will make you an object of terror to yourself and to all your friends, and they will fall by the sword of their enemies while your eyes are looking on; and I will give all Judah into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will take them into exile in Babylon and put them to death by the sword. ^5 And I will give all the wealth of this city, all its resources, all its precious things, and all the treasures of the kings of Judah into the hand of their enemies. And they will plunder them and seize them and take them to Babylon. ^6 And as for you, Pashʹhur, and all who live in your house, you will go into captivity. You will go off to Babylon and die there, and you will be buried there with all your friends, because you have prophesied lies to them.’”

 ^7 You have fooled me, O Jehovah, and I was fooled.

You used your strength against me, and you prevailed.

I have become a laughingstock all day long;

Everyone ridicules me.

 ^8 For whenever I speak, I must cry out and proclaim,

“Violence and destruction!”

For me the word of Jehovah has been the cause of insults and jeering all day long.

 ^9 So I said: “I am not going to make mention of him,

And I will speak no more in his name.”

But in my heart it became like a burning fire shut up in my bones,

And I was tired of holding it in;

I could no longer endure it.

^10 For I heard many evil rumors;

Terror surrounded me.

“Denounce him; let us denounce him!”

Every man wishing me peace was watching for my downfall:

“Perhaps he will make a foolish mistake,

And we can prevail and take our revenge against him.”

^11 But Jehovah was with me like a fearsome warrior.

That is why those persecuting me will stumble and will not prevail.

They will be put to great shame, for they will not succeed.

Their everlasting humiliation will not be forgotten.

^12 But you, O Jehovah of armies, are examining the righteous one;

You see the innermost thoughts[*] and the heart.

Let me see your vengeance on them,

For to you I have committed my legal case.

^13 Sing to Jehovah! Praise Jehovah!

For he has rescued the poor one[*] from the hand of evildoers.

^14 Cursed be the day I was born!

May the day my mother gave birth to me not be blessed!

^15 Cursed be the man who brought good news to my father, saying:

“A son has been born to you, a boy!”

Making him rejoice greatly.

^16 May that man become like cities that Jehovah overthrew without regret.

May he hear an outcry in the morning and the sound of alarm at midday.

^17 Why did he not put me to death in the womb,

So that my mother would become my burial place

And her womb would always remain pregnant?

^18 Why did I have to come out of the womb

To see trouble and grief,

To end my days in shame?

^ Jer. 20:12 Or “deepest emotions.” Lit., “kidneys.”

^ Jer. 20:13 Or “the soul of the poor one.”

Jeremiah  23 : 1 - 40

23 “Woe to the shepherds who are destroying and scattering the sheep of my pasture!” declares Jehovah.

^2 Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says against the shepherds who are shepherding my people: “You have scattered my sheep; you kept dispersing them, and you have not turned your attention to them.”

“So I will turn my attention to you because of your evil deeds,” declares Jehovah.

^3 “Then I will gather together the remnant of my sheep from all the lands to which I have dispersed them, and I will bring them back to their pasture, and they will be fruitful and become many. ^4 And I will raise up over them shepherds who will really shepherd them. They will no longer be afraid or be terrified, and none will be missing,” declares Jehovah.

^5 “Look! The days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when I will raise up to David a righteous sprout.[*] And a king will reign and show insight and uphold justice and righteousness in the land. ^6 In his days Judah will be saved, and Israel will reside in security. And this is the name by which he will be called: Jehovah Is Our Righteousness.”

^7 “However, the days are coming,” declares Jehovah, “when they will no longer say, ‘As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought the people of Israel out of the land of Egypt!’ ^8 but rather, ‘As surely as Jehovah is alive, who brought out and brought back the descendants of the house of Israel from the land of the north and from all the lands to which I had dispersed them,’ and they will dwell in their own land.”

^9 Concerning the prophets:

My heart is broken within me.

All my bones are shaking.

I am like a man who is drunk

And like a man overcome by wine,

Because of Jehovah and because of his holy words.

^10 For the land is full of adulterers;

Because of the curse the land has gone into mourning

And the pastures of the wilderness have dried up.

Their course is evil, and they abuse their power.

^11 “Both the prophet and the priest are polluted.[*]

Even in my own house I have found their wickedness,” declares Jehovah.

^12 “So their path will become slippery and dark;

They will be pushed and will fall.

For I will bring calamity on them

In the year of reckoning,” declares Jehovah.

^13 “And in the prophets of Sa·marʹi·a I have seen what is repulsive.

Their prophecies are incited by Baʹal,

And they lead my people Israel astray.

^14 And in the prophets of Jerusalem I have seen horrible things.

They commit adultery and walk in falsehood;

They encourage[*] evildoers,

And they do not turn away from their wickedness.

To me they are all like Sodʹom,

And her inhabitants are like Go·morʹrah.”

^15 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies says against the prophets:

“Here I am making them eat wormwood

And giving them poisoned water to drink.

For from the prophets of Jerusalem apostasy has spread throughout the land.”

^16 This is what Jehovah of armies says:

“Do not listen to the words of the prophets who are prophesying to you.

They are deluding you.[*]

The vision they speak is from their own heart,

Not from the mouth of Jehovah.

^17 They are saying again and again to those who disrespect me,

‘Jehovah has said: “You will enjoy peace.”’

And to everyone who follows his own stubborn heart they say,

‘No calamity will come upon you.’

^18 For who has stood in the inner circle of Jehovah

To see and hear his word?

Who has paid attention to his word in order to hear it?

^19 Look! The windstorm of Jehovah will burst out in fury;

Like a whirling tempest it will whirl down on the head of the wicked.

^20 The anger of Jehovah will not turn back

Until he has carried out and accomplished the intentions of his heart.

In the final part of the days you will clearly understand this.

^21 I did not send the prophets, yet they ran.

I did not speak to them, yet they prophesied.

^22 But if they had stood in my inner circle,

They would have made my people hear my words

And would have caused them to turn back from their bad way and their evil deeds.”

^23 “Am I only a God nearby,” declares Jehovah, “and not a God also from far away?”

^24 “Can any man hide in a concealed place where I cannot see him?” declares Jehovah.

“Do I not fill the heavens and the earth?” declares Jehovah.

^25 “I have heard the prophets who are prophesying lies in my name say, ‘I had a dream! I had a dream!’ ^26 How long will this continue in the heart of the prophets, to prophesy lies? They are prophets of the deceit of their own heart. ^27 They intend to make my people forget my name by the dreams they relate to one another, just as their fathers forgot my name because of Baʹal. ^28 Let the prophet who has a dream relate the dream, but the one who has my word should speak my word truthfully.”

“What does the straw have in common with the grain?” declares Jehovah.

^29 “Is not my word just like a fire,” declares Jehovah, “and like a forge hammer that smashes the crag?”

^30 “So here I am against the prophets,” declares Jehovah, “who steal my words from one another.”

^31 “Here I am against the prophets,” declares Jehovah, “those who use their tongue to say, ‘He declares!’”

^32 “Here I am against the prophets of lying dreams,” declares Jehovah, “who relate them and lead my people astray because of their lies and their boasting.”

“But I did not send them or command them. So they will not benefit this people at all,” declares Jehovah.

^33 “And when this people or a prophet or a priest asks you, ‘What is the burden[*] of Jehovah?’ you should reply to them, ‘“You people are the burden! And I will cast you off,” declares Jehovah.’ ^34 As for the prophet or the priest or the people who say, ‘This is the burden[*] of Jehovah!’ I will turn my attention on that man and on his household. ^35 This is what each of you is saying to his fellow and to his brother, ‘What has Jehovah answered? And what has Jehovah spoken?’ ^36 But the burden[*] of Jehovah you should mention no more, for the burden[*] is each one’s own word, and you have changed the words of the living God, Jehovah of armies, our God.

^37 “This is what you will say to the prophet, ‘What answer has Jehovah given you? And what has Jehovah spoken? ^38 And if you keep saying, “The burden[*] of Jehovah!” this is what Jehovah says: “Because of your saying, ‘This word is the burden[*] of Jehovah,’ after I told you, ‘You must not say: “The burden[*] of Jehovah!”’ ^39 look! I will lift you up and throw you away from my presence, both you and the city that I gave to you and your forefathers. ^40 And I will bring on you everlasting disgrace and everlasting humiliation, which will not be forgotten.”’”

^ Jer. 23:5 Or “heir.”

^ Jer. 23:11 Or “apostate.”

^ Jer. 23:14 Lit., “strengthen the hands of.”

^ Jer. 23:16 Or “They are filling you with empty hopes.”

^ Jer. 23:33 Or “burdensome message.” The Hebrew word has a double meaning: “a weighty divine pronouncement” or “something burdensome.”

^ Jer. 23:34 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:36 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:36 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

^ Jer. 23:38 Or “burdensome message.”

Jeremiah  24 : 1 - 10

24 Then Jehovah showed me two baskets of figs set before the temple of Jehovah, after King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon had carried into exile Jec·o·niʹah[*] son of Je·hoiʹa·kim, the king of Judah, along with the princes of Judah, the craftsmen, and the metalworkers;[*] he took them from Jerusalem to Babylon. ^2 One basket had very good figs, like early figs, but the other basket had very bad figs, so bad that they could not be eaten.

^3 Jehovah then asked me: “What do you see, Jeremiah?” So I said: “Figs; the good figs are very good, but the bad ones are very bad, so bad that they cannot be eaten.”

^4 Then the word of Jehovah came to me, saying: ^5 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Like these good figs, so I will regard in a good way the exiles of Judah, whom I have sent away from this place to the land of the Chal·deʹans. ^6 I will keep my eye on them for their good, and I will cause them to return to this land. I will build them up, and I will not tear down; I will plant them, and I will not uproot. ^7 And I will give them a heart to know me, that I am Jehovah. They will become my people, and I will become their God, for they will return to me with all their heart.

^8 “‘But concerning the bad figs that are so bad they cannot be eaten, this is what Jehovah says: “So I will regard King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah, his princes, the remnant of Jerusalem who are left in this land, and those who are dwelling in the land of Egypt. ^9 I will make them an object of horror and calamity to all the kingdoms of the earth, a reproach, a proverbial saying, a cause for ridicule, and a curse in all the places to which I disperse them. ^10 And I will send against them the sword, the famine, and the pestilence,[*] until they have perished from the land that I gave to them and to their forefathers.”’”

^ Jer. 24:1 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 24:1 Also called Jehoiachin and Coniah.

^ Jer. 24:1 Or possibly, “builders of bulwarks.”

^ Jer. 24:10 Or “disease.”

Jeremiah  25 : 1 - 38

25 The word that came to Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah in the fourth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, which was the first year of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon. ^2 This is what Jeremiah the prophet spoke concerning[*] all the people of Judah and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem:

^3 “From the 13th year of Jo·siʹah son of Aʹmon, the king of Judah, to this day, these 23 years, the word of Jehovah has come to me, and I kept speaking to you again and again,[*] but you would not listen. ^4 And Jehovah sent all his servants the prophets to you, sending them again and again,[*] but you would not listen or incline your ear to hear. ^5 They would say, ‘Turn back, please, each of you from your evil ways and your evil deeds; then you will continue dwelling for a long time to come in the land that Jehovah long ago gave to you and to your forefathers. ^6 Do not follow other gods and serve them and bow down to them, offending me with the work of your hands; otherwise I will bring calamity on you.’

^7 “‘But you would not listen to me,’ declares Jehovah. ‘Instead you offended me with the work of your hands, to your own calamity.’

^8 “Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘“Because you would not obey my words, ^9 I am sending for all the families of the north,” declares Jehovah, “sending for King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon, my servant, and I will bring them against this land and against its inhabitants and against all these surrounding nations. I will devote them to destruction and make them an object of horror and something to whistle at and a perpetual ruin. ^10 I will put an end to the sound of exultation and the sound of rejoicing from them, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the sound of the hand mill and the light of the lamp. ^11 And all this land will be reduced to ruins and will become an object of horror, and these nations will have to serve the king of Babylon for 70 years.”’

^12 “‘But when 70 years have been fulfilled, I will call to account[*] the king of Babylon and that nation for their error,’ declares Jehovah, ‘and I will make the land of the Chal·deʹans a desolate wasteland for all time. ^13 I will bring on that land all my words that I have spoken against it, all that is written in this book that Jeremiah has prophesied against all the nations. ^14 For many nations and great kings will make slaves of them, and I will repay them according to their deeds and the work of their own hands.’”

^15 For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel said to me: “Take this cup of the wine of wrath out of my hand, and make all the nations to whom I send you drink it. ^16 And they will drink and stagger and act like madmen because of the sword that I am sending among them.”

^17 So I took the cup out of the hand of Jehovah and made all the nations to whom Jehovah sent me drink: ^18 starting with Jerusalem and the cities of Judah, her kings and her princes, to make them a ruin, an object of horror, something to whistle at and a curse, as it is today; ^19 then Pharʹaoh king of Egypt and his servants, his princes, and all his people, ^20 and all their mixed populations; all the kings of the land of Uz; all the kings of the land of the Phi·lisʹtines, Ashʹke·lon, Gazʹa, Ekʹron, and those remaining of Ashʹdod; ^21 Eʹdom, Moʹab, and the Amʹmon·ites; ^22 all the kings of Tyre, all the kings of Siʹdon, and the kings of the island in the sea; ^23 Deʹdan, Teʹma, Buz, and all those with hair clipped at the temples; ^24 all the kings of the Arabians and all the kings of the mixed populations who reside in the wilderness; ^25 all the kings of Zimʹri, all the kings of Eʹlam, and all the kings of the Medes; ^26 and all the kings of the north near and far, one after the other, and all the other kingdoms of the earth that are on the surface of the ground; and the king of Sheʹshach[*] will drink after them.

^27 “And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “Drink and get drunk and vomit and fall so that you cannot get up because of the sword that I am sending among you.”’ ^28 And if they refuse to take the cup out of your hand to drink, say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “You must drink it! ^29 For look! if I am bringing calamity first on the city that bears my name, should you go unpunished?”’

“‘You will not go unpunished, for I am calling for a sword against all the inhabitants of the earth,’ declares Jehovah of armies.

^30 “And you are to prophesy all these words to them and say to them,

‘From on high Jehovah will roar,

And from his holy dwelling he will make his voice heard.

He will roar loudly against his abiding place.

Shouting like those treading the winepress,

He will sing triumphantly against all the inhabitants of the earth.’

^31 ‘A noise will resound to the ends of the earth,

For Jehovah has a controversy with the nations.

He will personally pass judgment on all humans.[*]

And he will put the wicked to the sword,’ declares Jehovah.

^32 This is what Jehovah of armies says:

‘Look! A calamity is spreading from nation to nation,

And a great tempest will be unleashed from the remotest parts of the earth.

^33 “‘And those slain by Jehovah in that day will be from one end of the earth clear to the other end of the earth. They will not be mourned, nor will they be gathered up or buried. They will become like manure on the surface of the ground.’

^34 Wail, you shepherds, and cry out!

Wallow about, you majestic ones of the flock,

Because the time of your slaughter and your dispersion has come,

And you will fall like a precious vessel!

^35 The shepherds have no place to flee,

And there is no escape for the majestic ones of the flock.

^36 Listen! The outcry of the shepherds

And the wailing of the majestic ones of the flock,

For Jehovah is devastating their pasture.

^37 And the peaceful dwelling places have been made lifeless

Because of the burning anger of Jehovah.

^38 He has left his lair just like a young lion,[*]

For their land has become an object of horror

Because of the cruel sword

And because of his burning anger.”

^ Jer. 25:1 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 25:2 Or “to.”

^ Jer. 25:3 Lit., “rising up early and speaking.”

^ Jer. 25:4 Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 25:9 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 25:12 Or “punish.”

^ Jer. 25:26 This appears to be a cryptographic name for Babel (Babylon).

^ Jer. 25:31 Lit., “all flesh.”

^ Jer. 25:38 Or “a maned young lion.”

Jeremiah  26 : 1 - 24

26 In the beginning of the reign of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, this word came from Jehovah: ^2 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Stand in the courtyard of the house of Jehovah and speak concerning[*] all the people of the cities of Judah who are coming in to worship[*] at the house of Jehovah. Tell them everything that I command you; do not take away a word. ^3 Perhaps they will listen and each one will turn back from his evil way, and I will change my mind concerning[*] the calamity that I intend to bring on them because of their evil deeds. ^4 Say to them: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘If you will not listen to me by following my law[*] that I have placed before you, ^5 by listening to the words of my servants the prophets, whom I am sending to you again and again,[*] whom you have not listened to, ^6 then I will make this house like Shiʹloh, and I will make this city an object of cursing to all the nations of the earth.’”’”

^7 And the priests and the prophets and all the people heard Jeremiah speaking these words in the house of Jehovah. ^8 So when Jeremiah had finished speaking all that Jehovah had commanded him to speak to all the people, then the priests and the prophets and all the people seized him and said: “You will surely die. ^9 Why have you prophesied in the name of Jehovah, saying, ‘This house will become like Shiʹloh, and this city will be devastated and left without an inhabitant’?” And all the people gathered around Jeremiah in the house of Jehovah.

^10 When the princes of Judah heard these words, they came up from the house[*] of the king to the house of Jehovah and sat down at the entrance of the new gate of Jehovah. ^11 The priests and the prophets said to the princes and to all the people: “This man deserves the death penalty, because he has prophesied against this city just as you have heard with your own ears.”

^12 Jeremiah then said to all the princes and to all the people: “It was Jehovah who sent me to prophesy against this house and against this city all the words that you have heard. ^13 So now, reform your ways and your actions and obey the voice of Jehovah your God, and Jehovah will change his mind concerning[*] the calamity that he has spoken against you. ^14 But as for me, I am in your hand. Do to me whatever seems good and right in your eyes. ^15 Only know for certain that if you put me to death, you will bring innocent blood upon yourselves and upon this city and upon her inhabitants, for in truth Jehovah sent me to you to speak all these words in your hearing.”

^16 Then the princes and all the people said to the priests and the prophets: “This man does not deserve the death penalty, for he spoke to us in the name of Jehovah our God.”

^17 Furthermore, some of the elders of the land rose up and began saying to the entire congregation of the people: ^18 “Miʹcah of Moʹresh·eth was prophesying in the days of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah, and he said to all the people of Judah, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says:

“Zion will be plowed up as a field,

Jerusalem will become heaps of ruins,

And the mountain of the House[*] will become like high places in a forest.”’[*]

^19 “Did King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah and all Judah then put him to death? Did he not fear Jehovah and beg for Jehovah’s favor,[*] so that Jehovah changed his mind concerning[*] the calamity that he had spoken against them? So we are about to bring a great calamity on ourselves.[*]

^20 “And there was another man prophesying in the name of Jehovah, U·riʹjah son of She·maiʹah from Kirʹi·ath-jeʹa·rim, who prophesied against this city and against this land with words like those of Jeremiah. ^21 King Je·hoiʹa·kim and all his mighty men and all the princes heard his words, and the king sought to put him to death. When U·riʹjah heard of it, he at once became afraid and fled to Egypt. ^22 Then King Je·hoiʹa·kim sent El·naʹthan the son of Achʹbor and other men with him to Egypt. ^23 They brought U·riʹjah from Egypt and took him to King Je·hoiʹa·kim, who then struck him down with the sword and cast his dead body into the graveyard of the common people.”

^24 But A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan supported Jeremiah, so that he was not handed over to the people to be put to death.

^ Jer. 26:2 Or “to.”

^ Jer. 26:2 Or “bow down.”

^ Jer. 26:3 Or “feel regret over.”

^ Jer. 26:4 Or “instruction.”

^ Jer. 26:5 Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 26:10 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 26:13 Or “feel regret over.”

^ Jer. 26:18 Or “the temple mount.”

^ Jer. 26:18 Or “like a wooded ridge.”

^ Jer. 26:19 Or “try to soften the face of Jehovah.”

^ Jer. 26:19 Or “felt regret over.”

^ Jer. 26:19 Or “our souls.”

Jeremiah  27 : 1 - 22

27 In the beginning of the reign of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, this word came to Jeremiah from Jehovah: ^2 “This is what Jehovah has told me, ‘Make for yourself straps and yoke bars, and put them on your neck. ^3 Then send them to the king of Eʹdom, the king of Moʹab, the king of the Amʹmon·ites, the king of Tyre, and the king of Siʹdon by the hand of the messengers who have come to Jerusalem to King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah. ^4 Give them this command for their masters:

“‘“This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says; this is what you should say to your masters, ^5 ‘It is I who made the earth, mankind, and the beasts that are on the surface of the earth by my great power and by my outstretched arm; and I have given it to whomever I please.[*] ^6 And now I have given all these lands into the hand of my servant King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon; even the wild beasts of the field I have given him to serve him. ^7 All the nations will serve him and his son and his grandson until the time for his own land comes, when many nations and great kings will make him their slave.’

^8 “‘“‘If any nation or kingdom refuses to serve King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon and refuses to put its neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, I will punish that nation with the sword, with famine, and with pestilence,’[*] declares Jehovah, ‘until I have finished them off by his hand.’

^9 “‘“‘Therefore, do not listen to your prophets, your diviners, your dreamers, your magicians, and your sorcerers, who are saying to you: “You will not serve the king of Babylon.” ^10 For they are prophesying lies to you, so that you will be taken far away from your land and I will disperse you and you will perish.

^11 “‘“‘But the nation that brings its neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon and serves him, I will allow to remain[*] on its land,’ declares Jehovah, ‘to cultivate it and dwell in it.’”’”

^12 Also to King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah I spoke in the same way, saying: “Bring your necks under the yoke of the king of Babylon and serve him and his people, and you will keep living. ^13 Why should you and your people die by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence, as Jehovah has said about the nation that will not serve the king of Babylon? ^14 Do not listen to the words of the prophets who are saying to you, ‘You will not serve the king of Babylon,’ because they are prophesying lies to you.

^15 “‘For I have not sent them,’ declares Jehovah, ‘but they are prophesying lies in my name, with the result that I will disperse you and you will perish, you and the prophets who are prophesying to you.’”

^16 And to the priests and to all this people I said: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Do not listen to the words of your prophets who are prophesying to you: “Look! The utensils of the house of Jehovah will be brought back from Babylon very soon!” for they are prophesying lies to you. ^17 Do not listen to them. Serve the king of Babylon and you will keep living. Why should this city become a ruin? ^18 But if they are prophets and if the word of Jehovah is with them, please let them beg Jehovah of armies that the remaining utensils in the house of Jehovah, in the house[*] of the king of Judah, and in Jerusalem may not be taken away to Babylon.’

^19 “For this is what Jehovah of armies says concerning the pillars, the Sea,[*] the carriages, and the remaining utensils that are left in this city, ^20 which King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon did not take when he took into exile Jec·o·niʹah son of Je·hoiʹa·kim, the king of Judah, from Jerusalem to Babylon, together with all the nobles of Judah and Jerusalem; ^21 yes, this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says concerning the utensils that are left at the house of Jehovah, in the house[*] of the king of Judah, and in Jerusalem: ^22 ‘“To Babylon they will be brought, and there they will remain until the day I turn my attention to them,” declares Jehovah. “Then I will bring them back and restore them to this place.”’”

^ Jer. 27:5 Lit., “to whom it is right in my eyes.”

^ Jer. 27:8 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 27:11 Lit., “rest.”

^ Jer. 27:18 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 27:19 That is, the copper Sea of the temple.

^ Jer. 27:21 Or “palace.”

Jeremiah  28 : 1 - 17

28 In that same year, in the beginning of the reign of King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, the prophet Han·a·niʹah the son of Azʹzur from Gibʹe·on said to me in the house of Jehovah in the presence of the priests and all the people: ^2 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon. ^3 Within two years[*] I am bringing back to this place all the utensils of the house of Jehovah that King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon took from this place and brought to Babylon.’” ^4 “‘And I will bring back to this place Jec·o·niʹah son of Je·hoiʹa·kim, the king of Judah, and all the exiles of Judah who have gone to Babylon,’ declares Jehovah, ‘for I will break the yoke of the king of Babylon.’”

^5 Then Jeremiah the prophet spoke to Han·a·niʹah the prophet in the presence of the priests and all the people who were standing in the house of Jehovah. ^6 Jeremiah the prophet said: “Amen![*] May Jehovah do this! May Jehovah fulfill your words that you prophesied by bringing back from Babylon to this place the utensils of the house of Jehovah and all the exiled people! ^7 However, hear, please, this message that I am speaking in your ears and in the ears of all the people. ^8 Long ago the prophets who were prior to me and prior to you used to prophesy concerning many lands and great kingdoms, about war, calamity, and pestilence.[*] ^9 If a prophet prophesies about peace and the word of that prophet comes true, then it will be known that Jehovah truly sent that prophet.”

^10 At that Han·a·niʹah the prophet took the yoke bar off the neck of the prophet Jeremiah and broke it. ^11 Han·a·niʹah then said in the presence of all the people: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Just like this I will break the yoke of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon from off the neck of all the nations within two years.’” And Jeremiah the prophet went on his way.

^12 After Han·a·niʹah the prophet had broken the yoke bar from off the neck of Jeremiah the prophet, this message of Jehovah came to Jeremiah: ^13 “Go and say to Han·a·niʹah, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “You have broken yoke bars of wood, but instead of them you will make yoke bars of iron.” ^14 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “I will put an iron yoke bar on the neck of all these nations, to serve King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon, and they must serve him. Even the wild beasts of the field I will give him.”’”

^15 Jeremiah the prophet then said to Han·a·niʹah the prophet: “Listen, please, O Han·a·niʹah! Jehovah has not sent you, but you have caused this people to trust in a lie. ^16 Therefore this is what Jehovah says, ‘Look! I am removing you from the face of the ground. This year you will die, for you have urged rebellion against Jehovah.’”

^17 So Han·a·niʹah the prophet died in that year, in the seventh month.

^ Jer. 28:3 Lit., “years of days.”

^ Jer. 28:6 Or “So be it!”

^ Jer. 28:8 Or “disease.”

Jeremiah  29 : 1 - 32

29 These are the words of the letter that Jeremiah the prophet sent from Jerusalem to the rest of the elders among the exiled people, the priests, the prophets, and all the people, whom Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar had taken into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon, ^2 after King Jec·o·niʹah, the queen mother,[*] the court officials, the princes of Judah and Jerusalem, and the craftsmen and the metalworkers[*] had gone out of Jerusalem. ^3 He sent the letter by the hand of El·aʹsah the son of Shaʹphan and Gem·a·riʹah the son of Hil·kiʹah, whom King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah sent to Babylon to King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar of Babylon. It said:

^4 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says to all the exiled people, whom I have caused to go into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon, ^5 ‘Build houses and live in them. Plant gardens and eat their fruit. ^6 Take wives and have sons and daughters; take wives for your sons and give your daughters in marriage, so that they too may have sons and daughters. Become many there, and do not decrease. ^7 And seek the peace of the city to which I have exiled you, and pray in its behalf to Jehovah, for in its peace you will have peace. ^8 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “Do not let your prophets and your diviners who are among you deceive you, and do not listen to the dreams that they are dreaming. ^9 For ‘they are prophesying lies to you in my name. I have not sent them,’ declares Jehovah.”’”

^10 “For this is what Jehovah says, ‘When 70 years at Babylon are fulfilled, I will turn my attention to you, and I will make good my promise by bringing you back to this place.’

^11 “‘For I well know the thoughts that I am thinking toward you,’ declares Jehovah, ‘thoughts of peace, and not of calamity, to give you a future and a hope. ^12 And you will call me and come and pray to me, and I will listen to you.’

^13 “‘You will seek me and find me, for you will search for me with all your heart. ^14 And I will let you find me,’ declares Jehovah. ‘And I will gather your captives and collect you together out of all the nations and places to which I have dispersed you,’ declares Jehovah. ‘And I will bring you back to the place from which I caused you to go into exile.’

^15 “But you have said, ‘Jehovah has raised up prophets for us in Babylon.’

^16 “For this is what Jehovah says to the king sitting on the throne of David and to all the people dwelling in this city, your brothers who have not gone with you into exile, ^17 ‘This is what Jehovah of armies says: “Here I am sending against them the sword, the famine, and the pestilence,[*] and I will make them like rotten[*] figs that are so bad they cannot be eaten.”’

^18 “‘And I will pursue them with the sword, with famine, and with pestilence, and I will make them an object of horror to all the kingdoms of the earth, and a curse, and an object of astonishment, something to whistle at, and a reproach among all the nations to which I disperse them, ^19 because they have not listened to my words that I sent to them with my servants the prophets,’ declares Jehovah, ‘sending them again and again.’[*]

“‘But you have not listened,’ declares Jehovah.

^20 “Therefore, hear the word of Jehovah, all you exiled people, whom I have sent away from Jerusalem to Babylon. ^21 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says concerning Aʹhab the son of Ko·laiʹah and concerning Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Ma·a·seiʹah, who are prophesying lies to you in my name, ‘Here I am giving them into the hand of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon, and he will strike them down before your eyes. ^22 And what happens to them will become a curse spoken by all the exiles of Judah in Babylon: “May Jehovah make you like Zed·e·kiʹah and like Aʹhab, whom the king of Babylon roasted in the fire!” ^23 for they have acted disgracefully in Israel, committing adultery with the wives of their neighbors and speaking false words in my name that I did not command them.

“‘“I am the One who knows, and I am a witness,” declares Jehovah.’”

^24 “And to She·maiʹah of Ne·helʹam you will say, ^25 ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “Because you sent in your name letters to all the people who are in Jerusalem, to Zeph·a·niʹah son of Ma·a·seiʹah, the priest, and to all the priests, saying, ^26 ‘Jehovah has made you priest instead of Je·hoiʹa·da the priest to become the overseer of the house of Jehovah, to be in charge of any madman who acts like a prophet and to put him into the stocks and into the pillory;[*] ^27 why, then, have you not rebuked Jeremiah of Anʹa·thoth, who is acting as a prophet for you? ^28 For he even sent to us at Babylon, saying: “It will be a long time! Build houses and live in them. Plant gardens and eat their fruit,—”’”’”

^29 When Zeph·a·niʹah the priest read this letter in the hearing of Jeremiah the prophet, ^30 the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying: ^31 “Send to all the exiled people, saying, ‘This is what Jehovah says concerning She·maiʹah of Ne·helʹam: “Because She·maiʹah prophesied to you, though I did not send him, and he tried to make you trust in lies, ^32 therefore this is what Jehovah says, ‘Here I am turning my attention to She·maiʹah of Ne·helʹam and his descendants. Not one man of his will survive among this people, and he will not see the good that I will do for my people,’ declares Jehovah, ‘for he has urged rebellion against Jehovah.’”’”

^ Jer. 29:2 Or “the lady.”

^ Jer. 29:2 Or possibly, “builders of bulwarks.”

^ Jer. 29:17 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 29:17 Or possibly, “burst.”

^ Jer. 29:19 Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 29:21 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 29:26 Or “neck irons.”

Jeremiah  32 : 1 - 44

32 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah in the 10th year of King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah, that is, the 18th year of Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar.[*] ^2 At that time the armies of the king of Babylon were besieging Jerusalem, and Jeremiah the prophet was confined in the Courtyard of the Guard in the house[*] of the king of Judah. ^3 For King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah had confined him, saying, “Why do you prophesy like this? You say, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “I will give this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will capture it, ^4 and King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah will not escape from the Chal·deʹans, for he will surely be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will speak to him face-to-face and see him eye to eye.”’ ^5 ‘He will take Zed·e·kiʹah to Babylon, and there he will remain until I turn my attention to him,’ declares Jehovah. ‘Although you keep fighting against the Chal·deʹans, you will not succeed.’”

^6 Jeremiah said: “The word of Jehovah has come to me, saying, ^7 ‘Here Hanʹa·mel the son of Shalʹlum your uncle[*] will come to you and say: “Buy for yourself my field in Anʹa·thoth, because you have the first right to repurchase it.”’”

^8 Hanʹa·mel the son of my uncle came to me, just as Jehovah had said, into the Courtyard of the Guard, and he said to me: “Please buy my field in Anʹa·thoth, in the land of Benjamin, for you have the right to take possession of it and to repurchase it. Buy it for yourself.” At that I knew that this was by the word of Jehovah.

^9 So I bought the field in Anʹa·thoth from Hanʹa·mel the son of my uncle. I weighed out the money to him, seven shekels[*] and ten silver pieces. ^10 Then I recorded it in a deed, affixed the seal, called in witnesses, and weighed the money in the scales. ^11 I took the deed of purchase, the one that was sealed according to the commandment and legal requirements, as well as the one that was left unsealed, ^12 and I gave the deed of purchase to Barʹuch son of Ne·riʹah son of Mah·seiʹah in the presence of Hanʹa·mel the son of my uncle, the witnesses who wrote in the deed of purchase, and all the Jews who were sitting in the Courtyard of the Guard.

^13 I now commanded Barʹuch in their presence, saying: ^14 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Take these deeds, this deed of purchase, the sealed one and the other deed left unsealed, and put them into an earthenware vessel, so that they may be kept for a long time.’ ^15 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Houses and fields and vineyards will again be bought in this land.’”

^16 Then I prayed to Jehovah after giving the deed of purchase to Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah, saying: ^17 “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Look! You made the heavens and the earth by your great power and by your outstretched arm. Nothing is too wonderful for you, ^18 the One showing loyal love to thousands, but repaying the error of the fathers to[*] their sons after them, the true God, the great and mighty One, whose name is Jehovah of armies. ^19 You are great in counsel[*] and mighty in deed, you whose eyes observe all the ways of men, to give to each one according to his ways and according to what he does. ^20 You have performed signs and miracles in the land of Egypt, which are known down to this day, and thus you have made a name for yourself in Israel and among mankind, as it is today. ^21 And you brought your people Israel out of the land of Egypt, with signs, with miracles, with a mighty hand, with an outstretched arm, and with terrifying deeds.

^22 “In time you gave them this land that you swore to give to their forefathers, a land flowing with milk and honey. ^23 And they came in and took possession of it, but they did not obey your voice or walk in your law. They did not do anything you commanded them to do, so that you caused all this calamity to befall them. ^24 Look! Men have come with siege ramparts to capture the city, and because of the sword, the famine, and the pestilence,[*] the city will certainly fall into the hands of the Chal·deʹans who are fighting against it; what you said has all happened, as you now see. ^25 But you have told me, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘Buy for yourself the field with money and call in witnesses,’ although the city will certainly be given into the hand of the Chal·deʹans.”

^26 At that the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying: ^27 “Here I am, Jehovah, the God of all mankind.[*] Is there anything too wonderful for me? ^28 So this is what Jehovah says, ‘Here I am handing this city over to the Chal·deʹans and into the hand of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon, and he will capture it. ^29 And the Chal·deʹans fighting against this city will come in and set this city on fire and burn it down along with the houses on whose roofs the people offered sacrifices to Baʹal and poured out drink offerings to other gods to offend me.’

^30 “‘For the people of Israel and of Judah have done only what was bad in my eyes, from their youth on; the people of Israel keep offending me by the work of their hands,’ declares Jehovah. ^31 ‘For this city, from the day that they built it down to this day, has been nothing but a cause of anger and wrath to me, so that it must be removed from before my face, ^32 because of all the evil that the people of Israel and of Judah have done to offend me—they, their kings, their princes, their priests, their prophets, and the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^33 They kept turning their backs to me, not their faces; although I tried to teach them again and again,[*] none of them would listen to receive discipline. ^34 And they put their disgusting idols in the house that bears my name, in order to defile it. ^35 Furthermore, they built the high places of Baʹal in the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom,[*] in order to make their sons and their daughters pass through the fire to Moʹlech, something that I had not commanded them and that had never come into my heart[*] to do such a detestable thing, causing Judah to sin.’

^36 “Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says concerning this city that you are saying will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon by the sword, the famine, and the pestilence, ^37 ‘Here I will gather them together from all the lands where I dispersed them in my anger and in my wrath and in great indignation, and I will bring them back to this place and let them dwell in security. ^38 And they will be my people, and I will be their God. ^39 And I will give them one heart and one way so that they may always fear me, for their own good and the good of their children after them. ^40 And I will make with them an everlasting covenant, that I will not turn away from doing good to them; and I will put the fear of me in their hearts, so that they will not turn away from me. ^41 I will exult over them to do good to them, and I will firmly plant them in this land, with all my heart and with all my soul.’”[*]

^42 “For this is what Jehovah says, ‘Just as I have brought on this people all this great calamity, so I will bring on them all the goodness[*] that I am promising them. ^43 And fields will again be bought in this land, though you are saying: “It is a wasteland without man and beast, and it has been handed over to the Chal·deʹans.”’

^44 “‘Fields will be bought with money, deeds of purchase will be recorded and sealed, and witnesses will be called in the land of Benjamin, in the areas around Jerusalem, in the cities of Judah, in the cities of the mountainous region, in the cities of the lowland, and in the cities of the south, because I will bring back their captives,’ declares Jehovah.”

^ Jer. 32:1 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 32:2 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 32:7 That is, paternal uncle.

^ Jer. 32:9 A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ Jer. 32:18 Lit., “into the bosom of.”

^ Jer. 32:19 Or “great as regards your purposes.”

^ Jer. 32:24 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 32:27 Lit., “all flesh.”

^ Jer. 32:28 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 32:33 Lit., “rising up early and teaching.”

^ Jer. 32:35 See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

^ Jer. 32:35 Or “had never entered my thoughts.”

^ Jer. 32:41 See Glossary.

^ Jer. 32:42 Or “the good things.”

Jeremiah  33 : 1 - 26

33 The word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah the second time, while he was still confined in the Courtyard of the Guard, saying: ^2 “This is what Jehovah the Maker of earth says, Jehovah who formed it and firmly established it; Jehovah is his name, ^3 ‘Call to me, and I will answer you and readily tell you great and incomprehensible things that you have not known.’”

^4 “For this is what Jehovah the God of Israel says concerning the houses of this city and the houses of the kings of Judah that are pulled down because of the siege ramparts and the sword, ^5 and concerning those who are coming to fight the Chal·deʹans, filling these places with the carcasses of those whom I struck down in my anger and in my wrath, those whose evil has caused me to hide my face from this city: ^6 ‘Here I am bringing recuperation and health to her, and I will heal them and reveal to them an abundance of peace and truth. ^7 And I will bring back the captives of Judah and the captives of Israel, and I will build them up as I did at the start. ^8 And I will purify them from all the guilt of their sins against me, and I will forgive all the guilt of their sins and their transgressions against me. ^9 And she will become to me a name of exultation, a praise, and a beauty before all the nations of the earth who will hear of all the goodness that I bestow on them. And they will be in dread and will tremble because of all the goodness and peace that I will bestow on her.’”

^10 “This is what Jehovah says: ‘In this place that you will say is a wasteland, without man or livestock, in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem that are desolate, without man or inhabitant or livestock, there will again be heard ^11 the sound of exultation and the sound of rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the voice of those saying: “Give thanks to Jehovah of armies, for Jehovah is good; his loyal love endures forever!”’

“‘They will bring thanksgiving offerings into the house of Jehovah, for I will bring back the captives of the land, as at the start,’ says Jehovah.”

^12 “This is what Jehovah of armies says: ‘In this wasteland, without man or livestock, and in all its cities, there will again be pastures for the shepherds to rest their flocks.’

^13 “‘In the cities of the mountainous region, in the cities of the lowland, in the cities of the south, in the land of Benjamin, in the areas around Jerusalem, and in the cities of Judah, flocks will again pass under the hands of the one counting them,’ says Jehovah.”

^14 “‘Look! The days are coming,’ declares Jehovah, ‘when I will fulfill the good promise that I have spoken concerning the house of Israel and the house of Judah. ^15 In those days and at that time I will cause to sprout for David a righteous sprout,[*] and he will execute justice and righteousness in the land. ^16 In those days Judah will be saved and Jerusalem will reside in security. And this is what she will be called: Jehovah Is Our Righteousness.’”

^17 “For this is what Jehovah says: ‘There will never fail to be a man from David’s line to sit on the throne of the house of Israel, ^18 nor will the Levitical priests ever fail to have a man stand before me to offer whole burnt offerings, to burn grain offerings, and to offer sacrifices.’”

^19 And the word of Jehovah again came to Jeremiah, saying: ^20 “This is what Jehovah says, ‘If you could break my covenant regarding the day and my covenant regarding the night, to prevent day and night from coming at their proper time, ^21 only then could my covenant with my servant David be broken, so that he should not have a son ruling as king on his throne, and so also my covenant with the Levitical priests, my ministers. ^22 Just as the army of the heavens cannot be counted and the sand of the sea cannot be measured, so I will multiply the offspring[*] of my servant David and the Levites who are ministering to me.’”

^23 And the word of Jehovah again came to Jeremiah, saying: ^24 “Have you not taken note of what this people is saying, ‘Jehovah will reject the two families that he chose’? And they are treating my own people with disrespect, and they no longer regard them as a nation.

^25 “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Just as surely as I have established my covenant regarding the day and the night, the laws[*] of heaven and earth, ^26 so I will never reject the offspring[*] of Jacob and of my servant David, so as not to take from his offspring[*] rulers over the descendants[*] of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. For I will gather back their captives and have pity on them.’”

^ Jer. 33:15 Or “heir.”

^ Jer. 33:22 Lit., “seed.”

^ Jer. 33:25 Or “statutes.”

^ Jer. 33:26 Lit., “seed.”

^ Jer. 33:26 Lit., “seed.”

^ Jer. 33:26 Lit., “seed.”

Jeremiah  34 : 1 - 22

34 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, when King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon and all his army and all the kingdoms of the earth under his dominion and all the peoples were fighting against Jerusalem and all her cities:

^2 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘Go and speak to King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah and tell him: “This is what Jehovah says, ‘Here I am giving this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will burn it with fire. ^3 And you will not escape out of his hand, for you will without fail be caught and handed over to him. And you will see the king of Babylon eye to eye, and he will speak to you face-to-face, and you will go to Babylon.’ ^4 However, hear the word of Jehovah, O King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah, ‘This is what Jehovah says concerning you: “You will not die by the sword. ^5 In peace you will die, and they will make a burning ceremony for you as they did for your fathers, the former kings who were before you, and they will mourn you, ‘Alas, O master!’ for ‘I have spoken the word,’ declares Jehovah.”’”’”

^6 Jeremiah the prophet then spoke all these words to King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah in Jerusalem, ^7 when the armies of the king of Babylon were fighting against Jerusalem and against all the cities of Judah that were left, against Laʹchish and against A·zeʹkah; for they were the only fortified cities that remained of the cities of Judah.

^8 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah after King Zed·e·kiʹah had made a covenant with all the people in Jerusalem to proclaim liberty to them, ^9 that everyone should free his Hebrew slaves, male and female, so that no one would keep a fellow Jew as his slave. ^10 So all the princes and all the people obeyed. They had entered into the covenant that everyone should free his male and female slaves and not keep them as slaves any longer. They obeyed and let them go. ^11 However, they later brought back the male and female slaves whom they had freed, and they again forced them back into slavery. ^12 So the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying:

^13 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘I made a covenant with your forefathers in the day I brought them out of the land of Egypt, out of the house of slavery, saying: ^14 “At the end of seven years, each of you should free his Hebrew brother who was sold to you and who has served you six years; you must set him free.” But your forefathers did not listen or incline their ears to me. ^15 And recently[*] you yourselves turned around and did what was right in my eyes by proclaiming liberty to your fellow men, and you made a covenant before me in the house that bears my name. ^16 But then you turned around and profaned my name by bringing back your male and female slaves whom you had freed according to their desire,[*] and you forced them back into slavery.’

^17 “Therefore this is what Jehovah says: ‘You have not obeyed me in proclaiming liberty, each one to his brother and to his fellow man. So I will now proclaim liberty to you,’ declares Jehovah, ‘to the sword, to pestilence,[*] and to famine, and I will make you an object of horror to all the kingdoms of the earth. ^18 And this is what will happen to the men who violated my covenant by not carrying out the words of the covenant that they made before me when they cut the calf in two and passed between the halves, ^19 namely, the princes of Judah, the princes of Jerusalem, the court officials, the priests, and all the people of the land who passed between the halves of the calf: ^20 I will hand them over to their enemies and to those seeking to take their lives,[*] and their dead bodies will become food for the birds of the heavens and for the beasts of the earth. ^21 And I will give King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah and his princes into the hand of their enemies and into the hand of those seeking to take their lives[*] and into the hand of the armies of the king of Babylon, who are withdrawing from against you.’

^22 “‘Here I will give the order,’ declares Jehovah, ‘and I will bring them back to this city, and they will fight against it and capture it and burn it with fire; and the cities of Judah I will make a wasteland, without an inhabitant.’”

^ Jer. 34:1 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 34:15 Lit., “today.”

^ Jer. 34:16 Or “soul.”

^ Jer. 34:17 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 34:20 Or “seeking their souls.”

^ Jer. 34:21 Or “seeking their souls.”

Jeremiah  35 : 1 - 19

35 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah in the days of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, saying: ^2 “Go to the house of the Reʹcha·bites and speak with them and bring them into the house of Jehovah, into one of the dining rooms;[*] then offer them wine to drink.”

^3 So I took Ja·az·a·niʹah the son of Jeremiah the son of Hab·az·zi·niʹah, his brothers, all his sons, and the entire house of the Reʹcha·bites ^4 into the house of Jehovah. I brought them to the dining room of the sons of Haʹnan the son of Ig·da·liʹah, a man of the true God, which was next to the dining room of the princes that was above the dining room of Ma·a·seiʹah the son of Shalʹlum the doorkeeper. ^5 Then I put cups and goblets full of wine before the men of the house of the Reʹcha·bites and said to them: “Drink wine.”

^6 But they said: “We will not drink wine, because Je·honʹa·dab[*] the son of Reʹchab, our forefather, gave us this command, ‘Neither you nor your sons must ever drink wine. ^7 And you must not build a house, sow seed, or plant or obtain a vineyard. Instead, you must always dwell in tents, so that you may live for a long time in the land where you are residing as foreigners.’ ^8 So we continue to obey the voice of Je·honʹa·dab the son of our forefather Reʹchab in all that he commanded us, by never drinking any wine—we, our wives, our sons, and our daughters. ^9 And we do not build houses to dwell in, nor do we have vineyards or fields or seed. ^10 We keep living in tents and obeying all that Je·honʹa·dab[*] our forefather commanded us. ^11 But when King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon came up against the land, we said, ‘Come, let us go into Jerusalem to escape the army of the Chal·deʹans and of the Syrians,’ and now we are living in Jerusalem.”

^12 And the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah, saying: ^13 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Go and say to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem: “Were you not continually urged to obey my words?” declares Jehovah. ^14 “Je·honʹa·dab the son of Reʹchab commanded his descendants not to drink wine, and they have carried out his words by not drinking it to this day, thus obeying the order of their forefather. However, I have spoken to you again and again,[*] but you have not obeyed me. ^15 And I kept sending all my servants the prophets to you, sending them again and again,[*] saying, ‘Turn back, please, each of you from your evil ways, and do what is right! Do not walk after other gods and serve them. Then you will keep dwelling in the land that I gave to you and your forefathers.’ But you did not incline your ear or listen to me. ^16 The descendants of Je·honʹa·dab the son of Reʹchab have carried out the order that their forefather gave them, but these people have not listened to me.”’”

^17 “Therefore this is what Jehovah, the God of armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Here I am bringing on Judah and on all the inhabitants of Jerusalem all the calamity that I have warned them about, for I have spoken to them, but they would not listen, and I kept calling to them, but they would not answer.’”

^18 And Jeremiah said to the household of the Reʹcha·bites: “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Because you have obeyed the order of your forefather Je·honʹa·dab and you continue to observe all his orders, doing exactly what he ordered you, ^19 this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “There will never fail to be a descendant of Je·honʹa·dab[*] the son of Reʹchab to serve in my presence.”’”

^ Jer. 35:2 Or “the chambers.”

^ Jer. 35:6 Lit., “Jonadab,” the shortened form of Jehonadab.

^ Jer. 35:10 Lit., “Jonadab,” the shortened form of Jehonadab.

^ Jer. 35:11 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 35:14 Lit., “rising up early and speaking.”

^ Jer. 35:15 Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 35:19 Lit., “Jonadab,” the shortened form of Jehonadab.

Jeremiah  36 : 1 - 32

36 Now in the fourth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, this word came to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: ^2 “Take a scroll[*] and write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and Judah and all the nations, from the first day I spoke to you in the days of Jo·siʹah to this day. ^3 Perhaps when those of the house of Judah hear of all the calamity that I intend to bring on them, they may turn back from their evil ways, so that I may forgive their error and their sin.”

^4 Jeremiah then called Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah, and Jeremiah dictated all the words that Jehovah had spoken to him, and Barʹuch wrote them in the scroll.[*] ^5 Then Jeremiah commanded Barʹuch: “I am confined and unable to enter the house of Jehovah. ^6 So you are the one who must go in and read aloud the words of Jehovah from the scroll that you wrote at my dictation. Read them in the hearing of the people at the house of Jehovah on the day of a fast; thus you will read them to all the people of Judah who come in from their cities. ^7 Perhaps their request for favor will reach Jehovah, and they will turn back, each one from his evil ways, for great is the anger and the wrath that Jehovah has declared against this people.”

^8 So Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah did all that Jeremiah the prophet had commanded him; he read aloud from the scroll[*] the words of Jehovah at the house of Jehovah.

^9 Now in the fifth year of Je·hoiʹa·kim son of Jo·siʹah, the king of Judah, in the ninth month, all the people in Jerusalem and all the people who came into Jerusalem from the cities of Judah proclaimed a fast before Jehovah. ^10 Barʹuch then read aloud from the scroll[*] the words of Jeremiah at the house of Jehovah, in the chamber[*] of Gem·a·riʹah the son of Shaʹphan the copyist,[*] in the upper courtyard, at the entrance of the new gate of the house of Jehovah, in the hearing of all the people.

^11 When Mi·caiʹah the son of Gem·a·riʹah the son of Shaʹphan heard all the words of Jehovah from the scroll,[*] ^12 he went down to the house[*] of the king, to the secretary’s chamber. All the princes[*] were sitting there: E·lishʹa·ma the secretary, De·laʹiah the son of She·maiʹah, El·naʹthan the son of Achʹbor, Gem·a·riʹah the son of Shaʹphan, Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Han·a·niʹah, and all the other princes. ^13 Mi·caiʹah told them all the words that he had heard when Barʹuch read from the scroll[*] in the hearing of the people.

^14 Then all the princes sent Je·huʹdi the son of Neth·a·niʹah the son of Shel·e·miʹah the son of Cushʹi to Barʹuch, saying: “Come and bring with you the scroll from which you read in the hearing of the people.” Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah took the scroll in his hand and went in to them. ^15 They said to him: “Sit down, please, and read it aloud to us.” So Barʹuch read it to them.

^16 Now as soon as they heard all the words, they looked at one another in dread, and they said to Barʹuch: “We must certainly tell the king all these words.” ^17 And they asked Barʹuch: “Tell us, please, how you wrote all these words. Was it at his dictation?” ^18 Barʹuch replied to them: “He dictated all these words to me, and I wrote them down with ink in this scroll.”[*] ^19 The princes said to Barʹuch: “Go and hide yourselves, you and Jeremiah, and do not let anyone know where you are.”

^20 Then they went in to the king, to the courtyard, and deposited the scroll in the chamber of E·lishʹa·ma the secretary, and they told the king everything they had heard.

^21 So the king sent Je·huʹdi out to get the scroll, and he brought it from the chamber of E·lishʹa·ma the secretary. Je·huʹdi began to read it in the hearing of the king and of all the princes standing by the king. ^22 The king was sitting in the winter house, in the ninth month,[*] with a fire burning in the brazier before him. ^23 After Je·huʹdi had read three or four columns, the king would cut off that portion with the secretary’s knife and pitch it into the fire that was burning in the brazier, until the entire scroll ended up in the fire that was in the brazier. ^24 And they felt no dread; neither the king nor all his servants who heard all these words ripped their garments apart. ^25 Although El·naʹthan, De·laʹiah, and Gem·a·riʹah pleaded with the king not to burn the scroll, he did not listen to them. ^26 Further, the king commanded Je·rahʹme·el the son of the king, Se·raiʹah the son of Azʹri·el, and Shel·e·miʹah the son of Abʹde·el to seize Barʹuch the secretary and Jeremiah the prophet, but Jehovah kept them concealed.

^27 And the word of Jehovah again came to Jeremiah after the king had burned up the scroll containing the words that Barʹuch had written at Jeremiah’s dictation, saying: ^28 “Take another scroll and write on it all the same words that were on the first scroll, which King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah burned up. ^29 And you should say against King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah, ‘This is what Jehovah says: “You have burned up this scroll and said, ‘Why have you written on it: “The king of Babylon will certainly come and destroy this land and empty it of man and beast”?’ ^30 Therefore this is what Jehovah says against King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah, ‘He will have no one to sit on the throne of David, and his dead body will be left exposed to the heat by day and the frost by night. ^31 I will call him and his descendants[*] and his servants to account for their error, and I will bring on them and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem and on the men of Judah all the calamity that I have spoken against them, but they did not listen.’”’”

^32 Jeremiah then took another scroll and gave it to Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah, the secretary, and at Jeremiah’s dictation he wrote on it all the words of the scroll[*] that King Je·hoiʹa·kim of Judah had burned in the fire. And many more words like those were added.

^ Jer. 36:2 Lit., “a scroll of a book.”

^ Jer. 36:4 Lit., “the scroll of the book.”

^ Jer. 36:8 Or “book.”

^ Jer. 36:10 Or “book.”

^ Jer. 36:10 Or “dining room.”

^ Jer. 36:10 Or “scribe.”

^ Jer. 36:11 Or “book.”

^ Jer. 36:12 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 36:12 Or “court officials.”

^ Jer. 36:13 Or “book.”

^ Jer. 36:18 Or “book.”

^ Jer. 36:22 The last half of November and the first half of December. See App. B15.

^ Jer. 36:31 Lit., “seed.”

^ Jer. 36:32 Or “book.”

Jeremiah  37 : 1 - 21

37 And King Zed·e·kiʹah the son of Jo·siʹah began to reign in place of Co·niʹah[*] the son of Je·hoiʹa·kim, for King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon made him king in the land of Judah. ^2 But he and his servants and the people of the land did not listen to the words of Jehovah spoken through Jeremiah the prophet.

^3 And King Zed·e·kiʹah sent Je·huʹcal the son of Shel·e·miʹah and Zeph·a·niʹah the son of Ma·a·seiʹah the priest to Jeremiah the prophet, saying: “Please pray in our behalf to Jehovah our God.” ^4 Jeremiah was moving about freely among the people, for they had not yet put him in prison. ^5 Now Pharʹaoh’s army had set out from Egypt, and the Chal·deʹans who were besieging Jerusalem heard the report about them. So they withdrew from against Jerusalem. ^6 Then the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah the prophet, saying: ^7 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, ‘This is what you should say to the king of Judah, who sent you to me to inquire of me: “Look! The army of Pharʹaoh that is coming to assist you will have to go back to its land, Egypt. ^8 And the Chal·deʹans will come back and fight against this city and capture it and burn it with fire.” ^9 This is what Jehovah says, “Do not deceive yourselves[*] by saying, ‘The Chal·deʹans will surely go away from against us,’ because they will not go away. ^10 Even if you were to strike down the entire army of the Chal·deʹans who are fighting against you and only their wounded men were left, they would still rise up from their tents and burn this city with fire.”’”

^11 When the Chal·deʹan army had withdrawn from against Jerusalem because of Pharʹaoh’s army, ^12 Jeremiah set out from Jerusalem to the land of Benjamin to receive his portion there among his people. ^13 But when he reached the Gate of Benjamin, the officer in charge of the guard, whose name was I·riʹjah the son of Shel·e·miʹah the son of Han·a·niʹah, seized Jeremiah the prophet and said: “You are deserting to the Chal·deʹans!” ^14 But Jeremiah said: “It is not true! I am not deserting to the Chal·deʹans.” But he did not listen to him. So I·riʹjah arrested Jeremiah and brought him in to the princes. ^15 The princes were furious with Jeremiah, and they beat him and imprisoned him[*] in the house of Je·honʹa·than the secretary, which had been made into a prison. ^16 Jeremiah was put into the dungeon,[*] into the vaulted rooms, and he remained there many days.

^17 Then King Zed·e·kiʹah sent for him, and the king secretly questioned him in his house.[*] He asked, “Is there any word from Jehovah?” Jeremiah said, “There is!” and he continued, “You will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon!”

^18 Jeremiah also said to King Zed·e·kiʹah: “How have I sinned against you and against your servants and against this people, so that you have put me into the prison? ^19 Where, now, are your prophets who prophesied to you, ‘The king of Babylon will not come against you and against this land’? ^20 Now listen, please, O my lord the king. May you grant, please, my request for favor. Do not send me back to the house of Je·honʹa·than the secretary, or I will die there.” ^21 So King Zed·e·kiʹah ordered that Jeremiah be put in custody in the Courtyard of the Guard, and he was given a round loaf of bread daily from the street of the bakers until all the bread in the city was gone. And Jeremiah remained in the Courtyard of the Guard.

^ Jer. 37:1 Also called Jehoiachin and Jeconiah.

^ Jer. 37:1 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 37:9 Or “your souls.”

^ Jer. 37:15 Lit., “put him into the house of the fetters.”

^ Jer. 37:16 Lit., “the house of the cistern.”

^ Jer. 37:17 Or “palace.”

Jeremiah  40 : 1 - 16

40 The word that came to Jeremiah from Jehovah after Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard let him go free from Raʹmah. He had taken him there bound with handcuffs, and he was among all the exiles of Jerusalem and of Judah who were being deported to Babylon. ^2 Then the chief of the guard took Jeremiah and said to him: “Jehovah your God foretold this calamity against this place, ^3 and Jehovah has brought it about just as he said, because you people sinned against Jehovah and did not obey his voice. That is why this has happened to you. ^4 Now I am releasing you today from the handcuffs that were on your hands. If it seems good to you to come with me to Babylon, come, and I will look after you. But if you do not want to come with me to Babylon, do not come. See! The entire land is before you. Go wherever you choose.”

^5 While Jeremiah still had not turned back, Neb·uʹzar·adʹan said: “Return to Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan, whom the king of Babylon has appointed over the cities of Judah, and stay with him among the people; or go wherever you choose.”

The chief of the guard then gave him a food allowance and a gift and let him go. ^6 So Jeremiah went to Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam at Mizʹpah and stayed with him among the people who were left in the land.

^7 In time all the army chiefs who were in the field with their men heard that the king of Babylon had appointed Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam over the land and that he had appointed him over the men, women, and children from the poor people of the land who had not been deported to Babylon. ^8 So they came to Ged·a·liʹah at Mizʹpah. They were Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah, Jo·haʹnan and Jonʹa·than the sons of Ka·reʹah, Se·raiʹah the son of Tan·huʹmeth, the sons of Eʹphai the Ne·tophʹa·thite, and Jez·a·niʹah the son of the Ma·acʹa·thite, together with their men. ^9 Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan swore an oath to them and to their men, saying: “Do not be afraid of serving the Chal·deʹans. Live in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with you. ^10 As for me, I will stay in Mizʹpah to represent you to[*] the Chal·deʹans who come to us. But you should gather wine, summer fruits, and oil and put them in your storage containers and settle in the cities that you have taken over.”

^11 And all the Jews who were in Moʹab, Amʹmon, and Eʹdom, as well as those who were in all the other lands, also heard that the king of Babylon had let a remnant stay in Judah and that he had appointed over them Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan. ^12 So all the Jews began returning from all the places to which they had been dispersed, and they came into the land of Judah, to Ged·a·liʹah at Mizʹpah. And they gathered wine and summer fruits in very great quantity.

^13 Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs who were in the field came to Ged·a·liʹah at Mizʹpah. ^14 They said to him: “Do you not know that Baʹa·lis, the king of the Amʹmon·ites, has sent Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah to kill you?”[*] But Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam did not believe them.

^15 Then Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah secretly told Ged·a·liʹah in Mizʹpah: “I want to go and strike down Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah, and no one will know. Why should he kill you,[*] and why should all the people of Judah who have gathered to you be scattered and the remnant of Judah perish?” ^16 But Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam said to Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah: “Do not do this, for what you are saying concerning Ishʹma·el is a lie.”

^ Jer. 40:10 Lit., “to stand before.”

^ Jer. 40:14 Or “to strike your soul?”

^ Jer. 40:15 Or “strike your soul.”

Jeremiah  41 : 1 - 18

41 In the seventh month Ishʹma·el son of Neth·a·niʹah son of E·lishʹa·ma, who was of the royal line[*] and one of the principal men of the king, came with ten other men to Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam at Mizʹpah. As they were eating a meal together in Mizʹpah, ^2 Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah and the ten men who were with him rose up and struck down Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan with the sword. So he put to death the one whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land. ^3 Ishʹma·el also struck down all the Jews who were with Ged·a·liʹah in Mizʹpah, as well as the Chal·deʹan soldiers who were there.

^4 On the second day after Ged·a·liʹah had been put to death, before anyone knew about it, ^5 there came 80 men from Sheʹchem, from Shiʹloh, and from Sa·marʹi·a. Their beards were shaved off, their garments were ripped apart, they had cut themselves, and they had grain offerings and frankincense in their hand to bring to the house of Jehovah. ^6 So Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah went out from Mizʹpah to meet them, weeping as he walked along. When he encountered them, he said to them: “Come to Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam.” ^7 But when they came into the city, Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah and his men slaughtered them and threw them into the cistern.

^8 But there were ten men among them who said to Ishʹma·el: “Do not put us to death, for we have hidden stores of wheat, barley, oil, and honey in the field.” So he refrained from putting them to death along with their brothers. ^9 Now Ishʹma·el threw all the carcasses of the men he had killed into a great cistern, the one that King Aʹsa had made because of King Baʹa·sha of Israel. This was the cistern that Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah filled with the slain men.

^10 Ishʹma·el took captive all the rest of the people in Mizʹpah, including the daughters of the king and all the people left in Mizʹpah, whom Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard had put in the custody of Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam. Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah took them captive and went off to cross over to the Amʹmon·ites.

^11 When Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs who were with him heard about all the evil that Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah had done, ^12 they took all the men and went off to fight against Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah, and they found him by the great waters[*] in Gibʹe·on.

^13 All the people who were with Ishʹma·el rejoiced when they saw Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs with him. ^14 Then all the people whom Ishʹma·el had taken captive from Mizʹpah turned around and went back with Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah. ^15 But Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah and eight of his men escaped from Jo·haʹnan and went to the Amʹmon·ites.

^16 Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs who were with him took with them the rest of the people from Mizʹpah, those whom they had rescued from Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah after he had struck down Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam. They brought the men, the soldiers, the women, the children, and the court officials back from Gibʹe·on. ^17 So they went and stayed in the lodging place of Chimʹham next to Bethʹle·hem, intending to go on into Egypt ^18 because of the Chal·deʹans. For they had become afraid of them, since Ishʹma·el the son of Neth·a·niʹah had struck down Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam, whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land.

^ Jer. 41:1 Lit., “the seed of the kingdom.”

^ Jer. 41:12 Or possibly, “great pool.”

Jeremiah  42 : 1 - 22

42 Then all the army chiefs, and Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah, Jez·a·niʹah the son of Ho·shaiʹah, and all the people, from the least to the greatest, approached ^2 and said to Jeremiah the prophet: “Hear, please, our request for favor, and pray in our behalf to Jehovah your God, in behalf of all this remnant, for just a few of many are left, as you can see. ^3 May Jehovah your God tell us the way we should walk and what we should do.”

^4 Jeremiah the prophet replied to them: “I have heard you, and I am praying to Jehovah your God according to your request; and every word that Jehovah answers you, I will tell you. I will not hold back a word from you.”

^5 They replied to Jeremiah: “May Jehovah be a true and faithful witness against us if we do not do exactly as Jehovah your God instructs us through you. ^6 Whether good or bad, we will obey the voice of Jehovah our God, to whom we are sending you, so that it may go well with us because we obey the voice of Jehovah our God.”

^7 Now ten days later the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah. ^8 So he called for Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and for all the army chiefs who were with him and for all the people, from the least to the greatest. ^9 He said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says, to whom you sent me to present your request for favor before him: ^10 ‘If you will indeed remain in this land, then I will build you up and not tear you down, and I will plant you and not uproot you, for I will feel regret[*] over the calamity I have caused you. ^11 Do not be afraid because of the king of Babylon, whom you fear.’

“‘Do not be afraid because of him,’ declares Jehovah, ‘for I am with you, to save you and to rescue you out of his hand. ^12 And I will show you mercy, and he will have mercy on you and return you to your own land.

^13 “‘But if you say, “No, we will not remain in this land!” and you disobey the voice of Jehovah your God ^14 by saying, “No, we will go instead to the land of Egypt, where we will not see war or hear the sound of the horn or hunger for bread; there is where we will live,” ^15 then hear the word of Jehovah, O remnant of Judah. This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “If you are absolutely determined to go to Egypt and you go there to reside,[*] ^16 then the very sword you are afraid of will catch up with you there in the land of Egypt, and the very famine you fear will follow after you to Egypt, and there you will die. ^17 And all the men who are determined to go to Egypt to reside there will die by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence.[*] None of them will survive or escape the calamity that I will bring on them.”’

^18 “For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Just as my anger and my wrath were poured out on the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so my wrath will be poured out on you if you go to Egypt, and you will become a curse, an object of horror, a malediction, and a reproach, and you will never again see this place.’

^19 “Jehovah has spoken against you, O remnant of Judah. Do not go to Egypt. You should know for a certainty that I have warned you today ^20 that your error will cost you your lives.[*] For you sent me to Jehovah your God, saying, ‘Pray in our behalf to Jehovah our God, and tell us everything that Jehovah our God says, and we will do it.’ ^21 And I told you today, but you will not obey the voice of Jehovah your God or do anything he sent me to tell you. ^22 Therefore, know for a certainty that by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence you will die in the place where you desire to go and reside.”

^ Jer. 42:10 Or “feel grieved.”

^ Jer. 42:15 Or “to reside for a while.”

^ Jer. 42:17 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 42:20 Or “souls.”

Jeremiah  43 : 1 - 13

43 When Jeremiah had finished speaking to all the people all these words from Jehovah their God, every single word that Jehovah their God had sent him to tell them, ^2 Az·a·riʹah the son of Ho·shaiʹah, Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah, and all the presumptuous men said to Jeremiah: “What you are saying is a lie! Jehovah our God has not sent you to say, ‘Do not go to Egypt to reside there.’ ^3 But Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah is inciting you against us to hand us over to the Chal·deʹans, to put us to death or to take us into exile in Babylon.”

^4 So Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs and all the people disobeyed the voice of Jehovah to remain in the land of Judah. ^5 Instead, Jo·haʹnan the son of Ka·reʹah and all the army chiefs took with them all the remnant of Judah who had returned to reside in the land of Judah from all the nations where they had been dispersed. ^6 They took the men, the women, the children, the daughters of the king, and everyone[*] whom Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard had left with Ged·a·liʹah the son of A·hiʹkam the son of Shaʹphan, as well as Jeremiah the prophet and Barʹuch the son of Ne·riʹah. ^7 And they went into the land of Egypt, for they did not obey the voice of Jehovah, and they went as far as Tahʹpan·hes.

^8 Then the word of Jehovah came to Jeremiah in Tahʹpan·hes, saying: ^9 “Take in your hand large stones, and hide them in the mortar in the brick terrace at the entrance of the house of Pharʹaoh in Tahʹpan·hes, with the Jewish men looking on. ^10 Then say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: “Here I am sending for Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will place his throne right above these stones that I have hidden, and he will extend his royal tent over them. ^11 And he will come in and strike the land of Egypt. Whoever is meant for deadly plague will be for deadly plague, and whoever is meant for captivity will be for captivity, and whoever is meant for the sword will be for the sword. ^12 And I will set the houses[*] of the gods of Egypt on fire, and he will burn them and lead them captive. He will wrap the land of Egypt around himself just as a shepherd wraps himself in his garment, and he will depart from there in peace.[*] ^13 And he will break to pieces the pillars[*] of Beth-sheʹmesh[*] in the land of Egypt, and he will burn the houses[*] of the gods of Egypt with fire.”’”

^ Jer. 43:6 Or “every soul.”

^ Jer. 43:10 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 43:12 Or “temples.”

^ Jer. 43:12 Or “unharmed.”

^ Jer. 43:13 Or “obelisks.”

^ Jer. 43:13 Or “House (Temple) of the Sun,” that is, Heliopolis.

^ Jer. 43:13 Or “temples.”

Jeremiah  44 : 1 - 30

44 The word that came to Jeremiah for all the Jews living in the land of Egypt, those living in Migʹdol, Tahʹpan·hes, Noph,[*] and the land of Pathʹros, saying: ^2 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘You have seen all the calamity that I brought on Jerusalem and on all the cities of Judah, and today they are in ruins, without an inhabitant. ^3 It is because of the evil things that they did to offend me by going and making sacrifices and serving other gods whom they had not known, neither you nor your forefathers. ^4 I kept sending all my servants the prophets to you, sending them again and again,[*] saying: “Please do not do this detestable thing that I hate.” ^5 But they did not listen or incline their ear to turn back from their evil by not making sacrifices to other gods. ^6 So my wrath and my anger were poured out and burned in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem, and they became a ruin and a wasteland, as they are today.’

^7 “And now this is what Jehovah, the God of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Why are you causing a great calamity to yourselves,[*] so that every man and woman, child and infant, will perish from Judah, leaving you without a remnant? ^8 Why should you offend me with the works of your hands by sacrificing to other gods in the land of Egypt where you have gone to reside? You will perish and become an object of cursing and a reproach among all the nations of the earth. ^9 Have you forgotten the wicked deeds of your forefathers and the wicked deeds of the kings of Judah and the wicked deeds of their wives, as well as your own wicked deeds and the wicked deeds of your wives, that were done in the land of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem? ^10 Down to this day they have not humbled themselves,[*] they have shown no fear, nor have they walked in my law and my statutes that I set before you and your forefathers.’

^11 “Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘Here I am determined to bring calamity on you, to destroy all Judah. ^12 And I will take the remnant of Judah who were determined to go to the land of Egypt to reside there, and they will all perish in the land of Egypt. They will fall by the sword and perish by the famine; from the least to the greatest, they will die by the sword and by famine. And they will become a curse, an object of horror, a malediction, and a reproach. ^13 I will punish those dwelling in the land of Egypt just as I punished Jerusalem, with the sword, with famine, and with pestilence.[*] ^14 And the remnant of Judah who have gone to reside in the land of Egypt will not escape or survive to return to the land of Judah. They will long[*] to return and dwell there, but they will not return, except for a few escapees.’”

^15 All the men who knew that their wives had been making sacrifices to other gods and all the wives who were standing there, who formed a large group, and all the people who were living in the land of Egypt, in Pathʹros, answered Jeremiah: ^16 “We will not listen to the word that you have spoken to us in the name of Jehovah. ^17 Instead, we will surely carry out every word that our mouths have spoken, to make sacrifices to the Queen of Heaven[*] and to pour out drink offerings to her, just as we, our forefathers, our kings, and our princes did in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem when we were satisfied with bread and were well-off, when we saw no calamity at all. ^18 From the time we quit making sacrifices to the Queen of Heaven[*] and pouring out drink offerings to her, we have lacked everything and have perished by the sword and by the famine.”

^19 The women added: “And when we were making sacrifices to the Queen of Heaven[*] and pouring out drink offerings to her, was it without the consent of our husbands that we made sacrificial cakes shaped in her image and we poured out drink offerings to her?”

^20 Then Jeremiah said to all the people, to the men and their wives and to all the people who were speaking to him: ^21 “The sacrifices that you, your forefathers, your kings, your princes, and the people of the land made in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem—Jehovah remembered them and they came up into his heart! ^22 Finally Jehovah could no longer put up with your evil practices and the detestable things you had done, and your land became a devastated place, an object of horror and cursing, without an inhabitant, as it is today. ^23 It is because you have made these sacrifices and because you have sinned against Jehovah by not obeying the voice of Jehovah and following his law, his statutes, and his reminders that this calamity has come upon you, as is the case today.”

^24 Jeremiah continued to say to all the people and to all the women: “Hear the word of Jehovah, all you of Judah who are in the land of Egypt. ^25 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says, ‘What you and your wives have spoken with your mouths, you have fulfilled with your hands, for you said: “We will surely carry out our vows to make sacrifices to the Queen of Heaven[*] and to pour out drink offerings to her.” You women will surely carry out your vows and perform your vows.’

^26 “Therefore hear the word of Jehovah, all you of Judah who are living in the land of Egypt: ‘“Here I swear by my own great name,” says Jehovah, “that my name will no longer be called on in an oath by any man of Judah in all the land of Egypt who says, ‘As surely as the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is alive!’ ^27 Now I am watching over them to bring calamity and not something good; all the men of Judah in the land of Egypt will perish by the sword and by the famine, until they cease to exist. ^28 Only a few will escape the sword and return from the land of Egypt to the land of Judah. Then all the remnant of Judah who came to the land of Egypt to reside there will know whose word has come true, mine or theirs!”’”

^29 “‘And this is the sign for you,’ declares Jehovah, ‘that I will punish you in this place, so that you will know that my words promising calamity against you will surely come true. ^30 This is what Jehovah says: “Here I am giving Pharʹaoh Hophʹra, the king of Egypt, into the hand of his enemies and of those seeking to take his life,[*] just as I gave King Zed·e·kiʹah of Judah into the hand of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon, who was his enemy and who sought to take his life.”’”[*]

^ Jer. 44:1 Or “Memphis.”

^ Jer. 44:4 Lit., “rising up early and sending.”

^ Jer. 44:7 Or “your souls.”

^ Jer. 44:10 Or “felt crushed.”

^ Jer. 44:13 Or “disease.”

^ Jer. 44:14 Or “lift up their soul.”

^ Jer. 44:17 The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites; possibly a fertility goddess.

^ Jer. 44:18 The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites; possibly a fertility goddess.

^ Jer. 44:19 The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites; possibly a fertility goddess.

^ Jer. 44:25 The title of a goddess worshipped by apostate Israelites; possibly a fertility goddess.

^ Jer. 44:30 Or “seeking his soul.”

^ Jer. 44:30 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 44:30 Or “was seeking his soul.”

Jeremiah  50 : 1 - 46

50 The word that Jehovah spoke concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chal·deʹans, through Jeremiah the prophet:

 ^2 “Declare it among the nations and proclaim it.

Raise a signal[*] and proclaim it.

Do not hide anything!

Say, ‘Babylon has been captured.

Bel has been put to shame.

Merʹo·dach has become terrified.

Her images have been put to shame.

Her disgusting idols[*] have become terrified.’

 ^3 For a nation has come against her from the north.

It makes her land an object of horror;

No one is dwelling in her.

Both man and beast have taken flight;

They have gone away.”

^4 “In those days and at that time,” declares Jehovah, “the people of Israel and the people of Judah will come together. They will weep as they walk, and together they will seek Jehovah their God. ^5 They will ask the way to Zion, with their faces turned in that direction, saying, ‘Come and let us join ourselves to Jehovah in an everlasting covenant that will not be forgotten.’ ^6 My people have become a flock of lost sheep. Their own shepherds caused them to stray. They led them away onto the mountains, roaming from mountain to hill. They have forgotten their resting-place. ^7 All those finding them have devoured them, and their enemies have said, ‘We are not guilty, because they sinned against Jehovah, against the dwelling place of righteousness and the hope of their forefathers, Jehovah.’”

 ^8 “Flee out of the midst of Babylon,

Go out of the land of the Chal·deʹans,

And be like the leading animals before the flock.

 ^9 For here I am raising up and bringing against Babylon

An assembly of great nations from the land of the north.

They will come against her in battle formation;

From there she will be captured.

Their arrows are like those of a warrior

Causing bereavement of children;

They do not come back without results.

^10 Chal·deʹa will become a spoil.

All those taking spoil from her will be fully satisfied,” declares Jehovah.

^11 “For you kept rejoicing, you kept exulting

When pillaging my own inheritance.

For you kept pawing like a heifer in the grass,

And you kept neighing like stallions.

^12 Your mother has been put to shame.

She who gave birth to you has been disappointed.

Look! She is the least of the nations,

A waterless wilderness and a desert.

^13 Because of the indignation of Jehovah she will not be inhabited;

She will become utterly desolate.

Anyone passing by Babylon will stare in horror

And whistle because of all her plagues.

^14 Come against Babylon in battle formation on every side,

All you who are bending[*] the bow.

Shoot at her, spare no arrow,

For it is against Jehovah that she has sinned.

^15 Shout a war cry against her on every side.

She has surrendered.[*]

Her pillars have fallen, her walls are torn down,

For it is the vengeance of Jehovah.

Take your vengeance on her.

Do to her just as she has done.

^16 Cut off the sower from Babylon

And the one handling the sickle in harvesttime.

Because of the cruel sword, each will return to his own people,

Each one will flee to his own land.

^17 “The people of Israel are scattered sheep. Lions have dispersed them. First the king of As·syrʹi·a devoured them; then King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon gnawed on their bones. ^18 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, says: ‘Here I will deal with the king of Babylon and with his land in the same way that I dealt with the king of As·syrʹi·a. ^19 And I will bring Israel back to his pasture, and he will graze on Carʹmel and on Baʹshan, and on the mountains of Eʹphra·im and of Gilʹe·ad he[*] will be satisfied.’”

^20 “In those days and at that time,” declares Jehovah,

“Israel’s guilt will be searched for,

But there will be none,

And the sins of Judah will not be found,

For I will forgive those whom I let remain.”

^21 “Go up against the land of Mer·a·thaʹim and against the inhabitants of Peʹkod.

Let them be massacred and completely destroyed,”[*] declares Jehovah.

“Do all that I have commanded you.

^22 There is the sound of war in the land,

A great catastrophe.

^23 How the forge hammer of all the earth has been cut down and broken!

How Babylon has become an object of horror among the nations!

^24 I have laid a snare for you, and you have been caught, O Babylon,

And you did not know it.

You were found and captured,

For it was Jehovah whom you opposed.

^25 Jehovah has opened his storehouse,

And he brings out the weapons of his indignation.

For the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has a work

In the land of the Chal·deʹans.

^26 Come against her from distant places.

Open up her granaries.

Pile her up like heaps of grain.

Destroy her completely.[*]

May she have no one left.

^27 Massacre all her young bulls;

Let them go down to the slaughter.

Woe to them, for their day has come,

Their time of reckoning!

^28 There is the sound of those fleeing,

Those escaping from the land of Babylon,

To declare in Zion the vengeance of Jehovah our God,

The vengeance for his temple.

^29 Summon archers against Babylon,

All who are bending[*] the bow.

Camp all around her; let no one escape.

Repay her according to her activity.

Do to her just as she has done.

For she has acted arrogantly against Jehovah,

Against the Holy One of Israel.

^30 So her young men will fall in her public squares,

And all her soldiers will perish[*] in that day,” declares Jehovah.

^31 “Look! I am against you, O defiant one,” declares the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies,

“For your day must come, the time that I will call you to account.

^32 You, O defiant one, will stumble and fall,

With no one to raise you up.

And I will set your cities on fire,

And it will consume everything around you.”

^33 This is what Jehovah of armies says:

“The people of Israel and Judah are oppressed,

And all those taking them captive have held onto them.

They have refused to let them go.

^34 But their Repurchaser is strong.

Jehovah of armies is his name.

He will surely plead their legal case,

In order to give rest to the land

And to bring agitation to the inhabitants of Babylon.”

^35 “There is a sword against the Chal·deʹans,” declares Jehovah,

“Against the inhabitants of Babylon and against her princes and against her wise ones.

^36 There is a sword against the empty talkers,[*] and they will act foolishly.

There is a sword against her warriors, and they will become terrified.

^37 There is a sword against their horses and their war chariots,

And against all the mixed populations in her midst,

And they will become like women.

There is a sword against her treasures, and they will be plundered.

^38 There is a devastation on her waters, and they will be dried up.

For it is a land of graven images,

And because of their frightful visions they keep acting with madness.

^39 Therefore, the desert creatures will dwell with the howling animals,

And in her the ostriches will dwell.

She will never again be inhabited,

Nor will she be a place of residence throughout all generations.”

^40 “Just as with God’s overthrow of Sodʹom and Go·morʹrah and of their neighboring towns,” declares Jehovah, “no one will dwell there, and no man will settle there.

^41 Look! A people is coming in from the north;

A great nation and grand kings will be raised up

From the remotest parts of the earth.

^42 Bow and javelin they wield.

They are cruel and will show no mercy.

Their sound is like the roaring sea,

As they ride on their horses.

Like one man, they line up in battle formation against you, O daughter of Babylon.

^43 The king of Babylon has heard the report about them,

And his hands drop down.

Anguish seizes him,

Pain like that of a woman giving birth.

^44 “Look! Someone will come up against the secure pastures like a lion from the dense thickets along the Jordan, but in a moment I will make them run away from her. And I will appoint over her the chosen one. For who is like me, and who will challenge me? What shepherd can stand before me? ^45 Therefore hear, O men, the decision[*] that Jehovah has made against Babylon and what he has thought out against the land of the Chal·deʹans.

Surely the little ones of the flock will be dragged away.

He will make their dwelling place desolate because of them.

^46 At the sound of Babylon’s capture, the earth will quake,

And an outcry will be heard among the nations.”

^ Jer. 50:2 Or “signal pole.”

^ Jer. 50:2 The Hebrew term may be related to a word for “dung” and is used as an expression of contempt.

^ Jer. 50:14 Lit., “treading.”

^ Jer. 50:15 Lit., “given her hand.”

^ Jer. 50:17 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 50:19 Or “his soul.”

^ Jer. 50:21 Or “and devote them to destruction.”

^ Jer. 50:26 Or “Devote her to destruction.”

^ Jer. 50:29 Lit., “treading.”

^ Jer. 50:30 Lit., “be silenced.”

^ Jer. 50:36 Or “the false prophets.”

^ Jer. 50:45 Or “counsel.”

Jeremiah  52 : 1 - 34

52 Zed·e·kiʹah was 21 years old when he became king, and he reigned for 11 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Ha·muʹtal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libʹnah. ^2 He continued to do what was bad in Jehovah’s eyes, according to all that Je·hoiʹa·kim had done. ^3 It was because of Jehovah’s anger that these things took place in Jerusalem and in Judah, until he cast them out of his sight. And Zed·e·kiʹah rebelled against the king of Babylon. ^4 In the ninth year of Zed·e·kiʹah’s reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] of Babylon came with all his army against Jerusalem. They camped against it and built a siege wall all around it. ^5 And the city was under siege until the 11th year of King Zed·e·kiʹah.

^6 In the fourth month, on the ninth day of the month, the famine was severe in the city, and there was no food for the people of the land. ^7 Finally the city wall was broken through, and all the soldiers fled from the city by night through the gate between the double wall near the king’s garden, while the Chal·deʹans were surrounding the city; and they continued by the way of the Arʹa·bah. ^8 But the Chal·deʹan army pursued the king, and they overtook Zed·e·kiʹah in the desert plains of Jerʹi·cho, and all his troops were scattered from his side. ^9 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Ribʹlah in the land of Haʹmath, and he passed sentence on him. ^10 And the king of Babylon slaughtered Zed·e·kiʹah’s sons before his eyes, and he also slaughtered all the princes of Judah there at Ribʹlah. ^11 Then the king of Babylon blinded Zed·e·kiʹah’s eyes, bound him with copper fetters, brought him to Babylon, and kept him imprisoned until the day of his death.

^12 In the fifth month, on the tenth day of the month, that is, in the 19th year of King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] the king of Babylon, Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard, who was an attendant of the king of Babylon, came into Jerusalem. ^13 He burned down the house of Jehovah, the king’s house,[*] and all the houses of Jerusalem; he also burned down every large house. ^14 And the walls surrounding Jerusalem were pulled down by the entire Chal·deʹan army that was with the chief of the guard.

^15 Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard took into exile some of the lowly people and the rest of the people who were left in the city. He also took the deserters who had defected to the king of Babylon as well as the rest of the master craftsmen. ^16 But Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard left some of the poorest people of the land to serve as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers.

^17 And the Chal·deʹans broke into pieces the copper pillars of the house of Jehovah and the carriages and the copper Sea that were in the house of Jehovah, and they carried all the copper away to Babylon. ^18 They also took the cans, the shovels, the extinguishers, the bowls, the cups, and all the copper utensils used in the temple service. ^19 The chief of the guard took the basins, the fire holders, the bowls, the cans, the lampstands, the cups, and the bowls that were of genuine gold and silver. ^20 As for the two pillars, the Sea, the 12 copper bulls under the Sea, and the carriages that King Solʹo·mon had made for the house of Jehovah, the copper of all these articles was beyond weighing.

^21 As for the pillars, each pillar was 18 cubits[*] high, a measuring cord of 12 cubits could encircle it; its thickness was four fingerbreadths,[*] and it was hollow. ^22 And the capital on it was of copper; and the height of the one capital was five cubits; and the network and pomegranates all around on the capital were all made of copper. The second pillar was just like it, also the pomegranates. ^23 There were 96 pomegranates on the sides; in all, there were 100 pomegranates around the network.

^24 The chief of the guard also took Se·raiʹah the chief priest, Zeph·a·niʹah the second priest, and the three doorkeepers. ^25 And he took from the city one court official who was the commissioner over the soldiers, seven close associates of the king who were found in the city, as well as the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and 60 men of the common people of the land who were yet found in the city. ^26 Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard took them and brought them to the king of Babylon at Ribʹlah. ^27 The king of Babylon struck them down and put them to death at Ribʹlah in the land of Haʹmath. Thus Judah went into exile from its land.

^28 These are the people whom Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar[*] took into exile: in the seventh year, 3,023 Jews.

^29 In the 18th year of Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar,[*] 832 people[*] were taken from Jerusalem.

^30 In the 23rd year of Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar,[*] Neb·uʹzar·adʹan the chief of the guard took Jews into exile, 745 people.[*]

In all, 4,600 people[*] were taken into exile.

^31 Then in the 37th year of the exile of King Je·hoiʹa·chin of Judah, in the 12th month, on the 25th day of the month, King Eʹvil-merʹo·dach of Babylon, in the year he became king, released[*] King Je·hoiʹa·chin of Judah and brought him out of prison. ^32 He spoke kindly with him and put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings who were with him in Babylon. ^33 So Je·hoiʹa·chin took off his prison garments, and he regularly ate before him all the days of his life. ^34 A regular allowance of food was given him from the king of Babylon, day after day, until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

^ Jer. 52:4 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:12 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:13 Or “palace.”

^ Jer. 52:21 A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

^ Jer. 52:21 A fingerbreadth equaled 1.85 cm (0.73 in.). See App. B14.

^ Jer. 52:28 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:29 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:29 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:30 Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ Jer. 52:30 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:30 Or “souls.”

^ Jer. 52:31 Lit., “raised up the head of.”

Ezekiel  1 : 1 - 28

EZEKIEL

1 In the 30th year, on the fifth day of the fourth month, while I was among the exiled people by the river Cheʹbar, the heavens were opened and I began to see visions of God. ^2 On the fifth day of the month—that is, in the fifth year of the exile of King Je·hoiʹa·chin— ^3 the word of Jehovah came to Ezekiel[*] son of Buʹzi the priest by the river Cheʹbar in the land of the Chal·deʹans. There the hand of Jehovah came upon him.

^4 As I was looking, I saw a tempestuous wind coming from the north, and there was a huge cloud and flashing fire[*] surrounded by a bright light, and from the midst of the fire was something that looked like electrum.[*] ^5 Within it were what looked like four living creatures, and the appearance of each one was like that of a human. ^6 Each one had four faces and four wings. ^7 Their feet were straight, and the soles of their feet were like those of a calf, and they were shining like the glow of burnished copper. ^8 They had human hands under their wings on all four sides, and the four of them had faces and wings. ^9 Their wings were touching one another. They would not turn when they went; they would each go straight forward.

^10 Their faces had this appearance: Each of the four had a man’s face with a lion’s face on the right, a bull’s face on the left, and each of the four had an eagle’s face. ^11 That is how their faces were. Their wings were spread out above them. Each had two wings that were touching one another and two wings covering their bodies.

^12 They would each go straight forward, going wherever the spirit would incline them to go. They would not turn as they went. ^13 And the living creatures had the appearance of burning coals of fire, and something that looked like torches of bright fire was moving back and forth between the living creatures, and lightning was flashing out from the fire. ^14 And when the living creatures would go forth and return, their movement had the appearance of flashes of lightning.

^15 As I was watching the living creatures, I saw one wheel on the earth beside each of the living creatures with four faces. ^16 The wheels and their structure appeared to glow like chrysʹo·lite, and the four of them looked alike. Their appearance and structure looked as though a wheel were within a wheel.[*] ^17 When they moved, they could go in any of the four directions without turning as they went. ^18 Their rims were so high that they inspired awe, and the rims of all four were full of eyes all around. ^19 Whenever the living creatures moved, the wheels would move along with them, and when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth, the wheels would also be lifted up. ^20 They would go where the spirit inclined them to go, wherever the spirit went. The wheels would be lifted up together with them, for the spirit operating on the living creatures[*] was also in the wheels. ^21 When they moved, these would move; and when they stood still, these would stand still; and when they were lifted up from the earth, the wheels would be lifted up together with them, for the spirit operating on the living creatures was also in the wheels.

^22 Over the heads of the living creatures was the likeness of an expanse that sparkled like awesome ice, stretched out above their heads. ^23 Under the expanse their wings were straight,[*] one to the other. Each one had two wings for covering one side of their bodies and two for covering the other side. ^24 When I heard the sound of their wings, it was like a sound of rushing waters, like the sound of the Almighty. When they moved, it was like the sound of an army. When they stood still, they would let their wings down.

^25 There was a voice above the expanse over their heads. (When they stood still, they would let their wings down.) ^26 Above the expanse that was over their heads was what looked like a sapphire stone, and it resembled a throne. Sitting on the throne up above was someone whose appearance resembled that of a human. ^27 I saw something glowing like electrum that was like a fire radiating from what appeared to be his waist and upward; and from his waist down, I saw something that resembled fire. There was a brilliance all around him ^28 like that of a rainbow in a cloud on a rainy day. That was how the surrounding brilliant light appeared. It was like the appearance of the glory of Jehovah. When I saw it, I fell facedown and began to hear the voice of someone speaking.

^ Ezek. 1:3 Meaning “God Strengthens.”

^ Ezek. 1:4 Or “and lightning.”

^ Ezek. 1:4 A shining alloy of gold and silver.

^ Ezek. 1:16 Possibly centered at right angles on the same axis.

^ Ezek. 1:20 Lit., “the spirit of the living creature.”

^ Ezek. 1:23 Or possibly, “extended out straight.”

Ezekiel  3 : 1 - 27

3 Then he said to me: “Son of man, eat what is before you.[*] Eat this scroll, and go, speak to the house of Israel.”

^2 So I opened my mouth, and he made me eat this scroll. ^3 He went on to say to me: “Son of man, eat this scroll that I am giving you, and fill your stomach with it.” So I began to eat it, and it was as sweet as honey in my mouth.

^4 He said to me: “Son of man, go in among the house of Israel and speak my words to them. ^5 For you are not being sent to a people who speak an unintelligible language or an unknown tongue, but to the house of Israel. ^6 You are not being sent to many peoples speaking an unintelligible language or an unknown tongue, whose words you cannot understand. If I would send you to them, they would listen to you. ^7 But the house of Israel will refuse to listen to you, for they do not want to listen to me. All those of the house of Israel are hardheaded and hardhearted. ^8 Look! I have made your face exactly as hard as their faces and your forehead exactly as hard as their foreheads. ^9 I have made your forehead like a diamond, harder than flint. Do not be afraid of them or be terrified by their faces, for they are a rebellious house.”

^10 He went on to say to me: “Son of man, take to heart and listen to all my words that I speak to you. ^11 Go in among the exiles of your people[*] and speak to them. Tell them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says,’ whether they listen or refuse to listen.”

^12 A spirit then carried me along and I heard behind me a great rumbling sound that said: “May the glory of Jehovah be praised from his place.” ^13 There was the sound of the wings of the living creatures as they were brushing against one another, and the sound of the wheels next to them, and the sound of a great rumbling. ^14 And the spirit carried me along and took me, and I went in bitterness and in the rage of my spirit, and the hand of Jehovah rested strongly on me. ^15 So I went to the exiled people at Tel-aʹbib, who were dwelling by the river Cheʹbar, and I stayed there where they were dwelling; and in a dazed condition, I stayed among them for seven days.

^16 At the end of seven days the word of Jehovah came to me:

^17 “Son of man, I have appointed you as a watchman to the house of Israel; and when you hear a word from my mouth, you must warn them from me. ^18 When I say to someone wicked, ‘You will surely die,’ but you do not warn him, and you fail to speak in order to warn the wicked one to turn from his wicked course so that he may stay alive, he will die for his error because he is wicked, but I will ask his blood back from you.[*] ^19 But if you warn someone wicked and he does not turn back from his wickedness and from his wicked course, he will die for his error, but you will certainly save your own life.[*] ^20 But when someone righteous abandons his righteousness and does what is wrong,[*] I will put a stumbling block before him and he will die. If you did not warn him, he will die for his sin and his righteous acts will not be remembered, but I will ask his blood back from you.[*] ^21 But if you have warned the righteous one not to sin, and he does not sin, he will surely keep alive because he was warned, and you will have saved your own life.”[*]

^22 The hand of Jehovah came upon me there, and he said to me: “Get up, go to the valley plain, and I will speak with you there.” ^23 So I got up and went to the valley plain, and look! the glory of Jehovah was there, like the glory that I saw by the river Cheʹbar, and I fell facedown. ^24 Then spirit entered into me and made me stand up on my feet, and he spoke to me and said:

“Go, shut yourself inside your house. ^25 As for you, son of man, they will put ropes on you and tie you with them so that you cannot go out among them. ^26 And I will make your tongue stick to the roof of your mouth, and you will become mute, unable to reprove them, because they are a rebellious house. ^27 But when I speak with you I will open your mouth, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says.’ Let the one listening listen, and let the one refusing to listen refuse, because they are a rebellious house.

^ Ezek. 3:1 Lit., “eat what you find.”

^ Ezek. 3:11 Lit., “of the sons of your people.”

^ Ezek. 3:18 Or “I will hold you accountable for his blood.”

^ Ezek. 3:19 Or “soul.”

^ Ezek. 3:20 Or “does injustice.”

^ Ezek. 3:20 Or “I will hold you accountable for his blood.”

^ Ezek. 3:21 Or “soul.”